<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd">
<topic id="introductory-note">
  <title>INTRODUCTORY NOTE</title>
  <body>
    <p class="center">By Professor J. Arthur Thomson</p>
    
    <p>Was it not the great philosopher and mathematician Leibnitz who said that
      the more knowledge advances the more it becomes possible to condense it into
      little books? Now this &quot;Outline of Science&quot; is certainly not a
      little book, and yet it illustrates part of the meaning of Leibnitz&#39;s
      wise saying. For here within reasonable compass there is a library of little
      books&#x2014;an outline of many sciences.</p>
    
    <p>It will be profitable to the student in proportion to the discrimination
      with which it is used. For it is not in the least meant to be of the nature
      of an Encyclopædia, giving condensed and comprehensive articles with a big
      full stop at the end of each. Nor is it a collection of &quot;primers,&quot;
      beginning at the very beginning of each subject and working methodically
      onwards. That is not the idea.</p>
    
    <p>What then is the aim of this book? It is to give the intelligent
      student-citizen, otherwise called &quot;the man in the street,&quot; a bunch
      of intellectual keys by which to open doors which have been hitherto shut to
      him, partly because he got no glimpse of the treasures behind the doors, and
      partly because the portals were made forbidding by an unnecessary display of
      technicalities. Laying aside conventional modes of treatment and seeking
      rather to open up the subject as one might on a walk with a friend, the work
      offers the student what might be called informal introductions to the various
      departments of knowledge. To put it in another way, the articles are meant to
      be clues which the reader may follow till he has left his starting point very
      far behind. Perhaps when he has gone far on his own he will not be ungrateful
      to the simple book of &quot;instructions to travellers&quot; which
      this<ph outputclass='pagenum'>[Pg iv]</ph>
      &quot;Outline of Science&quot; is intended to be. The simple
      &quot;bibliographies&quot; appended to the various articles will be enough to
      indicate &quot;first books.&quot; Each article is meant to be an invitation
      to an intellectual adventure, and the short lists of books are merely
      finger-posts for the beginning of the journey.</p>
    
    <p>We confess to being greatly encouraged by the reception that has been
      given to the English serial issue of &quot;The Outline of Science.&quot; It
      has been very hearty&#x2014;we might almost say enthusiastic. For we agree
      with Professor John Dewey, that &quot;the future of our civilisation depends
      upon the widening spread and deepening hold of the scientific habit of
      mind.&quot; And we hope that this is what &quot;The Outline of Science&quot;
      makes for. Information is all to the good; interesting information is better
      still; but best of all is the education of the scientific habit of mind.
      Another modern philosopher, Professor L. T. Hobhouse, has declared that the
      evolutionist&#39;s mundane goal is &quot;the mastery by the human mind of the
      conditions, internal as well as external, of its life and growth.&quot; Under
      the influence of this conviction &quot;The Outline of Science&quot; has been
      written. For life is not for science, but science for life. And even more
      than science, to our way of thinking, is the individual development of the
      scientific way of looking at things. Science is our legacy; we must use it if
      it is to be our very own.<ph outputclass='pagenum'>[Pg v]</ph></p>
  </body>
</topic>
