<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p2-chapter-2" ><title>Chapter 2</title><body><p>On the 9th of October the bark canoe was entirely finished. Pencroft had kept his promise,
        and a light boat, the shell of which was joined together by the flexible twigs of the
        crejimba, had been constructed in five days. A seat in the stern, a second seat in the
        middle to preserve the equilibrium, a third seat in the bows, rowlocks for the two oars, a
        scull to steer with, completed the little craft, which was twelve feet long, and did not
        weigh more than two hundred pounds. The operation of launching it was extremely simple. The
        canoe was carried to the beach and laid on the sand before Granite House, and the rising
        tide floated it. Pencroft, who leaped in directly, maneuvered it with the scull and declared
        it to be just the thing for the purpose to which they wished to put it.</p><p>"Hurrah!" cried the sailor, who did not disdain to celebrate thus his own triumph. "With
        this we could go round--"</p><p>"The world?" asked Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"No, the island. Some stones for ballast, a mast and a sail, which the captain will make
        for us some day, and we shall go splendidly! Well, captain--and you, Mr. Spilett; and you,
        Herbert; and you, Neb--aren't you coming to try our new vessel? Come along! we must see if
        it will carry all five of us!"</p><p>This was certainly a trial which ought to be made. Pencroft soon brought the canoe to the
        shore by a narrow passage among the rocks, and it was agreed that they should make a trial
        of the boat that day by following the shore as far as the first point at which the rocks of
        the south ended.</p><p>As they embarked, Neb cried,--</p><p>"But your boat leaks rather, Pencroft."</p><p>"That's nothing, Neb," replied the sailor; "the wood will get seasoned. In two days there
        won't be a single leak, and our boat will have no more water in her than there is in the
        stomach of a drunkard. Jump in!"</p><p>They were soon all seated, and Pencroft shoved off. The weather was magnificent, the sea as
        calm as if its waters were contained within the narrow limits of a lake. Thus the boat could
        proceed with as much security as if it was ascending the tranquil current of the Mercy.</p><p>Neb took one of the oars, Herbert the other, and Pencroft remained in the stern in order to
        use the scull.</p><p>The sailor first crossed the channel, and steered close to the southern point of the islet.
        A light breeze blew from the south. No roughness was found either in the channel or the
        green sea. A long swell, which the canoe scarcely felt, as it was heavily laden, rolled
        regularly over the surface of the water. They pulled out about half a mile distant from the
        shore, that they might have a good view of Mount Franklin.</p><p>Pencroft afterwards returned towards the mouth of the river. The boat then skirted the
        shore, which, extending to the extreme point, hid all Tadorn's Fens.</p><p>This point, of which the distance was increased by the irregularity of the coast, was
        nearly three miles from the Mercy. The settlers resolved to go to its extremity, and only go
        beyond it as much as was necessary to take a rapid survey of the coast as far as Claw
        Cape.</p><p>The canoe followed the windings of the shore, avoiding the rocks which fringed it, and
        which the rising tide began to cover. The cliff gradually sloped away from the mouth of the
        river to the point. This was formed of granite reeks, capriciously distributed, very
        different from the cliff at Prospect Heights, and of an extremely wild aspect. It might have
        been said that an immense cartload of rocks had been emptied out there. There was no
        vegetation on this sharp promontory, which projected two miles from the forest, and it thus
        represented a giant's arm stretched out from a leafy sleeve.</p><p>The canoe, impelled by the two oars, advanced without difficulty. Gideon Spilett, pencil in
        one hand and notebook in the other, sketched the coast in bold strokes. Neb, Herbert, and
        Pencroft chatted, while examining this part of their domain, which was new to them, and, in
        proportion as the canoe proceeded towards the south, the two Mandible Capes appeared to
        move, and surround Union Bay more closely.</p><p>As to Cyrus Harding, he did not speak; he simply gazed, and by the mistrust which his look
        expressed, it appeared that he was examining some strange country.</p><p>In the meantime, after a voyage of three-quarters of an hour, the canoe reached the
        extremity of the point, and Pencroft was preparing to return, when Herbert, rising, pointed
        to a black object, saying,--</p><p>"What do I see down there on the beach?"</p><p>All eyes turned towards the point indicated.</p><p>"Why," said the reporter, "there is something. It looks like part of a wreck half buried in
        the sand."</p><p>"Ah!" cried Pencroft, "I see what it is!"</p><p>"What?" asked Neb.</p><p>"Barrels, barrels, which perhaps are full," replied the sailor.</p><p>"Pull to the shore, Pencroft!" said Cyrus.</p><p>A few strokes of the oar brought the canoe into a little creek, and its passengers leaped
        on shore.</p><p>Pencroft was not mistaken. Two barrels were there, half buried in the sand, but still
        firmly attached to a large chest, which, sustained by them, had floated to the moment when
        it stranded on the beach.</p><p>"There has been a wreck, then, in some part of the island," said Herbert.</p><p>"Evidently," replied Spilett.</p><p>"But what's in this chest?" cried Pencroft, with very natural impatience. "What's in this
        chest? It is shut up, and nothing to open it with! Well, perhaps a stone--"</p><p>And the sailor, raising a heavy block, was about to break in one of the sides of the chest,
        when the engineer arrested his hand.</p><p>"Pencroft," said he, "can you restrain your impatience for one hour only?"</p><p>"But, captain, just think! Perhaps there is everything we want in there!"</p><p>"We shall find that out, Pencroft," replied the engineer; "but trust to me, and do not
        break the chest, which may be useful to us. We must convey it to Granite House, where we can
        open it easily, and without breaking it. It is quite prepared for a voyage; and since it has
        floated here, it may just as well float to the mouth of the river."</p><p>"You are right, captain, and I was wrong, as usual," replied the sailor.</p><p>The engineer's advice was good. In fact, the canoe probably would not have been able to
        contain the articles possibly enclosed in the chest, which doubtless was heavy, since two
        empty barrels were required to buoy it up. It was, therefore, much better to tow it to the
        beach at Granite House.</p><p>And now, whence had this chest come? That was the important question. Cyrus Harding and his
        companions looked attentively around them, and examined the shore for several hundred steps.
        No other articles or pieces of wreck could be found. Herbert and Neb climbed a high rock to
        survey the sea, but there was nothing in sight--neither a dismasted vessel nor a ship under
        sail.</p><p>However, there was no doubt that there had been a wreck. Perhaps this incident was
        connected with that of the bullet? Perhaps strangers had landed on another part of the
        island? Perhaps they were still there? But the thought which came naturally to the settlers
        was, that these strangers could not be Malay pirates, for the chest was evidently of
        American or European make.</p><p>All the party returned to the chest, which was of an unusually large size. It was made of
        oak wood, very carefully closed and covered with a thick hide, which was secured by copper
        nails. The two great barrels, hermetically sealed, but which sounded hollow and empty, were
        fastened to its sides by strong ropes, knotted with a skill which Pencroft directly
        pronounced sailors alone could exhibit. It appeared to be in a perfect state of
        preservation, which was explained by the fact that it had stranded on a sandy beach, and not
        among rocks. They had no doubt whatever, on examining it carefully, that it had not been
        long in the water, and that its arrival on this coast was recent. The water did not appear
        to have penetrated to the inside, and the articles which it contained were no doubt
        uninjured.</p><p>It was evident that this chest had been thrown overboard from some dismasted vessel driven
        towards the island, and that, in the hope that it would reach the land, where they might
        afterwards find it, the passengers had taken the precaution to buoy it up by means of this
        floating apparatus.</p><p>"We will tow this chest to Granite House," said the engineer, "where we can make an
        inventory of its contents; then, if we discover any of the survivors from the supposed
        wreck, we can return it to those to whom it belongs. If we find no one--"</p><p>"We will keep it for ourselves!" cried Pencroft. "But what in the world can there be in
        it?"</p><p>The sea was already approaching the chest, and the high tide would evidently float it. One
        of the ropes which fastened the barrels was partly unlashed and used as a cable to unite the
        floating apparatus with the canoe. Pencroft and Neb then dug away the sand with their oars,
        so as to facilitate the moving of the chest, towing which the boat soon began to double the
        point, to which the name of Flotsam Point was given.</p><p>The chest was heavy, and the barrels were scarcely sufficient to keep it above water. The
        sailor also feared every instant that it would get loose and sink to the bottom of the sea.
        But happily his fears were not realized, and an hour and a half after they set out--all that
        time had been taken up in going a distance of three miles--the boat touched the beach below
        Granite House.</p><p>Canoe and chest were then hauled up on the sands; and as the tide was then going out, they
        were soon left high and dry. Neb, hurrying home, brought back some tools with which to open
        the chest in such a way that it might be injured as little as possible, and they proceeded
        to its inventory. Pencroft did not try to hide that he was greatly excited.</p><p>The sailor began by detaching the two barrels, which, being in good condition, would of
        course be of use. Then the locks were forced with a cold chisel and hammer, and the lid
        thrown back. A second casing of zinc lined the interior of the chest, which had been
        evidently arranged that the articles which it enclosed might under any circumstances be
        sheltered from damp.</p><p>"Oh!" cried Neb, "suppose it's jam!</p><p>"I hope not," replied the reporter.</p><p>"If only there was--" said the sailor in a low voice.</p><p>"What?" asked Neb, who overheard him.</p><p>"Nothing!"</p><p>The covering of zinc was torn off and thrown back over the sides of the chest, and by
        degrees numerous articles of very varied character were produced and strewn about on the
        sand. At each new object Pencroft uttered fresh hurrahs, Herbert clapped his hands, and Neb
        danced up and down. There were books which made Herbert wild with joy, and cooking utensils
        which Neb covered with kisses!</p><p>In short, the colonists had reason to be extremely satisfied, for this chest contained
        tools, weapons, instruments, clothes, books; and this is the exact list of them as stated in
        Gideon Spilett's note-book:</p><p>--Tools:--3 knives with several blades, 2 woodmen's axes, 2 carpenter's hatchets, 3 planes,
        2 adzes, 1 twibil or mattock, 6 chisels, 2 files, 3 hammers, 3 gimlets, 2 augers, 10 bags of
        nails and screws, 3 saws of different sizes, 2 boxes of needles.</p><p>Weapons:--2 flint-lock guns, 2 for percussion caps, 2 breach-loader carbines, 5 boarding
        cutlasses, 4 sabers, 2 barrels of powder, each containing twenty-five pounds; 12 boxes of
        percussion caps.</p><p>Instruments:--1 sextant, 1 double opera-glass, 1 telescope, 1 box of mathematical
        instruments, 1 mariner's compass, 1 Fahrenheit thermometer, 1 aneroid barometer, 1 box
        containing a photographic apparatus, object-glass, plates, chemicals, etc.</p><p>Clothes:-2 dozen shirts of a peculiar material resembling wool, but evidently of a
        vegetable origin; 3 dozen stockings of the same material.</p><p>Utensils:-1 iron pot, 6 copper saucepans, 3 iron dishes, 10 metal plates, 2 kettles, 1
        portable stove, 6 table-knives,</p><p>Books:-1 Bible, 1 atlas, 1 dictionary of the different Polynesian idioms, 1 dictionary of
        natural science, in six volumes; 3 reams of white paper, 2 books with blank pages.</p><p>"It must be allowed," said the reporter, after the inventory had been made, "that the owner
        of this chest was a practical man! Tools, weapons, instruments, clothes, utensils,
        books--nothing is wanting! It might really be said that he expected to be wrecked, and had
        prepared for it beforehand."</p><p>"Nothing is wanting, indeed," murmured Cyrus Harding thoughtfully.</p><p>"And for a certainty," added Herbert, "the vessel which carried this chest and its owner
        was not a Malay pirate!"</p><p>"Unless," said Pencroft, "the owner had been taken prisoner by pirates--"</p><p>"That is not admissible," replied the reporter. "It is more probable that an American or
        European vessel has been driven into this quarter, and that her passengers, wishing to save
        necessaries at least, prepared this chest and threw it overboard."</p><p>"Is that your opinion, captain?" asked Herbert.</p><p>"Yes, my boy," replied the engineer, "that may have been the case. It is possible that at
        the moment, or in expectation of a wreck, they collected into this chest different articles
        of the greatest use in hopes of finding it again on the coast--"</p><p>"Even the photographic box!" exclaimed the sailor incredulously.</p><p>"As to that apparatus," replied Harding, "I do not quite see the use of it; and a more
        complete supply of clothes or more abundant ammunition would have been more valuable to us
        as well as to any other castaways!"</p><p>"But isn't there any mark or direction on these instruments, tools, or books, which would
        tell us something about them?" asked Gideon Spilett.</p><p>That might be ascertained. Each article was carefully examined, especially the books,
        instruments and weapons. Neither the weapons nor the instruments, contrary to the usual
        custom, bore the name of the maker; they were, besides, in a perfect state, and did not
        appear to have been used. The same peculiarity marked the tools and utensils; all were new,
        which proved that the articles had not been taken by chance and thrown into the chest, but,
        on the contrary, that the choice of things had been well considered and arranged with care.
        This was also indicated by the second case of metal which had preserved them from damp, and
        which could not have been soldered in a moment of haste.</p><p>As to the dictionaries of natural science and Polynesian idioms, both were English; but
        they neither bore the name of the publisher nor the date of publication.</p><p>The same with the Bible printed in English, in quarto, remarkable from a typographic point
        of view, and which appeared to have been often used.</p><p>The atlas was a magnificent work, comprising maps of every country in the world, and
        several planispheres arranged upon Mercator's projection, and of which the nomenclature was
        in French--but which also bore neither date nor name of publisher.</p><p>There was nothing, therefore, on these different articles by which they could be traced,
        and nothing consequently of a nature to show the nationality of the vessel which must have
        recently passed these shores.</p><p>But, wherever the chest might have come from, it was a treasure to the settlers on Lincoln
        Island. Till then, by making use of the productions of nature, they had created everything
        for themselves, and, thanks to their intelligence, they had managed without difficulty. But
        did it not appear as if Providence had wished to reward them by sending them these
        productions of human industry? Their thanks rose unanimously to Heaven.</p><p>However, one of them was not quite satisfied: it was Pencroft. It appeared that the chest
        did not contain something which he evidently held in great esteem, for in proportion as they
        approached the bottom of the box, his hurrahs diminished in heartiness, and, the inventory
        finished, he was heard to mutter these words:--"That's all very fine, but you can see that
        there is nothing for me in that box!"</p><p>This led Neb to say,--</p><p>"Why, friend Pencroft, what more do you expect?"</p><p>"Half a pound of tobacco," replied Pencroft seriously, "and nothing would have been wanting
        to complete my happiness!"</p><p>No one could help laughing at this speech of the sailor's.</p><p>But the result of this discovery of the chest was, that it was now more than ever necessary
        to explore the island thoroughly. It was therefore agreed that the next morning at break of
        day, they should set out, by ascending the Mercy so as to reach the western shore. If any
        castaways had landed on the coast, it was to be feared they were without resources, and it
        was therefore the more necessary to carry help to them without delay.</p><p>During the day the different articles were carried to Granite House, where they were
        methodically arranged in the great hall. This day--the 29th of October--happened to be a
        Sunday, and, before going to bed, Herbert asked the engineer if he would not read them
        something from the Gospel.</p><p>"Willingly," replied Cyrus Harding.</p><p>He took the sacred volume, and was about to open it, when Pencroft stopped him,
        saying,--"Captain, I am superstitious. Open at random and read the first verse which, your
        eye falls upon. We will see if it applies to our situation."</p><p>Cyrus Harding smiled at the sailor's idea, and, yielding to his wish, he opened exactly at
        a place where the leaves were separated by a marker.</p><p>Immediately his eyes were attracted by a cross which, made with a pencil, was placed
        against the eighth verse of the seventh chapter of the Gospel of St. Matthew. He read the
        verse, which was this:--</p><p>"For every one that asketh receiveth; and he that seeketh findeth."</p><p/></body></topic>