<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p2-chapter-7" ><title>Chapter 7</title><body><p>The settlers in Lincoln Island had now regained their dwelling, without having been obliged
        to reach it by the old opening, and were therefore spared the trouble of mason's work. It
        was certainly lucky, that at the moment they were about to set out to do so, the apes had
        been seized with that terror, no less sudden than inexplicable, which had driven them out of
        Granite House. Had the animals discovered that they were about to be attacked from another
        direction? This was the only explanation of their sudden retreat.</p><p>During the day the bodies of the apes were carried into the wood, where they were buried;
        then the settlers busied themselves in repairing the disorder caused by the intruders,
        disorder but not damage, for although they had turned everything in the rooms topsy-turvy,
        yet they had broken nothing. Neb relighted his stove, and the stores in the larder furnished
        a substantial repast, to which all did ample justice.</p><p>Jup was not forgotten, and he ate with relish some stonepine almonds and rhizome roots,
        with which he was abundantly supplied. Pencroft had unfastened his arms, but judged it best
        to have his legs tied until they were more sure of his submission.</p><p>Then, before retiring to rest, Harding and his companions seated round their table,
        discussed those plans, the execution of which was most pressing. The most important and most
        urgent was the establishment of a bridge over the Mercy, so as to form a communication with
        the southern part of the island and Granite House; then the making of an enclosure for the
        musmons or other woolly animals which they wished to capture.</p><p>These two projects would help to solve the difficulty as to their clothing, which was now
        serious. The bridge would render easy the transport of the balloon case, which would furnish
        them with linen, and the inhabitants of the enclosure would yield wool which would supply
        them with winter clothes.</p><p>As to the enclosure, it was Cyrus Harding's intention to establish it at the sources of the
        Red Creek, where the ruminants would find fresh and abundant pasture. The road between
        Prospect Heights and the sources of the stream was already partly beaten, and with a better
        cart than the first, the material could be easily conveyed to the spot, especially if they
        could manage to capture some animals to draw it.</p><p>But though there might be no inconvenience in the enclosure being so far from Granite
        House, it would not be the same with the poultry-yard, to which Neb called the attention of
        the colonists. It was indeed necessary that the birds should be close within reach of the
        cook, and no place appeared more favorable for the establishment of the said poultry-yard
        than that portion of the banks of the lake which was close to the old opening.</p><p>Water-birds would prosper there as well as others, and the couple of tinamous taken in
        their last excursion would be the first to be domesticated.</p><p>The next day, the 3rd of November, the new works were begun by the construction of the
        bridge, and all hands were required for this important task. Saws, hatchets, and hammers
        were shouldered by the settlers, who, now transformed into carpenters, descended to the
        shore.</p><p>There Pencroft observed,--</p><p>"Suppose, that during our absence, Master Jup takes it into his head to draw up the ladder
        which he so politely returned to us yesterday?"</p><p>"Let us tie its lower end down firmly," replied Cyrus Harding.</p><p>This was done by means of two stakes securely fixed in the sand. Then the settlers,
        ascending the left bank of the Mercy, soon arrived at the angle formed by the river.</p><p>There they halted, in order to ascertain if the bridge could be thrown across. The place
        appeared suitable.</p><p>In fact, from this spot, to Port Balloon, discovered the day before on the southern coast,
        there was only a distance of three miles and a half, and from the bridge to the Port, it
        would be easy to make a good cart-road which would render the communication between Granite
        House and the south of the island extremely easy.</p><p>Cyrus Harding now imparted to his companions a scheme for completely isolating Prospect
        Heights so as to shelter it from the attacks both of quadrupeds and quadrumana. In this way,
        Granite House, the Chimneys, the poultry-yard, and all the upper part of the plateau which
        was to be used for cultivation, would be protected against the depredations of animals.
        Nothing could be easier than to execute this project, and this is how the engineer intended
        to set to work.</p><p>The plateau was already defended on three sides by water-courses, either artificial or
        natural. On the northwest, by the shores of Lake Grant, from the entrance of the passage to
        the breach made in the banks of the lake for the escape of the water.</p><p>On the north, from this breach to the sea, by the new water-course which had hollowed out a
        bed for itself across the plateau and shore, above and below the fall, and it would be
        enough to dig the bed of this creek a little deeper to make it impracticable for animals, on
        all the eastern border by the sea itself, from the mouth of the aforesaid creek to the mouth
        of the Mercy.</p><p>Lastly, on the south, from the mouth to the turn of the Mercy where the bridge was to be
        established.</p><p>The western border of the plateau now remained between the turn of the river and the
        southern angle of the lake, a distance of about a mile, which was open to all comers. But
        nothing could be easier than to dig a broad deep ditch, which could be filled from the lake,
        and the overflow of which would throw itself by a rapid fall into the bed of the Mercy. The
        level of the lake would, no doubt, be somewhat lowered by this fresh discharge of its
        waters, but Cyrus Harding had ascertained that the volume of water in the Red Creek was
        considerable enough to allow of the execution of this project.</p><p>"So then," added the engineer, "Prospect Heights will become a regular island, being
        surrounded with water on all sides, and only communicating with the rest of our domain by
        the bridge which we are about to throw across the Mercy, the two little bridges already
        established above and below the fall; and, lastly, two other little bridges which must be
        constructed, one over the canal which I propose to dig, the other across to the left bank of
        the Mercy. Now, if these bridges can be raised at will, Prospect Heights will be guarded
        from any surprise."</p><p>The bridge was the most urgent work. Trees were selected, cut down, stripped of their
        branches, and cut into beams, joists, and planks. The end of the bridge which rested on the
        right bank of the Mercy was to be firm, but the other end on the left bank was to be
        movable, so that it might be raised by means of a counterpoise, as some canal bridges are
        managed.</p><p>This was certainly a considerable work, and though it was skillfully conducted, it took
        some time, for the Mercy at this place was eighty feet wide. It was therefore necessary to
        fix piles in the bed of the river so as to sustain the floor of the bridge and establish a
        pile-driver to act on the tops of these piles, which would thus form two arches and allow
        the bridge to support heavy loads.</p><p>Happily there was no want of tools with which to shape the wood, nor of iron-work to make
        it firm, nor of the ingenuity of a man who had a marvelous knowledge of the work, nor
        lastly, the zeal of his companions, who in seven months had necessarily acquired great skill
        in the use of their tools; and it must be said that not the least skilful was Gideon
        Spilett, who in dexterity almost equaled the sailor himself. "Who would ever have expected
        so much from a newspaper man!" thought Pencroft.</p><p>The construction of the Mercy bridge lasted three weeks of regular hard work. They even
        breakfasted on the scene of their labors, and the weather being magnificent, they only
        returned to Granite House to sleep.</p><p>During this period it may be stated that Master Jup grew more accustomed to his new
        masters, whose movements he always watched with very inquisitive eyes. However, as a
        precautionary measure, Pencroft did not as yet allow him complete liberty, rightly wishing
        to wait until the limits of the plateau should be settled by the projected works. Top and
        Jup were good friends and played willingly together, but Jup did everything solemnly.</p><p>On the 20th of November the bridge was finished. The movable part, balanced by the
        counterpoise, swung easily, and only a slight effort was needed to rise it; between its
        hinge and the last cross-bar on which it rested when closed, there existed a space of twenty
        feet, which was sufficiently wide to prevent any animals from crossing.</p><p>The settlers now began to talk of fetching the balloon-case, which they were anxious to
        place in perfect security; but to bring it, it would be necessary to take a cart to Port
        Balloon, and consequently, necessary to beat a road through the dense forests of the Far
        West. This would take some time. Also, Neb and Pencroft having gone to examine into the
        state of things at Port Balloon, and reported that the stock of cloth would suffer no damage
        in the grotto where it was stored, it was decided that the work at Prospect Heights should
        not be discontinued.</p><p>"That," observed Pencroft, "will enable us to establish our poultry-yard under better
        conditions, since we need have no fear of visits from foxes nor the attacks of other
        beasts."</p><p>"Then," added Neb, "we can clear the plateau, and transplant wild plants to it."</p><p>"And prepare our second corn-field!" cried the sailor with a triumphant air.</p><p>In fact, the first corn-field sown with a single grain had prospered admirably, thanks to
        Pencroft's care. It had produced the ten ears foretold by the engineer, and each ear
        containing eighty grains, the colony found itself in possession of eight hundred grains, in
        six months, which promised a double harvest each year.</p><p>These eight hundred grains, except fifty, which were prudently reserved, were to be sown in
        a new field, but with no less care than was bestowed on the single grain.</p><p>The field was prepared, then surrounded with a strong palisade, high and pointed, which
        quadrupeds would have found difficulty in leaping. As to birds, some scarecrows, due to
        Pencroft's ingenious brain, were enough to frighten them. The seven hundred and fifty grains
        deposited in very regular furrows were then left for nature to do the rest.</p><p>On the 21st of November, Cyrus Harding began to plan the canal which was to close the
        plateau on the west, from the south angle of Lake Grant to the angle of the Mercy. There was
        there two or three feet of vegetable earth, and below that granite. It was therefore
        necessary to manufacture some more nitro-glycerine, and the nitro-glycerine did its
        accustomed work. In less than a fortnight a ditch, twelve feet wide and six deep, was dug
        out in the hard ground of the plateau. A new trench was made by the same means in the rocky
        border of the lake, forming a small stream, to which they gave the name of Creek Glycerine,
        and which was thus an affluent of the Mercy. As the engineer had predicted, the level of the
        lake was lowered, though very slightly. To complete the enclosure the bed of the stream on
        the beach was considerably enlarged, and the sand supported by means of stakes.</p><p>By the end of the first fortnight of December these works were finished, and Prospect
        Heights--that is to say, a sort of irregular pentagon, having a perimeter of nearly four
        miles, surrounded by a liquid belt--was completely protected from depredators of every
        description.</p><p>During the month of December, the heat was very great. In spite of it, however, the
        settlers continued their work, and as they were anxious to possess a poultry-yard they
        forthwith commenced it.</p><p>It is useless to say that since the enclosing of the plateau had been completed, Master Jup
        had been set at liberty. He did not leave his masters, and evinced no wish to escape. He was
        a gentle animal, though very powerful and wonderfully active. He was already taught to make
        himself useful by drawing loads of wood and carting away the stones which were extracted
        from the bed of Creek Glycerine.</p><p>The poultry-yard occupied an area of two hundred square yards, on the southeastern bank of
        the lake. It was surrounded by a palisade, and in it were constructed various shelters for
        the birds which were to populate it. These were simply built of branches and divided into
        compartments, made ready for the expected guests.</p><p>The first were the two tinamous, which were not long in having a number of young ones; they
        had for companions half a dozen ducks, accustomed to the borders of the lake. Some belonged
        to the Chinese species, of which the wings open like a fan, and which by the brilliancy of
        their plumage rival the golden pheasants. A few days afterwards, Herbert snared a couple of
        gallinaceae, with spreading tails composed of long feathers, magnificent alectors, which
        soon became tame. As to pelicans, kingfishers, water-hens, they came of themselves to the
        shores of the poultry-yard, and this little community, after some disputes, cooing,
        screaming, clucking, ended by settling down peacefully, and increased in encouraging
        proportion for the future use of the colony.</p><p>Cyrus Harding, wishing to complete his performance, established a pigeon- house in a corner
        of the poultry-yard. There he lodged a dozen of those pigeons which frequented the rocks of
        the plateau. These birds soon became accustomed to returning every evening to their new
        dwelling, and showed more disposition to domesticate themselves than their congeners, the
        wood- pigeons.</p><p>Lastly, the time had come for turning the balloon-case to use, by cutting it up to make
        shirts and other articles; for as to keeping it in its present form, and risking themselves
        in a balloon filled with gas, above a sea of the limits of which they had no idea, it was
        not to be thought of.</p><p>It was necessary to bring the case to Granite House, and the colonists employed themselves
        in rendering their heavy cart lighter and more manageable. But though they had a vehicle,
        the moving power was yet to be found.</p><p>But did there not exist in the island some animal which might supply the place of the
        horse, ass, or ox? That was the question.</p><p>"Certainly," said Pencroft, "a beast of burden would be very useful to us until the captain
        has made a steam cart, or even an engine, for some day we shall have a railroad from Granite
        House to Port Balloon, with a branch line to Mount Franklin!"</p><p>One day, the 23rd of December, Neb and Top were heard shouting and barking, each apparently
        trying to see who could make the most noise. The settlers, who were busy at the Chimneys,
        ran, fearing some vexatious incident.</p><p>What did they see? Two fine animals of a large size that had imprudently ventured on the
        plateau, when the bridges were open. One would have said they were horses, or at least
        donkeys, male and female, of a fine shape, dove-colored, the legs and tail white, striped
        with black on the head and neck. They advanced quietly without showing any uneasiness, and
        gazed at the men, in whom they could not as yet recognize their future masters.</p><p>"These are onagers!" cried Herbert, "animals something between the zebra and the
        quagga!"</p><p>"Why not donkeys?" asked Neb.</p><p>"Because they have not long ears, and their shape is more graceful!"</p><p>"Donkeys or horses," interrupted Pencroft, "they are 'moving powers,' as the captain would
        say, and as such must be captured!"</p><p>The sailor, without frightening the animals, crept through the grass to the bridge over
        Creek Glycerine, lowered it, and the onagers were prisoners.</p><p>Now, should they seize them with violence and master them by force? No. It was decided that
        for a few days they should be allowed to roam freely about the plateau, where there was an
        abundance of grass, and the engineer immediately began to prepare a stable near the
        poultry-yard, in which the onagers might find food, with a good litter, and shelter during
        the night.</p><p>This done, the movements of the two magnificent creatures were left entirely free, and the
        settlers avoided even approaching them so as to terrify them. Several times, however, the
        onagers appeared to wish to leave the plateau, too confined for animals accustomed to the
        plains and forests. They were then seen following the water-barrier which everywhere
        presented itself before them, uttering short neighs, then galloping through the grass, and
        becoming calmer, they would remain entire hours gazing at the woods, from which they were
        cut off for ever!</p><p>In the meantime harness of vegetable fiber had been manufactured, and some days after the
        capture of the onagers, not only the cart was ready, but a straight road, or rather a
        cutting, had been made through the forests of the Far West, from the angle of the Mercy to
        Port Balloon. The cart might then be driven there, and towards the end of December they
        tried the onagers for the first time.</p><p>Pencroft had already coaxed the animals to come and eat out of his hand, and they allowed
        him to approach without making any difficulty, but once harnessed they reared and could with
        difficulty be held in. However, it was not long before they submitted to this new service,
        for the onager, being less refractory than the zebra, is frequently put in harness in the
        mountainous regions of Southern Africa, and it has even been acclimatized in Europe, under
        zones of a relative coolness.</p><p>On this day all the colony, except Pencroft who walked at the animals' heads, mounted the
        cart, and set out on the road to Port Balloon.</p><p>Of course they were jolted over the somewhat rough road, but the vehicle arrived without
        any accident, and was soon loaded with the case and rigging of the balloon.</p><p>At eight o'clock that evening the cart, after passing over the Mercy bridge, descended the
        left bank of the river, and stopped on the beach. The onagers being unharnessed, were thence
        led to their stable, and Pencroft before going to sleep gave vent to his feelings in a deep
        sigh of satisfaction that awoke all the echoes of Granite House.</p><p/></body></topic>