<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p2-chapter-6" ><title>Chapter 6</title><body><p>Cyrus Harding stood still, without saying a word. His companions searched in the darkness
        on the wall, in case the wind should have moved the ladder, and on the ground, thinking that
        it might have fallen down.... But the ladder had quite disappeared. As to ascertaining if a
        squall had blown it on the landing-place, half way up, that was impossible in the dark.</p><p>"If it is a joke," cried Pencroft, "it is a very stupid one! To come home and find no
        staircase to go up to your room by--that's nothing for weary men to laugh at."</p><p>Neb could do nothing but cry out "Oh! oh! oh!"</p><p>"I begin to think that very curious things happen in Lincoln Island!" said Pencroft.</p><p>"Curious?" replied Gideon Spilett, "not at all, Pencroft, nothing can be more natural. Some
        one has come during our absence, taken possession of our dwelling and drawn up the
        ladder."</p><p>"Some one," cried the sailor. "But who?"</p><p>"Who but the hunter who fired the bullet?" replied the reporter.</p><p>"Well, if there is any one up there," replied Pencroft, who began to lose patience, "I will
        give them a hail, and they must answer."</p><p>And in a stentorian voice the sailor gave a prolonged "Halloo!" which was echoed again and
        again from the cliff and rocks.</p><p>The settlers listened and they thought they heard a sort of chuckling laugh, of which they
        could not guess the origin. But no voice replied to Pencroft, who in vain repeated his
        vigorous shouts.</p><p>There was something indeed in this to astonish the most apathetic of men, and the settlers
        were not men of that description. In their situation every incident had its importance, and,
        certainly, during the seven months which they had spent on the island, they had not before
        met with anything of so surprising a character.</p><p>Be that as it may, forgetting their fatigue in the singularity of the event, they remained
        below Granite House, not knowing what to think, not knowing what to do, questioning each
        other without any hope of a satisfactory reply, every one starting some supposition each
        more unlikely than the last. Neb bewailed himself, much disappointed at not being able to
        get into his kitchen, for the provisions which they had had on their expedition were
        exhausted, and they had no means of renewing them.</p><p>"My friends," at last said Cyrus Harding, "there is only one thing to be done at present;
        wait for day, and then act according to circumstances. But let us go to the Chimneys. There
        we shall be under shelter, and if we cannot eat, we can at least sleep."</p><p>"But who is it that has played us this cool trick?" again asked Pencroft, unable to make up
        his mind to retire from the spot.</p><p>Whoever it was, the only thing practicable was to do as the engineer proposed, to go to the
        Chimneys and there wait for day. In the meanwhile Top was ordered to mount guard below the
        windows of Granite House, and when Top received an order he obeyed it without any
        questioning. The brave dog therefore remained at the foot of the cliff while his master with
        his companions sought a refuge among the rocks.</p><p>To say that the settlers, notwithstanding their fatigue, slept well on the sandy floor of
        the Chimneys would not be true. It was not only that they were extremely anxious to find out
        the cause of what had happened, whether it was the result of an accident which would be
        discovered at the return of day, or whether on the contrary it was the work of a human
        being; but they also had very uncomfortable beds. That could not be helped, however, for in
        some way or other at that moment their dwelling was occupied, and they could not possibly
        enter it.</p><p>Now Granite House was more than their dwelling, it was their warehouse. There were all the
        stores belonging to the colony, weapons, instruments, tools, ammunition, provisions, etc. To
        think that all that might be pillaged and that the settlers would have all their work to do
        over again, fresh weapons and tools to make, was a serious matter. Their uneasiness led one
        or other of them also to go out every few minutes to see if Top was keeping good watch.
        Cyrus Harding alone waited with his habitual patience, although his strong mind was
        exasperated at being confronted with such an inexplicable fact, and he was provoked at
        himself for allowing a feeling to which he could not give a name, to gain an influence over
        him. Gideon Spilett shared his feelings in this respect, and the two conversed together in
        whispers of the inexplicable circumstance which baffled even their intelligence and
        experience.</p><p>"It is a joke," said Pencroft; "it is a trick some one has played us. Well, I don't like
        such jokes, and the joker had better look out for himself, if he falls into my hands, I can
        tell him."</p><p>As soon as the first gleam of light appeared in the east, the colonists, suitably armed,
        repaired to the beach under Granite House. The rising sun now shone on the cliff and they
        could see the windows, the shutters of which were closed, through the curtains of
        foliage.</p><p>All here was in order; but a cry escaped the colonists when they saw that the door, which
        they had closed on their departure, was now wide open.</p><p>Some one had entered Granite House--there could be no more doubt about that.</p><p>The upper ladder, which generally hung from the door to the landing, was in its place, but
        the lower ladder was drawn up and raised to the threshold. It was evident that the intruders
        had wished to guard themselves against a surprise.</p><p>Pencroft hailed again.</p><p>No reply.</p><p>"The beggars," exclaimed the sailor. "There they are sleeping quietly as if they were in
        their own house. Hallo there, you pirates, brigands, robbers, sons of John Bull!"</p><p>When Pencroft, being a Yankee, treated any one to the epithet of "son of John Bull," he
        considered he had reached the last limits of insult.</p><p>The sun had now completely risen, and the whole facade of Granite House became illuminated
        by its rays; but in the interior as well as on the exterior all was quiet and calm.</p><p>The settlers asked if Granite House was inhabited or not, and yet the position of the
        ladder was sufficient to show that it was; it was also certain that the inhabitants, whoever
        they might be, had not been able to escape. But how were they to be got at?</p><p>Herbert then thought of fastening a cord to an arrow, and shooting the arrow so that it
        should pass between the first rounds of the ladder which hung from the threshold. By means
        of the cord they would then be able to draw down the ladder to the ground, and so
        re-establish the communication between the beach and Granite House. There was evidently
        nothing else to be done, and, with a little skill, this method might succeed. Very
        fortunately bows and arrows had been left at the Chimneys, where they also found a quantity
        of light hibiscus cord. Pencroft fastened this to a well-feathered arrow. Then Herbert
        fixing it to his bow, took a careful aim for the lower part of the ladder.</p><p>Cyrus Harding, Gideon Spilett, Pencroft, and Neb drew back, so as to see if anything
        appeared at the windows. The reporter lifted his gun to his shoulder and covered the
        door.</p><p>The bow was bent, the arrow flew, taking the cord with it, and passed between the two last
        rounds.</p><p>The operation had succeeded.</p><p>Herbert immediately seized the end of the cord, but, at that moment when he gave it a pull
        to bring down the ladder, an arm, thrust suddenly out between the wall and the door, grasped
        it and dragged it inside Granite House.</p><p>"The rascals!" shouted the sailor. "If a ball can do anything for you, you shall not have
        long to wait for it.</p><p>"But who was it?" asked Neb.</p><p>"Who was it? Didn't you see?"</p><p>"No."</p><p>"It was a monkey, a sapajou, an orangoutang, a baboon, a gorilla, a sagoin. Our dwelling
        has been invaded by monkeys, who climbed up the ladder during our absence."</p><p>And, at this moment, as if to bear witness to the truth of the sailor's words, two or three
        quadrumana showed themselves at the windows, from which they had pushed back the shutters,
        and saluted the real proprietors of the place with a thousand hideous grimaces.</p><p>"I knew that it was only a joke," cried Pencroft; "but one of the jokers shall pay the
        penalty for the rest."</p><p>So saying, the sailor, raising his piece, took a rapid aim at one of the monkeys and fired.
        All disappeared, except one who fell mortally wounded on the beach. This monkey, which was
        of a large size, evidently belonged to the first order of the quadrumana. Whether this was a
        chimpanzee, an orangoutang, or a gorilla, he took rank among the anthropoid apes, who are so
        called from their resemblance to the human race. However, Herbert declared it to be an
        orangoutang.</p><p>"What a magnificent beast!" cried Neb.</p><p>"Magnificent, if you like," replied Pencroft; "but still I do not see how we are to get
        into our house."</p><p>"Herbert is a good marksman," said the reporter, "and his bow is here. He can try
        again."</p><p>"Why, these apes are so cunning," returned Pencroft; "they won't show themselves again at
        the windows and so we can't kill them; and when I think of the mischief they may do in the
        rooms and storehouse--"</p><p>"Have patience," replied Harding; "these creatures cannot keep us long at bay."</p><p>"I shall not be sure of that till I see them down here," replied the sailor. "And now,
        captain, do you know how many dozens of these fellows are up there?"</p><p>It was difficult to reply to Pencroft, and as for the young boy making another attempt,
        that was not easy; for the lower part of the ladder had been drawn again into the door, and
        when another pull was given, the line broke and the ladder remained firm. The case was
        really perplexing. Pencroft stormed. There was a comic side to the situation, but he did not
        think it funny at all. It was certain that the settlers would end by reinstating themselves
        in their domicile and driving out the intruders, but when and how? this is what they were
        not able to say.</p><p>Two hours passed, during which the apes took care not to show themselves, but they were
        still there, and three or four times a nose or a paw was poked out at the door or windows,
        and was immediately saluted by a gun- shot.</p><p>"Let us hide ourselves," at last said the engineer. "Perhaps the apes will think we have
        gone quite away and will show themselves again. Let Spilett and Herbert conceal themselves
        behind those rocks and fire on all that may appear."</p><p>The engineer's orders were obeyed, and while the reporter and the lad, the best marksmen in
        the colony, posted themselves in a good position, but out of the monkeys' sight, Neb,
        Pencroft, and Cyrus climbed the plateau and entered the forest in order to kill some game,
        for it was now time for breakfast and they had no provisions remaining.</p><p>In half an hour the hunters returned with a few rock pigeons, which they roasted as well as
        they could. Not an ape had appeared. Gideon Spilett and Herbert went to take their share of
        the breakfast, leaving Top to watch under the windows. They then, having eaten, returned to
        their post.</p><p>Two hours later, their situation was in no degree improved. The quadrumana gave no sign of
        existence, and it might have been supposed that they had disappeared; but what seemed more
        probable was that, terrified by the death of one of their companions, and frightened by the
        noise of the firearms, they had retreated to the back part of the house or probably even
        into the store-room. And when they thought of the valuables which this storeroom contained,
        the patience so much recommended by the engineer, fast changed into great irritation, and
        there certainly was room for it.</p><p>"Decidedly it is too bad," said the reporter; "and the worst of it is, there is no way of
        putting an end to it."</p><p>"But we must drive these vagabonds out somehow," cried the sailor. "We could soon get the
        better of them, even if there are twenty of the rascals; but for that, we must meet them
        hand to hand. Come now, is there no way of getting at them?"</p><p>"Let us try to enter Granite House by the old opening at the lake," replied the
        engineer.</p><p>"Oh!" shouted the sailor, "and I never thought of that."</p><p>This was in reality the only way by which to penetrate into Granite House so as to fight
        with and drive out the intruders. The opening was, it is true, closed up with a wall of
        cemented stones, which it would be necessary to sacrifice, but that could easily be rebuilt.
        Fortunately, Cyrus Harding had not as yet effected his project of hiding this opening by
        raising the waters of the lake, for the operation would then have taken some time.</p><p>It was already past twelve o'clock, when the colonists, well armed and provided with picks
        and spades, left the Chimneys, passed beneath the windows of Granite House, after telling
        Top to remain at his post, and began to ascend the left bank of the Mercy, so as to reach
        Prospect Heights.</p><p>But they had not made fifty steps in this direction, when they heard the dog barking
        furiously.</p><p>And all rushed down the bank again.</p><p>Arrived at the turning, they saw that the situation had changed.</p><p>In fact, the apes, seized with a sudden panic, from some unknown cause, were trying to
        escape. Two or three ran and clambered from one window to another with the agility of
        acrobats. They were not even trying to replace the ladder, by which it would have been easy
        to descend; perhaps in their terror they had forgotten this way of escape. The colonists,
        now being able to take aim without difficulty, fired. Some, wounded or killed, fell back
        into the rooms, uttering piercing cries. The rest, throwing themselves out, were dashed to
        pieces in their fall, and in a few minutes, so far as they knew, there was not a living
        quadrumana in Granite House.</p><p>At this moment the ladder was seen to slip over the threshold, then unroll and fall to the
        ground.</p><p>"Hullo!" cried the sailor, "this is queer!"</p><p>"Very strange!" murmured the engineer, leaping first up the ladder.</p><p>"Take care, captain!" cried Pencroft, "perhaps there are still some of these rascals.</p><p>"We shall soon see," replied the engineer, without stopping however.</p><p>All his companions followed him, and in a minute they had arrived at the threshold. They
        searched everywhere. There was no one in the rooms nor in the storehouse, which had been
        respected by the band of quadrumana.</p><p>"Well now, and the ladder," cried the sailor; "who can the gentleman have been who sent us
        that down?"</p><p>But at that moment a cry was heard, and a great orang, who had hidden himself in the
        passage, rushed into the room, pursued by Neb.</p><p>"Ah, the robber!" cried Pencroft.</p><p>And hatchet in hand, he was about to cleave the head of the animal, when Cyrus Harding
        seized his arm, saying,--</p><p>"Spare him, Pencroft."</p><p>"Pardon this rascal?"</p><p>"Yes! it was he who threw us the ladder!"</p><p>And the engineer said this in such a peculiar voice that it was difficult to know whether
        he spoke seriously or not.</p><p>Nevertheless, they threw themselves on the orang, who defended himself gallantly, but was
        soon overpowered and bound.</p><p>"There!" said Pencroft. "And what shall we make of him, now we've got him?"</p><p>"A servant!" replied Herbert.</p><p>The lad was not joking in saying this, for he knew how this intelligent race could be
        turned to account.</p><p>The settlers then approached the ape and gazed at it attentively. He belonged to the family
        of anthropoid apes, of which the facial angle is not much inferior to that of the
        Australians and Hottentots. It was an orangoutang, and as such, had neither the ferocity of
        the gorilla, nor the stupidity of the baboon. It is to this family of the anthropoid apes
        that so many characteristics belong which prove them to be possessed of an almost human
        intelligence. Employed in houses, they can wait at table, sweep rooms, brush clothes, clean
        boots, handle a knife, fork, and spoon properly, and even drink wine . . . doing everything
        as well as the best servant that ever walked upon two legs. Buffon possessed one of these
        apes, who served him for a long time as a faithful and zealous servant.</p><p>The one which had been seized in the hall of Granite House was a great fellow, six feet
        high, with an admirably poportioned frame, a broad chest, head of a moderate size, the
        facial angle reaching sixty-five degrees, round skull, projecting nose, skin covered with
        soft glossy hair, in short, a fine specimen of the anthropoids. His eyes, rather smaller
        than human eyes, sparkled with intelligence; his white teeth glittered under his mustache,
        and he wore a little curly brown beard.</p><p>"A handsome fellow!" said Pencroft; "if we only knew his language, we could talk to
        him."</p><p>"But, master," said Neb, "are you serious? Are we going to take him as a servant?"</p><p>"Yes, Neb," replied the engineer, smiling. "But you must not be jealous."</p><p>"And I hope he will make an excellent servant," added Herbert. "He appears young, and will
        be easy to educate, and we shall not be obliged to use force to subdue him, nor draw his
        teeth, as is sometimes done. He will soon grow fond of his masters if they are kind to
        him."</p><p>"And they will be," replied Pencroft, who had forgotten all his rancor against "the
        jokers."</p><p>Then, approaching the orang,--</p><p>"Well, old boy!" he asked, "how are you?"</p><p>The orang replied by a little grunt which did not show any anger.</p><p>"You wish to join the colony?" again asked the sailor. "You are going to enter the service
        of Captain Cyrus Harding?"</p><p>Another respondent grunt was uttered by the ape.</p><p>"And you will be satisfied with no other wages than your food?"</p><p>Third affirmative grunt.</p><p>"This conversation is slightly monotonous," observed Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"So much the better," replied Pencroft; "the best servants are those who talk the least.
        And then, no wages, do you hear, my boy? We will give you no wages at first, but we will
        double them afterwards if we are pleased with you."</p><p>Thus the colony was increased by a new member. As to his name the sailor begged that in
        memory of another ape which he had known, he might be called Jupiter, and Jup for short.</p><p>And so, without more ceremony, Master Jup was installed in Granite House.</p><p/></body></topic>