<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p2-chapter-12" ><title>Chapter 12</title><body><p>In the evening the hunters returned, having enjoyed good sport, and being literally loaded
        with game; indeed, they had as much as four men could possibly carry. Top wore a necklace of
        teal and Jup wreaths of snipe round his body.</p><p>"Here, master," cried Neb; "here's something to employ our time! Preserved and made into
        pies we shall have a welcome store! But I must have some one to help me. I count on you,
        Pencroft."</p><p>"No, Neb," replied the sailor; "I have the rigging of the vessel to finish and to look
        after, and you will have to do without me."</p><p>"And you, Mr. Herbert?"</p><p>"I must go to the corral to-morrow, Neb," replied the lad.</p><p>"It will be you then, Mr. Spilett, who will help me?"</p><p>"To oblige you, Neb, I will," replied the reporter; "but I warn you that if you disclose
        your receipts to me, I shall publish them."</p><p>"Whenever you like, Mr. Spilett," replied Neb; "whenever you like."</p><p>And so the next day Gideon Spilett became Neb's assistant and was installed in his culinary
        laboratory. The engineer had previously made known to him the result of the exploration
        which he had made the day before, and on this point the reporter shared Harding's opinion,
        that although he had found nothing, a secret still remained to be discovered!</p><p>The frost continued for another week, and the settlers did not leave Granite House unless
        to look after the poultry-yard. The dwelling was filled with appetizing odors, which were
        emitted from the learned manipulation of Neb and the reporter. But all the results of the
        chase were not made into preserved provisions; and as the game kept perfectly in the intense
        cold, wild duck and other fowl were eaten fresh, and declared superior to all other aquatic
        birds in the known world.</p><p>During this week, Pencroft, aided by Herbert, who handled the sailmaker's needle with much
        skill, worked with such energy that the sails of the vessel were finished. There was no want
        of cordage. Thanks to the rigging which had been discovered with the case of the balloon,
        the ropes and cables from the net were all of good quality, and the sailor turned them all
        to account. To the sails were attached strong bolt ropes, and there still remained enough
        from which to make the halyards, shrouds, and sheets, etc. The blocks were manufactured by
        Cyrus Harding under Pencroft's directions by means of the turning lathe. It therefore
        happened that the rigging was entirely prepared before the vessel was finished. Pencroft
        also manufactured a flag, that flag so dear to every true American, containing the stars and
        stripes of their glorious Union. The colors for it were supplied from certain plants used in
        dyeing, and which were very abundant in the island; only to the thirty-seven stars,
        representing the thirty- seven States of the Union, which shine on the American flag, the
        sailor added a thirty-eighth, the star of "the State of Lincoln," for he considered his
        island as already united to the great republic. "And," said he, "it is so already in heart,
        if not in deed!"</p><p>In the meantime, the flag was hoisted at the central window of Granite House, and the
        settlers saluted it with three cheers.</p><p>The cold season was now almost at an end, and it appeared as if this second winter was to
        pass without any unusual occurrence, when on the night of the 11th of August, the plateau of
        Prospect Heights was menaced with complete destruction.</p><p>After a busy day the colonists were sleeping soundly, when towards four o'clock in the
        morning they were suddenly awakened by Top's barking.</p><p>The dog was not this time barking near the mouth of the well, but at the threshold of the
        door, at which he was scratching as if he wished to burst it open. Jup was also uttering
        piercing cries.</p><p>"Hello, Top!" cried Neb, who was the first awake. But the dog continued to bark more
        furiously than ever.</p><p>"What's the matter now?" asked Harding.</p><p>And all dressing in haste rushed to the windows, which they opened.</p><p>Beneath their eyes was spread a sheet of snow which looked gray in the dim light. The
        settlers could see nothing, but they heard a singular yelping noise away in the darkness. It
        was evident that the beach had been invaded by a number of animals which could not be
        seen.</p><p>"What are they?" cried Pencroft.</p><p>"Wolves, jaguars, or apes?" replied Neb.</p><p>"They have nearly reached the plateau," said the reporter.</p><p>"And our poultry-yard," exclaimed Herbert, "and our garden!"</p><p>"Where can they have crossed?" asked Pencroft.</p><p>"They must have crossed the bridge on the shore," replied the engineer, "which one of us
        must have forgotten to close."</p><p>"True," said Spilett, "I remember having left it open."</p><p>"A fine job you have made of it, Mr. Spilett," cried the sailor.</p><p>"What is done cannot be undone," replied Cyrus Harding. "We must consult what it will now
        be best to do."</p><p>Such were the questions and answers which were rapidly exchanged between Harding and his
        companions. It was certain that the bridge had been crossed, that the shore had been invaded
        by animals, and that whatever they might be they could by ascending the left bank of the
        Mercy reach Prospect Heights. They must therefore be advanced against quickly and fought
        with if necessary.</p><p>"But what are these beasts?" was asked a second time, as the yelpings were again heard more
        loudly than before. These yelps made Herbert start, and he remembered having heard them
        before during his first visit to the sources of the Red Creek.</p><p>"They are colpeo foxes!" he exclaimed.</p><p>"Forward!" shouted the sailor.</p><p>And all arming themselves with hatchets, carbines, and revolvers, threw themselves into the
        lift and soon set foot on the shore.</p><p>Colpeos are dangerous animals when in great numbers and irritated by hunger, nevertheless
        the colonists did not hesitate to throw themselves into the midst of the troop, and their
        first shots vividly lighting up the darkness made their assailants draw back.</p><p>The chief thing was to hinder these plunderers from reaching the plateau, for the garden
        and the poultry-yard would then have been at their mercy, and immense, perhaps irreparable
        mischief, would inevitably be the result, especially with regard to the corn-field. But as
        the invasion of the plateau could only be made by the left bank of the Mercy, it was
        sufficient to oppose the colpeos on the narrow bank between the river and the cliff of
        granite.</p><p>This was plain to all, and, by Cyrus Harding's orders, they reached the spot indicated by
        him, while the colpeos rushed fiercely through the gloom. Harding, Gideon Spilett, Herbert,
        Pencroft and Neb posted themselves in impregnable line. Top, his formidable jaws open,
        preceded the colonists, and he was followed by Jup, armed with knotty cudgel, which he
        brandished like a club.</p><p>The night was extremely dark, it was only by the flashes from the revolvers as each person
        fired that they could see their assailants, who were at least a hundred in number, and whose
        eyes were glowing like hot coals.</p><p>"They must not pass!" shouted Pencroft.</p><p>"They shall not pass!" returned the engineer.</p><p>But if they did not pass it was not for want of having attempted it. Those in the rear
        pushed on the foremost assailants, and it was an incessant struggle with revolvers and
        hatchets. Several colpeos already lay dead on the ground, but their number did not appear to
        diminish, and it might have been supposed that reinforcements were continually arriving over
        the bridge.</p><p>The colonists were soon obliged to fight at close quarters, not without receiving some
        wounds, though happily very slight ones. Herbert had, with a shot from his revolver, rescued
        Neb, on whose back a colpeo had sprung like a tiger cat. Top fought with actual fury, flying
        at the throats of the foxes and strangling them instantaneously. Jup wielded his weapon
        valiantly, and it was in vain that they endeavored to keep him in the rear. Endowed
        doubtless with sight which enabled him to pierce the obscurity, he was always in the thick
        of the fight uttering from time to time--a sharp hissing sound, which was with him the sign
        of great rejoicing.</p><p>At one moment he advanced so far, that by the light from a revolver he was seen surrounded
        by five or six large colpeos, with whom he was coping with great coolness.</p><p>However, the struggle was ended at last, and victory was on the side of the settlers, but
        not until they had fought for two long hours! The first signs of the approach of day
        doubtless determined the retreat of their assailants, who scampered away towards the North,
        passing over the bridge, which Neb ran immediately to raise. When day had sufficiently
        lighted up the field of battle, the settlers counted as many as fifty dead bodies scattered
        about on the shore.</p><p>"And Jup!" cried Pencroft; "where is Jup?" Jup had disappeared. His friend Neb called him,
        and for the first time Jup did not reply to his friend's call.</p><p>Everyone set out in search of Jup, trembling lest he should be found among the slain; they
        cleared the place of the bodies which stained the snow with their blood. Jup was found in
        the midst of a heap of colpeos whose broken jaws and crushed bodies showed that they had to
        do with the terrible club of the intrepid animal.</p><p>Poor Jup still held in his hand the stump of his broken cudgel, but deprived of his weapon
        he had been overpowered by numbers, and his chest was covered with severe wounds.</p><p>"He is living," cried Neb, who was bending over him.</p><p>"And we will save him," replied the sailor. "We will nurse him as if he was one of
        ourselves."</p><p>It appeared as if Jup understood, for he leaned his head on Pencroft's shoulder as if to
        thank him. The sailor was wounded himself, but his wound was insignificant, as were those of
        his companions; for thanks to their firearms they had been almost always able to keep their
        assailants at a distance. It was therefore only the orang whose condition was serious.</p><p>Jup, carried by Neb and Pencroft, was placed in the lift, and only a slight moan now and
        then escaped his lips. He was gently drawn up to Granite House. There he was laid on a
        mattress taken from one of the beds, and his wounds were bathed with the greatest care. It
        did not appear that any vital part had been reached, but Jup was very weak from loss of
        blood, and a high fever soon set in after his wounds had been dressed. He was laid down,
        strict diet was imposed, "just like a real person," as Neb said, and they made him swallow
        several cups of a cooling drink, for which the ingredients were supplied from the vegetable
        medicine chest of Granite House. Jup was at first restless, but his breathing gradually
        became more regular, and he was left sleeping quietly. From time to time Top, walking on
        tip-toe, as one might say, came to visit his friend, and seemed to approve of all the care
        that had been taken of him. One of Jup's hands hung over the side of his bed, and Top licked
        it with a sympathizing air.</p><p>They employed the day in interring the dead, who were dragged to the forest of the Far
        West, and there buried deep.</p><p>This attack, which might have had such serious consequences, was a lesson to the settlers,
        who from this time never went to bed until one of their number had made sure that all the
        bridges were raised, and that no invasion was possible.</p><p>However, Jup, after having given them serious anxiety for several days, began to recover.
        His constitution brought him through, the fever gradually subsided, and Gideon Spilett, who
        was a bit of a doctor, pronounced him quite out of danger. On the 16th of August, Jup began
        to eat. Neb made him nice little sweet dishes, which the invalid devoured with great relish,
        for if he had a pet failing it was that of being somewhat of a gourmend, and Neb had never
        done anything to cure him of this fault.</p><p>"What would you have?" said he to Gideon Spilett, who sometimes expostulated with him for
        spoiling the ape. "Poor Jup has no other pleasure than that of the palate, and I am only too
        glad to be able to reward his services in this way!"</p><p>Ten days after taking to his bed, on the 21st of August, Master Jup arose. His wounds were
        healed, and it was evident that he would not be long in regaining his usual strength and
        agility. Like all convalescents, he was tremendously hungry, and the reporter allowed him to
        eat as much as he liked, for he trusted to that instinct, which is too often wanting in
        reasoning beings, to keep the orang from any excess. Neb was delighted to see his pupil's
        appetite returning.</p><p>"Eat away, my Jup," said he, "and don't spare anything; you have shed your blood for us,
        and it is the least I can do to make you strong again!"</p><p>On the 25th of August Neb's voice was heard calling to his companions.</p><p>"Captain, Mr. Spilett, Mr. Herbert, Pencroft, come! come!"</p><p>The colonists, who were together in the dining-room, rose at Neb's call, who was then in
        Jup's room.</p><p>"What's the matter?" asked the reporter.</p><p>"Look," replied Neb, with a shout of laughter. And what did they see? Master Jup smoking
        calmly and seriously, sitting crosslegged like a Turk at the entrance to Granite House!</p><p>"My pipe," cried Pencroft. "He has taken my pipe! Hello, my honest Jup, I make you a
        present of it! Smoke away, old boy, smoke away!"</p><p>And Jup gravely puffed out clouds of smoke which seemed to give him great satisfaction.
        Harding did not appear to be much astonished at this incident, and he cited several examples
        of tame apes, to whom the use of tobacco had become quite familiar.</p><p>But from this day Master Jup had a pipe of his own, the sailor's ex-pipe, which was hung in
        his room near his store of tobacco. He filled it himself, lighted it with a glowing coal,
        and appeared to be the happiest of quadrumana. It may readily be understood that this
        similarity of tastes of Jup and Pencroft served to tighten the bonds of friendship which
        already existed between the honest ape and the worthy sailor.</p><p>"Perhaps he is really a man," said Pencroft sometimes to Neb. "Should you be surprised to
        hear him beginning to speak to us some day?"</p><p>"My word, no," replied Neb. "What astonishes me is that he hasn't spoken to us before, for
        now he wants nothing but speech!"</p><p>"It would amuse me all the same," resumed the sailor, "if some fine day he said to me,
        'Suppose we change pipes, Pencroft.'"</p><p>"Yes," replied Neb, "what a pity he was born dumb!"</p><p>With the month of September the winter ended, and the works were again eagerly commenced.
        The building of the vessel advanced rapidly, she was already completely decked over, and all
        the inside parts of the hull were firmly united with ribs bent by means of steam, which
        answered all the purposes of a mold.</p><p>As there was no want of wood, Pencroft proposed to the engineer to give a double lining to
        the hull, to insure the strength of the vessel.</p><p>Harding, not knowing what the future might have in store for them, approved the sailor's
        idea of making the craft as strong as possible. The interior and deck of the vessel was
        entirely finished towards the 15th of September. For calking the seams they made oakum of
        dry seaweed, which was hammered in between the planks; then these seams were covered with
        boiling tar, which was obtained in great abundance from the pines in the forest.</p><p>The management of the vessel was very simple. She had from the first been ballasted with
        heavy blocks of granite walled up, in a bed of lime, twelve thousand pounds of which they
        stowed away.</p><p>A deck was placed over this ballast, and the interior was divided into two cabins; two
        benches extended along them and served also as lockers. The foot of the mast supported the
        partition which separated the two cabins, which were reached by two hatchways let into the
        deck.</p><p>Pencroft had no trouble in finding a tree suitable for the mast. He chose a straight young
        fir, with no knots, and which he had only to square at the step, and round off at the top.
        The ironwork of the mast, the rudder and the hull had been roughly but strongly forged at
        the Chimneys. Lastly, yards, masts, boom, spars, oars, etc., were all furnished by the first
        week in October, and it was agreed that a trial trip should be taken round the island, so as
        to ascertain how the vessel would behave at sea, and how far they might depend upon her.</p><p>During all this time the necessary works had not been neglected. The corral was enlarged,
        for the flock of musmons and goats had been increased by a number of young ones, who had to
        be housed and fed. The colonists had paid visits also to the oyster bed, the warren, the
        coal and iron mines, and to the till then unexplored districts of the Far West forest, which
        abounded in game. Certain indigenous plants were discovered, and those fit for immediate use
        contributed to vary the vegetable stores of Granite House.</p><p>They were a species of ficoide, some similar to those of the Cape, with eatable fleshy
        leaves, others bearing seeds containing a sort of flour.</p><p>On the 10th of October the vessel was launched. Pencroft was radiant with joy, the
        operation was perfectly successful; the boat completely rigged, having been pushed on
        rollers to the water's edge, was floated by the rising tide, amid the cheers of the
        colonists, particularly of Pencroft, who showed no modesty on this occasion. Besides his
        importance was to last beyond the finishing of the vessel, since, after having built her, he
        was to command her. The grade of captain was bestowed upon him with the approbation of all.
        To satisfy Captain Pencroft, it was now necessary to give a name to the vessel, and, after
        many propositions had been discussed, the votes were all in favor of the "Bonadventure." As
        soon as the "Bonadventure" had been lifted by the rising tide, it was seen that she lay
        evenly in the water, and would be easily navigated. However, the trial trip was to be made
        that very day, by an excursion off the coast. The weather was fine, the breeze fresh, and
        the sea smooth, especially towards the south coast, for the wind was blowing from the
        northwest.</p><p>"All hands on board," shouted Pencroft; but breakfast was first necessary, and it was
        thought best to take provisions on board, in the event of their excursion being prolonged
        until the evening.</p><p>Cyrus Harding was equally anxious to try the vessel, the model of which had originated with
        him, although on the sailor's advice he had altered some parts of it, but he did not share
        Pencroft's confidence in her, and as the latter had not again spoken of the voyage to Tabor
        Island, Harding hoped he had given it up. He would have indeed great reluctance in letting
        two or three of his companions venture so far in so small a boat, which was not of more than
        fifteen tons' burden.</p><p>At half-past ten everybody was on board, even Top and Jup, and Herbert weighed the anchor,
        which was fast in the sand near the mouth of the Mercy. The sail was hoisted, the Lincolnian
        flag floated from the masthead, and the "Bonadventure," steered by Pencroft, stood out to
        sea.</p><p>The wind blowing out of Union Bay she ran before it, and thus showed her owners, much to
        their satisfaction, that she possessed a remarkably fast pair of heels, according to
        Pencroft's mode of speaking. After having doubled Flotsam Point and Claw Cape, the captain
        kept her close hauled, so as to sail along the southern coast of the island, when it was
        found she sailed admirably within five points of the wind. All hands were enchanted, they
        had a good vessel, which, in case of need, would be of great service to them, and with fine
        weather and a fresh breeze the voyage promised to be charming.</p><p>Pencroft now stood off the shore, three or four miles across from Port Balloon. The island
        then appeared in all its extent and under a new aspect, with the varied panorama of its
        shore from Claw Cape to Reptile End, the forests in which dark firs contrasted with the
        young foliage of other trees and overlooked the whole, and Mount Franklin whose lofty head
        was still whitened with snow.</p><p>"How beautiful it is!" cried Herbert.</p><p>"Yes, our island is beautiful and good," replied Pencroft. "I love it as I loved my poor
        mother. It received us poor and destitute, and now what is wanting to us five fellows who
        fell on it from the sky?"</p><p>"Nothing," replied Neb; "nothing, captain."</p><p>And the two brave men gave three tremendous cheers in honor of their island!</p><p>During all this time Gideon Spilett, leaning against the mast, sketched the panorama which
        was developed before his eyes.</p><p>Cyrus Harding gazed on it in silence.</p><p>"Well, Captain Harding," asked Pencroft, "what do you think of our vessel?"</p><p>"She appears to behave well," replied the engineer.</p><p>"Good! And do you think now that she could undertake a voyage of some extent?"</p><p>"What voyage, Pencroft?"</p><p>"One to Tabor Island, for instance."</p><p>"My friend," replied Harding, "I think that in any pressing emergency we need not hesitate
        to trust ourselves to the 'Bonadventure' even for a longer voyage; but you know I should see
        you set off to Tabor Island with great uneasiness, since nothing obliges you to go
        there."</p><p>"One likes to know one's neighbors," returned the sailor, who was obstinate in his idea.
        "Tabor Island is our neighbor, and the only one! Politeness requires us to go at least to
        pay a visit."</p><p>"By Jove," said Spilett, "our friend Pencroft has become very particular about the
        proprieties all at once!"</p><p>"I am not particular about anything at all," retorted the sailor, who was rather vexed by
        the engineer's opposition, but who did not wish to cause him anxiety.</p><p>"Consider, Pencroft," resumed Harding, "you cannot go alone to Tabor Island."</p><p>"One companion will be enough for me."</p><p>"Even so," replied the engineer, "you will risk depriving the colony of Lincoln Island of
        two settlers out of five."</p><p>"Out of six," answered Pencroft; "you forget Jup."</p><p>"Out of seven," added Neb; "Top is quite worth another."</p><p>"There is no risk at all in it, captain," replied Pencroft.</p><p>"That is possible, Pencroft; but I repeat it is to expose ourselves uselessly."</p><p>The obstinate sailor did not reply, and let the conversation drop, quite determined to
        resume it again. But he did not suspect that an incident would come to his aid and change
        into an act of humanity that which was at first only a doubtful whim.</p><p>After standing off the shore the "Bonadventure" again approached it in the direction of
        Port Balloon. It was important to ascertain the channels between the sandbanks and reefs,
        that buoys might be laid down since this little creek was to be the harbor.</p><p>They were not more than half a mile from the coast, and it was necessary to tack to beat
        against the wind. The "Bonadventure" was then going at a very moderate rate, as the breeze,
        partly intercepted by the high land, scarcely swelled her sails, and the sea, smooth as
        glass, was only rippled now and then by passing gusts.</p><p>Herbert had stationed himself in the bows that he might indicate the course to be followed
        among the channels, when all at once he shouted,--</p><p>"Luff, Pencroft, luff!"</p><p>"What's the matter," replied the sailor; "a rock?"</p><p>"No--wait," said Herbert; "I don't quite see. Luff again--right--now."</p><p>So saying, Herbert, leaning over the side, plunged his arm into the water, and pulled it
        out, exclaiming,--</p><p>"A bottle!"</p><p>He held in his hand a corked bottle which he had just seized a few cables' length from the
        shore.</p><p>Cyrus Harding took the bottle. Without uttering a single word he drew the cork, and took
        from it a damp paper, on which were written these words:--</p><p>"Castaway . . . . Tabor island: 153deg W. long., 37deg 11' S. lat."</p><p/></body></topic>