<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23486">
   <title>BROWN, JOHN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWN, JOHN--> (1800-1859), American abolitionist, leader of the
  famous attack upon Harper's Ferry, in 1859, was born on the 9th of May
  1800, at Torrington, Connecticut. He is said to have been descended from
  Peter Brown, who went to America in the <i>Mayflower</i>, and he was the
  grandson of Captain John Brown, who served in the War of Independence. He
  was taken by his father, Owen Brown, to Hudson, Ohio, in 1805. At the age
  of eighteen he began to prepare himself for the Congregational ministry,
  but soon changed his mind and turned his attention to land surveying. He
  engaged successively in the tanning business, in sheep-raising, and in
  the wool trade, but met with little success and in 1842, at Akron, Ohio,
  became bankrupt. In 1849, after having lived in Ohio, Pennsylvania, and
  Massachusetts, he removed to North Elba, N.Y., where he engaged in
  farming on part of the land which was being given in small tracts, by its
  owner Gerrit Smith, to negro settlers. Long before this he had conceived
  a strong hatred for the institution of slavery, and had determined to do
  what he could to bring about its destruction. In 1854 five of his sons
  removed to Kansas, where the violent conflict was beginning between the
  "free-state" and the pro-slavery settlers, and in the following year
  Brown, leaving the rest of his family at North Elba, joined them,
  settling near Osawatomie and immediately becoming a conspicuous figure in
  the border warfare. His name became particularly well known in connexion
  with the so-called "Pottawatomie massacre," the killing in cold blood, on
  the 25th of May 1856, by men under his orders, of five pro-slavery
  settlers in retaliation for the murder a short time previously of five
  "free-state" settlers. He also on the 2nd of June, at the head of about
  thirty men, captured Captain H. C. Pate and twenty-two pro-slavery men at
  Black Jack, and on the 30th of August 1856, with a small body of
  supporters, vigorously resisted an attack of a superior pro-slavery force
  upon Osawatomie. Brown then visited the Eastern states for the purpose of
  raising money to be used in the Kansas struggle and of arousing the
  people against slavery. After spending a short time in Kansas, in
  1858-1859 he proceeded to carry out a long-cherished scheme for
  facilitating the escape of fugitive slaves by establishing in the
  mountains of Virginia a stronghold in which such fugitives could take
  refuge and defend themselves against their pursuers. At Chatham, Canada,
  with eleven white and thirty-five negro associates, he adopted a
  "Provisional Constitution and Ordinance for the People of the United
  States." Brown was elected commander-in-chief, and from among this group
  a secretary of state, a secretary of war, a secretary of the treasury,
  and members of Congress were chosen. Later, with only twenty-two men
  supplied with arms furnished by the Massachusetts-Kansas committee, and
  with funds contributed (in ignorance of Brown's plans) by his intimate
  associates, Theodore Parker, George L. Stearns, T. W. Higginson, and F.
  B. Sanborn, all of Boston, and Gerrit Smith, of Peterboro, New York, he
  removed to a farm near Harper's Ferry, the site of a Federal arsenal,
  which he intended to capture as a preliminary to the carrying out of the
  main part of his plan. On the night of the 16th of October 1859, with
  only eighteen men, five of whom were negroes, he made the attack, easily
  capturing the arsenal and taking about sixty of the leading citizens
  prisoners to be used as hostages. On the following morning Brown and his
  followers were vigorously attacked, and on the 18th—a small force
  of United States marines under Colonel Robert E. Lee having
  arrived—were overpowered, Brown being seriously wounded after he
  had surrendered. Of the twenty-two men who had participated in the raid,
  ten were killed, seven were taken prisoners, and five escaped. On the
  other side five were killed and nine wounded. Brown was committed to the
  Charlestown, Virginia (now West Virginia), gaol on the 19th of October;
  on the 27th his trial began; on the 31st he was convicted of "treason,
  and conspiring and advising with slaves and other rebels, and murder in
  the first degree"; and on the 2nd of December he was hanged at
  Charlestown. His fellow-prisoners were likewise hanged soon afterwards.
  Brown was buried at North Elba, New York. The attack upon Harper's Ferry
  created widespread excitement, particularly in the Southern states; and
  among the abolitionists in the North Brown was looked upon as a martyr to
  their cause. Shortly after his death a famous popular song became widely
  current in the North, beginning:—</p>
      <fig outputclass="poem">
         <lines>
      John Brown's body lies a-mouldering in the grave,

      But his soul goes marching on.

    </lines>
      </fig>
      <p>Intensely religious in his nature, Brown possessed something of the
  gloomy fanaticism of his Puritan ancestors. The secret of his whole
  career lies in his emphatic conviction, to use the <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page661">[v.04 p.0661]</ph>words of
  Wendell Phillips, that he had "letters of marque from God"; that he had a
  divine commission to destroy slavery by violent means. He scouted the
  "milk and water principles" of the milder abolitionists, advocated
  vigorous resistance to the slave power, and expressed his ideas by
  actions rather than by words. It now seems that this policy aided very
  little in making Kansas a free state, and that the attack on Harper's
  Ferry, while creating much feeling at the moment, had very little effect
  on the subsequent course of events. It is safe to assume that secession
  and civil war would have followed the election of Lincoln if there had
  been no such raid into Virginia.</p>
      <p>Brown was twice married and was the father of twenty children, eight
  of whom died in early childhood. His sons aided him in all his
  undertakings, two of them being killed at Harper's Ferry; and Owen Brown,
  who died in 1889, was long the only survivor of the attack.</p>
      <p>See the life (1910) by O. G. Villard, and F. B. Sanborn's <i>Life and
  Letters of John Brown</i> (Boston, 1885); R. J. Hinton's <i>John Brown
  and His Men</i> (New York, 1894); James Redpath's <i>Public Life of
  Captain John Brown</i> (Boston, 1860); Von Hoist's essay, <i>John
  Brown</i> (Boston, 1889); and J. F. Rhodes, <i>History of the United
  States from the Compromise of 1850</i> (New York, 1890-1906).</p>
   </body>
</topic>