<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22172">
   <title>BROOKE, SIR JAMES</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROOKE, SIR JAMES--> (1803-1868), English soldier, traveller and
  raja of Sarawak, was born at Coombe Grove near Bath, on the 29th of April
  1803. His father, a member of the civil service of the East India
  Company, had long lived in Bengal. His mother was a woman of superior
  mind, and to her care he owed his careful early training. He received the
  ordinary school education, entered the service of the East India Company,
  and was sent out to India about 1825. On the outbreak of the Burmese War
  he was despatched with his regiment to the valley of the Brahmaputra;
  and, being dangerously wounded in an engagement near Rungpore, was
  compelled to return home (1826). After his recovery he travelled on the
  continent before going to India, and circumstances led him soon after to
  leave the service of the company. In 1830 he made a voyage to China, and
  during his passage among the islands of the Indian Archipelago, so rich
  in natural beauty, magnificence and fertility, but occupied by a
  population of savage tribes, continually at war with each other, and
  carrying on a system of piracy on a vast scale and with relentless
  ferocity, he conceived the great design of rescuing them from barbarism
  and bringing them within the pale of civilization. His purpose was
  confirmed by observations made during a second visit to China, and on his
  return to England he applied himself in earnest to making the necessary
  preparations. Having succeeded on the death of his father to a large
  property, he bought and equipped a yacht, the "Royalist," of 140 tons
  burden, and for three years tested its capacities and trained his crew of
  <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page645">[v.04
  p.0645]</ph>twenty men, chiefly in the Mediterranean. At length, on the
  27th of October 1838, he sailed from the Thames on his great adventure.
  On reaching Borneo, after various delays, he found the raja Muda Hassim,
  uncle of the reigning sultan, engaged in war in the province of Sarawak
  with several of the Dyak tribes, who had revolted against the sultan. He
  offered his aid to the raja; and with his crew, and some Javanese who had
  joined them, he took part in a battle with the insurgents, and they were
  defeated. For his services the title of raja of Sarawak was conferred on
  him by Muda Hassim, the former raja being deprived in his favour. It was,
  however, some time before the sultan could be induced to confirm his
  title (September 1841). During the next five years Raja Brooke was
  engaged in establishing his power, in making just reforms in
  administration, preparing a code of laws and introducing just and humane
  modes of dealing with the degraded subjects of his rule. But this was not
  all. He looked forward to the development of commerce as the most
  effective means of putting an end to the worst evils that afflicted the
  archipelago; and in order to make this possible, the way must first be
  cleared by the suppression, or a considerable diminution, of the
  prevailing piracy, which was not only a curse to the savage tribes
  engaged in it, but a standing danger to European and American traders in
  those seas. Various expeditions were therefore organized and sent out
  against the marauders, Dyaks and Malays, and sometimes even Arabs.
  Captain (afterwards Admiral Sir Harry) Keppel, and other commanders of
  British ships of war, received permission to co-operate with Raja Brooke
  in these expeditions. The pirates were attacked in their strongholds,
  they fought desperately, and the slaughter was immense. Negotiations with
  the chiefs had been tried, and tried in vain. The capital of the sultan
  of Borneo was bombarded and stormed, and the sultan with his army routed.
  He was, however, soon after restored to his dominion. So large was the
  number of natives, pirates and others, slain in these expeditions, that
  the "head-money" awarded by the British government to those who had taken
  part in them amounted to no less than £20,000. In October 1847 Raja
  Brooke returned to England, where he was well received by the government;
  and the corporation of London conferred on him the freedom of the city.
  The island of Labuan, with its dependencies, having been acquired by
  purchase from the sultan of Borneo, was erected into a British colony,
  and Raja Brooke was appointed governor and commander-in-chief. He was
  also named consul-general in Borneo. These appointments had been made
  before his arrival in England. The university of Oxford conferred on him
  the honorary degree of D.C.L., and in 1848 he was created K.C.B. He soon
  after returned to Sarawak, and was carried thither by a British
  man-of-war. In the summer of 1849 he led an expedition against the
  Seribas and Sakuran Dyaks, who still persisted in their piratical
  practices and refused to submit to British authority. Their defeat and
  wholesale slaughter was a matter of course. At the time of this
  engagement Sir James Brooke was lying ill with dysentery. He visited
  twice the capital of the sultan of Sala, and concluded a treaty with him,
  which had for one of its objects the expulsion of the sea-gypsies and
  other tribes from his dominions. In 1851 grave charges with respect to
  the operations in Borneo were brought against Sir James Brooke in the
  House of Commons by Joseph Hume and other members, especially as to the
  "head-money" received. To meet these accusations, and to vindicate his
  proceedings, he came to England. The evidence adduced was so conflicting
  that the matter was at length referred to a royal commission, to sit at
  Singapore. As the result of its investigation the charges were declared
  to be "not proven." Sir James, however, was soon after deprived of the
  governorship of Labuan, and the head-money was abolished. In 1867 his
  house in Sarawak was attacked and burnt by Chinese pirates, and he had to
  fly from the capital, Kuching. With a small force he attacked the
  Chinese, recovered the town, made a great slaughter of them, and drove
  away the rest. In the following year he came to England, and remained
  there for three years. During this time he was attacked by paralysis, a
  public subscription was raised, and an estate in Devonshire was bought
  and presented to him. He made two more visits to Sarawak, and on each
  occasion had a rebellion to suppress. He spent his last days on his
  estate at Burrator in Devonshire, and died there, on the 11th of June
  1868, being succeeded as raja of Sarawak by his nephew. Sir James Brooke
  was a man of the highest personal character, and he displayed rare
  courage both in his conflicts in the East and under the charges advanced
  against him in England.</p>
      <p>His <i>Private Letters</i> (1838 to 1853) were published in 1853.
  Portions of his <i>Journal</i> were edited by Captains Munday and Keppel.
  (See also <ph outputclass="sc">Sarawak</ph>.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>