<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23178">
   <title>BROUSSAIS, FRANÇOIS JOSEPH VICTOR</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROUSSAIS, FRANÇOIS JOSEPH VICTOR--> (1772-1838), French
  physician, was born at St Malo on the 17th of December 1772. From his
  father, who was also a physician, he received his first instructions in
  medicine, and he studied for some years at the college of Dinan. At the
  age of seventeen he entered one of the newly-formed republican regiments,
  but ill-health compelled him to withdraw after two years. He resumed his
  medical studies, and then obtained an appointment as surgeon in the navy.
  In 1799 he proceeded to Paris, wherein 1803 he graduated as M.D. In 1805
  he again joined the army in a professional capacity, and served in
  Germany and Holland. Returning to Paris in 1808 he published his
  <i>Histoire des phlegmasies ou inflammations chroniques</i>; then left
  again for active service in Spain. In 1814 he returned to Paris, and was
  appointed assistant-professor to the military hospital of the
  Val-de-Grace, where he first promulgated his peculiar doctrines on the
  relation between "life" and "stimulus," and on the physiological
  interdependence and sympathies of the various organs. His lectures were
  attended by great numbers of students, who received with the utmost
  enthusiasm the new theories which he propounded. In 1816 he published his
  <i>Examen de la doctrine médicale généralement adoptée</i>, which drew
  down upon its author the hatred of the whole medical faculty of Paris;
  but by degrees his doctrines triumphed, and in 1831 he was appointed
  professor of general pathology in the academy of medicine. In 1828 he
  published a work <i>De l'irritation et de la folie</i>, and towards the
  end of his life he attracted large audiences by his lectures on
  phrenology. He died at Vitry-sur-Seine on the 17th of November 1838.</p>
   </body>
</topic>