<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e32765">
   <title>BUDGELL, EUSTACE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUDGELL, EUSTACE--> (1686-1737), English man of letters, the son
  of Dr Gilbert Budgell, was born on the 19th of August 1686 at St Thomas,
  near Exeter. He matriculated in 1705 at Trinity College, Oxford, and
  afterwards joined the Inner Temple, London; but instead of studying law
  he devoted his whole attention to literature. Addison, who was first
  cousin to his mother, befriended him, and, on being appointed secretary
  to Lord Wharton, lord-lieutenant of Ireland in 1710, took Budgell with
  him as one of the clerks of his office. Budgell took part with Steele and
  Addison in writing the <i>Tatler</i>. He was also a contributor to the
  <i>Spectator</i> and the <i>Guardian</i>,—his papers being marked
  with an X in the former, and with an asterisk in the latter. He was
  subsequently made under-secretary to Addison, chief secretary to the
  lords justices of Ireland, and deputy-clerk of the council, and became a
  member of the Irish parliament. In 1717, when Addison became principal
  secretary of state in England, he procured for Budgell the place of
  accountant and comptroller-general of the revenue in Ireland. But the
  next year, the duke of Bolton being appointed lord-lieutenant, Budgell
  wrote a lampoon against E. Webster, his secretary. This led to his being
  removed from his post of accountant-general, upon which he returned to
  England, and, contrary to the advice of Addison, published his case in a
  pamphlet. In the year 1720 he lost £20,000 by the South Sea scheme, and
  afterwards spent £5000 more in unsuccessful attempts to get into
  parliament. He began to write pamphlets against the ministry, and
  published many papers in the <i>Craftsman</i>. In 1733 he started a
  weekly periodical called the <i>Bee</i>, which he continued for more than
  a hundred numbers. By the will of Matthew Tindal, the deist, who died in
  1733, a legacy of 2000 guineas was left to Budgell; but the bequest
  (which had, it was alleged, been inserted in the will by Budgell himself)
  was successfully disputed by Tindal's nephew and nearest heir, Nicholas
  Tindal, who translated and wrote a <i>Continuation</i> of the <i>History
  of England</i> of Paul de Rapin-Thoyras. Hence Pope's lines—</p>
      <fig outputclass="poem">
         <lines>
      "Let Budgell charge low Grub Street on his quill,

      And write whate'er he pleased—except his will."<xref href="#d1e32765/Footnote_311" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref>

         </lines>
      </fig>
      <p>Budgell is said to have sold the second volume of Tindal's
  <i>Christianity as Old as the Creation</i> to Bishop Gibson, by whom it
  was destroyed. The scandal caused by these transactions ruined him. On
  the 4th of May 1737, after filling his pockets with stones, he took a
  boat at Somerset-stairs, and while the boat was passing under the bridge
  threw himself into the river. On his desk was found a slip of paper with
  the words—"What Cato did, and Addison approved, cannot be wrong."
  Besides the works mentioned above, he wrote a translation (1714) of the
  <i>Characters</i> of Theophrastus. He never married, but left a natural
  daughter, Anne Eustace, who became an actress at Drury Lane.</p>
      <p>See Cibber's <i>Lives of the Poets</i>, vol. v.</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_311"> 
            <i>Epistle to Dr
  Arbuthnot</i>, lines 378-379.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>