<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e11667">
   <title>BRIDPORT</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIDPORT, ALEXANDER HOOD,--> <ph outputclass="sc">Viscount</ph>
  (1727-1814), British admiral, was the younger brother of Samuel, Lord
  Hood, and cousin of Sir Samuel and Captain Alexander Hood. Entering the
  navy in January 1741, he was appointed lieutenant of the "Bridgewater"
  six years later, and in that rank served for ten years in various ships.
  He was then posted to the "Prince," the flag-ship of Rear-Admiral
  Saunders (under whom Hood had served as a lieutenant) and in this command
  served in the Mediterranean for some time. Returning home, he was
  appointed to the "Minerva" frigate, in which he was present at Hawke's
  great victory in Quiberon Bay (20th November 1759). In 1761 the "Minerva"
  recaptured, after a long struggle, the "Warwick" of equal force, and
  later in the same year Captain Alexander Hood went in the "Africa" to the
  Mediterranean, where he served until the conclusion of peace. From this
  time forward he was in continuous employment afloat and ashore, and in
  the "Robust" was present at the battle of Ushant in 1778. Hood was
  involved in the court-martial on Admiral (afterwards Viscount) Keppel
  which followed this action, and although adverse popular feeling was
  aroused by the course which he took in Keppel's defence, his conduct does
  not seem to have injured his professional career. Two years later he was
  made rear-admiral of the white, and succeeded Kempenfeldt as one of
  Howe's flag-officers, and in the "Queen" (90) he was present at the
  relief of Gibraltar in 1782. For a time he sat in the House of Commons.
  Promoted vice-admiral in 1787, he became K.B. in the following year, and
  on the occasion of the Spanish armament in 1790 flew his flag again for a
  short time. On the outbreak of the war with France in 1793 Sir Alexander
  Hood once more went to sea, this time as Howe's second in command, and he
  had his share in the operations which culminated in the "Glorius First of
  June," and for his services was made Baron Bridport of Cricket St Thomas
  in Somerset <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page561">[v.04 p.0561]</ph>in the Irish peerage. Henceforth
  Bridport was practically in independent command. In 1795 he fought the
  much-criticized partial action of the 23rd of June off Belle-Ile, which,
  however unfavourably it was regarded in some quarters, was counted as a
  great victory by the public. Bridport's peerage was made English, and he
  became vice-admiral of England. In 1796-1797 he practically directed the
  war from London, rarely hoisting his flag afloat save at such critical
  times as that of the Irish expedition in 1797. In the following year he
  was about to put to sea when the Spithead fleet mutinied. He succeeded at
  first in pacifying the crew of his flag-ship, who had no personal grudge
  against their admiral, but a few days later the mutiny broke out afresh,
  and this time was uncontrollable. For a whole week the mutineers were
  supreme, and it was only by the greatest exertions of the old Lord Howe
  that order was then restored and the men returned to duty. After the
  mutiny had been suppressed, Bridport took the fleet to sea as
  commander-in-chief in name as well as in fact, and from 1798 to 1800
  personally directed the blockade of Brest, which grew stricter and
  stricter as time went on. In 1800 he was relieved by St Vincent, and
  retired from active duty after fifty-nine years' service. In reward for
  his fine record his peerage was made a viscounty. He spent the remaining
  years of his life in retirement. He died on the 2nd of May 1814. The
  viscounty in the English peerage died with him; the Irish barony passed
  to the younger branch of his brother's family, for whom the viscounty was
  recreated in 1868.</p>
      <p>See Charnock, <i>Biographia Navalis</i>, vi. 153; <i>Naval
  Chronicle</i>, i. 265; Ralfe, <i>Nav. Biog.</i> i. 202.</p>
   </body>
</topic>