<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e30624">
   <title>BUCKINGHAM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCKINGHAM,--> a market town and municipal borough and the county
  town of Buckinghamshire, England, in the Buckingham parliamentary
  division, 61 m. N.W. of London by a branch of the London &amp;
  North-Western railway. Pop. (1901) 3152. It lies in an open valley on the
  upper part of the river Ouse, which encircles the main portion of the
  town on three sides. The church of St Peter and St Paul, which was
  extensively restored by Sir Gilbert Scott, a native of this
  neighbourhood, is of the 18th century, and stands on the site of the old
  castle; the town hall dates from the close of the previous century; and
  the grammar school was founded by Edward VI., in part occupying buildings
  of earlier date, which retain Perpendicular and Decorated windows, and a
  Norman door. A chantry, founded in 1268 by Matthew Stratton, archdeacon
  of Buckingham, previously occupied the site; the Norman work may be a
  remnant of the chapel of a gild of the Holy Trinity. The manor house is
  of the early part of the 17th century, and other old houses remain. The
  adjacent mansion of Stowe, approached from the town by a magnificent
  avenue of elms, and surrounded by gardens very beautifully laid out, was
  the seat of the dukes of Buckingham until the extinction of the title in
  1889. Buckingham is served by a branch of the Grand Junction Canal, and
  has agricultural trade, manufactures of condensed milk and artificial
  manure, maltings and flour-mills; while an old industry survives to a
  modified extent in the manufacture of pillow-lace. The borough is under a
  mayor, 4 aldermen and 12 councillors. Area, 5006 acres.</p>
      <p>Buckingham (Bochingeham, Bukyngham) was an important stronghold in
  pre-Conquest times, and in 918 Edward the Elder encamped there with his
  army for four weeks, and threw up two forts on either side of the water.
  At the time of the Domesday survey there were twenty-six burgesses in
  Buckingham, which, together with the hamlet of Bourton, was assessed at
  one hide. Although it appears as a borough thus early, the town received
  no charter until 1554, when Queen Mary created it a free borough
  corporate with a bailiff, twelve principal burgesses and a steward, and
  defined the boundaries as extending in width from Dudley bridge to
  Thornborowe bridge and in length from Chackmore bridge to Padbury Mill
  bridge. A charter from Charles II. in 1684 was very shortly abandoned in
  favour of the original grant, which held force until the Municipal
  Corporations Act of 1835. In 1529 and from 1545 onwards Buckingham
  returned two members to parliament, until deprived by the Representation
  of the People Act of 1867 of one member, and by the Redistribution of
  Seats Act of 1885 of the other. Early mentions occur of markets and
  fairs, and from 1522, when Henry VIII. granted to Sir Henry Marney the
  borough of Buckingham with a Saturday market and two annual fairs, grants
  of fairs by various sovereigns were numerous. Buckingham was formerly an
  important agricultural centre, and Edward III. fixed here one of the
  staples for wool, but after the removal of these to Calais the trade
  suffered such decay that in an act of 32 Henry VIII. Buckingham is
  mentioned among thirty-six impoverished towns.</p>
   </body>
</topic>