<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e21074">
   <title>BRONCHIECTASIS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRONCHIECTASIS--> (Gr. <ph outputclass="grk">βρόγχια</ph>, bronchial tubes,
  and <ph outputclass="grk">ἒκτασις</ph>, extension),
  dilatation of the bronchi, a condition occurring in connexion with many
  diseases of the lungs. Bronchitis both acute and chronic, chronic
  pneumonia and phthisis, acute pneumonia and broncho-pneumonia, may all
  leave after them a bronchiectasis whose position is determined by the
  primary lesion. Other causes, acting mechanically, are tracheal and
  bronchial obstruction, as from the pressure of an aneurism, new growth,
  &amp;c. It used to be considered a disease of middle age, but of late
  years Dr Walter Carr has shown that the condition is a fairly common one
  among debilitated children after measles, whooping cough, &amp;c. The
  dilatation is commonly cylindrical, more rarely saccular, and it is the
  medium and smaller sized tubes that are generally affected, except where
  the cause is mechanical. The affection is usually of one lung only.
  Emphysema is a very common accompaniment. Though at first the symptoms
  somewhat resemble those of bronchitis, later they are quite distinctive.
  Cough is very markedly paroxysmal in character, and though severe is
  intermittent, the patient being entirely free for many hours at the time.
  The effect of posture is very marked. If the patient lie on the affected
  side, he may be free from cough the whole night, but if he turn to the
  sound side, or if he rises and bends forward, he brings up large
  quantities of bronchial secretion. The expectoration is characterized by
  its abundance and manner of expulsion. Where the dilatation is of the
  saccular variety, it may come up in such quantities and with so much
  suddenness as to gush from the mouth. It is very commonly foetid, as it
  is retained and decomposed <i>in situ</i>. Dyspnoea and haemoptysis
  occasionally occur, but are by no means the rule. If pyrexia is present,
  it is a serious symptom, as it is a sign of septic absorption in the
  bronchi, and may be the forerunner of gangrene. If gangrene does set in,
  it will be accompanied by severe attacks of shivering and sweating. Where
  the disease has lasted long, clubbing of fingers and toes is very common.
  The diagnosis from putrid bronchitis is usually fairly easily made, but
  at times it may be a matter of extreme difficulty to distinguish between
  this condition and a tuberculous cavity in the lung. Nothing can be done
  directly to cure this disease, but the patient's condition can be greatly
  alleviated. Creosote vapour baths are eminently satisfactory. A
  mechanical treatment much recommended by some of the German physicians is
  that of forced expiration.</p>
   </body>
</topic>