<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22234">
   <title>BROOK FARM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROOK FARM,--> the name applied to a tract of land in West
  Roxbury, Massachusetts, on which in 1841-1847 a communistic experiment
  was unsuccessfully tried. The experiment was one of the practical
  manifestations of the spirit of "Transcendentalism," in New England,
  though many of the more prominent transcendentalists took no direct part
  in it. The project was originated by George Ripley, who also virtually
  directed it throughout. In his words it was intended "to insure a more
  natural union between intellectual and manual labour than now exists; to
  combine the thinker and the worker, as far as possible, in the same
  individual; to guarantee the highest mental freedom by providing all with
  labour adapted to their tastes and talents, and securing to them the
  fruits of their industry; to do away with the necessity of menial
  services by opening the benefits of education and the profits of labour
  to all; and thus to prepare a society of liberal, intelligent and
  cultivated persons whose relations with each other would permit a more
  simple and wholesome life than can be led amidst the pressure of our
  competitive institutions." In short, its aim was to bring about the best
  conditions for an ideal civilization, reducing to a minimum the labour
  necessary for mere existence, and by this and by the simplicity of its
  social machinery saving the maximum of time for mental and spiritual
  education and development. At a time when Ralph Waldo Emerson could write
  to Thomas Carlyle, "We are all a little wild here with numberless
  projects of social reform; not a reading man but has a draft of a new
  community in his waistcoat pocket,"—the Brook Farm project
  certainly did not appear as impossible a scheme as many others that were
  in the air. At all events it enlisted the co-operation of men whose
  subsequent careers show them to have been something more than
  visionaries. The association bought a tract of land about 10 m. from
  Boston, and in the summer of 1841 began its enterprise with about twenty
  members. In September the "Brook Farm Institute of Agriculture and
  Education" was formally organized, the members <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page646">[v.04 p.0646]</ph>signing the
  Articles of Association and forming an unincorporated joint-stock
  company. The farm was assiduously, if not very skilfully, cultivated, and
  other industries were established—most of the members paying by
  labour for their board—but nearly all of the income, and sometimes
  all of it, was derived from the school, which deservedly took high rank
  and attracted many pupils. Among these were included George William
  Curtis and his brother James Burrill Curtis, Father Isaac Thomas Hecker
  (1819-1888), General Francis C. Barlow (1834-1896), who as
  attorney-general of New York in 1871-1873 took a leading part in the
  prosecution of the "Tweed Ring." For three years the undertaking went on
  quietly and simply, subject to few outward troubles other than financial,
  the number of associates increasing to seventy or eighty. It was during
  this period that Nathaniel Hawthorne had his short experience of Brook
  Farm, of which so many suggestions appear in the <i>Blithedale
  Romance</i>, though his preface to later editions effectually disposed of
  the idea—which gave him great pain—that he had either drawn
  his characters from persons there, or had meant to give any actual
  description of the colony. Emerson refused, in a kind and characteristic
  letter, to join the undertaking, and though he afterwards wrote of Brook
  Farm with not uncharitable humour as "a perpetual picnic, a French
  Revolution in small, an age of reason in a patty-pan," among its founders
  were many of his near friends. In 1844 the growing need of a more
  scientific organization, and the influence which F.M.C. Fourier's
  doctrines, as modified by Albert Brisbane (1809-1890), had gained in the
  minds of Ripley and many of his associates, combined to change the whole
  plan of the community. It was transformed, with the strong approval of
  all its chief members and the consent of the rest, into a Fourierist
  "phalanx" in 1845. There was an accession of new members, a momentary
  increase of prosperity, a brilliant new undertaking in the publication of
  a weekly journal, the <i>Harbinger</i>, in which Ripley, Charles A. Dana,
  Francis G. Shaw and John S. Dwight were the chief writers, and to which
  James Russell Lowell, J.G. Whittier, George William Curtis, Parke Godwin,
  T.W. Higginson, Horace Greeley and many more now and then contributed.
  But the individuality of the old Brook Farm was gone. The association was
  not rescued even from financial troubles by the change. With increasing
  difficulty it kept on till the spring of 1846, when a fire which
  destroyed its nearly completed "phalanstery" brought losses which caused,
  or certainly gave the final ostensible reason for, its dissolution. The
  experiment was abandoned in the autumn of 1847. Besides Ripley and
  Hawthorne, the principal members of the community were Charles A. Dana,
  John S. Dwight, Minot Pratt (<i>c.</i> 1805-1878), the head farmer, who,
  like George Partridge Bradford (1808-1890), left in 1845, and Warren
  Burton (1810-1866) a preacher and, later, a writer on educational
  subjects. Indirectly connected with the experiment, also, as visitors for
  longer or shorter periods but never as regular members, were Emerson,
  Amos Bronson Alcott, Orestes A. Brownson, Theodore Parker and William
  Henry Channing, Margaret Fuller and Elizabeth Palmer Peabody. The estate
  itself, after passing through various hands, came in 1870 into the
  possession of the "Association of the Evangelical Lutheran Church for
  Works of Mercy," which established here an orphanage, known as the
  "Martin Luther Orphan Home."</p>
      <p>The best account of Brook Farm is Lindsay Swift's <i>Brook Farm, Its
  Members, Scholars and Visitors</i> (New York, 1900). <i>Brook Farm:
  Historic and Personal Memoirs</i> (Boston, 1894), is by Dr J.T. Codman,
  one of the pupils in the school. See also Morris Hillquit's <i>History of
  Socialism in the United States</i> (New York, 1903).</p>
      <p>(E. L. B.)</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
            <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 2.
  </title>
         <desc/>
         <image href="images/brookite_2.png">
            <alt>Fig. 2.--Bipyramidal crystal of brookite.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
            <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 1.
  </title>
         <desc/>
         <image href="images/brookite_1.png">
            <alt>Fig. 1.--Tabular crystal of brookite.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
   </body>
</topic>