<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e20155">
   <title>BRODIE, SIR BENJAMIN COLLINS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRODIE, SIR BENJAMIN COLLINS-->, 1st Bart. (1783-1862), English
  physiologist and surgeon, was born in 1783 at Winterslow, Wiltshire. He
  received his early education from his father; then choosing medicine as
  his profession he went to London in 1801, and attended the lectures of
  John Abernethy. Two years later he became a pupil of Sir Everard Home at
  St George's hospital, and in 1808 was appointed assistant surgeon at that
  institution, on the staff of which he served for over thirty years. In
  1810 he was elected a fellow of the Royal Society, to which in the next
  four or five years he contributed several papers describing original
  investigations in physiology. At this period also he rapidly obtained a
  large and lucrative practice, and from time to time he wrote on surgical
  questions, contributing numerous papers to the Medical and Chirurgical
  Society, and to the medical journals. Probably his most important work is
  that entitled <i>Pathological and Surgical Observations on the Diseases
  of the Joints</i>, in which he attempts to trace the beginnings of
  disease in the different tissues that form a joint, and to give an exact
  value to the symptom of pain as evidence of organic disease. This volume
  led to the adoption by surgeons of measures of a conservative nature in
  the treatment of diseases of the joints, with consequent reduction in the
  number of amputations and the saving of many limbs and lives. He also
  wrote on diseases of the urinary organs, and on local nervous affections
  of a surgical character. In 1854 he published anonymously a volume of
  <i>Psychological Inquiries</i>; to a second volume which appeared in 1862
  his name was attached. He received many honours during his career. He
  attended George IV., was sergeant-surgeon to William IV. and Queen
  Victoria, and was made a baronet in 1834. He became a corresponding
  member of the French Institute in 1844, D.C.L. of Oxford in 1855, and
  president of the Royal Society in 1858, and he was the first president of
  the general medical council. He died at Broome Park, Surrey, on the 21st
  of October 1862. His collected works, with autobiography, were published
  in 1865 under the editorship of Charles Hawkins.</p>
      <p>His eldest son, Sir Benjamin Collins Brodie, 2nd Bart. (1817-1880),
  was appointed professor of chemistry at Oxford in 1865, and is chiefly
  known for his investigations on the allotropic states of carbon and for
  his discovery of graphitic acid.</p>
   </body>
</topic>