<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e2964">
   <title>BRIANÇON</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIANÇON,--> a strongly fortified town in the department of
  Hautes-Alpes in S.E. France. It is built at a height of 4334 ft. on a
  plateau which dominates the junction of the Durance with the Guisane. The
  town itself is formed of very steep and narrow, though picturesque
  streets. As it lies at the foot of the descent from the Mont Genèvre
  Pass, giving access to Turin, a great number of fortifications have been
  constructed on the heights around Briançon, especially towards the east.
  The Fort Janus is no less than 4000 ft. above the town. The parish
  church, with its two towers, was built 1703-1726, and occupies a very
  conspicuous position. The Pont d'Asfeld, E. of the town, was built in
  1734, and forms an arch of 131 ft. span, thrown at a height of 184 ft.
  across the Durance. The modern town extends in the plain at the S.W. foot
  of the plateau on which the old town is built and forms the suburb of Ste
  Catherine, with the railway station, and an important silk-weaving
  factory. Briançon is 51½ m. by rail from Gap. The commune had a civil
  population in 1906 of 4883 (urban population 3130), while the permanent
  garrison was 2641—in all 7524 inhabitants.</p>
      <p>Briançon was the <i>Brigantium</i> of the Romans and formed part of
  the kingdom of King Cottius. About 1040 it came into the hands of the
  counts of Albon (later dauphins of the Viennois) and thenceforth shared
  the fate of the Dauphiné. The Briançonnais included not merely the upper
  valley of the Durance (with those of its affluents, the Gyronde and the
  Guil), but also the valley of the Dora Riparia (Césanne, Oulx,
  Bardonnèche and Exilles), and that of the Chisone (Fénestrelles, Pérouse,
  Pragelas)—these glens all lying on the eastern slope of the chain
  of the Alps. But by the treaty of Utrecht (1713) all these valleys were
  handed over to Savoy in exchange for that of Barcelonnette, on the west
  slope of the Alps. In 1815 Briançon successfully withstood a siege of
  three months at the hands of the Allies, a feat which is commemorated by
  an inscription on one of its gates, <i>Le passé répond de
  l'avenir</i>.</p>
      <p>(W. A. B. C.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>