<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e11533">
   <title>BRIDGITTINES</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIDGITTINES,--> an order of Augustinian canonesses founded by St
  Bridget of Sweden (<i>q.v.</i>) <i>c.</i> 1350, and approved by Urban V.
  in 1370. It was a "double order," each convent having attached to it a
  small community of canons to act as chaplains, but under the government
  of the abbess. The order spread widely in Sweden and Norway, and played a
  remarkable part in promoting culture and literature in Scandinavia; to
  this is to be attributed the fact that the head house at Vastein, by Lake
  Vetter, was not suppressed till 1595. There were houses also in other
  lands, so that the total number amounted to 80. In England, the famous
  Bridgittine convent of Syon at Isleworth, Middlesex, was founded and
  royally endowed by Henry V. in 1415, and became one of the richest and
  most fashionable and influential nunneries in the country. It was among
  the few religious houses restored in Mary's reign, when nearly twenty of
  the old community were re-established at Syon. On Elizabeth's accession
  they migrated to the Low Countries, and thence, after many vicissitudes,
  to Rouen, and finally in 1594 to Lisbon. Here they remained, always
  recruiting their numbers from England, till 1861, when they returned to
  England. Syon House is now established at Chudleigh in Devon, the only
  English community that can boast an unbroken conventual existence since
  pre-Reformation times. Some six other Bridgittine convents exist on the
  Continent, but the order is now composed only of women.</p>
      <p>See Helyot, <i>Histoire des ordres religieux</i> (1715), iv. c. 4; Max
  Heimbucher, <i>Orden u. Kongregationen</i> (1907), ii. § 83;
  Herzog-Hauck, <i>Realencyklopädie</i> (ed. 3), art. "Birgitta"; A.
  Hamilton in <i>Dublin Review</i>, 1888, "The Nuns of Syon."</p>
      <p>(E. C. B.)</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page559">[v.04 p.0559]</ph>
      </p>
   </body>
</topic>