<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e15801">
   <title>BRITISH EAST AFRICA</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRITISH EAST AFRICA,--> a term, in its widest sense, including all
  the territory under British influence on the eastern side of Africa
  between German East Africa on the south and Abyssinia and the
  Anglo-Egyptian Sudan on the north. It comprises the protectorates of
  Zanzibar, Uganda and East Africa. Apart from a narrow belt of coastland,
  the continental area belongs almost entirely to the great plateau of East
  Africa, rarely falling below an elevation of 2000 ft., while extensive
  sections rise to a height of 6000 to 8000 ft. From the coast lowlands a
  series of steps with intervening plateaus leads to a broad zone of high
  ground remarkable for the abundant traces of volcanic action. This broad
  upland is furrowed by the eastern "rift-valley," formed by the subsidence
  of its floor and occupied in parts by lakes without outlet. Towards the
  west a basin of lower elevation is partially occupied by Victoria Nyanza,
  drained north to the Nile, while still farther inland the ground again
  rises to a second volcanic belt, culminating in the Ruwenzori range. (See
  <ph outputclass="sc">Zanzibar</ph>, and for Uganda protectorate see <ph outputclass="sc">Uganda</ph>.) The present article treats of the East Africa
  protectorate only.</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
  </title>
         <desc/>
         <image href="images/britisheastafrica_1.png">
            <alt>British East Africa.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>
         <i>Topography.</i>—The southern frontier, coterminous with the
  northern frontier of German East Africa, runs north-west from the mouth
  of the Umba river in 4° 40′ S. to Victoria Nyanza, which it strikes
  at 1° S., deviating, however, so as to leave Mount Kilimanjaro wholly in
  German territory. The eastern boundary is the Indian Ocean, the coast
  line being about 400 m. On the north the protectorate is bounded by
  Abyssinia and Italian Somaliland; on the west by Uganda. It has an area
  of about 240,000 sq. m., and a population estimated at from 2,000,000 to
  4,000,000, including some 25,000 Indians and 3000 Europeans. Of the
  Europeans many are emigrants from South Africa; they include some
  hundreds of Boer families.</p>
      <p>The first of the parallel zones—the coast plain or
  "Temborari"—is generally of insignificant width, varying from 2 to
  10 m., except in the valleys of the main rivers. The shore line is broken
  by bays and branching creeks, often cutting off islands from the
  mainland. Such are Mvita or Mombasa in 4° 4′ S., and the larger
  islands of Lamu, Manda and Patta (the Lamu archipelago), between 2°
  20′ and 2° S. Farther north the coast becomes straighter, with the
  one indentation of Port Durnford in 1° 10′ S., but skirted seawards
  by a row of small islands. Beyond the coast plain the country rises in a
  generally well defined step or steps to an altitude of some 800 ft.,
  forming the wide level plain called "Nyika" (uplands), largely composed
  of quartz. It contains large waterless areas, such as the Taru desert in
  the Mombasa district. The next stage in the ascent is marked by an
  intermittent line of mountains—gneissose or schistose—running
  generally north-north-west, sometimes in parallel chains, and
  representing the primitive axis of the continent. Their height varies
  from 5000 to 8000 ft. Farther inland grassy uplands extend to the eastern
  edge of the rift-valley, though varied with cultivated ground and forest,
  the former especially in Kikuyu, the latter between 0° and 0° 40′
  S. The most extensive grassy plains are those of Kapte or Kapote and
  Athi, between 1° and 2° S. The general altitude of these uplands, the
  surface of which is largely composed of lava, varies from 5000 to 8000
  ft. This zone contains the highest elevations in British East Africa,
  including the volcanic pile of Kenya (<i>q.v.</i>) (17,007 ft.), Sattima
  (13,214 ft.) and Nandarua (about 12,900 ft.). The Sattima (Settima)
  range, or Aberdare Mountains, has a general elevation of fully 10,000 ft.
  To the west the fall to the rift-valley is marked by a line of cliffs, of
  which the best-defined portions are the Kikuyu escarpment (8000 ft.),
  just south of 1° S., and the Laikipia escarpment, on the equator. One of
  the main watersheds of East Africa runs close to the eastern wall of the
  rift-valley, separating the basins of inland drainage from the rivers of
  the east coast, of which the two largest wholly within British East
  Africa are the Sabaki and Tana, both separately noticed. The Guaso Nyiro
  rises in the hills north-west of Kenya and flows in a north-east
  direction. After a course of over 350 m. the river in about 1° N., 39°
  30′ E. is lost in a marshy expanse known as the Lorian Swamp.</p>
      <p>The rift-valley, though with a generally level floor, is divided by
  transverse ridges into a series of basins, each containing a lake without
  outlet. The southernmost section within British East Africa is formed by
  the arid Dogilani plains, drained south towards German territory. At
  their north end rise the extinct volcanoes of Suswa (7800 ft.) and
  Longonot (8700), the latter on the ridge dividing off the next
  basin—that of Lake Naivasha. This is a small fresh-water lake, 6135
  ft. above the sea, measuring some 13 m each way. Its basin is closed to
  the north by the ridge of Mount Buru, beyond which is the basin of the
  <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page602">[v.04
  p.0602]</ph>still smaller Lakes Nakuro (5845 ft.) and Elmenteita (5860
  ft.), followed in turn by that of Lakes Hannington and Baringo
  (<i>q.v.</i>). Beyond Baringo the valley is drained north into Lake
  Sugota, in 2° N., some 35 m. long, while north of this lies the much
  larger Lake Rudolf (<i>q.v.</i>), the valley becoming here somewhat less
  defined.</p>
      <p>On the west of the rift-valley the wall of cliffs is best marked
  between the equator and 1° S., where it is known as the Mau Escarpment,
  and about 1° N., where the Elgeyo Escarpment falls to a longitudinal
  valley separated from Lake Baringo by the ridge of Kamasia. Opposite Lake
  Naivasha the Mau Escarpment is over 8000 ft. high. Its crest is covered
  with a vast forest. To the south the woods become more open, and the
  plateau falls to an open country drained towards the Dogilani plains. On
  the west the cultivated districts of Sotik and Lumbwa, broken by wooded
  heights, fall towards Victoria Nyanza. The Mau plateau reaches a height
  of 9000 ft. on the equator, north of which is the somewhat lower Nandi
  country, well watered and partly forested. In the treeless plateau of
  Uasin Gishu, west of Elgeyo, the land again rises to a height of over
  8000 ft., and to the west of this is the great mountain mass of Elgon
  (<i>q.v.</i>). East of Lake Rudolf and south of Lake Stefanie is a large
  waterless steppe, mainly volcanic in character, from which rise mountain
  ranges. The highest peak is Mount Kanjora, 6900 ft. high. South of this
  arid region, strewn with great lava stones, are the Rendile uplands,
  affording pasturage for thousands of camels. Running north-west and
  south-east between Lake Stefanie and the Daua tributary of the Juba is a
  mountain range with a steep escarpment towards the south. It is known as
  the Goro Escarpment, and at its eastern end it forms the boundary between
  the protectorate and Abyssinia. South-east of it the country is largely
  level bush covered plain, mainly waterless.</p>
      <p>[<i>Geology.</i>—The geological formations of British East
  Africa occur in four regions possessing distinct physiographical
  features. The coast plain, narrow in the south and rising somewhat
  steeply, consists of recent rocks. The foot plateau which succeeds is
  composed of sedimentary rocks dating from Trias to Jurassic. The ancient
  plateau commencing at Taru extends to the borders of Kikuyu and is
  composed of ancient crystalline rocks on which immense quantities of
  volcanic rocks—post-Jurassic to Recent—have accumulated to
  form the volcanic plateau of Central East Africa.</p>
      <p>The formations recognized are given in the following table:—</p>
      <table>
         <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="col1"/>
            <colspec colname="col2"/>
            <colspec colname="col3"/>
            <tbody>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                     <p>
                        <i>Sedimentary.</i>
                     </p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="vertical-align:middle; text-align:left">
                     <p>Recent</p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="vertical-align:middle; text-align:left">
                     <p>
                        <image href="images/$lbrace.png">
                           <alt>left brace</alt>
                        </image>
                     </p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>1. Alluvium and superficial sands.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>2. Modern lake deposits, living coral rock.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>3. Raised coral rock, conglomerate of Mombasa Island.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="vertical-align:middle; text-align:left">
                     <p>Pleistocene</p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="vertical-align:middle; text-align:left">
                     <p>
                        <image href="images/$lbrace.png">
                           <alt>left brace</alt>
                        </image>
                     </p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>4. Gravels with flint implements.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>5. Glacial beds of Kenya</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>Jurassic</p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>6. Shales and limestones of Changamwe.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="vertical-align:middle; text-align:left">
                     <p>Karroo</p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="vertical-align:middle; text-align:left">
                     <p>
                        <image href="images/$lbrace.png">
                           <alt>left brace</alt>
                        </image>
                     </p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>7. Flags and sandstones.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>8. Grits and shales of Masara and Taru.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>Carboniferous?</p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>9. Shales of the Sabaki river.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="vertical-align:middle; text-align:left">
                     <p>Archaean</p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="vertical-align:middle; text-align:left">
                     <p>
                        <image href="images/$lbrace.png">
                           <alt>left brace</alt>
                        </image>
                     </p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>10. Schists and quartzites of Nandi.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>11. Gneisses, schists, granites.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                     <p>
                        <i>Igneous and Volcanic.</i>
                     </p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>Recent</p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>Active, dormant and extinct volcanoes.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="vertical-align:middle; text-align:left">
                     <p>Post-Jurassic to Pleistocene</p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="vertical-align:middle; text-align:left">
                     <p>
                        <image href="images/$lbrace.png">
                           <alt>left brace</alt>
                        </image>
                     </p>
                  </entry>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>Kibo and volcanoes of the rift-valley.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                     <p>Kimawenzi, Kenya and plateau eruptions.</p>
                  </entry>
               </row>
            </tbody>
         </tgroup>
      </table>
      <p>
         <i>Archaean.</i>—These rocks prevail in the districts of Taru,
  Nandi and throughout Ukamba. A course gneiss is the predominant rock, but
  is associated with garnetiferous mica-schists and much intrusive granite.
  Hornblende schists and beds of metamorphic limestone are rare. Cherty
  quartzites interbedded with mylonites occur on the flanks of the Nandi
  hills, but their age is not known.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Carboniferous?</i>—From shales on the Sabaki river Dr Gregory
  obtained fish-scales and specimens of <i>Palaeanodonta Fischeri.</i>
      </p>
      <p>
         <i>Karroo.</i>—The grits of Masara, near Rabai mission station
  and Mombasa, have yielded specimens of <i>Glossopteris browniana</i> var.
  <i>indica</i>, thus indicating their Karroo age.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Jurassic.</i>—Shales and limestones of this age are well seen
  along the railway near Changamwe. They contain gigantic ammonites.
  According to Dr Waagen the ammonites show a striking analogy to forms
  from the Acanthicus zone of East India. Belemnites are plentiful.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Pleistocene.</i>—These are feebly represented by some boulder
  beds on the higher slopes of Kilimanjaro and Kenya. They show that in
  Pleistocene times the glaciers of Kilimanjaro and Kenya extended much
  farther down the mountain slopes.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Recent.</i>—The ancient and more modern lake deposits have so
  far yielded no mammalian or other organic remains of interest.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Igneous and Volcanic.</i>—A belt of volcanic rocks, over
  150,000 sq. m. in area, extends from beyond the southern to beyond the
  northern territorial limits. They belong to an older and a newer set. The
  older group commenced with a series of fissure eruptions along the site
  of the present rift-valley and parallel with it. From these fissures
  immense and repeated flows of lava spread over the Kapte and Laikipia
  plateaus. At about the same time, or a little later, Kenya and Kimawenzi,
  Elgon and Chibcharagnani were in eruption. The age of these volcanic
  outbursts cannot be more definitely stated than that they are
  post-Jurassic, and probably extended through Cretaceous into early
  Tertiary times. This great volcanic period was followed by the eruptions
  of Kibo and some of the larger volcanoes of the rift-valley. The flows
  from Kibo include nepheline and leucite basanite lavas rich in soda
  felspars. They bear a close resemblance to the Norwegian
  "Rhombenporphyrs." The chain of volcanic cones along the northern lower
  slopes of Kilimanjaro, those of the Kyulu mountains, Donyo Longonot and
  numerous craters in the rift-valley region, are of a slightly more recent
  date. A few of the volcanoes in the latter region have only recently
  become extinct; a few may be only dormant. Donyo Buru still emits small
  quantities of steam, while Mount Teleki, in the neighbourhood of Lake
  Rudolf, was in eruption at the close of the 19th century.]</p>
      <p>
         <i>Climate, Flora and Fauna.</i>—In its climate and vegetation
  British East Africa again shows an arrangement of zones parallel to the
  coast. The coast region is hot but is generally more healthy than the
  coast lands of other tropical countries, this being due to the constant
  <ph outputclass="correction">breeze</ph> from
  the Indian Ocean and to the dryness of the soil. The rainfall on the
  coast is about 35 in. a year, the temperature tropical. The succeeding
  plains and the outer plateaus are more arid. Farther inland the
  highlands—in which term may be included all districts over 5000 ft.
  high—are very healthy, fever being almost unknown. The average
  temperature is about 66° F. in the cool season and 73° F. in the hot
  season. Over 7000 ft. the climate becomes distinctly colder and frosts
  are experienced. The average rainfall in the highlands is between 40 and
  50 in. The country bordering Victoria Nyanza is typically tropical; the
  rainfall exceeds 60 in. in the year, and this region is quite unsuitable
  to Europeans. The hottest period throughout the protectorate is December
  to April, the coolest, July to September. The "greater rains" fall from
  March to June, the "smaller rains" in November and December. The rainfall
  is not, however, as regular as is usual in countries within the tropics,
  and severe droughts are occasionally experienced.</p>
      <p>In the districts bordering Victoria Nyanza the flora resembles that of
  Uganda (<i>q.v.</i>). The characteristic trees of the coast regions are
  the mangrove and coco-nut palm. Ebony grows in the scrub-jungle. Vast
  forests of olives and junipers are found on the Mau escarpment; the
  cotton, fig and bamboo on the Kikuyu escarpment; and in several regions
  are dense forests of great trees whose lowest branches are 50 ft. from
  the ground. Two varieties of the valuable rubber-vine, <i>Landolphia
  florida</i> and <i>Landolphia Kirkii</i>, are found near the coast and in
  the forests. The higher mountains preserve distinct species, the
  surviving remnants of the flora of a cooler period.</p>
      <p>The fauna is not abundant except in large mammals, which are very
  numerous on the drier steppes. They include the camel (confined to the
  arid northern regions), elephant (more and more restricted to
  unfrequented districts), rhinoceros, buffalo, many kinds of antelope,
  zebra, giraffe, hippopotamus, lion and other carnivora, and numerous
  monkeys. In many parts the rhinoceros is particularly abundant and
  dangerous. Crocodiles are common in the larger rivers and in Victoria
  Nyanza. Snakes are somewhat rare, the most dangerous being the
  puff-adder. Centipedes and scorpions, as well as mosquitoes and other
  insects, are also less common than in most tropical countries. In some
  districts bees are exceedingly numerous. The birds include the ostrich,
  stork, bustard and secretary-bird among the larger varieties, the guinea
  fowl, various kinds of spur fowl, and the lesser bustard, the wild
  pigeon, weaver and hornbill. By the banks of lakes and rivers are to be
  seen thousands of cranes, pelicans and flamingoes.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Inhabitants.</i>—The white population is chiefly in the
  Kikuyu uplands, the rift-valley, and in the Kenya region. The whites are
  mostly agriculturists. There are also numbers of Indian settlers in the
  same districts. The African races include representatives of various
  stocks, as the country forms a borderland between the Negro and Hamitic
  peoples, and contains many tribes of doubtful affinities. The Bantu
  division of the negroes is represented chiefly in the south, the
  principal tribes being the Wakamba, Wakikuyu and Wanyika. By the
  north-east shores of Victoria Nyanza dwell the Kavirondo (<i>q.v.</i>), a
  race remarkable among the tribes of the protectorate for their nudity.
  Nilotic tribes, including the Nandi (<i>q.v.</i>), Lumbwa, Suk and
  Turkana, are found in the north-west. Of Hamitic strain are the Masai
  (<i>q.v.</i>), a race of cattle-rearers speaking a Nilotic language, who
  occupy part of the uplands bordering on the eastern rift-valley. A branch
  of the Masai which has adopted the settled life of agriculturists is
  known as the Wakuafi. The Galla section of the Hamites is represented,
  among others, by Borani living <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page603">[v.04 p.0603]</ph>south of the Goro Escarpment
  (though the true Boran countries are Liban and Dirri in Abyssinian
  territory), while Somali occupy the country between the Tana and Juba
  rivers. Of the Somali tribes the Herti dwell near the coast and are more
  or less stationary. Further inland is the nomadic tribe of Ogaden Somali.
  The Gurre, another Somali tribe, occupy the country south of the lower
  Daua. Primitive hunting tribes are the Wandorobo in Masailand, and
  scattered tribes of small stature in various parts. The coast-land
  contains a mixed population of Swahili, Arab and Indian immigrants, and
  representatives of numerous interior tribes.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Provinces and Towns.</i>—The protectorate has been divided
  into the provinces of Seyyidie (the south coast province, capital
  Mombasa); Ukamba, which occupies the centre of the protectorate (capital
  Nairobi); Kenya, the district of Mt. Kenya (capital Fort Hall); Tanaland,
  to the north of the two provinces first named (capital Lamu); Jubaland,
  the northern region (capital Kismayu); Naivasha (capital Naivasha); and
  Kisumu (capital Kisumu); each being in turn divided into districts and
  sub-districts. Naivasha and Kisumu, which adjoin the Victoria Nyanza,
  formed at first the eastern province of Uganda, but were transferred to
  the East Africa protectorate on the 1st of April 1902. The chief port of
  the protectorate is Mombasa (<i>q.v.</i>) with a population of about
  30,000. The harbour on the south-west side of Mombasa island is known as
  Kilindini, the terminus of the Uganda railway. On the mainland, nearly
  opposite Mombasa town, is the settlement of freed slaves named Freretown,
  after Sir Bartle Frere. Freretown (called by the natives Kisaoni) is the
  headquarters in East Africa of the Church Missionary Society. It is the
  residence of the bishop of the diocese of Mombasa and possesses a fine
  church and mission house. Lamu, on the island of the same name, 150 m.
  north-east of Mombasa, is an ancient settlement and the headquarters of
  the coast Arabs. Here are some Portuguese ruins, and a large Arab city is
  buried beneath the sands. The other towns of note on the coast are
  Malindi, Patta, Kipini and Kismayu. At Malindi, the "Melind" of
  <i>Paradise Lost</i>, is the pillar erected by Vasco da Gama when he
  visited the port in 1498. The harbour is very shallow. Kismayu, the
  northernmost port of the protectorate, 320 m. north-east of Mombasa, is
  the last sheltered anchorage on the east coast and is invaluable as a
  harbour of refuge. Flourishing towns have grown up along the Uganda
  railway. The most important, Nairobi (<i>q.v.</i>), 327 m. from Mombasa,
  257 from Port Florence, was chosen in 1907 as the administrative capital
  of the protectorate. Naivasha, 64 m. north-north-west of Nairobi, lies in
  the rift-valley close to Lake Naivasha, and is 6230 ft. above the sea. It
  enjoys an excellent climate and is the centre of a European agricultural
  settlement. Kisumu or Port Florence (a term confined to the harbour) is a
  flourishing town built on a hill overlooking Victoria Nyanza. It is the
  entrepôt for the trade of Uganda.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Communications.</i>—Much has been done to open up the country
  by means of roads, including a trunk road from Mombasa, by Kibwezi in the
  upper Sabaki basin, and Lake Naivasha, to Berkeley Bay on Victoria
  Nyanza. But the most important engineering work undertaken in the
  protectorate was the construction of a railway from Mombasa to Victoria
  Nyanza, for which a preliminary survey was executed in 1892, and on which
  work was begun in 1896. The line chosen roughly coincides with that of
  the road, until the equator is reached, after which it strikes by a more
  direct route across the Mau plateau to the lake, which it reaches at Port
  Florence on Kavirondo Gulf. The railway is 584 m. long and is of metre
  (3.28 ft.) gauge, the Sudan, and South and Central African lines being of
  3 ft. 6 in. gauge. The Uganda railway is essentially a mountain line,
  with gradients of one in fifty and one in sixty. From Mombasa it crosses
  to the mainland by a bridge half a mile long, and ascends the plateau
  till it reaches the edge of the rift-valley, 346 m. from its starting
  point, at the Kikuyu Escarpment, where it is 7600 ft. above the sea. It
  then descends across ravines bridged by viaducts to the valley floor,
  dropping to a level of 6011 ft., and next ascending the opposite (Mau)
  escarpment to the summit, 8321 ft. above sea-level—the highest
  point on the line. In the remaining 100 m. of its course the level sinks
  to 3738 ft., the altitude of the station at Port Florence. The railway
  was built by the British government at a cost of £5,331,000, or about
  £9500 per mile. The first locomotive reached Victoria Nyanza on the 26th
  of December 1901; and the permanent way was practically completed by
  March 1903, when Sir George Whitehouse, the engineer who had been in
  charge of the construction from the beginning, resigned his post. The
  railway, by doing away with the carriage of goods by men, gave the final
  death-blow to the slave trade in that part of East Africa. It also
  facilitated the continued occupation and development of Uganda, which
  was, previous to its construction, an almost impossible task, owing to
  the prohibitive cost of the carriage of goods from the coast—£60
  per ton. The two avowed objects of the railway—the destruction of
  the slave trade and the securing of the British position in
  Uganda—have been attained; moreover, the railway by opening up land
  suitable for European settlement has also done much towards making a
  prosperous colony of the protectorate, which was regarded before the
  advent of the line as little better than a desert (see below,
  <i>History</i>). The railway also shows a fair return on the capital
  expenditure, the surplus after defraying all working expenses being
  £56,000 in 1905-1906 and £76,000 in 1906-1907.</p>
      <p>Mombasa is visited by the boats of several steamship companies, the
  German East Africa line maintaining a fortnightly service from Hamburg.
  There is also a regular service to and from India. A cable connecting
  Mombasa with Zanzibar puts the protectorate in direct telegraphic
  communication with the rest of the world. There is also an inland system
  of telegraphs connecting the chief towns with one another and with
  Uganda.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Agriculture and other Industries.</i>—In the coast region and
  by the shores of Victoria Nyanza the products are tropical, and
  cultivation is mainly in the hands of the natives or of Indian
  immigrants. There are, however, numerous plantations owned by Europeans.
  Rice, maize and other grains are raised in large quantities; cotton and
  tobacco are cultivated. The coco-nut palm plantations yield copra of
  excellent quality, and the bark of the mangrove trees is exported for
  tanning purposes. In some inland districts beans of the castor oil plant,
  which grows in great abundance, are a lucrative article of trade. The
  sugar-cane, which grows freely in various places, is cultivated by the
  natives. The collection of rubber likewise employs numbers of people.</p>
      <p>Among the European settlers in the higher regions much attention is
  devoted to the production of vegetables, and very large crops of potatoes
  are raised. Oats, barley, wheat and coffee are also grown. The uplands
  are peculiarly adapted for the raising of stock, and many of the white
  settlers possess large flocks and herds. Merino sheep have been
  introduced from Australia. Ostrich farms have also been established.
  Clover, lucerne, ryegrass and similar grasses have been introduced to
  improve and vary the fodder. Other vegetable products of economic value
  are many varieties of timber trees, and fibre-producing plants, which are
  abundant in the scrub regions between the coast and the higher land
  bordering the rift-valley. Over the greater part of the country the soil
  is light reddish loam; in the eastern plains it is a heavy black loam. As
  a rule it is easily cultivated. While the majority of the African tribes
  in the territory are not averse from agricultural labour, the number of
  men available for work on European holdings is small. Moreover, on some
  of the land most suited for cultivation by white men there is no native
  population.</p>
      <p>In addition to the fibre industry and cotton ginning there are
  factories for the curing of bacon. Native industries include the weaving
  of cloth and the making of mats and baskets. Stone and lime quarries are
  worked, and copper is found in the Tsavo district. Diamonds have been
  discovered in the Thika river, one of the headstreams of the Tana.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Trade.</i>—The imports consist largely of textiles, hardware
  and manufactured goods from India and Europe; Great Britain and India
  between them supplying over 50% of the total imports. Of other countries
  Germany has the leading share in the trade. The exports, which include
  the larger part of the external trade of Uganda, are chiefly copra, hides
  and skins, grains, potatoes, rubber, ivory, chillies, beeswax, cotton and
  fibre. The retail trade is largely in the hands of Indians. The value of
  the exports rose from £89,858 in 1900-1901 to £234,664 in 1904-1905, in
  which year the value of the imports for the first time exceeded £500,000.
  In 1906-1907 the volume of trade was £1,194,352, imports being valued at
  £753,647 and exports at £440,705. The United States takes 33% of the
  exports, Great Britain coming next with 15%.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Government.</i>—The system of government resembles that of a
  British crown colony. At the head of the administration is a governor,
  who has a deputy styled lieutenant-governor, provincial commissioners
  presiding over each province. There are also executive and legislative
  councils, unofficial nominated members serving on the last-named council.
  In the "ten-mile strip" (see below, <i>History</i>), the sultan of
  Zanzibar being territorial sovereign, the laws of Islam apply to the
  native and Arab population. The extra-territorial jurisdiction granted by
  the sultan to various Powers was in 1907 transferred to Great Britain.
  Domestic slavery formerly existed; but on the advice of the British
  government a decree was issued by the sultan on the 1st of August 1890,
  enacting that no one born after that date could be a slave, and this was
  followed in 1907 by a decree abolishing the legal status of slavery. In
  the rest of the protectorate slavery is not recognized in any form.
  Legislation is by ordinances made by the governor, with the assent of the
  legislative council. The judicial system is based on Indian models,
  though in cases in which Africans are concerned regard is had to <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page604">[v.04
  p.0604]</ph>native customs. Europeans have the right to trial by jury
  in serious cases. There is a police force of about 2000 men, and two
  battalions of the King's African Rifles are stationed in the
  protectorate. Revenue is derived chiefly from customs, licences and
  excise, railway earnings, and posts and telegraphs. Natives pay a hut
  tax. Since the completion of the Uganda railway, trade, and consequently
  revenue, has increased greatly. In 1900-1901 the revenue was £64,275 and
  the expenditure £193,438; in 1904-1905 the figures were: revenue
  £154,756, expenditure £302,559; in 1905-1906 the totals were £270,362 and
  £418,839, and in 1906-1907 (when the railway figures were included for
  the first time) £461,362 and £616,088. The deficiencies were made good by
  grants-in-aid from the imperial exchequer. The standard coin used is the
  rupee (16d.).</p>
      <p>Education is chiefly in the hands of the missionary societies, which
  maintain many schools where instruction is given in handicrafts, as well
  as in the ordinary branches of elementary education. There are Arab
  schools in Mombasa, and government schools for Europeans and Indians at
  Nairobi.</p>
      <p>
         <i>History.</i>—From the 8th century to the 11th Arabs and
  Persians made settlements along the coast and gained political supremacy
  at many places, leading to the formation of the so-called Zenj empire.
  The history of the coast towns from that time until the establishment of
  British rule is identified with that of Zanzibar (<i>q.v.</i>). The
  interior of what is now British East Africa was first made known in the
  middle of the 19th century by the German missionaries Ludwig Krapf and
  Johannes Rebmann, and by Baron Karl von der Decken (1833-1865) and
  others. Von der Decken and three other Europeans were murdered by Somali
  at a town called Bardera in October 1865, whilst exploring the Juba
  river. The countries east of Victoria Nyanza (Masailand, &amp;c.) were,
  however, first traversed throughout their whole extent by the Scottish
  traveller Joseph Thomson (<i>q.v.</i>) in 1883-1884. In 1888 Count S.
  Teleki (a Hungarian) discovered Lakes Rudolf and Stefanie.</p>
      <p>The growth of British interests in the country now forming the
  protectorate arises from its connexion with the sultanate of Zanzibar. At
  Zanzibar British influence was very strong in the last quarter of the
  19th century, and the seyyid or sultan, Bargash, depended greatly on the
  advice of the British representative, Sir John Kirk. In 1877 Bargash
  offered to Mr (afterwards Sir) William Mackinnon (1823-1893), chairman of
  the British India Steam Navigation Company, a merchant in whom he had
  great confidence, or to a company to be formed by him, a lease for 70
  years of the customs and administration of the whole of the mainland
  dominions of Zanzibar including, with certain reservations, rights of
  sovereignty. This was declined owing to a lack of support by the foreign
  office, and concessions obtained in 1884 by Mr (afterwards Sir) H.H.
  Johnston in the Kilimanjaro district were, at the time, disregarded. The
  large number of concessions acquired by Germans in 1884-1885 on the East
  African coast aroused, however, the interest of those who recognized the
  paramount importance of the maintenance of British influence in those
  regions. A British claim, ratified by an agreement with Germany in 1886,
  was made to the districts behind Mombasa; and in May 1887 Bargash granted
  to an association formed by Mackinnon a concession for the administration
  of so much of his mainland territory as lay outside the region which the
  British government had recognized as the German sphere of operations. By
  international agreement the mainland territories of the sultan were
  defined as extending 10 m. inland from the coast. Mackinnon's
  association, whose object <ph outputclass="sidenote">A chartered company
  formed.</ph> was to open up the hinterland as well as this ten-mile
  strip, became the Imperial British East Africa Company by a founder's
  agreement of April 1888, and received a royal charter in September of the
  same year. To this company the sultan made a further concession dated
  October 1888. On the faith of these concessions and the charters a sum of
  £240,000 was subscribed, and the company received formal charge of their
  concessions. The path of the company was speedily beset with
  difficulties, which in the first instance arose out of the aggressions of
  the German East African Company. This company had also received a grant
  from the sultan in October 1888, and its appearance on the coast was
  followed by grave disturbances among the tribes which had welcomed the
  British. This outbreak led to a joint British and German blockade, which
  seriously hampered trade operations. It had also been anticipated, in
  reliance on certain assurances of Prince Bismarck, emphasized by Lord
  Salisbury, that German enterprise in the interior of the country would be
  confined to the south of Victoria Nyanza. Unfortunately this expectation
  was not realized. Moreover German subjects put forward claims to coast
  districts, notably Lamu, within the company's sphere and in many ways
  obstructed the company's operations. In all these disputes the German
  government countenanced its own subjects, while the British foreign
  office did little or nothing to assist the company, sometimes directly
  discouraging its activity. Moreover, the company had agreed by the
  concession of October 1888 to pay a high revenue to the
  sultan—Bargash had died in the preceding March and the Germans were
  pressing his successor to give them a grant of Lamu—in lieu of the
  customs collected at the ports they took over. The disturbance caused by
  the German claims had a detrimental effect on trade and put a
  considerable strain on the resources of the company. The action of the
  company in agreeing to onerous financial burdens was dictated partly by
  regard for imperial interests, which would have been seriously weakened
  had Lamu gone to the Germans.</p>
      <p>By the hinterland doctrine, accepted both by Great Britain and Germany
  in the diplomatic correspondence of July 1887, Uganda would fall within
  Great Britain's "sphere of influence"; but German public opinion did not
  so regard the matter. German maps assigned the territory to Germany,
  while in England public opinion as strongly expected British influence to
  be paramount. In 1889 Karl Peters, a German official, led what was
  practically a raiding expedition into that country, after running a
  blockade of the ports. An expedition under F.J. Jackson had been sent by
  the company in the same year to Victoria Nyanza, but with instructions to
  avoid Uganda. In consequence of representations from Uganda, and of
  tidings he received of Peters's doings, Jackson, however, determined to
  go to that country. Peters retired at Jackson's approach, claiming,
  nevertheless, to have made certain treaties which constituted "effective
  occupation." Peters's treaty was dated the 1st of March 1890: Jackson
  concluded another in April. Meantime negotiations were proceeding in
  Europe; and by the Anglo-German agreement of the 1st of July 1890 Uganda
  was assigned to the British sphere. To consolidate their position in
  Uganda—the French missionaries there were hostile to Great
  Britain—the company sent thither Captain F.D. Lugard, who reached
  Mengo, the capital, in December 1890 and established the authority of the
  company despite French intrigues. In July 1890 representatives of the
  powers assembled at Brussels had agreed on common efforts for the
  suppression of the slave trade. The interference of the company in Uganda
  had been a material step towards that object, which they sought to
  further and at the same time to open up the country by the construction
  of a railway from Mombasa to Victoria Nyanza. But their resources being
  inadequate for such an undertaking they sought imperial aid. Although
  Lord Salisbury, then prime minister, paid the highest tribute to the
  company's labours, and a preliminary grant for the survey had been
  practically agreed upon, the scheme was wrecked in parliament. At a later
  date, however, the railway was built entirely at government cost
  (<i>supra</i>, § <i>Communications</i>). Owing to the financial strain
  imposed upon it the company decided to withdraw Captain Lugard and his
  forces in August 1891; and eventually the British government assumed a
  protectorate over the country (see <ph outputclass="sc">Uganda</ph>).</p>
      <p>Further difficulties now arose which led finally to the extinction of
  the company. Its pecuniary interests sustained a severe <ph outputclass="sidenote">The company and the crown.</ph> blow owing to the
  British government—which had taken Zanzibar under its protection in
  November 1890—declaring (June 1892) the dominions of the sultan
  within the free trade zone. This act extinguished the treaties regulating
  all tariffs and duties with foreign powers, and gave free trade all along
  the coast. The result for the company was that dues were now swept away
  without compensation, and the company was left saddled with the payment
  of the rent, and with the cost, in addition, of administration, <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page605">[v.04
  p.0605]</ph>the necessary revenue for which had been derived from the
  dues thus abolished. Moreover, a scheme of taxation which it drew up
  failed to gain the approval of the foreign office.</p>
      <p>In every direction the company's affairs had drifted into an
  <i>impasse</i>. Plantations had been taken over on the coast and worked
  at a loss, money had been advanced to native traders and lost, and
  expectations of trade had been disappointed. At this crisis Sir William
  Mackinnon, the guiding spirit of the company, died (June 1893). At a
  meeting of shareholders on the 8th of May 1894 an offer to surrender the
  charter to the government was approved, though not without strong
  protests. Negotiations dragged on for over two years, and ultimately the
  terms of settlement were that the government should purchase the
  property, rights and assets of the company in East Africa for £250,000.
  Although the company had proved unprofitable for the shareholders (when
  its accounts were wound up they disclosed a total deficit of £193,757) it
  had accomplished a great deal of good work and had brought under British
  sway not only the head waters of the upper Nile, but a rich and healthy
  upland region admirably adapted for European colonization. To the
  judgment, foresight and patriotism of Sir William Mackinnon British East
  Africa practically owes its foundation. Sir William and his colleagues of
  the company were largely animated by humanitarian motives—the
  desire to suppress slavery and to improve the condition of the natives.
  With this aim they prohibited the drink traffic, started industrial
  missions, built roads, and administered impartial justice. In the opinion
  of a later administrator (Sir C. Eliot), their work and that of their
  immediate successors was the greatest philanthropic achievement of the
  latter part of the 19th century.</p>
      <p>On the 1st of July 1895 the formal transfer to the British crown of
  the territory administered by the company took place at Mombasa, the
  foreign office assuming responsibility for its administration. The
  territory, hitherto known as "Ibea," from the initials of the company,
  was now styled the East Africa protectorate. The small sultanate of Witu
  (<i>q.v.</i>) on the mainland opposite Lamu, from 1885 to 1890 a German
  protectorate, was included in the British protectorate. Coincident with
  the transfer of the administration to the imperial government a dispute
  as to the succession to a chieftainship in the Mazrui, the most important
  Arab family on the coast, led to a revolt which lasted ten months and
  involved much hard fighting. It ended in April 1896 in the flight of the
  rebel leaders to German territory, where they were interned. The
  rebellion marks an important epoch in the history of the protectorate as
  its suppression definitely substituted European for Arab influence.
  "Before the rebellion," says Sir C. Eliot, "the coast was a protected
  Arab state; since its suppression it has been growing into a British
  colony."</p>
      <p>From 1896, when the building of the Mombasa-Victoria Nyanza railway
  was begun, until 1903, when the line was <ph outputclass="sidenote">A white
  man's country.</ph> practically completed, the energies of the
  administration were largely absorbed in that great work, and in
  establishing effective control over the Masai, Somali, and other tribes.
  The coast lands apart, the protectorate was regarded as valuable chiefly
  as being the high road to Uganda. But as the railway reached the high
  plateaus the discovery was made that there were large areas of
  land—very sparsely peopled—where the climate was excellent
  and where the conditions were favourable to European colonization. The
  completion of the railway, by affording transport facilities, made it
  practicable to open the country to settlers. The first application for
  land was made in April 1902 by the East Africa Syndicate—a company
  in which financiers belonging to the Chartered Company of South Africa
  were interested—which sought a grant of 500 sq. m.; and this was
  followed by other applications for considerable areas, a scheme being
  also propounded for a large Jewish settlement.</p>
      <p>During 1903 the arrival of hundreds of prospective settlers, chiefly
  from South Africa, led to the decision to entertain no more applications
  for large areas of land, especially as questions were raised concerning
  the preservation for the Masai of their rights of pasturage. In the
  carrying out of this policy a dispute arose between Lord Lansdowne,
  foreign secretary, and Sir Charles Eliot, who had been commissioner since
  1900. The foreign secretary, believing himself bound by pledges given to
  the syndicate, decided that they should be granted the lease of the 500
  sq. m. they had applied for; but after consulting officials of the
  protectorate then in London, he refused Sir Charles Eliot permission to
  conclude leases for 50 sq. m. each to two applicants from South Africa.
  Sir Charles thereupon resigned his post, and in a public telegram to the
  prime minister, dated Mombasa, the 21st of June 1904, gave as his
  reason:—"Lord Lansdowne ordered me to refuse grants of land to
  certain private persons while giving a monopoly of land on unduly
  advantageous terms to the East Africa Syndicate. I have refused to
  execute these instructions, which I consider unjust and impolitic."<xref href="#d1e15801/Footnote_121" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref>
      </p>
      <p>On the day Sir Charles sent this telegram the appointment of Sir
  Donald W. Stewart, the chief commissioner of Ashanti, to succeed him was
  announced. Sir Donald induced the Masai whose grazing rights were
  threatened to remove to another district, and a settlement of the land
  claims was arranged. An offer to the Zionist Association of land for
  colonization by Jews was declined in August 1905 by that body, after the
  receipt of a report by a commissioner sent to examine the land (6000 sq.
  m.) offered. Sir Donald Stewart died on the 1st of October 1905, and was
  succeeded by Colonel Hayes Sadler, the commissioner of Uganda. Meantime,
  in April 1905, the administration of the protectorate had been
  transferred from the foreign to the colonial office. By the close of 1905
  considerably over a million acres of land had been leased or sold by the
  protectorate authorities—about half of it for grazing purposes. In
  1907, to meet the demands of the increasing number of white inhabitants,
  who had formed a Colonists' Association<xref href="#d1e15801/Footnote_122" type="fn"><!--[2]--></xref> for the promotion of their
  interests, a legislative council was established, and on this council
  representatives of the settlers were given seats. The style of the chief
  official was also altered, "governor" being substituted for
  "commissioner". In the same year a scheme was drawn up for assisting the
  immigration of British Indians to the regions adjacent to the coast and
  to Victoria Nyanza, districts not suitable for settlement by
  Europeans.</p>
      <p>In general the relations of the British with the tribes of the
  interior have been satisfactory. The Somali in Jubaland have given some
  trouble, but the Masai, notwithstanding their warlike reputation,
  accepted peaceably the control of the whites. This was due, in great
  measure, to the fact that at the period in question plague carried off
  their cattle wholesale and reduced them for years to a state of want and
  weakness which destroyed their warlike habits. One of the most
  troublesome tribes proved to be the Nandi, who occupied the southern part
  of the plateau west of the Mau escarpment. They repeatedly raided their
  less warlike neighbours and committed wholesale thefts from the railway
  and telegraph lines. In September 1905 an expedition was sent against
  them which reduced the tribe to submission in the following November; and
  early in 1906 the Nandi were removed into a reserve. The majority of the
  natives, unaccustomed to regular work, showed themselves averse from
  taking service under the white farmers. The inadequacy of the labour
  supply was an early cause of trouble to the settlers, while the labour
  regulations enforced led, during 1907-1908, to considerable friction
  between the colonists and the administration.</p>
      <p>For several years after the establishment of the protectorate the
  northern region remained very little known and no attempt was made to
  administer the district. The natives were frequently raided by parties of
  Gallas and Abyssinians, and in the absence of a defined frontier
  Abyssinian government posts were pushed south to Lake Rudolf. The
  Abyssinians also made themselves masters of the Boran country. After long
  negotiations an agreement as to the boundary line between the lake and
  <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page606">[v.04
  p.0606]</ph>the river Juba was signed at Adis Ababa on the 6th of
  December 1907, and in 1908-1909 the frontier was delimited by an
  Anglo-Abyssinian commission, Major C.W. Gwynn being the chief British
  representative. Save for its north-eastern extremity Lake Rudolf was
  assigned to the British, Lake Stefanie falling to Abyssinia, while from
  about 4° 20′ N. the Daua to its junction with the Juba became the
  frontier.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Bibliography</ph>.—The most comprehensive
  account of the protectorate to the close of 1904, especially of its
  economic resources, is <i>The East Africa Protectorate</i>, by Sir
  Charles Eliot (London, 1905). The progress of the protectorate is
  detailed in the <i>Reports</i> by the governor issued annually by the
  British government since 1896, and in <i>Drumkey's Year Book for East
  Africa</i> (Bombay), first issued in 1908. The <i>Précis of
  Information</i> concerning the British East Africa Protectorate (issued
  by the War Office, London, 1901) is chiefly valuable for its historical
  information. The work of the Imperial British East Africa Company is
  concisely and authoritatively told from official documents in <i>British
  East Africa or Ibea</i>, by P.L. McDermont (new ed., London, 1895).
  Another book, valuable for its historical perspective, is <i>The
  Foundation of British East Africa</i>, by J.W. Gregory (London, 1901).
  Bishop A.R. Tucker's <i>Eighteen Years in Uganda and East Africa</i>
  (London, 1908) contains a summary of missionary labours. Of the works of
  explorers <i>Through Masai Land</i>, by Joseph Thomson (London, 1886), is
  specially valuable. For the northern frontier see Capt. P. Maud's report
  in <i>Africa No. 13</i> (1904). For geology see, besides Thomson's book,
  <i>The Great Rift Valley</i>, by J.W. Gregory (London, 1896); <i>Across
  an East African Glacier</i>, by Hans Meyer (London and Leipzig, 1890);
  and <i>Report relating to the Geology of the East Africa
  Protectorate</i>, by H.B. Muff (Colonial Office, London, 1908). For big
  game and ornithology see <i>On Safari</i>, by A. Chapman (London, 1908).
  The story of the building of the Uganda railway is summarized in the
  <i>Final Report of the Uganda Railway Committee, Africa, No. 11</i>
  (1904), published by the British government.</p>
      <p>(F. R. C.)</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_121"> See
  <i>Correspondence relating to the Resignation of Sir C. Eliot, Africa,
  No. 8</i> (1904).</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_122"> The Planters and
  Farmers' Association, as this organization was originally called, dates
  from 1903.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>