<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e29971">
   <title>BUCKHOLDT</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCKHOLDT--> [properly <ph outputclass="sc">Beukelsz</ph>, or <ph outputclass="sc">Bockelszoon</ph>], <b>JOHANN</b> (<i>c.</i> 1508-1535),
  Dutch Anabaptist fanatic, better known as <ph outputclass="sc">John of
  Leiden</ph>, from his place of birth, was the illegitimate son of
  Bockel, burgomaster of Soevenhagen, who afterwards married his mother. He
  was born about 1508, apprenticed to a tailor, became infected with the
  opinions of Thomas Münzer, travelled in pursuit of his trade (being four
  years in London), married a widow, became bankrupt, and in September 1533
  joined the Anabaptist movement under Johann Matthysz (Matthyszoon), baker
  of Haarlem. He had little education, but some literary faculty, and had
  written plays. On the 13th of January 1534 he appeared in Münster as an
  apostle of Matthysz. Good-looking and fluent, he fascinated women, and
  won the confidence of Bernard Knipperdollinck, a revolutionary cloth
  merchant, who gave him his daughter in marriage. The Münster Anabaptists
  took up arms on the 9th of February 1534 (see <ph outputclass="sc">Anabaptists</ph>). On the death of Matthysz (1534),
  Buckholdt succeeded him as prophet, added his widow to the number of his
  wives, and organized a new constitution for Münster, with twelve elders
  (suggested by the tribes of Israel) and other officers of a theocracy,
  but soon superseded these, making himself king of the new Zion. His
  arbitrary rule was marked by pomp and severity. Münster was retaken (June
  25, 1535) by its prince-bishop, Franz von Waldeck. Buckholdt, after many
  indignities, was cruelly executed on the 22nd of January 1536; his body,
  and those of his companions, were hung in cages to the tower of the
  Lamberti church. His portrait is in <i>Grouwelen der Hooftketteren</i>
  (Leiden, 1607; an English edition is appended to Alexander Ross's
  <i>Pansebeia</i>, 2nd ed., 1655); a better example of the same is given
  by Arend.</p>
      <p>See Arend, <i>Algemeene Geschiedenis des Vaderlands</i> (1846), ii.,
  iii., 629; Van der Aa, <i>Biographisch Woordenboek der Nederlanden</i>
  (1853); E. Belfort Bax, <i>Rise and Fail of the Anabaptists</i>
  (1903).</p>
      <p>(<ph outputclass="sc">A. Go.*</ph>)</p>
   </body>
</topic>