<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25319">
   <title>BRUGES</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUGES--> (Flemish <i>Brugge</i>, a name signifying the bridge or
  place of bridges), the capital of West Flanders, Belgium. Pop. (1904)
  53,728. The city contains some of the finest monuments of the great
  period of the Flemish communes, while its medieval appearance is better
  preserved, as a whole, than in the case of any other Belgian city. The
  cathedral of St Sauveur and the church of Notre-Dame, both specimens of
  early Pointed Gothic, date from the 13th and 14th centuries. Both are
  full of interest, but the cathedral was much injured by fire in 1839. The
  interior, however, is finely proportioned and exhibits beautiful modern
  polychrome decorations, numerous pictures and interesting monumental
  brasses. The church of Notre-Dame contains a fine De Crayer (The
  Adoration of the Magi), Michelangelo's marble group of the Virgin and
  Child, and the fine monuments with gilded copper effigies of Charles the
  Bold and his daughter, Mary of Burgundy. The hospital of St Jean, where
  the sick have been cared for since the 12th century, contains the chief
  works of Memling, including the famous reliquary of St Ursula. The
  market-hall was built in 1561-1566 on the site of an older building, some
  portions of which were utilized in its successor. The belfry which rises
  in the centre of the façade dates from the end of the 13th century; it
  has long been famous for its chime of bells, but the civic fathers have
  caused modern airs to be substituted for the old hymn. The hôtel de
  ville, the Chapelle du Saint-Sang and the church of St Jacques are all of
  interest. The first is Gothic and was begun about 1376. The second is a
  chapel of two storeys, the lower dating from 1150, while the upper was
  rebuilt in the 15th century, and there is a rich Flamboyant entrance with
  a stairway (1533). St Jacques' church is a foundation of the 13th
  century, but has extensive additions of the close of the 15th and 17th
  centuries. The Palais de Justice, of the 18th century, on the site of the
  House of the Franc—the outside burghers of the Franc district
  admitted to the full privileges of citizenship—contains a fine
  carved chimney-piece (1530). The house is supposed to have formed part of
  the residence of the counts of Flanders. There are numerous other
  buildings of minor antiquarian interest; the fine museum contains a
  representative gallery of early Flemish paintings; and of the old
  fortifications three gates remain. The <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page679">[v.04 p.0679]</ph>manufacture of
  lace now gives employment to at least 6000 persons in the town, and
  horticulture is carried on extensively in the suburbs. Commercial
  activity has been assisted by the new ship-canal to Zeebrugge, and by
  direct steamship service from Hull to Bruges. The steady growth of the
  population is evidence of increased prosperity. In 1880 the population
  was only 44,500, but it had risen in 1900 to 51,657 and in 1904 it was
  53,728.</p>
      <p>Bruges is said to have been a city in the 7th century, and the name
  Flanders was originally applied to it and not to the district. Baldwin
  II., count of Flanders, who married Elstrud, daughter of Alfred the
  Great, first fortified it, and made it his chief residence. Before the
  year 1180 Bruges was the recognized capital of Flanders, and the
  formality of proclaiming the new counts was always performed on the
  <i>marché du vendredi</i>, where the railway station is to-day. After
  1180 the premier position was assumed by Ghent, but until access by sea
  was stopped by the silting up of the Zwyn, which was complete by the year
  1490, Bruges was the equal in wealth and power of its neighbour. Proof of
  this is supplied by the marriage festivities in 1430, when Philip the
  Good, duke of Burgundy, wedded Isabel of Portugal, and founded the famous
  order of the Golden Fleece out of compliment to the staple industry of
  Bruges. Bruges was at the height of its prosperity in the 14th century,
  when it was the northern counterpart of Venice and its Bourse regulated
  the rate of exchange in Europe.</p>
      <p>(D. C. B.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>