<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22567">
   <title>BROOME, WILLIAM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROOME, WILLIAM--> (1689-1745), English scholar and poet, the son
  of a farmer, was born at Haslington, Cheshire, where he was baptized on
  the 3rd of May 1689. He was educated at Eton, where he became captain of
  the school, and at St John's College, Cambridge. He collaborated with
  John Ozell and William Oldisworth in a translation (1712) of the
  <i>Iliad</i> from the French version of Madame Dacier, and he contributed
  in the same year some verses to <i>Lintot's Miscellany</i>. He was
  introduced to Pope, who was at that time engaged on his translation of
  the <i>Iliad</i>. Pope asked Broome to make a digest for him of the notes
  of Eustathius, the 12th-century annotator of Homer. This task Broome
  executed to Pope's entire satisfaction, refusing any payment. He was
  rector of Sturston, Norfolk, and his prosperity was further assured by
  his marriage in 1716 with a rich widow, Mrs Elizabeth Clarke. When Pope
  undertook the translation of the <i>Odyssey</i>, he engaged Elijah Fenton
  and Broome to assist him. Broome's facility in verse had gained for him
  at college the nickname of "the poet," and he adapted his style very
  closely to Pope's. He translated the 2nd, 6th, 8th, 11th, 12th, 16th,
  18th and 23rd books, and practically provided all the notes. He was a
  vain, talkative man, and did not fail to make known his real share in the
  translation, of which Pope had given a very misleading account in the
  "proposals" issued to subscribers. He casually mentioned Broome as his
  coadjutor, as though his assistance was of an entirely subsidiary
  character. His influence over Broome was so strong that the latter was
  induced to write a note at the end of the translation minimizing his own
  share and implicating Fenton, who, moreover, had not wished his name to
  appear, in the deception. "If my performance," he said, "has merit either
  in these [the notes] or in any part of the translation, namely the 6th,
  11th and 18th books, it is but just to attribute it to the judgment and
  care of Mr Pope, by whose hand every sheet was corrected." For the
  <i>Odyssey</i> Pope received £4500, of which Broome, who had provided a
  third of the text and the notes, received £570. He had hoped to secure
  fame from his connexion with Pope, and when he found that Pope had no
  intention of praising him he complained bitterly of being underpaid. Pope
  thought that Broome's garrulity had caused the reports which were being
  circulated to his disadvantage, and ungenerously made satirical allusions
  to him in the <i>Dunciad</i>
         <xref href="#d1e22567/Footnote_161" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> and the <i>Bathos</i>. After
  these insults Broome's patience gave way, and there is a gap in his
  correspondence with Pope, but in 1730 the intercourse was renewed on
  friendly terms. In 1728 the degree of LL.D. was conferred on him by the
  university of Cambridge, and he was presented to the rectory of Pulham,
  Norfolk, and subsequently by Charles, 1st Earl Cornwallis, who had been
  his friend at Cambridge, to two livings, Oakley Magna in Essex, and Eye
  in Suffolk. He died at Bath on the 16th of November 1745.</p>
      <p>Broome was also the author of some translations from Anacreon printed
  in the <i>Gentleman's Magazine</i>, and of <i>Poems on Several
  Occasions</i> (1727). His poems are included in Johnson's and other
  collections of the British poets. His connexion with Pope is exhaustively
  discussed in Elwin and Courthope's edition of Pope's <i>Works</i> (viii.
  pp. 30-186), where the correspondence between the two is reproduced.</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_161"> i. 146, "worthy
  Settle Banks and Broome." A footnote (1743) explained away the allusion
  by making it apply to Richard Brome, the disciple of Ben Jonson. Also
  iii. 332, of which the original rendering was:—

            <lines>
      "Hibernian politics, O Swift, thy doom,
      And Pope's, translating ten whole years with Broome."
    </lines>
         <p>In the <i>Bathos</i> he was classed with the parrots and the
  tortoises.</p></fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>