<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25201">
   <title>BRUCITE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUCITE,--> a mineral consisting of magnesium hydroxide,
  Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>, and crystallizing in the rhombohedral system. It was
  first described in 1814 as "native magnesia" from New Jersey by A. Bruce,
  an American mineralogist, after whom the species was named by F.S.
  Beudant in 1824; the same name had, however, been earlier applied to the
  mineral now known as chondrodite. Brucite is usually found as platy
  masses, sometimes of considerable size, which have a perfect cleavage
  parallel to the surface of the plates. It is white, sometimes with a
  tinge of grey, blue or green, varies from transparent to translucent, and
  on the cleavage surfaces has a pronounced pearly lustre. In general
  appearance and softness (H = 2½) it is thus not unlike gypsum or talc,
  but it may be readily distinguished from these by its optical character,
  being uniaxial with positive birefringence, whilst gypsum is biaxial and
  talc has negative birefringence. The specific gravity is 2.38-2.40. In
  the variety known as nemalite the structure is finely fibrous and the
  lustre silky: this variety contains 5 to 8% of ferrous oxide replacing
  magnesia, and has consequently a rather higher specific gravity, viz.
  2.45. Another variety, manganbrucite, has the magnesia partly replaced by
  manganous oxide (14%), and thus forms a passage to the isomorphous
  mineral pyrochroite, Mn(OH)<sub>2</sub>.</p>
      <p>Brucite is generally associated with other magnesian minerals, such as
  magnesite and dolomite, and is commonly found in serpentine, or sometimes
  as small scales in phyllites and crystalline schists; it has also been
  observed in metamorphosed magnesian limestone, such as the rock known as
  predazzite from Predazzo in Tirol. The best crystals and foliated masses
  are from Texas in Pennsylvania, U.S.A., and from Swinaness in Unst, one
  of the Shetland Isles. Nemalite is from Hoboken, New Jersey, and from
  Afghanistan. At all these localities the mineral forms veins in
  serpentine.</p>
      <p>(L. J. S.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>