<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22911">
   <title>BROUGHAM, JOHN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROUGHAM, JOHN--> (1814-1880), British actor, was born at Dublin
  on the 9th of May 1814, and was educated for a surgeon. Owing to family
  misfortunes he was thrown upon his own resources and made his first
  appearance on the London stage in 1830, at the Tottenham Street theatre
  in <i>Tom and Jerry</i>, in which he played six characters. In 1831 he
  was a member of Madame Vestris's company, and wrote his first play, a
  burlesque. He remained with Madame Vestris as long as she and Charles
  Mathews retained Covent Garden, and he collaborated with Dion Boucicault
  in writing <i>London Assurance</i>, Dazzle being one of his best parts.
  In 1840 he managed the Lyceum theatre, for which he wrote several light
  burlesques, but in 1842 he moved to the United States, where he became a
  member of W.E. Burton's company, for which he wrote several comedies.
  Later he was the manager of Niblo's Garden, and in 1850 opened Brougham's
  Lyceum, which, like his next speculation, the lease of the Bowery
  theatre, was not financially a success. He was later connected with
  Wallack's and Daly's theatres, and wrote plays for both. In 1860 he
  returned to London, where he adapted or wrote several plays, including
  <i>The Duke's Motto</i> for Fechter. After the Civil War he returned to
  New York. Brougham's theatre was opened in 1869 with his comedy <i>Better
  Late than Never</i>, but this managerial experience was also unfortunate,
  and he took to playing with various stock companies. His last appearance
  was in 1879 as O'Reilly, the detective, in Boucicault's <i>Rescued</i>,
  and he died in New York on the 7th of June 1880. Brougham was the author
  of nearly 100 plays, most of them now forgotten. He was the founder of
  the Lotus Club in New York, and for a time its president. He also edited
  there in 1852 a comic paper called <i>The Lantern</i>, and published two
  collections of miscellaneous writings, <i>A Basket of Chips</i> and
  <i>The Bunsby Papers</i>. Brougham is said to have been the original of
  Harry Lorrequer in Charles Lever's novel. He was twice married, in 1838
  to Emma Williams (d. 1865), and in 1844 to Mrs Annette Hawley (d. 1870),
  both actresses.</p>
   </body>
</topic>