<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25752">
   <title>BRUNHILD</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNHILD--> (M.H. Ger. <i>Brünhilt</i> or <i>Prünhilt</i>, Nor.
  <i>Brynhildr</i>), the name of a mythical heroine of various versions of
  the legend of the Nibelungs. The name means "the warrior woman in armour"
  (from O.H. Ger. <i>brunjô</i>, <i>brunja</i>, M.H. Ger. <i>brunige</i>,
  <i>brünje</i>, <i>brünne</i>, a cuirass or coat of mail, O. Eng.
  <i>byrnie</i>, and O.H. Ger. <i>hiltja</i>, <i>hilta</i>, war), and in
  the Norse versions of the Nibelung myth, which preserves more of the
  primitive traditions than the <i>Nibelungenlied</i>, Brunhild is a
  valkyrie, the daughter of Odin, by whom, as a punishment for having
  against his orders helped a warrior to victory, she has been cast under a
  spell of sleep on Hindarfjell, a lonely rock summit, until the destined
  hero shall penetrate the wall of fire by which she is surrounded, and
  wake her. This is a variant of the widespread myth which survives in the
  popular fairy-story of "the sleeping beauty." The ingenuity of some
  German scholars has made of Brunhild a personification of the day, held
  prisoner upon the hill-tops till in the morning the sun-god comes to her
  rescue, then triumphing with him awhile, only to pass once more under the
  spell of the powers of mist and darkness. She is thus by some
  commentators contrasted with "the masked warrior woman" Kriemhild
  (<i>q.v.</i>), a personification of the power of night and death. But
  whatever be the dim original of the character of Brunhild—as to
  which authorities are by no means agreed—even in the northern
  versions its mythical interest is quite subordinate to its purely human
  interest. In the <i>Volsungasaga</i> she is the heroine of a tragedy of
  passion and wounded pride; it is she who compasses the death of Sigurd,
  who has broken his troth plighted to her, and then immolates herself on
  his funeral pyre in order that in the world of the dead he may be wholly
  hers. In the <i>Nibelungenlied</i>, on the other hand, she plays a
  comparatively colourless rôle. She still possesses superhuman attributes:
  like Atalanta, she can only be won by the man who is able to overcome her
  in trials of speed and strength; but, instead of a valkyrie sleeping on a
  lonely rock, she is, when Sigfrid goes to woo her on behalf of Gunther,
  queen of Îslant (Îsenlant), living in a castle called the Isenstein. In
  the tragedy of the death of Sigfrid her part is completely overshadowed
  by that of "the grim Hagen," and from the moment that the murder is
  decided on she drops almost completely out of the story. The poet of the
  <i>Nibelungenlied</i> evidently knew nothing of the tale of her
  self-immolation; for, though he has nothing definite to say about her
  after Sigfrid's death, he keeps her alive in a sort of dignified
  retirement. In the last 5000 lines or so of the poem Brunhild is only
  mentioned four times and takes no active part in the story. (See further
  under <ph outputclass="sc">Nibelungenlied</ph>.)</p>
      <p>(W. A. P.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>