<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e20170">
   <title>BRODIE, PETER BELLINGER</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRODIE, PETER BELLINGER--> (1815-1897), English geologist, son of
  P.B. Brodie, barrister, and nephew of Sir Benjamin C. Brodie, was born in
  London in 1815. While still residing with his father at Lincoln's Inn
  Fields, he gained some knowledge of natural history and an interest in
  fossils from visits to the museum of the Royal College of Surgeons, at a
  time when W. Clift was curator. Through the influence of Clift he was
  elected a fellow of the Geological Society early in 1834. Proceeding
  afterwards to Emmanuel College, Cambridge, he came under the spell of
  Sedgwick, and henceforth devoted all his leisure time to geology.
  Entering the church in 1838, he was curate at Wylye in Wiltshire, and for
  a short time at Steeple Claydon in Buckinghamshire, becoming later rector
  of Down Hatherley in Gloucestershire, and finally (1855) vicar of
  Rowington in Warwickshire, and rural dean. Records of geological
  observations in all these districts were published by him. At Cambridge
  he obtained fossil shells from the Pleistocene deposit at Barn well; in
  the Vale of Wardour he discovered in Purbeck Beds the isopod named by
  Milne-Edwards <i>Archaeoniscus Brodiei</i>; in Buckinghamshire he
  described the outliers of Purbeck and <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page626">[v.04 p.0626]</ph>Portland Beds;
  and in the Vale of Gloucester the Lias and Oolites claimed his attention.
  Fossil insects, however, formed the subject of his special studies
  (<i>History of the Fossil Insects of the Secondary Rocks of England</i>,
  1845), and many of his published papers relate to them. He was an active
  member of the Cotteswold Naturalists' Club and of the Warwickshire
  Natural History and Archaeological Society, and in 1854 he was chief
  founder of the Warwickshire Naturalists' and Archaeologists' Field Club.
  In 1887 the Murchison medal was awarded to him by the Geological Society
  of London. He died at Rowington, on the 1st of November 1897.</p>
      <p>See Memoir by H. B. Woodward in <i>Geological Magazine</i>, 1897, p.
  481 (with portrait).</p>
   </body>
</topic>