<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23581">
   <title>BROWN, ROBERT</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWN, ROBERT--> (1773-1858), British botanist, was born on the
  21st of December 1773 at Montrose, and was educated at the grammar school
  of his native town, where he had as contemporaries Joseph Hume and James
  Mill. In 1787 he entered Marischal College, Aberdeen, but two years
  afterwards removed to Edinburgh University, where his taste for botany
  attracted the attention of John Walker (1731-1803), then professor of
  natural history in the university. In 1795 he obtained a commission in
  the Forfarshire regiment of Fencible Infantry as "ensign and assistant
  surgeon," and served in the north of Ireland. In 1798 he made the
  acquaintance of Sir Joseph Banks, by whom in 1801 he was offered the post
  of naturalist to the expedition fitted out under Captain Matthew Flinders
  for the survey of the then almost unknown coasts of Australia. Ferdinand
  Bauer, afterwards familiarly associated with Brown in his botanical
  discoveries, was draughtsman; William Westall was landscape painter; and
  among the midshipmen was one afterwards destined to rise into fame as Sir
  John Franklin. In 1805 the expedition returned to England, having
  obtained, among other acquisitions, nearly 4000 species of plants, many
  of which were new. Brown was almost immediately appointed librarian of
  the Linnean Society. In this position, though one of no great emolument,
  he had abundant opportunities of pursuing his studies; but it was not
  until 1810 that he published the first volume of his great work, in
  Latin, the <i>Prodromus Florae Novae Hollandiae et Insulae Van
  Diemen</i>, which did much to further the general adoption of A.L. de
  Jussieu's natural system of plant classification. Its merits were
  immediately recognized, and it gave its author an international
  reputation among botanists. It is rare in its original edition, the
  author having suppressed it, hurt at the <i>Edinburgh Review</i> having
  fallen foul of its Latinity. With the exception of a supplement published
  in 1830, no more of the work appeared. In 1810 Brown became librarian to
  Sir Joseph Banks, who on his death in 1820 bequeathed to him the use and
  enjoyment of his library and collections for life. In 1827 an arrangement
  was made by which these were transferred to the British Museum, with
  Brown's consent and in accordance with Sir Joseph's will. Brown then
  became keeper of this new botanical department, an office which he held
  until his death. Soon after Banks's decease he resigned the librarianship
  of the Linnean Society, and from 1849 to 1853 he served as its president.
  He received many honours. Elected a fellow of the Royal Society in 1811,
  he received its Copley medal in 1839, for his "discoveries on the subject
  of vegetable impregnation," and in 1833 he was elected one of the five
  foreign associates of the Institute of France. Among his other
  distinctions was membership of the order "pour le Mérite" of Prussia. In
  the <i>Academia Caesarea Naturae Curiosorum</i> he sat under the cognomen
  of Ray. He died on the 10th of June 1858, in the house in Soho Square,
  London, bequeathed to him by Sir Joseph Banks. His works, which embrace
  not only systematic botany, but also plant anatomy and physiology, are
  distinguished by their thoroughness and conscientious accuracy, and
  display powers at once of minute detail and of broad generalization. The
  continual movements observed by the microscope among minute particles
  suspended in a liquid were noticed by him in 1827, and hence are known as
  "Brownian movements."</p>
      <p>In 1825-1834 his works up to that date were collected and published in
  four divisions by Nees von Esenbeck, in German, under the title of
  <i>Vermischte botanische Schriften</i> (Leipzig and Nuremberg). In 1866
  the Ray Society reprinted, under the editorship of his friend and
  successor in the keepership of the Botanical Department of the British
  Museum, J.J. Bennet, his complete writings, the <i>Prodromus</i> alone
  excepted. In these <i>Miscellaneous Works</i> (2 vols., with atlas of
  plates) the history of his discoveries can be best followed.</p>
   </body>
</topic>