<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e24522">
   <title>BROWNING, ROBERT</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWNING, ROBERT--> (1812-1889), English poet, was born at
  Camberwell, London, on the 7th of May 1812. He was the son of Robert
  Browning (1781-1866), who for fifty years was employed in the Bank of
  England. Earlier Brownings had been settled in Wiltshire and Dorsetshire,
  and there is no ground for the statement that the family was partly of
  Jewish origin. The poet's mother was a daughter of William Wiedemann, a
  German who had settled in Dundee and married a Scottish wife. His parents
  had one other child, a daughter, Sarianna, born in 1814. They lived
  quietly in Camberwell. The elder Browning <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page671">[v.04 p.0671]</ph>had a
  sufficient income and was indifferent to money-making. He had strong
  literary and artistic tastes. He was an ardent book collector, and so
  good a draughtsman that paternal authority alone had prevented him from
  adopting an artistic career. He had, like his son, a singular faculty for
  versifying, and helped the boy's early lessons by twisting the Latin
  grammar into grotesque rhymes. He lived, as his father had done, to be
  84, with unbroken health. The younger Robert inherited, along with other
  characteristics, much of his father's vigour of constitution. From the
  mother, who had delicate health, he probably derived his excessive
  nervous irritability; and from her, too, came his passion for music. The
  family was united by the strongest mutual affection, and the parents
  erred, if anything, on the side of indulgence. Browning was sent to a
  school in the neighbourhood, but left it when fourteen, and had little
  other teaching. He had a French tutor for the next two years, and in his
  eighteenth year he attended some Greek lectures at the London University.
  At school he never won a prize, though it was more difficult to avoid
  than to win prizes. He was more conspicuous for the love of birds and
  beasts, which he always retained, than for any interest in his lessons.
  He rather despised his companions and made few friends. A precocious
  poetical capacity, however, showed itself in extra-scholastic ways. He
  made his schoolfellows act plays, partly written by himself. He had
  composed verses before he could write, and when twelve years old
  completed a volume of poems called <i>Incondita</i>. His parents tried
  unsuccessfully to find a publisher; but his verses were admired by Sarah
  Flower, afterwards Mrs Adams, a well-known hymn-writer of the day, and by
  W.J. Fox, both of whom became valuable friends. A copy made by Miss
  Flower was in existence in 1871, but afterwards destroyed by the author.
  Browning had the run of his father's library, and acquired a very unusual
  amount of miscellaneous reading. Quarles' <i>Emblems</i> was an especial
  favourite; and besides the Elizabethan dramatists and standard English
  books, he had read all the works of Voltaire. Byron was his first master
  in poetry, but about the age of fourteen he fell in accidentally with
  Shelley and Keats. For Shelley in particular he conceived an <ph outputclass="correction">enthusiastic</ph>
  admiration which lasted for many years, though it was qualified in his
  later life.</p>
      <p>The more aggressive side of Browning's character was as yet the most
  prominent; and a self-willed lad, conscious of a growing ability, found
  himself cramped in Camberwell circles. He rejected the ordinary careers.
  He declined the offer of a clerkship in the Bank of England; and his
  father, who had found the occupation uncongenial, not only approved the
  refusal but cordially accepted the son's decision to take poetry for his
  profession. For good or evil, Browning had been left very much to his own
  guidance, and if his intellectual training suffered in some directions,
  the liberty permitted the development of his marked originality. The
  parental yoke, however, was too light to provoke rebellion. Browning's
  mental growth led to no violent breach with the creeds of his childhood.
  His parents became Dissenters in middle life, but often attended Anglican
  services; and Browning, though he abandoned the dogmas, continued to
  sympathize with the spirit of their creed. He never took a keen interest
  in the politics of the day, but cordially accepted the general position
  of contemporary Liberalism. His worship of Shelley did not mean an
  acceptance of his master's hostile attitude towards Christianity, still
  less did he revolt against the moral discipline under which he had been
  educated. He frequented literary and artistic circles, and was
  passionately fond of the theatre; but he was entirely free from a coarse
  Bohemianism, and never went to bed, we are told, without kissing his
  mother. He lived with his parents until his marriage. His mother lived
  till 1849, and his father till 1866, and his affectionate relations to
  both remained unaltered. Browning's first published poem, <i>Pauline</i>,
  appeared anonymously in 1833. He always regarded it as crude, and
  destroyed all the copies of this edition that came within his reach. It
  was only to avoid unauthorized reprints that he consented with reluctance
  to republishing it in the collected works of 1868. The indication of
  genius was recognized by W.J. Fox, who hailed it in the <i>Monthly
  Repository</i> as marking the advent of a true poet. <i>Pauline</i>
  contains an enthusiastic invocation of Shelley, whose influence upon its
  style and conception is strongly marked. It is the only one of Browning's
  works which can be regarded as imitative. In the winter of 1833 he went
  to St Petersburg on a visit to the Russian consul-general, Mr
  Benckhausen. There he wrote the earliest of his dramatic lyrics,
  "Porphyria's Lover" and "Johannes Agricola." In the spring of 1834 he
  visited Italy for the first time, going to Venice and Asolo.</p>
      <p>Browning's personality was fully revealed in his next considerable
  poems, <i>Paracelsus</i> (1835) and <i>Sordello</i> (1840). With
  <i>Pauline</i>, however, they form a group. In an essay (prefixed to the
  spurious Shelley letters of 1851), Browning describes Shelley's poetry
  "as a sublime fragmentary essay towards a presentment of the
  correspondency of the universe to Deity." The phrase describes his own
  view of the true functions of a poet, and Browning, having accepted the
  vocation, was meditating the qualifications which should fit him for his
  task. The hero of <i>Pauline</i> is in a morbid state of mind which
  endangers his fidelity to his duty. <i>Paracelsus</i> and <i>Sordello</i>
  are studies in the psychology of genius, illustrating its besetting
  temptations. Paracelsus fails from intellectual pride, not balanced by
  love of his kind, and from excessive ambition, which leads him to seek
  success by unworthy means. Sordello is a poet distracted between the
  demands of a dreamy imagination and the desire to utter the thoughts of
  mankind. He finally gives up poetry for practical politics, and gets into
  perplexities only to be solved by his death. <i>Pauline</i> might in some
  indefinite degree reflect Browning's own feelings, but in the later poems
  he adopts his characteristic method of speaking in a quasi-dramatic mood.
  They are, as he gave notice, "poems, not dramas." The interest is not in
  the external events, but in the "development of a soul"; but they are
  observations of other men's souls, not direct revelations of his own.
  Paracelsus was based upon a study of the original narrative, and Sordello
  was a historical though a very indefinite person. The background of
  history is intentionally vague in both cases. There is one remarkable
  difference between them. The <i>Paracelsus</i>, though full of noble
  passages, is certainly diffuse. Browning heard that John Sterling had
  complained of its "verbosity," and tried to remedy this failing by the
  surgical expedient of cutting out the usual connecting words. Relative
  pronouns henceforth become scarce in his poetry, and the grammatical
  construction often a matter of conjecture. Words are forcibly jammed
  together instead of being articulately combined. To the ordinary reader
  many passages in his later work are both crabbed and obscure, but the
  "obscurity" never afterwards reached the pitch of <i>Sordello</i>. It is
  due to the vagueness with which the story is rather hinted than told, as
  well as to the subtlety and intricacy of the psychological expositions.
  The subtlety and vigour of the thought are indeed surprising, and may
  justify the frequent comparisons to Shakespeare; and it abounds in
  descriptive passages of genuine poetry.</p>
      <p>Still, Browning seems to have been misled by a fallacy. It was quite
  legitimate to subordinate the external incidents to the psychological
  development in which he was really interested, but to secure the
  subordination by making the incidents barely intelligible was not a
  logical consequence. We should not understand Hamlet's psychological
  peculiarities the better if we had to infer his family troubles from
  indirect hints. Browning gave more time to <i>Sordello</i> than to any
  other work, and perhaps had become so familiar with the story which he
  professed to tell that he failed to make allowance for his readers'
  difficulties. In any case it was not surprising that the ordinary reader
  should be puzzled and repelled, and the general recognition of his genius
  long delayed, by his reputation for obscurity.</p>
      <p>It might, however, be expected that he would make a more successful
  appeal to the public by purely dramatic work, in which he would have to
  limit his psychological speculation and to place his characters in plain
  situations. <i>Paracelsus</i> and <i>Sordello</i> show so great a power
  of reading character and appreciating subtler springs of conduct that its
  author clearly had one, at least, of the essential qualifications of a
  dramatist.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page672">[v.04 p.0672]</ph>
      </p>
      <p>Before <i>Sordello</i> appeared Browning had tried his hand in this
  direction. He was encouraged by outward circumstances as well as by his
  natural bent. He was making friends and gaining some real appreciative
  admirers. John Forster had been greatly impressed by <i>Paracelsus</i>.
  Browning's love of the theatre had led to an introduction to Macready in
  the winter of 1835-1836; and Macready, who had been also impressed by
  <i>Paracelsus</i>, asked him for a play. Browning consented and wrote
  <i>Strafford</i>, which was produced at Covent Garden in May 1837,
  Macready taking the principal part. Later dramas were <i>King Victor and
  King Charles</i>, published in 1842; <i>The Return of the Druses</i> and
  <i>A Blot on the 'Scutcheon</i> (both in 1843), <i>Colombe's Birthday</i>
  (1844), <i>Luria</i> and <i>A Soul's Tragedy</i> (both in 1846), and the
  fragmentary <i>In a Balcony</i> (1853). <i>Strafford</i> succeeded
  fairly, though the defection of Vandenhoff, who took the part of Pym,
  stopped its run after the fifth performance. The <i>Blot on the
  'Scutcheon</i>, produced by Macready as manager of Drury Lane on the 11th
  of February 1843, led to an unfortunate quarrel. Browning thought that
  Macready had felt unworthy jealousy of another actor, and had gratified
  his spite by an inadequate presentation of the play. He remonstrated
  indignantly and the friendship was broken off for years. Browning was
  disgusted by his experience of the annoyances of practical play-writing,
  though he was not altogether discouraged. The play had apparently such a
  moderate success as was possible under the conditions, and a similar
  modest result was attained by <i>Colombe's Birthday</i>, produced at
  Covent Garden on the 25th of April 1853. Browning, like other eminent
  writers of the day, failed to achieve the feat of attracting the British
  public by dramas of high literary aims, and soon gave up the attempt. It
  has been said by competent critics that some of the plays could be fitted
  for the stage by judicious adaptation. The <i>Blot on the 'Scutcheon</i>
  has a very clear and forcibly treated situation; and all the plays abound
  in passages of high poetic power. Like the poems, they deal with
  situations involving a moral probation of the characters, and often
  suggesting the ethical problems which always interested him. The speeches
  tend to become elaborate analyses of motive by the persons concerned, and
  try the patience of an average audience. For whatever reason, Browning,
  though he had given sufficient proofs of genius, had not found in these
  works the most appropriate mode of utterance.</p>
      <p>The dramas, after <i>Strafford</i>, formed the greatest part of a
  series of pamphlets called <i>Bells and Pomegranates</i>, eight of which
  were issued from 1841 to 1846. The name, he explained, was intended to
  indicate an "alternation of poetry and thought." The first number
  contained the fanciful and characteristic <i>Pippa Passes</i>. The
  seventh, significantly named <i>Dramatic Romances and Lyrics</i>,
  contained some of his most striking shorter poems. In 1844 he contributed
  six poems, among which were "The Flight of the Duchess" and "The Bishop
  orders his Tomb at St Praxed's Church," to Hood's <i>Magazine</i>, in
  order to help Hood, then in his last illness. These poems take the
  special form in which Browning is unrivalled. He wrote very few lyrical
  poems of the ordinary kind purporting to give a direct expression of his
  own personal emotions. But, in the lyric which gives the essential
  sentiment of some impressive dramatic situation, he has rarely been
  approached. There is scarcely one of the poems published at this time
  which can be read without fixing itself at once in the memory as a
  forcible and pungent presentation of a characteristic mood. Their vigour
  and originality failed to overcome at once the presumption against the
  author of <i>Sordello</i>. Yet Browning was already known to and
  appreciated by such literary celebrities of the day as Talfourd, Leigh
  Hunt, Procter, Monckton Milnes, Carlyle and Landor. His fame began to
  spread among sympathetic readers. The <i>Bells and Pomegranates</i>
  attracted the rising school of "pre-Raphaelites," especially D.G.
  Rossetti, who guessed the authorship of the anonymous <i>Pauline</i> and
  made a transcript from the copy in the British Museum. But his audience
  was still select.</p>
      <p>Another recognition of his genius was of incomparably more personal
  importance and vitally affected his history. In 1844 Miss Barrett (see
  <ph outputclass="sc">Browning, Elizabeth Barrett</ph>) published a volume
  of poems containing "Lady Geraldine's Courtship," with a striking phrase
  about Browning's poems. He was naturally gratified, and her special
  friend and cousin, John Kenyon, encouraged him to write to her. She
  admitted him to a personal interview after a little diffidence, and a
  hearty appreciation of literary genius on both sides was speedily ripened
  into genuine and most devoted love. Miss Barrett was six years older than
  Browning and a confirmed invalid with shaken nerves. She was tenderly
  attached to an autocratic father who objected on principle to the
  marriage of his children. The correspondence of the lovers (published in
  1899) shows not only their mutual devotion, but the chivalrous delicacy
  with which Browning behaved in a most trying situation. Miss Barrett was
  gradually encouraged to disobey the utterly unreasonable despotism. They
  made a clandestine marriage on the 12th of September 1846. The state of
  Miss Barrett's health suggested misgivings which made Browning's parents
  as well as his bride's disapprove of the match. She, however, appears to
  have become stronger for some time, though always fragile and incapable
  of much active exertion. She had already been recommended to pass a
  winter in Italy. Browning had made three previous tours there, and his
  impressions had been turned to account in <i>Sordello</i> and <i>Pippa
  Passes</i>, in <i>The Englishman in Italy</i> and <i>Home Thoughts from
  Abroad</i>. For the next fifteen years the Brownings lived mainly in
  Italy, making their headquarters at Florence in the Casa Guidi. A couple
  of winters were passed in Rome. In the summer of 1849 they were at Siena,
  where Browning was helpful to Landor, then in his last domestic troubles.
  They also visited England and twice spent some months in Paris. Their
  only child, Robert Wiedemann Browning, was born at Florence in 1849.
  Browning's literary activity during his marriage seems to have been
  comparatively small; <i>Christmas Eve and Easter Day</i> appeared in
  1850, while the two volumes called <i>Men and Women</i> (1855),
  containing some of his best work, showed that his power was still
  growing. His position involved some sacrifice and imposed limitations
  upon his energies. Mrs Browning's health required a secluded life; and
  Browning, it is said, never dined out during his marriage, though he
  enjoyed society and made many and very warm friendships. Among their
  Florence friends were Margaret Fuller Ossoli, Isa Blagden, Charles Lever
  and others. The only breach of complete sympathy with his wife was due to
  his contempt for "spiritualists" and "mediums," in whom she fully
  believed. His portrait of Daniel Dunglas Home as "Sludge the Medium" only
  appeared after her death. This domestic happiness, however, remained
  essentially unbroken until she died on 29th June 1861. The whole
  love-story had revealed the singular nobility of his character, and,
  though crushed for a time by the blow, he bore it manfully. Browning
  determined to return to England and superintend his boy's education at
  home. He took a house at 19 Warwick Crescent, Paddington, and became
  gradually acclimatized in London. He resumed his work and published the
  <i>Dramatis Personae</i> in 1864. The publication was well enough
  received to mark the growing recognition of his genius, which was
  confirmed by <i>The Ring and the Book</i>, published in four volumes in
  the winter of 1868-1869. In 1867 the university of Oxford gave him the
  degree of M.A. "by diploma," and Balliol College elected him as an
  honorary fellow. In 1868 he declined a virtual offer of the rectorship of
  St Andrews. He repeated the refusal on a later occasion (1884) from a
  dislike to the delivery of a public address. The rising generation was
  now beginning to buy his books; and he shared the homage of thoughtful
  readers with Tennyson, though in general popularity he could not approach
  his friendly rival. <i>The Ring and the Book</i> has been generally
  accepted as Browning's masterpiece. It was based on a copy of the
  <i>procès verbal</i> of Guido Franceschini's case discovered by him at
  Florence.</p>
      <p>The audacity of the scheme is surprising. To tell the story of a
  hideous murder twelve times over, to versify the arguments of counsel and
  the gossip of quidnuncs, and to insist upon every detail with the
  minuteness of a law report, could have occurred to no one else. The poem
  is so far at the opposite pole from <i>Sordello</i>. Vagueness of
  environment is replaced by a photographic <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page673">[v.04 p.0673]</ph>distinctness,
  though the psychological interest is dominant in both. Particular phrases
  may be crabbed, but nothing can be more distinct and vivid in thought and
  conception. If some of those "dramatic monologues" of which the book is
  formed fail to be poetry at all, some of them—that of Pompilia the
  victim, her champion Caponsacchi, and the pope who gives
  judgment—are in Browning's highest mood, and are as impressive from
  the ethical as from the poetical point of view. Pompilia was no doubt in
  some respects an idealized portrait of Mrs Browning. Other pieces may be
  accepted as a background of commonplace to throw the heroic into the
  stronger relief. <i>The Ring and the Book</i> is as powerful as its
  method is unique.</p>
      <p>Browning became gentler and more urbane as he grew older. His growing
  fame made him welcome in all cultivated circles, and he accepted the
  homage of his admirers with dignity and simplicity. He exerted himself to
  be agreeable in private society, though his nervousness made him
  invariably decline ever to make public speeches. He was an admirable
  talker, and took pains to talk his best. A strong memory supplied him
  with abundant anecdotes; and though occasionally pugnacious, he allowed a
  fair share of the conversation to his companions. Superficial observers
  sometimes fancied that the poet was too much sunk in the man of the
  world; but the appearance was due to his characteristic reluctance to lay
  bare his deeper feelings. When due occasion offered, the underlying
  tenderness of his affections was abundantly manifest. No one could show
  more delicate sympathy. He made many warm personal friendships in his
  later years, especially with women, to whom he could most easily confide
  his feelings. In the early years of this period he paid visits to country
  houses, but afterwards preferred to retire farther from the London
  atmosphere into secluded regions. He passed some holidays in remote
  French villages, Pornic, Le Croisic and St Aubyn, which have left traces
  in his poetry. <i>Gold Hair</i> is a legend of Pornic, and <i>Hervé
  Riel</i> was written at Le Croisic. At St Aubyn he had the society of
  Joseph Milsand, who had shown his warm appreciation of Browning's poetry
  by an article in the <i>Revue des Deux Mondes</i>, which in 1852 had led
  to a personal friendship lasting till Milsand's death in 1886. Browning
  sent to him the proof-sheets of all his later works for revision. In 1877
  Browning was at La Saisiaz on the Salève, near Geneva, where an old
  friend, Miss Egerton Smith, was staying. She died suddenly almost in his
  presence. She had constantly accompanied him to concerts during his
  London life. After her death he almost ceased to care for music. The
  shock of her loss produced the singular poem called <i>La Saisiaz</i>, in
  which he argues the problem of personal immortality with a rather
  indefinite conclusion. In later years Browning returned to Italy, and
  passed several autumns at Venice. He never visited Florence after his
  wife's death there.</p>
      <p>Browning's literary activity continued till almost the end of his
  life. He wrote constantly, though he composed more slowly. He considered
  twenty-five or thirty lines to be a good day's work. His later writings
  covered a very great variety of subjects, and were cast in many different
  forms. They show the old characteristics and often the old genius.
  Browning's marked peculiarity, the union of great speculative acuteness
  with intense poetical insight, involved difficulties which he did not
  always surmount. He does not seem to know whether he is writing poetry or
  when he is versifying logic; and when the speculative impulse gets the
  upper hand, his work suggests the doubt whether an imaginary dialogue in
  prose would not have been a more effective medium. He is analysing at
  length when he ought to be presenting a concrete type, while the
  necessities of verse complicate and obscure the reasoning. A curious
  example is the <i>Prince Hohenstiel-Schwangau</i> (1871), an <i>alias</i>
  for Louis Napoleon. The attempt to show how a questionable hero
  apologizes to himself recalls the very powerful "Bishop Blougram," and
  "Sludge, the medium," of earlier works, but becomes prolix and obscure.
  <i>Fifine at the Fair</i> (1872) is another curious speculation
  containing a defence of versatility in lovemaking by an imaginary Don
  Juan. Its occasionally cynical tone rather scandalized admirers, who
  scarcely made due allowance for its dramatic character. Browning's
  profound appreciation of high moral qualities is, however, always one
  main source of his power. In later years he became especially interested
  in stories of real life, which show character passing through some sharp
  ordeal. The <i>Red Cotton Nightcap Country</i> (1873), describing a
  strange tragedy which had recently taken place in France, and especially
  <i>The Inn Album</i> (1875), founded on an event in modern English
  society, are powerful applications of the methods already exemplified in
  <i>The Ring and the Book</i>. The <i>Dramatic Idyls</i> (1879 and 1880)
  are a collection of direct narratives, with less analytical disquisition,
  which surprised his readers by their sustained vigour. In the last
  volumes, <i>Jocoseria</i> (1883), <i>Ferishtah's Fancies</i> (1884),
  <i>Parleying with Certain People</i> (1887) and <i>Asolando</i> (1889),
  the old power is still apparent but the hand is beginning to fail. They
  contain discussions of metaphysical problems, such as the origin of evil,
  which are interesting as indications of his creed, but can scarcely be
  regarded as successful either poetically or philosophically.</p>
      <p>Another group of poems showed Browning's interest in Greek literature.
  <i>Balaustion's Adventure</i> (1871) includes a "transcript from
  Euripides," a translation, that is, of part of the <i>Alcestis</i>.
  <i>Aristophanes' Apology</i> (1875) included another translation from the
  <i>Heracles</i>, and in 1877 he published a very literal translation of
  the <i>Agamemnon</i>. This, it seems, was meant to disprove the doctrine
  that Æschylus was a model of literary style. Browning shared his wife's
  admiration for Euripides, and takes a phrase from one of her poems as a
  motto for <i>Balaustion's Adventure</i>. In the <i>Aristophanes'
  Apology</i> this leads characteristically to a long exposition by
  Aristophanes of his unsatisfactory reasons for ridiculing Euripides. It
  recalls the apologies of "Blougram" and Louis Napoleon, and contains some
  interesting indications of his poetical theory. Browning was to many
  readers as much prophet as poet. His religious position is most
  explicitly, though still not very clearly, set forth in the <i>Christmas
  Eve and Easter Day</i> (1850). Like many eminent contemporaries, he
  combined a disbelief in orthodox dogma with a profound conviction of the
  importance to the religious instincts of the symbols incorporated in
  accepted creeds. <i>Saul</i> (1845), <i>A Death in the Desert</i> (1864),
  and similar poems, show his strong sympathy with the spirit of the old
  belief, though his argumentative works have a more or less sceptical
  turn. It was scarcely possible, if desirable, to be original on such
  topics. His admirers hold that he shows an affinity to German
  metaphysicians, though he had never read their works nor made any express
  study of metaphysical questions. His distinctive tendency is to be found
  rather in the doctrine of life and conduct which both suggests and is
  illustrated by his psychological analyses. A very characteristic thought
  emphatically set forth in the <i>Rabbi Ben Ezra</i> (1864) and the
  <i>Grammarian's Funeral</i> (1855) is that a man's value is to be
  measured, not by the work done, but by the character which has been
  moulded. He delights in exhibiting the high moral instinct which dares to
  override ordinary convictions, or which is content with discharge of
  obscure duties, or superior to vulgar ambition and capable of
  self-sacrifice, because founded upon pure love and sympathy for human
  suffering. Browning's limitations are characteristic of the poetry of
  strong ethical preoccupations. His strong idiosyncrasy, his sympathy with
  the heroic and hatred of the base, was hardly to be combined with the
  Shakespearian capacity for sympathizing with the most varied types of
  character. Though he deals with a great variety of motive with singularly
  keen analysis, he takes almost exclusively the moral point of view. That
  point of view, however, has its importance, and his morality is often
  embodied in poetry of surpassing force. Browning's love of the grotesque,
  sometimes even of the horrible, creates many most graphic and indelible
  portraits. The absence of an exquisite sense for the right word is
  compensated by the singular power of striking the most brilliant flashes
  out of obviously wrong words, and forcing comic rhymes to express the
  deepest and most serious thoughts. Though he professed to care little for
  motive as apart from human interest, his incidental touches of
  description are unsurpassably vivid.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page674">[v.04 p.0674]</ph>
      </p>
      <p>The appreciation of Browning's genius became general in his later
  years, and zeal was perhaps a little heightened by the complacency of
  disciples able to penetrate a supposed mist of obscurity. The Browning
  Society, founded in 1881 by Dr F.J. Furnivall and Miss E.H. Hickey, was a
  product of this appreciation, and helped to extend the study of the
  poems. Browning accepted the homage in a simple and friendly way, though
  he avoided any action which would make him responsible for the
  publications. He received various honours: LL.D. degree from Cambridge in
  1879, the D.C.L. from Oxford in 1882, and LL.D. from Edinburgh in 1884.
  He became foreign correspondent to the Royal Academy in 1886. His son,
  who had settled at Venice, married in 1887, and Browning moved to De Vere
  Gardens. In the autumn of 1889 he went with his sister to visit his son,
  and stayed on the way at Asolo, which he had first seen in 1838, when it
  supplied the scenery of <i>Pippa Passes</i>. He was charmed with the
  place, and proposed to buy a piece of ground and to build upon it a house
  to be called "Pippa's Tower"—in memory of his early heroine. While
  his proposal was under consideration he went to his son at Venice. His
  health had been breaking for some time, and a cold, aggravated by
  weakness of the heart, brought on a fatal attack. He died on the 12th of
  December 1889. He was buried in Westminster Abbey on 31st December. It
  was suggested that his wife's body should be removed from Florence to be
  placed beside him; but their son rightly decided that her grave should
  not be disturbed.</p>
      <p>Browning's personal characteristics are so strongly stamped upon all
  his works that it is difficult to assign his place in contemporary
  thought. He is unique and outside of all schools. His style is so
  peculiar that he is the easiest of all poets to parody and the most
  dangerous to imitate. In spite of his early Shelley worship he is in
  certain respects more closely related to Wordsworth. Both of them started
  by accepting the poet's mission as quasi-prophetical or ethical. In other
  respects they are diametrically contrasted. Wordsworth expounded his
  philosophy by writing a poetical autobiography. Browning adheres to the
  dramatic method of which Wordsworth was utterly incapable. He often
  protested against the supposition that he put himself into his books. Yet
  there is no writer whose books seem to readers to be clearer revelations
  of himself. Nothing, in fact, is more characteristic of a man than his
  judgments of other men, and Browning's are keen and unequivocal. The
  revolutionary impulse had died out, and Browning has little to say either
  of the political questions which had moved Shelley and Byron, or of the
  social problems which have lately become more prominent. He represents
  the thought of a quieter epoch. He was little interested, too, in the
  historical or "romantic" aspect of life. He takes his subjects from a
  great variety of scenes and places—from ancient Greece, medieval
  Italy and modern France and England; but the interest for him is not in
  the picturesque surroundings, but in the human being who is to be found
  in all periods. Like Balzac, whom he always greatly admired, he is
  interested in the eternal tragedy and comedy of life. His problem is
  always to show what are the really noble elements which are eternally
  valuable in spite of failure to achieve tangible results. He gives, so
  far, another version of Wordsworth's doctrine of the cultivation of the
  "moral being." The psychological acuteness and the subtle analysis of
  character are, indeed, peculiar to himself. Like Carlyle, with whom he
  had certain points of affinity, he protests, though rather by implication
  than direct denunciation, against the utilitarian or materialistic view
  of life, and finds the divine element in the instincts which guide and
  animate every noble character. When he is really inspired by sympathy for
  such emotions he can make his most grotesque fancies and his most
  far-fetched analyses subservient to poetry of the highest order. It can
  hardly be denied that his intellectual ingenuity often tempts him to
  deviate from his true function, and that his observations are not to be
  excused because they result from an excess, instead of a deficiency, of
  intellectual acuteness. But the variety of his interests—aesthetic,
  philosophical and ethical—is astonishing, and his successes are
  poems which stand out as unique and unsurpassable in the literature of
  his time.</p>
      <p>
         <i>The Life and Letters of Browning</i>, by Mrs Sutherland Orr (1891),
  one of his most intimate friends in later years, and <i>The Love Letters
  of Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Barrett, 1845-1846</i>,
  published by his son in 1899, are the main authorities. A collection of
  Browning's poems in 2 vols. appeared in 1849, another in 3 vols. in 1863,
  another in 6 vols. in 1868, and a revised edition in 16 vols. in
  1888-1889; in 1896 Mr Augustine Birrell and Mr F.G. Kenyon edited a
  complete edition in 2 vols.; another two-volume edition was issued by
  Messrs Smith, Elder in 1900. Among commentaries on Browning's works, Mrs
  Sutherland Orr's <i>Handbook to the Works of Browning</i> was approved by
  the poet himself. See also the Browning Society's <i>Papers</i>; and Mr
  T.J. Wise's <i>Materials for a Bibliography of the Writings of Robert
  Browning</i>, included in the <i>Literary Anecdotes of the Nineteenth
  Century</i> (1895), by W. Robertson Nicoll and T.J. Wise; Mr. Edmund
  Gosse's <i>Robert Browning: Personalia</i> (1890), from notes supplied by
  Browning himself. Among biographical and critical authorities may be
  mentioned: J.T. Nettleship, <i>Essays</i> (1868); Arthur Symons, <i>An
  Introduction to the Study of Browning</i> (1886); Stopford Brooke, <i>The
  Poetry of Robert Browning</i> (1902); G.K. Chesterton, <i>Browning</i>
  (1908) in the "English Men of Letters" series.</p>
      <p>(L. S.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>