<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e19281">
   <title>BRITTANY</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRITTANY-->, or <ph outputclass="sc">Britanny</ph> (Fr.
  <i>Bretagne</i>), known as Armorica (<i>q.v.</i>) until the influx of
  Celts from Britain, an ancient province and duchy of France, consisting
  of the north-west peninsula, and nearly corresponding to the departments
  of Finistère, Côtes-du-Nord, Morbihan, Ille-et-Vilaine and Lower Loire.
  It is popularly divided into Upper or Western, and Lower or Eastern
  Brittany. Its greatest length between the English Channel and the
  Atlantic Ocean is 250 kilometres (about 155 English miles), and its
  superficial extent is 30,000 sq. kilometres (about 18,630 English sq.
  m.). It comprises two distinct zones, a maritime zone and an inland zone.
  In the centre there are two plateaus, partly covered with <i>landes</i>,
  unproductive moorland: the southern plateau is continued by the Montagnes
  Noires, and the northern is dominated by the Monts d'Arrée. These ranges
  nowhere exceed 1150 ft. in height, but from their wild nature they recall
  the aspect of high mountains. The waterways of Brittany are for the most
  part of little value owing to their torrent-like character. The only
  river basin of any importance is that of the Vilaine, which flows through
  Rennes. The coast is very much indented, especially along the English
  Channel, and is rocky and lined with reefs and islets. The mouths of the
  rivers form deep estuaries. Thus nature itself condemned Brittany to
  remain for a long time shut out from civilization. But in the 19th
  century the development of railways and other means of communication drew
  Brittany from its isolation. In the 19th century also agriculture
  developed in a remarkable manner. Many of the <i>landes</i> were cleared
  and converted into excellent pasturage, and on the coast market-gardening
  made great progress. In the fertile districts cereals too are cultivated.
  Industrial pursuits, except in a few seaport towns, which are rather
  French than Breton, have hitherto received but little attention.</p>
      <p>The Bretons are by nature conservative. They cling with almost equal
  attachment to their local customs and their religious superstitions. It
  was not till the 17th century that paganism was even nominally abolished
  in some parts, and there is probably no district in Europe where the
  popular Christianity has assimilated more from earlier creeds. Witchcraft
  and the influence of fairies are still often believed in. The costume of
  both sexes is very peculiar both in cut and colour, but varies
  considerably in different districts. Bright red, violet and blue are much
  used, not only by the women, but in the coats and waistcoats of the men.
  The reader will find full illustrations of the different styles in
  Bouet's <i>Breiz-izel, ou vie des Breions de l'Armorique</i> (1844). The
  Celtic language is still spoken in lower Brittany. Four dialects are
  pretty clearly marked (see the article <ph outputclass="sc">Celt</ph>:
  <i>Language</i>, "<i>Breton</i>," p. 328). Nowhere has the taste for
  marvellous legends been kept so green as in Brittany; and an entire
  folk-literature still flourishes there, as is manifested by the large
  number of folk-tales and folk-songs which have been collected of late
  years.</p>
      <p>The whole duchy was formerly divided into nine
  bishoprics:—Rennes, Dol, Nantes, St Malo and St Brieuc, in Upper
  Brittany and Tréguier, Vannes, Quimper and St Pol de Léon in Lower.</p>
      <p>
         <i>History.</i>—Of Brittany before the coming of the Romans we
  have no exact knowledge. The only traces left by the primitive
  populations are the megalithic monuments (dolmens, menhirs and
  cromlechs), which remain to this day in great numbers (see <ph outputclass="sc">Stone Monuments</ph>). In 56 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>
  the Romans destroyed the fleet of the Veneti, and in 52 the inhabitants
  of Armorica took part in the great insurrection of the Gauls against
  Caesar, but were subdued finally by him in 51. Roman civilization was
  then established for several centuries in Brittany.</p>
      <p>In the 5th century numbers of the Celtic inhabitants of Britain,
  flying from the Angles and Saxons, emigrated to Armorica, and populated a
  great part of the peninsula. Converted to Christianity, the new-comers
  founded monasteries which helped to clear the land, the greater part of
  which was barren and wild. The Celtic immigrants formed the counties of
  Vannes, Cornouaille, Léon and Domnonée. A powerful aristocracy was
  constituted, which owned estates and had them cultivated by serfs or
  villeins. The Celts sustained a long struggle against the Frankish kings,
  who only nominally occupied Brittany. Louis the Pious placed a native
  chief Nomenoë at the head of Brittany. There was then a fairly long
  period of peace; but Nomenoë rebelled against Charles the Bald, defeated
  him, and forced him, in 846, to recognize the independence of Brittany.
  The end of the 9th century and the beginning of the 10th were remarkable
  for the invasions of the Northmen. On several occasions they were driven
  back—by Salomon (d. 874) and afterwards by Alain, count of Vannes
  (d. 907)—but it was Alain Barbetorte (d. 952) who gained the
  decisive victory over them.</p>
      <p>In the second half of the 10th century and in the 11th century the
  counts of Rennes were predominant in Brittany. Geoffrey, son of Conan,
  took the title of duke of Brittany in 992. Conan II., Geoffrey's
  grandson, threatened by the revolts of the nobles, was attacked also by
  the duke of Normandy (afterwards William I. of England). Alain Fergent,
  one of his successors, defeated William in 1085, and forced him to make
  peace. But in the following century the Plantagenets succeeded in
  establishing themselves in Brittany. Conan IV., defeated by the revolted
  Breton nobles, appealed to Henry II. of England, who, in reward for his
  help, forced Conan to give his daughter in marriage to his son Geoffrey.
  Thus Henry II. became master of Brittany, and Geoffrey was recognized as
  duke of Brittany. But this new dynasty was not destined to last long.
  Geoffrey's posthumous son, Arthur, was assassinated by John of England in
  1203, and Arthur's sister Alix, who succeeded to his rights, was married
  in 1212 to Pierre de Dreux, who became duke. This was the beginning of a
  ducal dynasty of French origin, which lasted till the end of the 15th
  century.</p>
      <p>From that moment the ducal power gained strength in Brittany and
  succeeded in curbing the feudal nobles. Under French influence
  civilization made notable progress. For more than a century peace reigned
  undisturbed in Brittany. But in 1341 the death of John III., without
  direct heir, provoked a war of succession between the houses of Blois and
  Montfort, which lasted till 1364. This war of succession was, in reality,
  an incident of the Hundred Years' War, the partisans of Blois and
  Montfort supporting respectively the kings of France and England. In 1364
  John of Montfort (d. 1399) was recognized as duke of Brittany under the
  style of John IV.<xref href="#d1e19281/Footnote_141" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref>, but his reign <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page618">[v.04 p.0618]</ph>was
  constantly troubled, notably by his struggle with Olivier de Clisson
  (1336-1407). John V. (d. 1442), on the other hand, distinguished himself
  by his able and pacific policy. During his reign and the reigns of his
  successors, Francis I., Peter II. and Arthur III., the ducal authority
  developed in a remarkable manner. The dukes formed a standing army, and
  succeeded in levying hearth taxes (<i>fouages</i>) throughout Brittany.
  Francis II. (1435-1488) fought against Louis XI., notably during the War
  of the Public Weal, and afterwards engaged in the struggle against
  Charles VIII., known as "The Mad War" (<i>La Guerre Folle</i>). After the
  death of Francis II. the king of France invaded Brittany, and forced
  Francis's daughter, Anne of Brittany, to marry him in 1491. Thus the
  reunion of Brittany and France was prepared. After the death of Charles
  VIII. Anne married Louis XII. Francis I., who married Claude, the
  daughter of Louis XII. and Anne, settled the definitive annexation of the
  duchy by the contract of 1532, by which the maintenance of the privileges
  and liberties of Brittany was guaranteed. Until the Revolution Brittany
  retained its own estates. The royal power, however, was exerted to reduce
  the privileges of the province as much as possible. It often met with
  vigorous resistance, notably in the 18th century. The struggle was
  particularly keen between 1760 and 1769, when E. A. de V. du Plessis
  Richelieu, duc d'Aiguillon, had to fight simultaneously the estates and
  the parliament, and had a formidable adversary in L. R. de C. de la
  Chalotais. But under the monarchy the only civil war in Brittany in which
  blood was shed was the revolt of the duc de Mercœur (d. 1602)
  against the crown at the time of the troubles of the League, a revolt
  which lasted from 1589 to 1598. Mention, however, must also be made of a
  serious popular revolt which broke out in 1675—"the revolt of the
  stamped paper."</p>
      <p>See Bertrand d'Argentré, <i>Histoire de Bretagne</i> (Paris, 1586);
  Dom Lobineau, <i>Histoire de Bretagne</i> (Paris, 1702); Dom Morice,
  <i>Histoire de Bretagne</i> (1742-1756); T. A. Trollope, <i>A Summer in
  Brittany</i> (1840); A. du Chatellier, <i>L'Agriculture et les classes
  agricoles de la Bretagne</i> (1862); F. M. Luzel, <i>Légendes chrétiennes
  de la Basse-Bretagne</i> (Paris, 1881), and <i>Veillées bretonnes</i>
  (Paris, 1879); A. Dupuy, <i>La Réunion de la Bretagne à la France</i>
  (Paris, 1880), and <i>Études sur l'administration municipale en Bretagne
  au XVIII<sup>e</sup> siècle</i> (1891); J. Loth, <i>L'Émigration bretonne
  en Armorique du V<sup>e</sup> au VII<sup>e</sup> siècle</i> (Rennes,
  1883); H. du Cleuziou, <i>Bretagne artistique et pittoresque</i> (Paris,
  1886); Arthur de la Borderie, <i>Histoire de Bretagne</i> (Rennes, 1896
  seq.); J. Lemoine, <i>La Révolte du papier timbré ou des bonnets rouges
  en Bretagne en 1675</i> (1898); M. Marion, <i>La Bretagne et le duc
  d'Aiguillon</i> (Paris, 1898); B. Pocquet, <i>Le Duc d'Aiguillon et la
  Chalotais</i> (Paris, 1900-1902); Anatole le Braz, <i>Vieilles Histoires
  du pays breton</i> (1897), and <i>La Légende de la mort</i> (Paris,
  1902); Ernest Lavisse, <i>Histoire de France</i>, vol. i. (Paris, 1903);
  Henri Sée, <i>Étude sur les classes rurales en Bretagne au moyen âge</i>
  (1896), and <i>Les Classes rurales en Bretagne du XVI<sup>e</sup> siècle
  à la Revolution</i> (1906).</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_141"> Certain
  authorities count the father of this duke, another John of Montfort (d.
  1345), among the dukes of Brittany, and according to this enumeration the
  younger John becomes John V., not John IV., and his successor John VI.
  and not John V.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>