<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22748">
   <title>BROTHER</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROTHER-->, a male person in his relation to the other children of
  the same father and mother. "Brother" represents in English the Teutonic
  branch of a word common to the Indo-European languages, of. Ger.
  <i>Bruder</i>, Dutch <i>broeder</i>, Dan. and Swed. <i>broder</i>,
  &amp;c. In Celtic languages, Gaelic and Irish have <i>brathair</i>, and
  Welsh <i>brawd</i>; in Greek the word is <ph outputclass="grk">φράτηρ</ph>, in Lat. <i>frater</i>, from
  which come the Romanic forms, Fr. <i>frère</i>, Ital. <i>fratello</i>;
  the Span. <i>fray</i>, Port. <i>frei</i>, like the Ital. <i>frate</i>,
  <i>fra</i>, are only used of "friars." The Span. <i>hermano</i> and the
  Port. <i>irmāo</i>, the regular words for brother, are from Lat.
  <i>germanus</i>, born of the same father and mother. The Sanskrit word is
  <i>bhrātār</i>, and the ultimate Indo-European root is
  generally taken to be <i>bhar</i>, to bear (cf. M. H. Ger. <i>barn</i>,
  Scot, <i>bairn</i>, child, and such words as "birth," "burden").
  "Brother" has often been loosely used of kinsmen generally, or for
  members of the same tribe; also for quite fictitious relationships,
  <i>e.g.</i> "blood-brothers," through a sacramental rite of mutual
  blood-tasting, "foster-brothers," because suckled by the same nurse.
  Christianity, through the idea of the universal fatherhood of God,
  conceives all men as brothers; but in a narrower sense "the brethren" are
  the members of the Church, or, in a narrower still, of a confraternity or
  "brotherhood" within the Church. This latter idea is reproduced in those
  fraternal societies, <i>e.g.</i> the Freemasons, the members of which
  become "brothers" by initiation. "Brother" is also used symbolically, as
  implying equality, by sovereigns in addressing one another, and also by
  bishops.</p>
   </body>
</topic>