<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e21386">
   <title>BRONTË, CHARLOTTE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRONTË, CHARLOTTE--> (1816-1855), <b>EMILY</b> (1818-1848), and
  <b>ANNE</b> (1820-1849), English novelists, were three of the six
  children of Patrick Brontë, a clergyman of the Church of England, who for
  the last forty-one years of his life was perpetual incumbent of the
  parish of Haworth in the West Riding of Yorkshire. Patrick Brontë was
  born at Emsdale, Co. Down, Ireland, on the 17th of March 1777. His
  parents were of the peasant class, their original name of Brunty
  apparently having been changed by their son on his entry at St John's
  College, Cambridge, in 1802. In the intervening years he had been
  successively a weaver and schoolmaster in his native country. From
  Cambridge <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page638">[v.04 p.0638]</ph>he became a curate, first at
  Wethersfield in Essex, in 1806, then for a few months at Wellington,
  Salop, in 1809. At the end of 1809 he accepted a curacy at Dewsbury,
  Yorkshire, following up this by one at Hartshead-cum-Clifton in the same
  county. At Hartshead Patrick Brontë married in 1812 Maria Branwell, a
  Cornishwoman, and there two children were born to him, Maria (1813-1825)
  and Elizabeth (1814-1825). Thence Patrick Brontë removed to Thornton,
  some 3 m. from Bradford, and here his wife gave birth to four children,
  Charlotte, Patrick Branwell (1817-1848), Emily Jane, and Anne, three of
  whom were to attain literary distinction.</p>
      <p>In April 1820, three months after the birth of Anne Brontë, her father
  accepted the living of Haworth, a village near Keighley in Yorkshire,
  which will always be associated with the romantic story of the Brontës.
  In September of the following year his wife died. Maria Brontë lives for
  us in her daughter's biography only as the writer of certain letters to
  her "dear saucy Pat," as she calls her lover, and as the author of a
  recently published manuscript, an essay entitled <i>The Advantages of
  Poverty in Religious Concerns</i>, full of a sententiousness much
  affected at the time.</p>
      <p>Upon the death of Mrs Brontë her husband invited his sister-in-law,
  Elizabeth Branwell, to leave Penzance and to take up her residence with
  his family at Haworth. Miss Branwell accepted the trust and would seem to
  have watched over her nephew and five nieces with conscientious care. The
  two eldest of those nieces were not long in following their mother. Maria
  and Elizabeth, Charlotte and Emily, were all sent to the Clergy
  Daughters' school at Cowan Bridge in 1824, and Maria and Elizabeth
  returned home in the following year to die. How far the bad food and
  drastic discipline were responsible cannot be accurately demonstrated.
  Charlotte gibbeted the school long years afterwards in <i>Jane Eyre</i>,
  under the thin disguise of "Lowood," and the principal, the Rev. William
  Carus Wilson (1792-1859), has been universally accepted as the
  counterpart of Mr Naomi Brocklehurst in the same novel. But congenital
  disease more probably accounts for the tragedy from which happily
  Charlotte and Emily escaped, both returning in 1825 to a prolonged home
  life at Haworth. Here the four surviving children amused themselves in
  intervals of study under their aunt's guidance with precocious literary
  aspirations. The many tiny booklets upon which they laboured in the
  succeeding years have been happily preserved. We find stories, verses and
  essays, all in the minutest handwriting, none giving any indication of
  the genius which in the case of two of the four children was to add to
  the indisputably permanent in literature.</p>
      <p>At sixteen years of age—in 1831—Charlotte Brontë became a
  pupil at the school of Miss Margaret Wooler (1792-1885) at Roe Head,
  Dewsbury. She left in the following year to assist in the education of
  the younger sisters, bringing with her much additional proficiency in
  drawing, French and composition; she took with her also the devoted
  friendship of two out of her ten fellow-pupils—Mary Taylor
  (1817-1893) and Ellen Nussey (1817-1897). With Miss Taylor and Miss
  Nussey she corresponded for the remainder of her life, and her letters to
  the latter make up no small part of what has been revealed to us of her
  life story. Her next three years at Haworth were varied by occasional
  visits to one or other of these friends. In 1835 she returned to Miss
  Wooler's school at Roe Head as a governess, her sister Emily accompanying
  her as a pupil, but remaining only three months, and Anne then taking her
  place. The year following the school was removed to Dewsbury. In 1838
  Charlotte went back to Haworth and soon afterwards received her first
  offer of marriage—from a clergyman, Henry Nussey, the brother of
  her friend Ellen. This was followed a little later by a second offer from
  a curate named Bryce. She refused both and took a situation as nursery
  governess, first with the Sidgwicks of Stonegappe, Yorkshire, and later
  with the Whites at Rawdon in the same county. A few months of this,
  however, filled her with an ambition to try and secure greater
  independence as the possessor of a school of her own, and she planned to
  acquire more proficiency in "languages" on the continent, as a
  preliminary step. The aunt advanced some money, and accompanied by her
  sister Emily she became in February 1842 a pupil at the Pensionnat Héger,
  Brussels. Here both girls worked hard, and won the goodwill and indeed
  admiration of the principal teacher, M. Héger, whose wife was at the head
  of the establishment. But the two girls were hastily called back to
  England before the year had expired by the announcement of the critical
  illness of their aunt. Miss Branwell died on the 29th of October 1842.
  She bequeathed sufficient money to her nieces to enable them to
  reconsider their plan of life. Instead of a school at Bridlington which
  had been talked of, they could now remain with their father, utilize
  their aunt's room as a classroom, and take pupils. But Charlotte was not
  yet satisfied with what the few months on Belgian soil had done for her,
  and determined to accept M. Héger's offer that she should return to
  Brussels as a governess. Hence the year 1843 was passed by her at the
  Pensionnat Héger in that capacity, and in this period she undoubtedly
  widened her intellectual sphere by reading the many books in French
  literature that her friend M. Héger lent her. But life took on a very
  sombre shade in the lonely environment in which she found herself. She
  became so depressed that on one occasion she took refuge in the
  confessional precisely as did her heroine Lucy Snowe in <i>Villette</i>.
  In 1844 she returned to her father's house at Haworth, and the three
  sisters began immediately to discuss the possibilities of converting the
  vicarage into a school. Prospectuses were issued, but no pupils were
  forthcoming.</p>
      <p>Matters were complicated by the fact that the only brother, Patrick
  Branwell, had about this time become a confirmed drunkard. Branwell had
  been the idol of his aunt and of his sisters. Educated under his father's
  care, he had early shown artistic leanings, and the slender resources of
  the family had been strained to provide him with the means of entering at
  the Royal Academy as a pupil. This was in 1835. Branwell, it would seem,
  indulged in a glorious month of extravagance in London and then returned
  home. His art studies were continued for a time at Leeds, but it may be
  assumed that no commissions came to him, and at last he became tutor to
  the son of a Mr Postlethwaite at Barrow-in-Furness. Ten months later he
  was a booking-clerk at Sowerby Bridge station on the Leeds &amp;
  Manchester railway, and later at Luddenden Foot. Then he became tutor in
  the family of a clergyman named Robinson at Thorp Green, where his sister
  Anne was governess. Finally he returned to Haworth to loaf at the village
  inn, shock his sisters by his excesses, and to fritter his life away in
  painful sottishness. He died in September 1848, having achieved nothing
  reputable, and having disappointed all the hopes that had been centred in
  him. "My poor father naturally thought more of his <i>only</i> son than
  of his daughters," is one of Charlotte's dreary comments on the tragedy.
  In early years he had himself written both prose and verse; and a foolish
  story invented long afterwards attributed to him some share in his
  sisters' novels, particularly in Emily Brontë's <i>Wuthering Heights</i>.
  But Charlotte distinctly tells us that her brother never knew that his
  sisters had published a line. He was too much under the effects of drink,
  too besotted and muddled in that last year or two of life, to have any
  share in their intellectual enthusiasms.</p>
      <p>The literary life had, however, opened bravely for the three girls
  during those years. In 1846 a volume of verse appeared from the shop of
  Aylott &amp; Jones of Paternoster Row; "<i>Poems</i>, by Currer, Ellis
  and Acton Bell," was on the title-page. These names disguised the
  identity of Charlotte, Emily and Anne Brontë. The venture cost the
  sisters about £50 in all, but only two copies were sold. There were
  nineteen poems by Charlotte, twenty-one by Emily, and the same number by
  Anne. A consensus of criticism has accepted the fact that Emily's verse
  alone revealed true poetic genius. This was unrecognized then except by
  her sister Charlotte. It is obvious now to all.</p>
      <p>The failure of the poems did not deter the authors from further
  effort. They had each a novel to dispose of. Charlotte Brontë's was
  called <i>The Master</i>, which before it was sent off to London was
  retitled <i>The Professor</i>. Emily's story was entitled <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page639">[v.04
  p.0639]</ph>
         <i>Wuthering Heights</i>, and Anne's <i>Agnes Gray</i>. All
  these stories travelled from publisher to publisher. At last <i>The
  Professor</i> reached the firm of Smith, Elder &amp; Co., of Cornhill.
  The "reader" for that firm, R. Smith Williams (1800-1875), was impressed,
  as were also his employers. Charlotte Brontë received in August 1847 a
  letter informing her that whatever the merits of <i>The
  Professor</i>—and it was hinted that it lacked "varied
  interest"—it was too short for the three-volume form then counted
  imperative. The author was further told that a longer novel would be
  gladly considered. She replied in the same month with this longer novel,
  and <i>Jane Eyre</i> appeared in October 1847, to be wildly acclaimed on
  every hand, although enthusiasm was to receive a counterblast when more
  than a year later, in December 1848, Miss Rigby, afterwards Lady Eastlake
  (1809-1893), reviewed it in the <i>Quarterly</i>.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile the novels of Emily and Anne had been accepted by T. C.
  Newby. They were published together in three volumes in December 1847,
  two months later than <i>Jane Eyre</i>, although the proof sheets had
  been passed by the authors before their sister's novel had been sent to
  the publishers. The dilatoriness of Mr Newby was followed up by
  considerable energy when he saw the possibility of the novels by Ellis
  and Acton Bell sailing on the wave of Currer Bell's popularity, and he
  would seem very quickly to have accepted another manuscript by Anne
  Brontë, for <i>The Tenant of Wildfell Hall</i> was published by Newby in
  three volumes in June 1848. It was Newby's clever efforts to persuade the
  public that the books he published were by the author of <i>Jane Eyre</i>
  that led Charlotte and Anne to visit London this summer and interview
  Charlotte's publishers in Cornhill with a view to establishing their
  separate identity. Soon after their return home Branwell died (the 24th
  of September 1848), and less than three months later Emily died also at
  Haworth (the 19th December 1848). Then Anne became ill and on the 24th of
  May 1849 Charlotte accompanied her to Scarborough in the hope that the
  sea air would revive her. Anne died there on the 28th of May, and was
  buried in Scarborough churchyard. Thus in exactly eight months Charlotte
  Brontë lost all the three companions of her youth, and returned to
  sustain her father, fast becoming blind, in the now desolate home at
  Haworth.</p>
      <p>In the interval between the death of Branwell and of Emily, Charlotte
  had been engaged upon a new novel—<i>Shirley</i>. Two-thirds were
  written, but the story was then laid aside while its author was nursing
  her sister Anne. She completed the book after Anne's death, and it was
  published in October 1849. The following winter she visited London as the
  guest of her publisher, Mr George Smith, and was introduced to
  Thackerary, to whom she had dedicated <i>Jane Eyre</i>. The following
  year she repeated the visit, sat for her portrait to George Richmond, and
  was considerably lionized by a host of admirers. In August 1850 she
  visited the English lakes as the guest of Sir James Kay-Shuttleworth, and
  met Mrs Gaskell, Miss Martineau, Matthew Arnold and other interesting men
  and women. During this period her publishers assiduously lent her books,
  and her criticisms of them contained in many letters to Mr George Smith
  and Mr Smith Williams make very interesting reading. In 1851 she received
  a third offer of marriage, this time from Mr James Taylor, who was in the
  employment of her publishers. A visit to Miss Martineau at Ambleside and
  also to London to the Great Exhibition made up the events of this year.
  On her way home she visited Manchester and spent two days with Mrs
  Gaskell. During the year 1852 she worked hard with a new novel,
  <i>Villette</i>, which was published in January of 1853. In September of
  that year she received a visit from Mrs Gaskell at Haworth; in May 1854
  she returned it, remaining three days at Manchester, and planning with
  her hostess the details of her marriage, for at this time she had
  promised to unite herself with her father's curate, Arthur Bell Nicholls
  (1817-1906), who had long been a pertinacious suitor for her hand but had
  been discouraged by Mr Brontë. The marriage took place in Haworth church
  on the 29th of June 1854, the ceremony being performed by the Rev.
  Sutcliffe Sowden, Miss Wooler and Miss Nussey acting as witnesses. The
  wedded pair spent their honeymoon in Ireland, returning to Haworth, where
  they made their home with Mr Brontë, Mr Nicholls having pledged himself
  to continue in his position as curate to his father-in-law. After less
  than a year of married life, however, Charlotte Nicholls died of an
  illness incidental to childbirth, on the 31st of March 1855. She was
  buried in Haworth church by the side of her mother, Branwell and Emily.
  The father followed in 1861, and then her husband returned to Ireland,
  where he remained some years afterwards, dying in 1906.</p>
      <p>The bare recital of the Brontë story can give no idea of its undying
  interest, its exceeding pathos. Their life as told by their biographer
  Mrs Gaskell is as interesting as any novel. Their achievement, however,
  will stand on its own merits. Anne Brontë's two novels, it is true,
  though constantly reprinted, survive principally through the exceeding
  vitality of the Brontë tradition. As a hymn writer she still has a place
  in most religious communities. Emily is great alike as a novelist and as
  a poet. Her "Old Stoic" and "Last Lines" are probably the finest
  achievement of poetry that any woman has given to English literature. Her
  novel <i>Wuthering Heights</i> stands alone as a monument of intensity
  owing nothing to tradition, nothing to the achievement of earlier
  writers. It was a thing apart, passionate, unforgettable, haunting in its
  grimness, its grey melancholy. Among women writers Emily Brontë has a
  sure and certain place for all time. As a poet or maker of verse
  Charlotte Brontë is undistinguished, but there are passages of pure
  poetry of great magnificence in her four novels, and particularly in
  <i>Villette</i>. The novels <i>Jane Eyre</i> and <i>Villette</i> will
  always command attention whatever the future of English fiction, by
  virtue of their intensity, their independence, their rough
  individuality.</p>
      <p>The <i>Life of Charlotte Brontë</i>, by Mrs Gaskell, was first
  published in 1857. Owing to the many controversial questions it aroused,
  as to the identity of Lowood in <i>Jane Eyre</i> with Cowan Bridge
  school, as to the relations of Branwell Brontë with his employer's wife,
  as to the supposed peculiarities of Mr Brontë, and certain other minor
  points, the third edition was considerably changed. The <i>Life</i> has
  been many times reprinted, but may be read in its most satisfactory form
  in the Haworth edition (1902), issued by the original publishers, Smith,
  Elder &amp; Co. To this edition are attached a great number of letters
  written by Miss Brontë to her publisher, George Smith. The first new
  material supplied to supplement Mrs Gaskell's <i>Life</i> was contained
  in <i>Charlotte Brontë: a Monograph</i>, by T. Wemyss Reid (1877). This
  book inspired Mr A.C. Swinburne to issue separately a forcible essay on
  Charlotte and Emily Brontë, under the title of <i>A Note on Charlotte
  Brontë</i> (1877). A further collection of letters written by Miss Brontë
  was contained in <i>Charlotte Brontë and her Circle</i>, by Clement
  Shorter (1896), and interesting details can be gathered from the <i>Life
  of Charlotte Brontë</i>, by Augustine Birrell (1887), <i>The Brontës in
  Ireland</i>, by William Wright, D.D. (1893), <i>Charlotte Brontë and her
  Sisters</i>, by Clement Shorter (1906), and the Brontë Society
  publications, edited by Butler Wood (1895-1907). Miss A. Mary F. Robinson
  (Madame Duclaux) wrote a separate biography of Emily Brontë in 1883, and
  an essay in her <i>Grands Écrivains d'outre-Manche</i>. <i>The Brontës:
  Life and Letters</i>, by Clement Shorter (1907), contains the whole of C.
  Brontë's letters in chronological order.</p>
      <p>(C. K. S.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>