<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25602">
   <title>BRUNEL, ISAMBARD KINGDOM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNEL, ISAMBARD KINGDOM--> (1806-1859), English engineer, only
  son of Sir M.I. Brunel, was born at Portsmouth on the 9th of April 1806.
  He displayed in childhood singular powers of mental calculation, great
  skill and rapidity as a draughtsman, and a true feeling for art. At the
  age of fourteen he was sent to Paris, to study at the Collège Henri
  Quatre. In 1823 he entered his father's office as assistant-engineer,
  just at the time when the project of the Thames Tunnel was beginning to
  take shape; and during the later portion of the time, from 1825, when the
  work was begun, till 1828, when it was stopped by an irruption of the
  river, he was both nominal and actual resident engineer. In November 1829
  he sent in designs and plans for the projected suspension bridge over the
  Avon at Clifton, but in consequence of objections raised by Thomas
  Telford, the referee of the bridge committee, his plans were rejected.
  But a new design which he sent in on a second competition in 1831 was
  accepted, and he was appointed engineer. The works were begun in 1836,
  but owing to lack of funds were not completed until 1864, after Brunel's
  death; his design, however, was closely adhered to, and the chains
  employed came from the old Hungerford suspension bridge (London), which
  he had built in 1841-1845, but which was displaced in 1862 by the Charing
  Cross railway bridge.</p>
      <p>In March 1833 Brunel, at the age of twenty-seven, was appointed
  engineer of the newly-projected Great Western railway. For several years
  his energies were taxed to the utmost by the conflict with obstructive
  landowners and short-sighted critics; but he showed himself equal to the
  occasion, not only as a professional man, but as a persuasive negotiator.
  Among the engineering triumphs on that railway are the Hanwell viaduct,
  the Maidenhead bridge and the Box tunnel, at the time the longest in the
  world. The famous "battle of the gauges" took its rise from his
  introduction of the broad (7 ft.) gauge on that line. In 1846 he resigned
  his office as engineer of the Great Western railway. In 1844 he had
  recommended the adoption of the atmospheric system on the South Devon
  railway, but after a year's trial the system was abandoned. The last and
  greatest of Brunel's railway works was the Royal Albert bridge over the
  river Tamar at Saltash. This work, sanctioned by parliament in 1845, was
  constructed between 1853 and 1859.</p>
      <p>In addition to the arduous labours of railway engineering Brunel took
  a leading part in the systematic development of ocean steam navigation.
  As early as October 1835 he had suggested to the directors of the Great
  Western railway, that they should "make it longer, and have a steamboat
  to go from Bristol to New York, and call it the 'Great Western.'" The
  project was taken up, and the "Great Western" steamship was designed by
  Brunel, and built at Bristol under his superintendence. It was much
  longer than any steamer of the day, and was the first steamship built to
  make regular voyages across the Atlantic. While the vessel was building a
  controversy was raised about the practicability of Brunel's scheme, Dr D.
  Lardner asserting dogmatically that the voyage could not be made, and
  backing his assertion with an array of figures. His view was widely
  accepted, but the work went on, and the voyage was accomplished in 1838.
  Brunel at once undertook a still larger design in the "Great Britain,"
  which was the first large iron steamship, the largest ship afloat at that
  time, and the first large ship in which the screw-propeller was used. She
  made her first voyage from Liverpool to New York in August and September
  1845; but in the following year was carelessly run upon the rocks in
  Dundrum Bay on the coast of Ireland. After lying there nearly a year
  without material damage she was got off and was employed in the
  Australian trade. Brunel soon after began to meditate a still vaster
  project, the construction of a vessel large enough to carry all the coal
  required for a long voyage out, and if coal could not be had at the out
  port, then to carry enough also for the return voyage. It seemed to him,
  further, that a great increase of size would give many advantages for
  navigation. During his connexion as engineer with the Australian Mail
  Company he worked out into a practical shape his conception of a "great
  ship"; and in 1852 his scheme was laid before the directors of the
  Eastern Steam Navigation Company. It was adopted, the projector being
  appointed engineer, and after much time occupied about contracts and
  specifications the work was begun in December 1853. Immense difficulties
  in the progress of construction caused delays from time to time. The
  operation of launching was several times attempted in vain; but at length
  the gigantic vessel, the "Great Eastern," was got afloat on the 31st of
  January 1858. Much remained to be done to complete the ship; and her
  engineer, overworked and worn out with worry, broke down and did not see
  her begin her first voyage on the 7th of September 1859. On the 5th he
  was brought home from the ship suffering from a paralytic stroke, and on
  the 15th he died at his house in Westminster.</p>
      <p>In addition to the great works already described, Brunel was employed
  in the construction of many docks and piers, as at Monkwearmouth,
  Bristol, Plymouth, Briton Ferry, Brentford and Milford Haven. He was a
  zealous promoter of the Great Exhibition of 1851, and was a member of the
  committee on the section of machinery and of the building committee. He
  paid much attention to the improvement of large guns, and designed a
  floating gun-carriage for the attack on Kronstadt in the Russian War
  (1854); he also designed and superintended the construction of the
  hospital buildings at Erenkeni on the Dardanelles (1855). He was elected
  a fellow of the Royal Society in 1830, and in 1858 declined the
  presidency of the Institution of Civil Engineers through ill-health. He
  received the degree of D.C.L. from Oxford in 1857. In his work he was
  singularly free from professional jealousy, and was always ready to
  commend and help others, though, himself a man of remarkable industry and
  energy, he demanded a high standard of faithful service from his
  subordinates.</p>
      <p>See <i>The Life of I.K. Brunel, C.E.</i> (1870), by his son, Isambard
  Brunel.</p>
   </body>
</topic>