<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e27235">
   <title>BRYENNIUS, NICEPHORUS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRYENNIUS, NICEPHORUS--> (1062-1137), Byzantine soldier, statesman
  and historian, was born at Orestias (Adrianople). His father, of the same
  name, had revolted against the feeble Michael VII., but had been defeated
  and deprived of his eyesight. The son, who was distinguished for his
  learning, personal beauty and engaging qualities, gained the favour of
  Alexius I. (Comnenus) and the hand of his daughter Anna, with the titles
  of Caesar (then ranking third) and Panhypersebastos (one of the new
  dignities introduced by Alexius). Bryennius successfully defended the
  walls of Constantinople against the attacks of Godfrey of Bouillon
  (1097); conducted the peace negotiations between Alexius and Bohemund,
  prince of Antioch (1108); and played an important part in the defeat of
  Malik-Shah, the Seljuk sultan of Iconium (1116). After the death of
  Alexius, he refused to enter into the conspiracy set on foot by his
  mother-in-law and wife to depose John, the son of Alexius, and raise
  himself to the throne. His wife attributed his refusal to cowardice, but
  it seems from certain passages in his own work that he really regarded it
  as a crime to revolt against the rightful heir; the only reproach that
  can be brought against him is that he did not nip the conspiracy in the
  bud. He was on very friendly terms with the new emperor John, whom he
  accompanied on his Syrian campaign (1137), but was forced by illness to
  return to Byzantium, where he died in the same year. At the suggestion of
  his mother-in-law he wrote a history (called by him <ph outputclass="grk">Ὕλη
  Ἱστορίας</ph>,
  materials for a history) of the period from 1057 to 1081, from the
  victory of Isaac I. (Comnenus) over Michael VI. to the dethronement of
  Nicephorus Botaneiates by Alexius. The work has been described as rather
  a family chronicle than a history, the object of which was the
  glorification of the house of Comnenus. Part of the introduction is
  probably a later addition. In addition to information derived from older
  contemporaries (such as his father and father-in-law) Bryennius made use
  of the works of Michael Psellus, John Scylitza and Michael Attaliota. As
  might be expected, his views are biased by personal considerations and
  his intimacy with the royal family, which at the same time, however,
  afforded him unusual facilities for obtaining material. His model was
  Xenophon, whom he has imitated with <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page700">[v.04 p.0700]</ph>a tolerable
  measure of success; he abstains from an excessive use of simile and
  metaphor, and his style is concise and simple.</p>
      <p>Editio princeps, P. Possinus, 1661; in Bonn <i>Corpus Scriptorum Hist.
  Byz.</i>, by E. Meincke (1836), with du Cange's valuable commentary;
  Migne, <i>Patrologia Graeca</i>, cxxvii.; see also J. Seger,
  <i>Byzantinische Historiker des 10. und 11. Jahrhunderts</i> (1888), and
  C. Krumbacher, <i>Geschichte der byzantinischen Litteratur</i> (1897).
  The estimate of his work in R. Nicolai, <i>Griechische
  Literaturgeschichte</i>, iii. p. 76 (1878), is too unfavourable.</p>
   </body>
</topic>