<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e33167">
   <title>BUFFALO</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUFFALO,--> a name properly pertaining to an aberrant species of
  cattle which has been kept in a state of domestication in India and Egypt
  from time immemorial, and had been introduced from the latter country
  into southern Europe. It is now taken, however, to include not only this
  species, whose native home is India, but all more or less nearly related
  animals.<xref href="#d1e33167/Footnote_331" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref>
  Buffaloes are heavily built oxen, with sparsely haired skin, large ears,
  long, tufted tails, broad muzzles and massive angulated horns. In having
  only 13 pairs of ribs they resemble the typical oxen. African buffaloes
  all have the hair of the back directed backwards.</p>
      <p>In the Cape buffalo, <i>Bos (Bubalus) caffer</i>, the horns do not
  attain an excessive length, but in old bulls are so expanded and
  thickened at the base as to form a helmet-like mass protecting the whole
  forehead. Several more or less nearly allied local races have been named;
  and in Eastern Africa the buffaloes (<i>B. caffer aequinoctialis</i>)
  have smaller horns, which do not meet in the middle line. From this
  animal, which is brown instead of black, there seems to be a transition
  towards the red dwarf buffalo (<i>B. nanus</i>) of West Africa, an animal
  scarcely more than two-thirds the size of its gigantic southern cousin,
  with relatively small, much flattened, upwardly curved horns. In South
  Africa buffaloes frequent reedy swamps, where they associate in herds of
  from fifty to a hundred or more individuals. Old bulls may be met with
  either alone or in small parties of from two or three to eight or ten.
  This buffalo formerly roamed in herds over the plains of Central and
  Southern Africa, always in the near vicinity of water, but the numbers
  are greatly diminished. In Cape Colony some herds are protected by the
  government in the eastern forest-districts. This species has never been
  domesticated, nor does there appear to have been any attempt to reduce it
  to service. Like its Indian ally it is fond of water, which it visits at
  regular intervals during the twenty-four hours; it also plasters itself
  with mud, which, when hardened by the sun, protects it from the bite of
  the gadflies which in spite of its thick hide seem to cause it
  considerable annoyance. It is relieved of a portion of the parasitic
  ticks, so common on the hides of thick-skinned animals, by means of the
  red-beaked rhinoceros birds, <i>Buphaga erythrorhynca</i>, a dozen or
  more of which may be seen partly perched on its horns and partly moving
  about on its back, and picking up the ticks on which they feed. The
  hunter is often guided by these birds in his search for the buffalo, but
  oftener still they give timely warning to their host of the dangerous
  proximity of the hunter, and have thus earned the title of "the buffalo's
  guardian birds."</p>
      <p>In a wild state the typical Indian buffalo, <i>Bos (Bubalus)
  bubalis</i>, seems to be restricted to India and Ceylon, although some of
  the buffaloes found in the Malay Peninsula and Islands probably represent
  local races. The species has been introduced into Asia Minor, Egypt,
  Italy and elsewhere. The large size and wide separation of the horns, as
  well as the less thickly fringed ears, and the more elongated and narrow
  head, form marked points of distinction between the Asiatic and South
  African species. Moreover, all Asiatic buffaloes are distinguished from
  the African forms by having the hair on the fore-part of the back
  directed forwards; and these go far to support the views of those who
  would make them the types of a distinct subgenus, <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page757">[v.04 p.0757]</ph>or genus,
  <i>Buffelus</i>. In Assam there formerly existed a local race, <i>B.
  bubalis macrocercus</i>, characterized by the horns, which are of immense
  size, being directed mainly outwards, instead of curving upwards in a
  circular form. Another Assam race (<i>B. bubalis fulvus</i>) is
  characterized by the tawny, in place of black, colour of its hair and
  hide. The haunts of the Indian buffalo are the grass-jungles near swamps,
  in which the grass exceeds 20 ft. in height. Here the
  buffaloes—like the Indian rhinoceros—form covered pathways,
  in which they are completely concealed. The herds frequently include
  fifty or more individuals. These animals are fond of passing the day in
  marshes, where they love to wallow in the mud; they are by no means shy,
  and do much harm to the crops. The rutting-season occurs in autumn, when
  several females follow a single male, forming for the time a small herd.
  The period of gestation lasts for ten months, and the female produces one
  or two calves at a birth. The bull is capable, it is said, of
  overthrowing an elephant, and generally more than a match even for the
  tiger, which usually declines the combat when not impelled by hunger. The
  Indian driver of a herd of tame buffaloes does not shrink from entering a
  tiger-frequented jungle, his cattle, with their massive horns, making
  short work of any tiger that may come in their way. Buffalo fights and
  fights between buffaloes and tigers were recognized Indian sports in the
  old days. Domesticated buffaloes differ from their wild brethren merely
  by their inferior size and smaller horns; some of the latter being of the
  circular and others of the straight type. The milk is good and
  nourishing, but of a ropy consistency and a peculiar flavour.</p>
      <p>The tamarao, or Philippine buffalo, <i>Bos (Bubalus) mindorensis</i>,
  is a smaller animal, in many respects intermediate between the Indian
  buffalo and the dwarf anoa, or Celebes buffalo (<i>B.
  depressicornis</i>).</p>
      <p>(R. L.*)</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_331"> In America, it is
  worth noting, the term "buffalo" is almost universally taken, at all
  events in popular parlance, to designate the American bison, for which
  see <ph outputclass="sc">Bison</ph>.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>