<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e2852">
   <title>BREWSTER, WILLIAM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BREWSTER, WILLIAM--> (c. 1566-1644), American colonist, one of the
  leaders of the "Pilgrims," was born at Scrooby, in Nottinghamshire,
  England, about 1566. After studying for a short time at Cambridge, he was
  from 1584 to 1587 in the service of William Davison (? 1541-1608), who in
  1585 went to the Low Countries to negotiate an alliance with the
  states-general and in 1586 became assistant to Walsingham, Queen
  Elizabeth's secretary of state. Upon the disgrace of Davison, Brewster
  removed to Scrooby, where from 1590 until September 1607 he held the
  position of "Post," or postmaster responsible for the relays of horses on
  the post road, having previously, for a short time, assisted his father
  in that office. About 1602 his neighbours began to assemble for worship
  at his home, the Scrooby manor house, and in 1606 he joined them in
  organizing the Separatist church of Scrooby. After an unsuccessful
  attempt in 1607 (for which he was imprisoned for a short time), he, with
  other Separatists, removed to Holland in 1608 to obtain greater freedom
  of worship. At Leiden in 1609 he was chosen ruling elder of the
  Congregation. In Holland he supported himself first by teaching English
  and afterwards in 1616-1619, as the partner of one Thomas Brewer, by
  secretly printing, for sale in England, books proscribed by the English
  government, thus, says Bradford, having "imploymente inough." In 1619
  their types were seized and Brewer was arrested by the authorities of the
  university of Leiden, acting on the instance of the British ambassador,
  Sir Dudley Carleton. Brewster, however, escaped, and in the same year,
  with Robert Cushman (c. 1580-1625), obtained in London, on behalf of his
  associates, a land patent from the Virginia Company. In 1620 he emigrated
  to America on the "Mayflower," and was one of the founders of the
  Plymouth Colony. Here besides continuing until his death to act as ruling
  elder, he was also—regularly until the arrival of the first pastor,
  Ralph Smith (d. 1661), in 1629 and irregularly afterward—a
  "teacher," preaching "both powerfully and profitably to ye great
  contentment of ye hearers and their comfortable edification." By many he
  is regarded as pre-eminently the leader of the "Pilgrims." He died,
  probably on the 10th of April 1644.</p>
      <p>See Ashbel Steele's <i>Chief of the Pilgrims; or the Life and Time of
  William Brewster</i> (Philadelphia, 1857); and a sketch in William
  Bradford's <i>History of the Plimouth Plantation</i> (new ed., Boston,
  1898).</p>
   </body>
</topic>