<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e30555">
   <title>BUCKINGHAM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCKINGHAM, HENRY STAFFORD,--> <ph outputclass="sc">2nd Duke
  of</ph>
         <xref href="#d1e30555/Footnote_271" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref>
  (1454-1483), was the son of Humphrey Stafford, killed at the first battle
  of St Albans in 1455, and grandson of Humphrey the 1st duke (cr. 1444),
  killed at Northampton in 1460, both fighting for Lancaster. The 1st duke,
  who bore the title of earl of Buckingham in right of his mother, was the
  son of Edmund, 5th earl of Stafford, and of Anne, daughter of Thomas,
  duke <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page727">[v.04
  p.0727]</ph>of Gloucester, youngest son of Edward III.; Henry's mother
  was Margaret, daughter of Edmund Beaufort, 2nd duke of Somerset, grandson
  of John of Gaunt. Thus he came on both sides of the blood royal, and
  this, coupled with the vastness of his inheritance, made the young duke's
  future of importance to Edward IV. He was recognized as duke in 1465, and
  next year was married to Catherine Woodville, the queen's sister. On
  reaching manhood he was made a knight of the Garter in 1474, and in 1478
  was high steward at the trial of George, duke of Clarence. He had not
  otherwise filled any position of importance, but his fidelity might seem
  to have been secured by his marriage. However, after Edward's death,
  Buckingham was one of the first persons worked upon by Richard, duke of
  Gloucester. It was through his help that Richard obtained possession of
  the young king, and he was at once rewarded with the offices of justiciar
  and chamberlain of North and South Wales, and constable of all the royal
  castles in the principality and Welsh Marches. In the proceedings which
  led to the deposition of Edward V. he took a prominent part, and on the
  24th of June 1483 he urged the citizens at the Guildhall to take Richard
  as king, in a speech of much eloquence, "for he was neither unlearned and
  of nature marvellously well spoken." (More). At Richard's coronation he
  served as chamberlain, and immediately afterwards was made constable of
  England and confirmed in his powers in Wales. Richard might well have
  believed that the duke's support was secured. But early in August
  Buckingham withdrew from the court to Brecon. He may have thought that he
  deserved an even greater reward, or possibly had dreams of establishing
  his own claims to the crown. At all events, at Brecon he fell somewhat
  easily under the influence of his prisoner, John Morton (<i>q.v.</i>),
  who induced him to give his support to his cousin Henry Tudor, earl of
  Richmond. A widespread plot was soon formed, but Richard had early
  warning, and on the 15th of October, issued a proclamation against
  Buckingham. Buckingham, as arranged, prepared to enter England with a
  large force of Welshmen. His advance was stopped by an extraordinary
  flood on the Severn, his army melted away without striking a blow, and he
  himself took refuge with a follower, Ralph Bannister, at Lacon Hall, near
  Wem. The man betrayed him for a large reward, and on the 1st of November,
  Buckingham was brought to the king at Salisbury. Richard refused to see
  him, and after a summary trial had him executed next day (2nd of November
  1483), though it was a Sunday.</p>
      <p>Buckingham's eldest son, Edward (1478-1521), eventually succeeded him
  as 3rd duke, the attainder being removed in 1485; the second son, Henry,
  was afterwards earl of Wiltshire. The 3rd duke played an important part
  as lord high constable at the opening of the reign of Henry VIII., and is
  introduced into Shakespeare's play of that king, but he fell through his
  opposition to Wolsey, and in 1521 was condemned for treason and executed
  (17th of May); the title was then forfeited with his attainder, his only
  son Henry (1501-1563), who in his father's lifetime was styled earl of
  Stafford, being, however, given back his estates in 1522, and in 1547
  restored in blood by parliament with the title of Baron Stafford, which
  became extinct in this line with Roger, 5th Baron in 1640. In that year
  the barony of Stafford was granted to William Howard (1614-1680), who
  after two months was created Viscount Stafford; he was beheaded in 1680,
  and his son was created earl of Stafford in 1688, a title which became
  extinct in 1762; but in 1825 the descent to the barony of 1640 was
  established, to the satisfaction of the House of Lords, in the person of
  Sir G.W. Jerningham, in whose family it then continued.</p>
      <p>The chief original authorities for the life of the 2nd duke of
  Buckingham are the <i>Continuation of the Croyland Chronicle</i>; Sir
  Thomas More's <i>Richard III.</i>; and Fabyan's <i>Chronicle</i>. Amongst
  modern authorities consult J. Gairdner's <i>Richard III.</i>; and Sir. J.
  Ramsay's <i>Lancaster and York</i>.</p>
      <p>(C. L. K.)</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_271"> i.e. in the
  Stafford line; see above.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>