<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12742">
   <title>BRISSOT, JACQUES PIERRE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRISSOT, JACQUES PIERRE--> (1754-1793), who assumed the name of
  <ph outputclass="sc">de Warville</ph>, a celebrated French Girondist, was
  born at Chartres, where his father was an inn-keeper, in January 1754.
  Brissot received a good education and entered the office of a lawyer at
  Paris. His first works, <i>Théorie des lois criminelles</i> (1781) and
  <i>Bibliothèque philosophique du législateur</i> (1782), were on the
  philosophy of law, and showed how thoroughly Brissot was imbued with the
  ethical precepts of Rousseau. The first work was dedicated to Voltaire,
  and was received by the old <i>philosophe</i> with much favour. Brissot
  became known as a facile and able writer, and was engaged on the
  <i>Mercure</i>, on the <i>Courrier de l'Europe</i>, and on other papers.
  Ardently devoted to the service of humanity, he projected a scheme for a
  general concourse of all the savants in Europe, and started in London a
  paper, <i>Journal du Lycée de Londres</i>, which was to be the organ of
  their views. The plan was unsuccessful, and soon after his return to
  Paris Brissot was lodged in the Bastille on the charge of having
  published a work against the government. He obtained his release after
  four months, and again devoted himself to pamphleteering, but had
  speedily to retire for a time to London. On this second visit he became
  acquainted with some of the leading Abolitionists, and founded later in
  Paris a Société des Amis des Noirs, of which he was president during 1790
  and 1791. As an agent of this society he paid a visit to the United
  States in 1788, and in 1791 published his <i>Nouveau Voyage dans les
  États-Unis de l'Amerique Septentrionale</i> (3 vols.).</p>
      <p>From the first, Brissot threw himself heart and soul into the
  Revolution. He edited the <i>Patriote français</i> from 1789 to 1793, and
  being a well-informed and capable man took a prominent part in affairs.
  Upon the demolition of the Bastille the keys were presented to him.
  Famous for his speeches at the Jacobin club, he was elected a member of
  the municipality of Paris, then of the Legislative Assembly, and later of
  the National Convention. During the Legislative Assembly his knowledge of
  foreign affairs enabled him as member of the diplomatic committee
  practically to direct the foreign policy of France, and the declaration
  of war against the emperor on the 20th of April 1792, and that against
  England on the 1st of July 1793, were largely due to him. It was also
  Brissot who gave these wars the character of revolutionary propaganda. He
  was in many ways the leading spirit of the Girondists, who were also
  known as Brissotins. Vergniaud certainly was far superior to him in
  oratory, but Brissot was quick, eager, impetuous, and a man of wide
  knowledge. But he was at the same time vacillating, and not qualified to
  struggle against the fierce energies roused by the events of the
  Revolution. His party fell before the Mountain; sentence of arrest was
  passed against the leading members of it on the 2nd of June 1793. Brissot
  attempted to escape in disguise, but was arrested at Moulins. His
  demeanour at the trial was quiet and dignified; and on the 31st of
  October 1793 he died bravely with several other Girondists.</p>
      <p>See <i>Mémoires de Brissot, sur ses contemporains et la Révolution
  française</i>, published by his sons, with notes by F. de Montrol (Paris,
  1830); Helena Williams, <i>Souvenirs de la Révolution française</i>
  (Paris, 1827); F. A. Aulard, <i>Les Orateurs de la Législative et de la
  Convention</i> 2nd ed., (Paris, 1905); F. A. Aulard, <i>Les Portraits
  littéraires à la fin du XVIII<sup>e</sup> siècle, pendant la
  Révolution</i> (Paris, 1883).</p>
   </body>
</topic>