<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e336">
   <title>BRETON, BRITTON or BRITTAINE, NICHOLAS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRETON, BRITTON or BRITTAINE, NICHOLAS--> (1545?-1626), English
  poet, belonged to an old family settled at Layer-Breton, Essex. His
  father, William Breton, who had made a considerable fortune by trade,
  died in 1559, and the widow (née Elizabeth Bacon) married the poet George
  Gascoigne before her sons had attained their majority. Nicholas Breton
  was probably born at the "capitall mansion house" in Red Cross Street, in
  the parish of St Giles without Cripplegate, mentioned in his father's
  will. There is no official record of his residence at the university, but
  the diary of the Rev. Richard Madox tells us that he was at Antwerp in
  1583 and was "once of Oriel College." He married Ann Sutton in 1593, and
  had a family. He is supposed to have died shortly after the publication
  of his last work, <i>Fantastickes</i> (1626). Breton found a patron in
  Mary, countess of Pembroke, and wrote much in her honour until 1601, when
  she seems to have withdrawn her favour. It is probably safe to supplement
  the meagre record of his life by accepting as autobiographical some of
  the letters signed N.B. in <i>A Poste with a Packet of Mad Letters</i>
  (1603, enlarged 1637); the 19th letter of the second part contains a
  general complaint of many griefs, and proceeds as follows: "hath another
  been wounded in the warres, fared hard, lain in a cold bed many a bitter
  storme, and beene at many a hard banquet? all these have I; another
  imprisoned? so have I; another long been sicke? so have I; another
  plagued with an unquiet life? so have I; another indebted to his hearts
  griefe, and fame would pay and cannot? so am I." Breton was a facile
  writer, popular with his contemporaries, and forgotten by the next
  generation. His work consists of religious and pastoral poems, satires,
  and a number of miscellaneous prose tracts. His religious poems are
  sometimes wearisome by their excess of fluency and sweetness, but they
  are evidently the expression of a devout and earnest mind. His praise of
  the Virgin and his references to Mary Magdalene have suggested that he
  was a Catholic, but his prose writings abundantly prove that he was an
  ardent Protestant. Breton had little gift for satire, and his best work
  is to be found in his pastoral poetry. His <i>Passionate Shepheard</i>
  (1604) is full of sunshine and fresh air, and of unaffected gaiety. The
  third pastoral in this book—"Who can live in heart so glad As the
  merrie country lad"—is well known; with some other of Breton's
  daintiest poems, among them the lullaby, "Come little babe, come silly
  soule,"<xref href="#d1e336/Footnote_021" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref>—it is incorporated in A.H.
  Bullen's <i>Lyrics from Elizabethan Romances</i> (1890). His keen
  observation of country life appears also in his prose idyll, <i>Wits
  Trenchmour</i>, "a conference betwixt a scholler and an angler," and in
  his <i>Fantastickes</i>, a series of short prose pictures of the months,
  the Christian festivals and the hours, which throw much light on the
  customs of the times. Most of Breton's books are very rare and have great
  bibliographical value. His works, with the exception of some belonging to
  private owners, were collected by Dr A.B. Grosart in the <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page502">[v.04
  p.0502]</ph>
         <i>Chertsey Worthies Library</i> in 1879, with an elaborate
  introduction quoting the documents for the poet's history.</p>
      <p>Breton's poetical works, the titles of which are here somewhat
  abbreviated, include <i>The Workes of a Young Wit</i> (1577); <i>A
  Floorish upon Fancie</i> (1577); <i>The Pilgrimage to Paradise</i>
  (1592); <i>The Countess of Penbrook's Passion</i> (MS.), first printed by
  J.O. Halliwell Phillipps in 1853; <i>Pasquil's Fooles cappe</i>, entered
  at Stationers' Hall in 1600; <i>Pasquil's Mistresse</i> (1600);
  <i>Pasquil's Passe and Passeth Not</i> (1600); <i>Melancholike
  Humours</i> (1600); <i>Marie Magdalen's Love: a Solemne Passion of the
  Soules Love</i> (1595), the first part of which, a prose treatise, is
  probably by another hand; the second part, a poem in six-lined stanza, is
  certainly by Breton; <i>A Divine Poem</i>, including "The Ravisht Soul"
  and "The Blessed Weeper" (1601); <i>An Excellent Poem, upon the Longing
  of a Blessed Heart</i> (1601); <i>The Soules Heavenly Exercise</i>
  (1601); <i>The Soules Harmony</i> (1602); <i>Olde Madcappe newe Gaily
  mawfrey</i> (1602); <i>The Mother's Blessing</i> (1602); <i>A True
  Description of Unthankfulnesse</i> (1602); <i>The Passionate
  Shepheard</i> (1604); <i>The Soules Immortall Crowne</i> (1605); <i>The
  Honour of Valour</i> (1605); <i>An Invective against Treason; I would and
  I would not</i> (1614); <i>Bryton's Bowre of Delights</i> (1591), edited
  by Dr Grosart in 1893, an unauthorized publication which contained some
  poems disclaimed by Breton; <i>The Arbor of Amorous Devises</i> (entered
  at Stationers' Hall, 1594), only in part Breton's; and contributions to
  <i>England's Helicon</i> and other miscellanies of verse. Of his
  twenty-two prose tracts may be mentioned <i>Wit's Trenchmour</i> (1597),
  <i>The Wil of Wit</i> (1599), <i>A Poste with a Packet of Mad Letters</i>
  (1603). <i>Sir Philip Sidney's Ourania by N.B.</i> (1606); <i>Mary
  Magdalen's Lamentations</i> (1604), and <i>The Passion of a Discontented
  Mind</i> (1601), are sometimes, but erroneously, ascribed to Breton.</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_021">  This poem,
  however, comes from <i>The Arbor of Amorous Devises</i>, which is only in
  part Breton's work.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>