<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e30100">
   <title>BUCKINGHAM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS,--> <ph outputclass="sc">1st Duke
  of</ph>
         <xref href="#d1e30100/Footnote_251" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref>
  (1592-1628), English statesman, born in August 1592,<xref href="#d1e30100/Footnote_252" type="fn"><!--[2]--></xref> was a younger
  son of Sir George Villiers of Brooksby. His mother, Mary, daughter of
  Anthony Beaumont of Glenfield, Leicestershire, who was left a widow
  early, educated him for a courtier's life, sending him to France with Sir
  John Eliot; and the lad, being "by nature contemplative," took kindly to
  the training. He could dance well, fence well, and talk a little French,
  when in August 1614 he was brought before the king's notice, in the hope
  that he would take a fancy to him.</p>
      <p>The moment was favourable. Since Salisbury's death James had taken the
  business of government upon himself. But he wanted some one who would
  chat with him, and amuse him, and would also fill the office of private
  secretary, and save him from the trouble of saying no to importunate
  suitors. It would be an additional satisfaction if he could train the
  youth whom he might select in those arts of statesmanship of which he
  believed himself to be a perfect master. His first choice had not proved
  a happy one. Robert Carr, who had lately become earl of Somerset, had had
  his head turned by his elevation. He had grown peevish toward his master,
  and had placed himself at the head of the party which was working for a
  close alliance with Spain.</p>
      <p>The appearance of Villiers, beaming with animal spirits and good
  humour, was therefore welcomed by all who had an interest in opposing the
  designs of Spain, and he was appointed cupbearer the same year. For some
  little time still Somerset's pre-eminence was maintained. But on the 23rd
  of April 1615, Villiers, in spite of Somerset, was promoted to be
  gentleman of the bedchamber, and was knighted on the 24th; the charge of
  murdering Overbury, brought against Somerset in September, completed his
  downfall, and Villiers at once stepped into the place which he had
  vacated. On the 3rd of January 1616 he became master of the horse, on the
  24th of April he received the order of the Garter, and on the 27th of
  August 1616 was created Viscount Villiers and Baron Waddon, receiving a
  grant of land valued at £80,000, while on the 5th of January 1617 he was
  made earl, and on the 1st of January 1618 marquess of Buckingham. With
  the exception of the earl of Pembroke he was the richest nobleman in
  England.</p>
      <p>Those who expected him to give his support to the anti-Spanish party
  were at first doomed to disappointment. As yet he was no politician, and
  he contented himself with carrying out his master's orders, whatever they
  were. In his personal relations he was kindly and jovial towards all who
  did not thwart his wishes. But James had taught him to consider that the
  patronage of England was in his hands, and he took good care that no man
  should receive promotion of any kind who did not in one way or another
  pay court to him. As far as can be ascertained, he cared less for money
  than for the gratification of his vanity. But he had not merely himself
  to consider. His numerous kinsfolk were to be enriched by marriage, if in
  no other way, and Bacon, the great philosopher and statesman, was all but
  thrust from office because he had opposed a marriage suggested for one of
  Buckingham's brothers, while Cranfield, the first financier of the day,
  was kept from the treasury till he would forsake the woman whom he loved,
  to marry a penniless cousin of the favourite. On the 19th of January 1619
  James made him lord high admiral of England, hoping that the ardent,
  energetic youth would impart something of his own fire to those who were
  entrusted with the oversight of that fleet which had been almost ruined
  by the peculation and carelessness of the officials. Something of this,
  no doubt, was realized under Buckingham's eye. But he himself never
  pretended to the virtues of an administrator, and he was too ready to
  fill up appointments with men who flattered him, and too reluctant to
  dismiss them, if they served their country ill, to effect any permanent
  change for the better.</p>
      <p>It was about this time that he first took an independent part in
  politics. All England was talking of the revolution in Bohemia in the
  year before, and men's sympathy with the continental Protestants was
  increased when it was known that James's son-in-law had accepted the
  crown of Bohemia, and that in the summer of 1620 a Spanish force was
  preparing to invade the Palatinate. Buckingham at first had thrown
  himself into the popular movement. Before the summer of 1620 was at end,
  incensed by injuries inflicted on English sailors by the Dutch in the
  East Indies, he had swung round, and was in close agreement with
  Gondomar, the Spanish ambassador. He had now married Lady Katherine
  Manners, the daughter of the earl of Rutland, who was at heart a Roman
  Catholic, though she outwardly conformed to the English Church, and this
  alliance may have had something to do with the change.</p>
      <p>Buckingham's mistakes were owing mainly to his levity. If he passed
  briskly from one camp to the other, an impartial <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page723">[v.04 p.0723]</ph>observer might
  usually detect some personal motive at the bottom. But it is hardly
  probable that he was himself conscious of anything of the sort. When he
  was in reality acting under the influence of vanity or passion it was
  easy for him to persuade himself that he was doing his duty to his
  country.</p>
      <p>The parliament which met in 1621, angry at discovering that no help
  was to be sent to the Palatinate, broke out into a loud outcry against
  the system of monopolies, from which Buckingham's brothers and dependants
  had drawn a profit, which was believed to be greater than it really was.
  At first he pleaded for a dissolution. But he was persuaded by Bishop
  Williams that it would be a wiser course to put himself at the head of
  the movement, and at a conference of the Commons with the Lords
  acknowledged that his two brothers had been implicated, but declared that
  his father had begotten a third who would aid in punishing them. In the
  impeachment of Bacon which soon followed, Buckingham, who owed much to
  his wise counsels, gave him that assistance which was possible without
  imperilling his own position and influence. He at first demanded the
  immediate dissolution of parliament, but afterwards, when the cry rose
  louder against the chancellor, joined in the attack, making however some
  attempt to mitigate the severity of the charges against him during the
  hearing of his case before the House of Lords. Notwithstanding, he took
  advantage of Bacon's need of assistance to wring from him the possession
  of York House.</p>
      <p>In the winter of 1621, and the succeeding year, Buckingham was
  entirely in Gondomar's hands; and it was only with some difficulty that
  in May 1622 Laud argued him out of a resolution to declare himself a
  Roman Catholic. In December 1621 he actively supported the dissolution of
  parliament, and there can be little doubt that when the Spanish
  ambassador left England the following May, he had come to an
  understanding with Buckingham that the prince of Wales should visit
  Madrid the next year, on which occasion the Spanish court hoped to effect
  his conversion to the Roman Catholic Church before giving him the hand of
  the infanta Maria. They set out on their adventurous expedition on the
  17th of February 1623, arriving at Madrid, after passing through Paris on
  the 7th of March. Each party had been the dupe of the other. Charles and
  Buckingham were sanguine in hoping for the restitution of the Palatinate
  to James's son-in-law, as a marriage gift to Charles; while the Spaniards
  counted on the conversion of Charles to Roman Catholicism and other
  extreme concessions (see <ph outputclass="sc">Charles I</ph>.). The
  political differences were soon accentuated by personal disputes between
  Buckingham and Olivares and the grandees, and when the two young men
  sailed together from Santander in September, it was with the final
  resolution to break entirely with Spain.</p>
      <p>James had gratified his favourite in his absence by raising him to a
  dukedom. But the splendour which now gathered round Buckingham was owing
  to another source than James's favour. He had put himself at the head of
  the popular movement against Spain, and when James, acknowledging sorely
  against his will that the Palatinate could only be recovered by force,
  summoned the parliament which met in February 1624, Buckingham, with the
  help of the heir apparent, took up an independent political position.
  James was half driven, half persuaded to declare all negotiations with
  Spain at an end. For the moment Buckingham was the most popular man in
  England.</p>
      <p>It was easier to overthrow one policy than to construct another. The
  Commons would have been content with sending some assistance to the
  Dutch, and with entering upon a privateering war with Spain. James, whose
  object was to regain the Palatinate, believed this could only be
  accomplished by a continental alliance, in which France took part. As
  soon as parliament was prorogued, negotiations were opened for a marriage
  between Charles and the sister of Louis XIII., Henrietta Maria. But a
  difficulty arose. James and Charles had engaged to the Commons that there
  should be no concessions to the English Roman Catholics, and Louis would
  not hear of the marriage unless very large concessions were made.
  Buckingham, impatient to begin the war as soon as possible, persuaded
  Charles, and the two together persuaded James to throw over the promises
  to the Commons, and to accept the French terms. It was no longer possible
  to summon parliament to vote supplies for the war till the marriage had
  been completed, when remonstrances to its conditions would be
  useless.</p>
      <p>Buckingham, for Buckingham was now virtually the ruler of England, had
  thus to commence war without money. He prepared to throw 12,000
  Englishmen, under a German adventurer, Count Mansfeld, through France
  into the Palatinate. The French insisted that he should maroh through
  Holland. It mattered little which way he took. Without provisions, and
  without money to buy them, the wretched troops sickened and died in the
  winter frosts. Buckingham's first military enterprise ended in disastrous
  failure.</p>
      <p>Buckingham had many other schemes in his teeming brain. He had offered
  to send aid to Christian IV., king of Denmark, who was proposing to make
  war in Germany, and had also a plan for sending an English fleet to
  attack Genoa, the ally of Spain, and a plan for sending an English fleet
  to attack Spain itself.</p>
      <p>Before these schemes could be carried into operation James died on the
  27th of March 1625. The new king and Buckingham were at one in their aims
  and objects. Both were anxious to distinguish themselves by the
  chastisement of Spain, and the recovery of the Palatinate. Both were
  young and inexperienced. But Charles, obstinate when his mind was made
  up, was sluggish in action and without fertility in ideas, and he had
  long submitted his mind to the versatile and brilliant favourite, who was
  never at a loss what to do next, and who unrolled before his eyes visions
  of endless possibilities in the future. Buckingham was sent over to Paris
  to urge upon the French court the importance of converting its alliance
  into active co-operation.</p>
      <p>There was a difficulty in the way. The Huguenots of La Rochelle were
  in rebellion, and James had promised the aid of English ships to suppress
  that rebellion. Buckingham, who seems at first to have consented to the
  scheme, was anxious to mediate peace between the king of France and his
  subjects, and to save Charles from compromising himself with his
  parliament by the appearance of English ships in an attack upon
  Protestants. When he returned his main demands were refused, but hopes
  were given him that peace would be made with the Huguenots. On his way
  through France he had the insolence to make love to the queen of
  France.</p>
      <p>Soon after his return parliament was opened. It would have been hard
  for Charles to pass through the session with credit. Under Buckingham's
  guidance he had entered into engagements involving an enormous
  expenditure, and these engagements involved a war on the continent, which
  had never been popular in the House of Commons. The Commons, too,
  suspected the marriage treaty contained engagements of which they
  disapproved. They asked for the full execution of the laws against the
  Roman Catholics, and voted but little money in return. Before they
  reassembled at Oxford on the 1st of August, the English ships had found
  their way into the hands of the French, to be used against La Rochelle.
  The Commons met in an ill-humour. They had no confidence in Buckingham,
  and they asked that persons whom they could trust should be admitted to
  the king's council before they would vote a penny. Charles stood by his
  minister, and on the 12th of August he dissolved his first
  parliament.</p>
      <p>Buckingham and his master set themselves to work to conquer public
  opinion. On the one hand, they threw over their engagements to France on
  behalf of the English Roman Catholics. On the other hand they sent out a
  large fleet to attack Cadiz, and to seize the Spanish treasure-ships.
  Buckingham went to the Hague to raise an immediate supply by pawning the
  crown jewels, to place England at the head of a great Protestant
  alliance, and to enter into fresh obligations to furnish money to the
  king of Denmark. It all ended in failure. The fleet returned from Cadiz,
  having effected nothing. The crown jewels produced but a small sum, and
  the money for the king of Denmark could only be raised by an appeal to
  parliament. In the meanwhile the king of France was deeply offended by
  the treatment of <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page724">[v.04 p.0724]</ph>the Roman Catholics, and by the
  seizure of French vessels on the ground that they were engaged in
  carrying goods for Spain.</p>
      <p>When Charles's second parliament met on the 6th of February 1626, it
  was not long before, under Eliot's guidance, it asked for Buckingham's
  punishment. He was impeached before the House of Lords on a long string
  of charges. Many of these charges were exaggerated, and some were untrue.
  His real crime was his complete failure as the leader of the
  administration. But as long as Charles refused to listen to the
  complaints of his minister's incompetency, the only way in which the
  Commons could reach him was by bringing criminal charges against him.
  Charles dissolved his second parliament as he had dissolved his first.
  Subsequently the Star Chamber declared the duke innocent of the charges,
  and on the 1st of June Buckingham was elected chancellor of Cambridge
  University.</p>
      <p>To find money was the great difficulty. Recourse was had to a forced
  loan, and men were thrown into prison for refusing to pay it. Disasters
  had occurred to Charles's allies in Germany. The fleet sent out under
  Lord Willoughby (earl of Lindsey) against the Spaniards returned home
  shattered by a storm, and a French war was impending in addition to the
  Spanish one. The French were roused to reprisals by Charles's persistence
  in seizing French vessels. Unwilling to leave La Rochelle open to the
  entrance of an English fleet, Richelieu laid siege to that stronghold of
  the French Huguenots. On the 27th of June 1627 Buckingham sailed from
  Portsmouth at the head of a numerous fleet, and a considerable land
  force, to relieve the besieged city.</p>
      <p>His first enterprise was the siege of the fort of St Martin's, on the
  Isle of Ré. The ground was hard, and the siege operations were converted
  into a blockade. On the 27th of September the defenders of the fort
  announced their readiness to surrender the next morning. In the night a
  fresh gale brought over a flotilla of French provision boats, which
  dashed through the English blockading squadron. The fort was provisioned
  for two months more. Buckingham resolved to struggle on, and sent for
  reinforcements from England. Charles would gladly have answered to his
  call. But England had long since ceased to care for the war. There was no
  money in the exchequer, no enthusiasm in the nation to supply the want.
  Before the reinforcements could arrive the French had thrown a superior
  force upon the island, and Buckingham was driven to retreat on the 29th
  of October with heavy loss, only 2989 troops out of nearly 7000 returning
  to England.</p>
      <p>His spirits were as buoyant as ever. Ill luck, or the misconduct of
  others, was the cause of his failure. He had new plans for carrying on
  the war. But the parliament which met on the 17th of March 1628 was
  resolved to exact from the king an obligation to refrain from encroaching
  for the future on the liberties of his subjects.</p>
      <p>In the parliamentary battle, which ended in the concession of the
  Petition of Right, Buckingham took an active share as a member of the
  House of Lords. He resisted as long as it was possible to resist the
  demand of the Commons, that the king should abandon his claim to imprison
  without showing cause. When the first unsatisfactory answer to the
  petition was made by the king on the 2nd of June, the Commons suspected,
  probably with truth, that it had been dictated by Buckingham. They
  prepared a remonstrance on the state of the nation, and Coke at last
  named the duke as the cause of all the misfortunes that had occurred.
  "The duke of Bucks is the cause of all our miseries ... that man is the
  grievance of grievances." Though on the 7th of June the king granted a
  satisfactory answer to the petition, the Commons proceeded with their
  remonstrance, and on the 11th demanded that he might no longer continue
  in office.</p>
      <p>Once more Charles refused to surrender Buckingham, and a few days
  later he prorogued parliament in anger. The popular feeling was greatly
  excited. Lampoons circulated freely from hand to hand, and Dr Lambe, a
  quack doctor, who dabbled in astrology, and was believed to exercise
  influence over Buckingham, was murdered in the streets of London. Rude
  doggerel lines announced that the duke should share the doctor's
  fate.</p>
      <p>With the clouds gathering round him, Buckingham went down to
  Portsmouth to take the command of one final expedition for the relief of
  La Rochelle. For the first time even he was beginning to acknowledge that
  he had undertaken a task beyond his powers. There was a force of inertia
  in the officials which resisted his efforts to spur them on to an
  enterprise which they believed to be doomed to failure. He entered gladly
  into a scheme of pacification proposed by the Venetian ambassador. But
  before he could know whether there was to be peace or war, the knife of
  an assassin put an end to his career. John Felton, who had served at Ré,
  had been disappointed of promotion, and had not been paid that which was
  due to him for his services, read the declaration of the Commons that
  Buckingham was a public enemy, and eagerly caught at the excuse for
  revenging his private wrongs under cover of those of his country.
  Waiting, on the morning of the 23rd of August, beside the door of the
  room in which Buckingham was breakfasting, he stabbed him to the heart as
  he came out.</p>
      <p>Buckingham married Lady Katherine Manners, daughter of Francis, 6th
  earl of Rutland, by whom he left three sons and one daughter, of whom
  George, the second son (1628-1687), succeeded to the dukedom.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Bibliography</ph>.—Article in the <i>Dict. of
  Nat. Biography</i>, by S.R. Gardiner; <i>Life of Buckingham</i>, by Sir
  Henry Wotton (1642), reprinted in <i>Harleian Miscellany</i>, viii. 613;
  <i>A Parallel between Robert Earl of Essex and George late Duke of
  Buckingham</i>, by the same writer (1641), in the <i>Thomason Tracts</i>,
  164 (20); <i>Characters</i> of the same by Edward, Earl of Clarendon
  (1706); <i>Life of George Villiers, Duke of Buckingham, &amp;c.</i>
  (London, 1740); <i>Historical and Biographical Memoirs of George
  Villiers, Duke of Buckingham</i> (London, 1819); <i>Letters of the Duke
  and Duchess of Buckingham</i> (Edinburgh, 1834); <i>Historia Vitae ...
  Ricardi II., &amp;c.</i>, by Thos. Hearne (1729); <i>Documents
  illustrating the Impeachment of Buckingham</i>, published by the Camden
  Society and edited by S.R. Gardiner (1889); <i>Epistolae Hoelianae</i>
  (James Howell), 187, 189, 203; <i>Poems and Songs relating to George
  Villiers, Duke of Buckingham</i>, ed. by R. W. Fairholt for the Percy
  Society (1850); Rous's <i>Diary</i> (Camden Soc., 1856), p. 27; <i>Gent.
  Mag.</i> (1845), ii. 137-144 (portrait of Buckingham dead); <i>Cal. of
  State Papers</i>, and MSS. in the British Museum (various collections).
  Hist. MSS. Comm. Series. See also P. Gibbs, <i>The Romance of George
  Villiers, 1st Duke of Buckingham</i> (1908).</p>
      <p>(S. R. G.; P. C. Y.)</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_251"> 
            <i>i.e.</i> in the
  Villiers line; see above.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_252"> The <i>Life</i>,
  by Sir Henry Wotton, gives August 28th as the date of his birth, but,
  when relating his death on August 23rd, adds, "thus died the great peer
  in the 36th year of his age compleat and three days over." August 28th
  was therefore probably a misprint for August 20th.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>