<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e11944">
   <title>BRIGANDAGE.</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIGANDAGE.--> The brigand is supposed to derive his name from the
  O. Fr. <i>brigan</i>, which is a form of the Ital. <i>brigante,</i> an
  irregular or partisan soldier. There can be no doubt as to the origin of
  the word "bandit," which has the same meaning. In Italy, which is not
  unjustly considered the home of the most accomplished European brigands,
  a <i>bandito</i> was a man declared outlaw by proclamation, or
  <i>bando</i>, called in Scotland "a decree of horning" because it was
  delivered by a blast of a horn at the town cross. The brigand, therefore,
  is the outlaw who conducts warfare after the manner of an irregular or
  partisan soldier by skirmishes and surprises, who makes the war support
  itself by plunder, by extorting blackmail, by capturing prisoners and
  holding them to ransom, who enforces his demands by violence, and kills
  the prisoners who cannot pay. In certain conditions the brigand has not
  been a mere malefactor. "It is you who are the thieves"—"<i>I
  Ladroni, siete voi,</i>"—was the defence of the Calabrian who was
  tried as a brigand by a French court-martial during the reign of Murat in
  Naples. Brigandage may be, and not infrequently has been, the last
  resource of a people subject to invasion. The Calabrians who fought for
  Ferdinand of Naples, and the Spanish irregular levies, which maintained
  the national resistance against the French from 1808 to 1814, were called
  brigands by their enemies. In the Balkan peninsula, under Turkish rule,
  the brigands (called <i>klephts</i> by the Greeks and <i>hayduks</i> or
  <i>haydutzi</i> by the Slavs) had some claim to believe themselves the
  representatives of their people against oppressors. The only approach to
  an attempt to maintain order was the permission given to part of the
  population to carry arms in order to repress the klephts. They were hence
  called "armatoli." As a matter of fact the armatole were rather the
  allies than the enemies of the klephts. The invader who reduces a nation
  to anarchy, and then suffers from the disorder he creates, always calls
  his opponents brigands. It is a natural consequence of such a war, but a
  very disastrous one, for the people who have to have recourse to these
  methods of defence, that the brigand acquires some measure of honourable
  prestige from his temporary association with patriotism and honest men.
  The patriot band attracts the brigand proper, who is not averse to
  continue his old courses under an honourable pretext. "<i>Viva Fernando y
  vamos robando</i>" (Long life to Ferdinand, and let us go robbing) has
  been said by not unfair critics to have been the maxim of many Spanish
  guerrilleros. Italy and Spain suffered for a long time from the disorder
  developed out of the popular resistance to the French. Numbers of the
  guerrilleros of both countries, who in normal conditions might have been
  honest, had acquired a preference <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page564">[v.04 p.0564]</ph>for living on
  the country, and for occasional booty, which they could not resign when
  the enemy had retired. Their countrymen had to work for a second
  deliverance from their late defenders. In the East the brigand has had a
  freer scope, and has even founded kingdoms. David's following in the cave
  of Adullam was such material as brigands are made of. "And every one that
  was in distress, and every one that was in debt, and every one that was
  discontented, gathered themselves unto him, and he became a captain over
  them: and there were with him about four hundred men." Nadir Shah of
  Persia began in just such a cave of Adullam, and lived to plunder Delhi
  with a host of Persians and Afghans.</p>
      <p>The conditions which favour the development of brigandage may be
  easily summed up. They are first bad administration, and then, in a less
  degree, the possession of convenient hiding-places. A country of mountain
  and forest is favourable to the brigand. The highlands of Scotland
  supplied a safe refuge to the "gentlemen reavers," who carried off the
  cattle of the Sassenach landlords. The Apennines, the mountains of
  Calabria, the Sierras of Spain, were the homes of the Italian "banditos"
  and the Spanish "bandoleros" (banished men) and "salteadores" (raiders).
  The forests of England gave cover to the outlaws whose very much
  flattered portrait is to be found in the ballads of Robin Hood. The
  "maquis," i.e. the bush of Corsica, and its hills, have helped the
  Corsican brigand, as the bush of Australia covered the bushranger. But
  neither forest thicket nor mountain is a lasting protection against a
  good police, used with intelligence by the government, and supported by
  the law-abiding part of the community. The great haunts of brigands in
  Europe have been central and southern Italy and the worst-administered
  parts of Spain, except those which fell into the hands of the Turks.
  "Whenever numerous troops of banditti, multiplied by success and
  impunity, publicly defy, instead of eluding, the justice of their
  country, we may safely infer that the excessive weakness of the
  government is felt and abused by the lowest ranks of the community," is
  the judgment passed by Gibbon on the disorders of Sicily in the reign of
  the emperor Gallienus. This weakness has not always been a sign of real
  feebleness in the government. England was vigorously ruled in the reign
  of William III., when "a fraternity of plunderers, thirty in number
  according to the lowest estimate, squatted near Waltham Cross under the
  shades of Epping Forest, and built themselves huts, from which they
  sallied forth with sword and pistol to bid passengers stand." It was not
  because the state was weak that the Gubbings (so called in contempt from
  the trimmings and refuse of fish) infested Devonshire for a generation
  from their headquarters near Brent Tor, on the edge of Dartmoor. It was
  because England had not provided herself with a competent rural police.
  In relatively unsettled parts of the United States there has been a
  considerable amount of a certain kind of brigandage. In early days the
  travel routes to the far West were infested by highwaymen, who, however,
  seldom united into bands, and such outlaws, when captured, were often
  dealt with in an extra-legal manner, e.g. by "vigilance committees." The
  Mexican brigand Cortina made incursions into Texas before the Civil War.
  In Canada the mounted police have kept brigandage down, and in Mexico the
  "Rurales" have made an end of the brigands. Such curable evils as the
  highwaymen of England, and their like in the States, are not to be
  compared with the "Écorcheurs," or Skinners, of France in the 15th
  century, or the "Chauffeurs" of the revolutionary epoch. The first were
  large bands of discharged mercenary soldiers who pillaged the country.
  The second were ruffians who forced their victims to pay ransom by
  holding their feet in fires. Both flourished because the government was
  for the time disorganized by foreign invasion or by revolution. These
  were far more terrible evils than the licence of criminals, who are
  encouraged by a fair prospect of impunity because there is no permanent
  force always at hand to check them, and to bring them promptly to
  justice. At the same time it would be going much too far to say that the
  absence of an efficient police is the sole cause of brigandage in
  countries not subject to foreign invasion, or where the state is not very
  feeble. The Sicilian peasants of whom Gibbon wrote were not only
  encouraged by the hope of impunity, but were also maddened by an
  oppressive system of taxation and a cruel system of land tenure. So were
  the Gauls and Spaniards who throughout the 3rd and 4th centuries were a
  constant cause of trouble to the empire, under the name of Bagaudae, a
  word of uncertain origin. In the years preceding the French Revolution,
  the royal government commanded the services of a strong army, and a
  numerous <i>maréchaussée</i> or gendarmerie. Yet it was defied by the
  troops of smugglers and brigands known as <i>faux saulniers</i>,
  unauthorized salt-sellers, and gangs of poachers haunted the king's
  preserves round Paris. The salt monopoly and the excessive preservation
  of the game were so oppressive that the peasantry were provoked to
  violent resistance and to brigandage. They were constantly suppressed,
  but as the cause of the disorder survived, so its effects were
  continually renewed. The offenders enjoyed a large measure of public
  sympathy, and were warned or concealed by the population, even when they
  were not actively supported. The traditional outlaw who spared the poor
  and levied tribute on the rich was, no doubt, always a creature of
  fiction. The ballad which tells us how "Rich, wealthy misers were
  abhorred, By brave, free-hearted Bliss" (a rascal hanged for highway
  robbery at Salisbury in 1695) must have been a mere echo of the Robin
  Hood songs. But there have been times and countries in which the law and
  its administration have been so far regarded as enemies by people who
  were not themselves criminals, that all who defied them have been sure of
  a measure of sympathy. Then and there it was that brigandage has
  flourished, and has been difficult to extirpate. Schinder-Hannes, Jack
  the Skinner, whose real name was Johann Buckler, and who was born at
  Muklen on the Rhine, flourished from 1797 to 1802 because there was no
  proper police to stop him; it is also true that as he chiefly plundered
  the Jews he had a good deal of Christian sympathy. When caught and
  beheaded he had no successors.</p>
      <p>The brigandage of Greece, southern Italy, Corsica and Spain had deeper
  roots, and has never been quite suppressed. All four countries are well
  provided with hiding-places in forest and mountain. In all the
  administration has been bad, the law and its officers have been regarded
  as dangers, if not as deliberate enemies, so that they have found little
  native help, and, what is not the least important cause of the
  persistence of brigandage, there have generally been local potentates who
  found it to their interest to protect the brigand. The case of Greece
  under Turkish rule need not be dealt with. Whoever was not a klepht was
  the victim of some official extortioner. It would be grossly unfair to
  apply the name brigand to the Mainotes and similar clans, who had to
  choose between being flayed by the Turks or living by the sword under
  their own law. When it became independent Greece was extremely ill
  administered under a nominal parliamentary government by politicians who
  made use of the brigands for their own purposes. The result was the state
  of things described with only pardonable exaggeration in Edmond About's
  amusing <i>Roi de la montagne</i>. An authentic and most interesting
  picture of the Greek brigands will be found in the story of the captivity
  of S. Soteropoulos, an ex-minister who fell into their hands. It was
  translated into English under the title of <i>The Brigands of the
  Morea</i>, by the Rev. J.O. Bagdon (London, 1868). The misfortunes of
  Soteropoulos led to the adoption of strong measures which cleared the
  Morea, where the peasantry gave active support to the troops when they
  saw that the government was in earnest. But brigandage was not yet
  extinct in Greece. In 1870 an English party, consisting of Lord and Lady
  Muncaster, Mr Vyner, Mr Lloyd, Mr Herbert, and Count de Boyl, was
  captured at Oropos, near Marathon, and a ransom of £25,000 was demanded.
  Lord and Lady Muncaster were set at liberty to seek for the ransom, but
  the Greek government sent troops in pursuit of the brigands, and the
  other prisoners were then murdered. The scoundrels were hunted down,
  caught, and executed, and Greece has since then been tolerably free from
  this reproach. In the Balkan peninsula, under Turkish rule, brigandage
  continued to exist in connexion <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page565">[v.04 p.0565]</ph>with Christian revolt against the
  Turk, and the race conflicts of Albanians, Walachians, Pomuks, Bulgarians
  and Greeks. In Corsica the "maquis" has never been without its brigand
  hero, because industry has been stagnant, family feuds persist, and the
  government has never quite succeeded in persuading the people to support
  the law. The brigand is always a hero to at least one faction of
  Corsicans.</p>
      <p>The conditions which favour brigandage have been more prevalent, and
  for longer, in Italy than elsewhere in western Europe, with the standing
  exception of Corsica, which is Italian in all but political allegiance.
  Until the middle of the 19th century Italy was divided into small states,
  so that the brigand who was closely pursued in one could flee to another.
  Thus it was that Marco Sciarra of the Abruzzi, when hard pressed by the
  Spanish viceroy of Naples—just before and after 1600—could
  cross the border of the papal states and return on a favourable
  opportunity. When pope and viceroy combined against him he took service
  with Venice, from whence he could communicate with his friends at home,
  and pay them occasional visits. On one such visit he was led into a trap
  and slain. Marco Sciarra had terrorized the country far and wide at the
  head of 600 men. He was the follower and imitator of Benedetto Mangone,
  of whom it is recorded that, having stopped a party of travellers which
  included Torquato Tasso, he allowed them to pass unharmed out of his
  reverence for poets and poetry. Mangone was finally taken, and beaten to
  death with hammers at Naples. He and his like are the heroes of much
  popular verse, written in <i>ottava rima</i>, and beginning with the
  traditional epic invocation to the muse. A fine example is "The most
  beautiful history of the life and death of Pietro Mancino, chief of
  Banditti," which has remained popular with the people of southern Italy.
  It begins:—</p>
      <fig outputclass="poem">
         <lines>
      "Io canto li ricatti, e il fiero ardire

      Del gran Pietro Mancino fuoruscito"

      (Pietro Mancino that great outlawed man

      I sing, and all his rage.)

    </lines>
      </fig>
      <p>In Naples the number of competing codes and jurisdictions, the
  survival of the feudal power of the nobles, who sheltered banditti, just
  as a Highland chief gave refuge to "caterans" in Scotland, and the
  helplessness of the peasantry, made brigandage chronic, and the same
  conditions obtained in Sicily. The Bourbon dynasty reduced brigandage
  very much, and secured order on the main high-roads. But it was not
  extinguished, and it revived during the French invasion. This was the
  flourishing time of the notorious Fra Diavolo, who began as brigand and
  blossomed into a patriot. Fra Diavolo was captured and executed by the
  French. When Ferdinand was restored on the fall of Napoleon he employed
  an English officer, General Sir Richard Church, to suppress the brigands.
  General Church, who kept good order among his soldiers, and who made them
  pay for everything, gained the confidence of the peasantry, and restored
  a fair measure of security. It was he who finally brought to justice the
  villainous Don Ciro Anicchiarico—priest and brigand—who
  declared at his trial with offhand indifference that he supposed he had
  murdered about seventy people first and last. When a brother priest was
  sent to give him the consolations of religion, Ciro cut him short,
  saying, "Stop that chatter, we are two of a trade: we need not play the
  fool to one another" (<i>Lasciate queste chiacchiere, siamo dell' istessa
  professione: non ci burliamo fra noi</i>). Every successive revolutionary
  disturbance in Naples saw a recrudescence of brigandage down to the
  unification of 1860-1861, and then it was years before the Italian
  government rooted it out. The source of the trouble was the support the
  brigands received from various kinds of "<i>manuténgoli</i>"
  (maintainers)—great men, corrupt officials, political parties, and
  the peasants who were terrorized, or who profited by selling the brigands
  food and clothes. In Sicily brigandage has been endemic. In 1866 two
  English travellers, Mr E.J.C. Moens and the Rev. J.C. Murray Aynesley,
  were captured and held to ransom. Mr Moens found that the "manuténgoli"
  of the brigands among the peasants charged famine prices for food, and
  extortionate prices for clothes and cartridges. What is true of Naples
  and Sicily is true of other parts of Italy <i>mutatis mutandis</i>. In
  Tuscany, Piedmont and Lombardy the open country has been orderly, but the
  borders infested with brigands. The worst district outside Calabria has
  been the papal states. The Austrian general, Frimont, did, however,
  partly clear the Romagna about 1820, though at a heavy cost of life to
  his soldiers—mostly Bohemian Jägers—from the malaria.</p>
      <p>The history of brigandage in Spain is very similar. It may be said to
  have been endemic in and south of the Sierra Morena. In the north it has
  flourished when government was weak, and after foreign invasion and civil
  wars. But it has always been put down easily by a capable administration.
  It reached its greatest heights in Catalonia, where it began in the
  strife of the peasants against the feudal exactions of the landlords. It
  had its traditional hero, Roque Guinart, who figures in the second part
  of Don Quixote. The revolt against the house of Austria in 1640, and the
  War of the Succession (1700-1714), gave a great stimulus to Catalan
  brigandage. But it was then put down in a way for which Italy offers no
  precedent. A country gentleman named Pedro Veciana, hereditary
  <i>balio</i> (military and civil lieutenant) of the archbishop of
  Tarragona in the town of Valls, armed his farm-servants, and resisted the
  attacks of the brigands. With the help of neighbouring country gentlemen
  he formed a strong band, known as the Mozos (Boys) of Veciana. The
  brigands combined to get rid of him by making an attack on the town of
  Valls, but were repulsed with great loss. The government of Philip V.
  then commissioned Veciana to raise a special corps of police, the
  "escuadra de Cataluna," which still exists. For five generations the
  colonel of the escuadra was always a Veciana. At all times in central and
  northern Spain the country population has supported the police when the
  government would act firmly. Since the organization of the excellent
  constabulary called "La Guardia Civil" by the duke of Ahumada, about
  1844, brigandage has been well kept down. At the close of the Carlist War
  in 1874 a few bands infested Catalonia, but one of the worst was
  surprised, and all its members battered to death with boxwood cudgels by
  a gang of charcoal-burners on the ruins of the castle of San Martin de
  Centellas. In such conditions as these brigandage cannot last. More
  sympathy is felt for "bandoleros" in the south, and there also they find
  Spanish equivalents for the "manuténgoli" of Italy. The tobacco smuggling
  from Gibraltar keeps alive a lawless class which sinks easily into pure
  brigandage. Perhaps the influence of the Berber blood in the population
  helps to prolong this barbarism. The Sierra Morena, and the Serrania de
  Ronda, have produced the bandits whose achievements form the subject of
  popular ballads, such as Francisco Esteban El Guapo (Francis Stephen, the
  Buck or Dandy), Don Juan de Serralonga, Pedranza, &amp;c. The name of
  José Maria has been made familiar to all the world by Merimée's story,
  <i>Carmen</i>, and by Bizet's opera. José Maria, called El Tempranillo
  (the early bird), was a historical personage, a liberal in the rising
  against Ferdinand VII., 1820-1823, then a smuggler, then a "bandolero."
  He was finally bought off by the government, and took a commission to
  suppress the other brigands. Jose Maria was at last shot by one of them,
  whom he was endeavouring to arrest. The civil guard prevents brigandage
  from reaching any great height in normal times, but in 1905 a bandit of
  the old stamp, popularly known as "El Vivillo" (the Vital Spark), haunted
  the Serrania de Ronda.</p>
      <p>The brigand life has been made the subject of much romance. But when
  stripped of fiction it appears that the bands have been mostly recruited
  by men who had been guilty of homicide, out of jealousy or in a gambling
  quarrel, and who remained in them not from love of the life, but from
  fear of the gallows. A reformed brigand, known as Passo di Lupo (Wolf's
  Step), confessed to Mr McFarlane about 1820 that the weaker members of
  the band were terrorized and robbed by the bullies, and that murderous
  conflicts were constant among them.</p>
      <p>The "dacoits" or brigands of India were of the same stamp as their
  European colleagues. The Pindaris were more than brigands, and the Thugs
  were a religious sect.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Authorities</ph>.—The literature of
  brigandage, apart from pure romances, or official reports of trials, is
  naturally extensive. Mr <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page566">[v.04 p.0566]</ph>McFarlane's <i>Lives and Exploits
  of Banditti and Robbers</i> (London, 1837) is a useful introduction to
  the subject. The author saw a part of what he wrote about, and gives many
  references, particularly for Italy. A good bibliography of Spanish
  brigandage will be found in the <i>Reseña Historica de la Guardia
  Civil</i> of Eugenio de la Iglesia (Madrid, 1898). For actual pictures of
  the life, nothing is better than the <i>English Travellers and Italian
  Brigands</i> of W.J.C. Moens (London, 1866), and <i>The Brigands of the
  Morea</i>, by S. Soteropoulos, translated by the Rev. J.O. Bagdon
  (London, 1868).</p>
      <p>(D. H.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>