<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e26549">
   <title>BRUSSELS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUSSELS--> (Fr. <i>Bruxelles</i>, Flem. <i>Brussel</i>), the
  capital of the kingdom of Belgium, and of the province of Brabant,
  situated in 50° 51′ N., 4° 22′ E., about 70 m. from the sea
  at Ostend. It occupies the plain or valley of the Senne, and the sides
  and crest of the hill lying to the east and south-east of that valley. It
  is now extending over the hills west of the valley, and to the north is
  the town or commune of Laeken, which is practically part of the city.
  Brussels suffered severely in 1695 from the bombardment of the French
  under Villeroi, who fired into the town with red-hot shot. Sixteen
  churches and 4000 houses were burnt down, and the historic buildings on
  the Grand Place were seriously injured, the houses of the Nine Nations on
  the eastern side being completely destroyed. In 1731 the famous palace of
  the Netherlands was destroyed by fire, and the only remains of this
  edifice are some ruined arches and walls in a remote comer of the grounds
  of the king's palace. The Porte de Hal is the only one of the eight gates
  in the old wall left standing. It dates from 1381, and is well worth more
  careful examination than it receives. In the latter half of the 18th
  century it served as a kind of bastille for political prisoners, and is
  now used as a museum in which a rather nondescript collection of
  articles, some from Mexico, has been allowed to accumulate. With regard
  to the fine boulevards of the Upper Town, it may be mentioned that about
  1765 they were planted with the double row of lime trees which still
  constitute their chief ornament by Prince Charles of Lorraine while
  governing the Netherlands for his sister-in-law, the empress Maria
  Theresa. The residence of this prince was the palace of William the
  Silent, before he declared against Spam, and it is now used partly for
  the royal library, which contains the famous <i>librairie de
  Bourgogne</i>, and partly for the museum <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page693">[v.04 p.0693]</ph>of modern
  pictures. The only other "hotel" or palace in Brussels is that of the
  duke d'Arenberg. In the 16th century this was the residence of Count
  Egmont, but very little of the building of his day remains. In the same
  street, the rue des Petits Carmes, was the Hôtel Culembourg in which the
  famous oath of the beggars was taken. It has long been demolished and the
  new barracks of the Grenadier regiment have been erected on the site.</p>
      <p>The only other buildings of importance dating from medieval times are
  the three churches of Ste Gudule (often erroneously called the
  cathedral), Notre-Dame des Victoires or Church of the Sablon, and
  Notre-Dame de la Chapelle, or simply la Chapelle, and the hotel de ville
  and the Maison du Roi on the Grand Place. The church of Ste Gudule, also
  dedicated to St Michael, is built on the side of the hill originally
  called St Michael's Mount, and now covered by the fashionable quarters
  which are included under the comprehensive description, of the Upper
  Town. It was begun about the year 1220, and is considered one of the
  finest specimens left of pointed Gothic. It is said to have been
  completed in 1273, with the exception of the two towers which were added
  in the 14th or 15th century. Some of the stained glass is very rich,
  dating from the 13th to the 15th century. In many of the windows there
  are figures of leading members of the houses of Burgundy and Habsburg.
  The curious oak pulpit representing Adam and Eve expelled from the Garden
  of Eden came originally from the Jesuit church at Louvain, and is
  considered the masterpiece of Verbruggen. The church of the Sablon is
  said to have been founded in 1304 by the gild of Crossbowmen to celebrate
  the battle of Woeringen. In a side chapel is a fine monument to the
  princely family of Thurn and Taxis, which had the monopoly of the postal
  service in the old empire. La Chapelle is still older, dating nominally
  from 1210, the choir and transept being considered to date from about
  fifty years later. There are some fine monuments, especially one to the
  duke de Croy who died in 1624. The two churches last named have undergone
  much renovation both outside and inside.</p>
      <p>The Grand Place is by its associations one of the most interesting
  public squares in Europe. On its flags were fought out many feuds between
  rival gilds; Egmont and Horn, and many other gallant men whose names have
  been forgotten, were executed here under the shadow of its ancient
  buildings, and in more recent times Dumouriez proclaimed the French
  Republic where the dukes of Brabant and Burgundy were wont to hold their
  jousts. Apart from its associations the Grand Place contains two of the
  finest and most ornate buildings not merely in the capital but in
  Belgium. Of these the hôtel de ville, which is far the larger of the two,
  occupies the greater part of the south side of the square. Its facade has
  the disadvantage of having had one half begun about half a century before
  the other. The older, which is the richer in design, forms the left side
  of the building and dates from 1410, while the right, less rich and
  shorter, was begun in 1443. The fine tower, 360 ft. in height, is crowned
  by the golden copper figure of St Michael, 16 ft. in height, erected here
  as early as 1454. This tower lies behind the extremity of the left wing
  of the building. Opposite the town-hall is the smaller but extremely
  ornate Maison du Roi. This was never a royal residence as the name would
  seem to imply, but its description appears to have been derived from the
  fact that it was usually in this building that the royal address was read
  to the states-general. As this building was almost destroyed by
  Villeroi's bombardment it possesses no claim to antiquity, indeed the
  existing building was only completed in 1877. Egmont and Horn were
  sentenced in the hôtel de ville, and passed their last night in the
  Maison du Roi.</p>
      <p>Among the principal buildings erected in the city during the 18th
  century are the king's palace and the house of parliament or Palais de la
  Nation, which face the south and north sides of the park respectively.
  The palace occupies part of the site covered by the old palace burnt down
  in 1731, and it was built in the reign of the empress Maria Theresa. It
  originally consisted of two detached buildings, but in 1826-1827 King
  William I. of the Netherlands caused them to be connected. The palace
  contains two fine rooms used for court ceremonies, and a considerable
  number of pictures. In 1904 a bill was passed in the chambers for the
  enlargement and embellishment of the palace. The adjacent buildings, viz.
  the department of the civil list, formerly the residence of the marquis
  d'Assche, and the Hôtel de Bellevue, held under a kind of perpetual lease
  granted by the empress Maria Theresa, were absorbed in the palace, and a
  new façade was constructed which occupies the entire length of the Place
  du Palais. At the same time a piece was cut off the park to prevent the
  undue contraction of the Place by the necessary bringing forward of the
  palace, and the pits which played a certain part in the revolution of
  1830 when the Dutch defended the park for a few days against the Belgians
  were filled up. The Palais de la Nation was constructed between 1779 and
  1783, also during the Austrian period. It was intended for the
  states-general and government offices. During the French occupation the
  law courts sat there, and from 1817 to 1830 it was assigned for the
  sittings of the states-general. It is now divided between the senate and
  the chamber of representatives. In 1833 the part assigned to the latter
  was burnt out, and has since been reconstructed. The buildings flanking
  the chambers and nearer the park are government offices with residences
  for the ministers attached.</p>
      <p>The improvements effected in Brussels during the 19th century were
  enormous, and completely transformed the city. The removal of the old
  wall was followed by the creation of the quartier Léopold, and at a later
  period of the quartier Louis in the Upper Town. In the lower, under the
  energetic direction of two burgomasters, De Brouckere and Anspach, not
  less sweeping changes were effected. The Senne was bricked in, and the
  fine boulevards du Nord, Anspach, Hainaut and Midi took the place of
  slums. The Bourse and the post-office are two fine modern buildings in
  this quarter of the city. The Column of the Congress—<i>i.e.</i> of
  the Belgian representatives who founded the kingdom of
  Belgium—surmounted by a statue of King Leopold I., was erected in
  1859, and in 1866 the foundation-stone was laid of the Palais de Justice,
  which was not finished till 1883, at a cost of sixty million francs. This
  edifice, the design of the architect Poelaert, is in the style of Karnak
  and Nineveh, but surmounted with a dome, and impresses by its grandiose
  proportions (see <ph outputclass="sc">Architecture</ph>, Plate XI. fig.
  121). It is well placed on the brow of the hill at the southern extremity
  of the rue de la Régence (the prolongation of the rue Royale), and can be
  seen from great distances. In the rue de la Régence are the new picture
  gallery, a fine building with an exceedingly good collection of pictures,
  the palace of the count of Flanders, and the garden of the Petit Sablon,
  which contains statues of Egmont and Horn, and a large number of
  statuettes representing the various gilds and handicrafts. Immediately
  above this garden is the Palais d'Arenberg. Perhaps the memorial that
  attracts the greatest amount of public interest in Brussels is that to
  the Belgians who were killed during the fighting with the Dutch in
  September 1830. This has been erected in a little square called the Place
  des Martyrs, not far from the Monnaie theatre. Outside Brussels at Evere
  is the chief cemetery, with fine monuments to the British officers killed
  at Waterloo (removed from the church in that village), to the French
  soldiers who died on Belgian soil in 1870-71, and another to the
  Prussians.</p>
      <p>Many as were the changes in Brussels during the 19th century, those in
  progress at its close and at the beginning of the 20th have effected a
  marked alteration in the town. These have been rendered possible only by
  the excellent system of electric tramways which have brought districts
  formerly classed as pure country within reach of the citizens. The
  construction of the fine Avenue de Louise (1½ m. long) from the Boulevard
  de Waterloo to the Bois de la Cambre was the first of these efforts to
  bring the remote suburbs within easy reach, at the same time furnishing
  an approach to the "bois" of Brussels that might in some degree be
  compared with the Champs Élysées in Paris. Another avenue of later
  construction (6½ m. in length) connects the park of the Cinquantenaire
  with Tervueren. This route is extremely <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page694">[v.04 p.0694]</ph>picturesque,
  traverses part of the forest of Soignies, and is lined by many
  fashionable villas and country houses. Other improvements projected in
  1908 on the slope of the hill immediately below the Place Royale included
  the removal of the old tortuous and steep street called the "Montagne de
  la Cour" to give place to a Mont des Arts. A little lower down and not
  far from the university (which occupies the house of the famous cardinal
  Granvelle of the 16th century) a central railway terminus was designed on
  a vast scale. These improvements connote the obliteration of the
  insanitary and overcrowded courts and alleys which were to be found
  between all the main streets, few in number, connecting the upper and the
  lower towns. The ridge on the west and north-west of the Senne valley
  never formed part of the town, and it was from it that Villeroi bombarded
  the city. The suburbs on this ridge, from south to north, are Anderlecht,
  Molenbeek and Koekelberg, and Laeken with its royal château and park
  forms the northern part of the Brussels conglomeration. Brussels has been
  growing at such a rapid rate that the inclusion of this ridge, and more
  particularly at Koekelberg, within the town limits, was contemplated in
  1908.</p>
      <p>The completion of the harbour works, making Brussels a seaport by
  giving sea-going vessels access thereto, was taken in hand in 1897. The
  completed work provides for a waterway for steamers drawing 24 ft. by the
  Willibroek Canal into the Ruppel and the Scheldt. There are steamers
  plying direct from Brussels to London, and 372 vessels of a total tonnage
  of 76,000 entered and left the port in 1905. The Willibroek Canal was
  made in the 16th century, and William I. of the Netherlands is entitled
  to the credit of having first thought of converting it into a ship canal
  from Brussels to the Scheldt. Nothing was done, however, in his time to
  carry out the scheme. The distance from Brussels to the Ruppel is only 20
  m., and thus Brussels is only about 33 m. farther from the sea than
  Antwerp.</p>
      <p>In addition to the advantages it enjoys from being the seat of the
  court and the government, Brussels is the centre of many prosperous
  industries. The manufactures of lace, carpets and curtains, furniture and
  carriages may be particularly mentioned, but it is chiefly as a place of
  residence for the well-to-do that the city has increased in size and
  population. Schools of all kinds are abundant. At the École Militaire
  youths are trained nominally for the army, but many go there who intend
  to enter one of the professions or the public service. This school used
  to occupy part of the old abbey of the Cambre, situated in a hollow near
  the bois and the avenue Louise, but owing to its insanitary position it
  has been removed to a new building near the Cinquantenaire. There is a
  university, to which admission is easy and where the fees are moderate,
  and the Conservatoire provides as good musical teaching as can be found
  in Europe. Music can be enjoyed every day in the year either out of doors
  or under cover. During the winter and spring the opera continues without
  a break at the Théâtre de la Monnaie, which may be called the national
  theatre. Concerts are held frequently, as the Belgians are a musical
  people. Of late years sport has taken a prominent part in Belgian life.
  There are athletic institutions, and football is quite a popular game.
  Horse-racing has also come into vogue, and Boitsfort, in the bois, and
  Groenendael, farther off in the Forêt de Soignies, are fashionable places
  of reunion for society.</p>
      <p>The town of Brussels has a separate administration, which is directed
  by a burgomaster and sheriffs at the head of a town council, whose
  headquarters are in the hôtel de ville. In the Brussels agglomeration are
  nine suburbs or communes, each self-governing with burgomaster and
  sheriffs located in a Maison Communale. These suburbs (beginning on the
  north and following the circumference eastward) are Schaerbeek, St
  Josse-ten-Noode, Etterbeek, Ixelles, St Gilles, Cureghem, Anderlecht,
  Molenbeek and Koekelberg. Laeken, which is really a tenth suburb, is
  classified as a town. In 1856 the population of Brussels alone was
  152,828, and by 1880 it had only increased to 162,498. In 1890 the
  figures were 176,138; in 1900, 183,686; and in December 1904, 194,196.
  The great increase has been in the suburbs, amounting to nearly 80% in
  twenty-five years. In 1880 the population of the ten suburbs including
  Laeken was 248,079. In 1904 the total was 436,453, thus giving for the
  whole of Brussels a grand total of 630,649.</p>
      <p>
         <i>History.</i>—The name Brussel seems to have been derived from
  Broeksele, the village on the marsh or brook, and probably it was the
  most used point for crossing the Senne on the main Roman and Frank road
  between Tournai and Cologne. The Senne, a small tributary of the Scheldt,
  flows through the lower town, but since 1868 it has been covered in, and
  some of the finest boulevards in the lower town have been constructed
  over the course of the little river. The name Broeksele is mentioned by
  the chroniclers in the 8th century, and in the 10th the church of Ste
  Gudule is said to have been endowed by the emperor Otto I. In the next
  two centuries Brussels grew in size and importance, and its trade gilds
  were formed on lines similar to those of Ghent. In 1312 Duke John II. of
  Brabant granted the citizens their charter, distinguished from others as
  that of Cortenberg. In 1356 Duke Wenceslas confirmed this charter and
  also the Golden Bull of the emperor Charles IV. of 1349 by his famous
  "Joyous Entry" into Louvain, the capital of the duchy. These three deeds
  or enactments constituted the early constitution of the South
  Netherlands, which, with one important modification in the time of
  Charles V., remained intact till the Brabant revolution in the reign of
  Joseph II. In 1357 Wenceslas ordered a new wall embracing a greater area
  than the earlier one to be constructed round Brussels, and this was
  practically intact until after the Belgian revolution in 1830-1831. It
  took twelve, or, according to others, twenty-two years to build. In 1383
  the dukes of Brabant transferred their capital from Louvain to Brussels,
  although for some time they did not trust themselves out of the strong
  castle which they had erected at Vilvorde, half-way between the two
  turbulent cities. During this period the population of Brussels is
  supposed to have been 50,000, or one-fifth of that of Ghent. In 1420 the
  gilds of Brussels obtained a further charter recognizing their status as
  the Nine Nations, a division still existing. Having fixed their seat of
  government at Brussels the dukes of Brabant proceeded to build a castle
  and place of residence on the Caudenberg hill, which is practically the
  site of the Place Royale and the king's palace to-day. This ducal
  residence, enlarged and embellished by its subsequent occupants, became
  eventually the famous palace of the Netherlands which witnessed the
  abdication of Charles V. in 1555, and was destroyed by fire in 1731. In
  1430 died Philip, last duke of Brabant as a separate ruler, and the duchy
  was merged in the possessions of the duke of Burgundy.</p>
      <p>In the 17th century Brussels was described (Comte de Ségur, quoting
  the memoirs of M. de la Serre) as "one of the finest, largest and
  best-situated cities not only of Brabant but of the whole of Europe. The
  old quarters which preserve in our time an aspect so singularly
  picturesque with their sloping and tortuous streets, the fine hotels of
  darkened stone sculptured in the Spanish fashion, and the magnificence of
  the Place of the hôtel de ville were buried behind an enceinte of walls
  pierced by eight lofty gates flanked with one hundred and twenty-seven
  round towers at almost equal distance from each other like the balls of a
  crown. At a distance of less than a mile was the forest of Soignies with
  great numbers of stags, red and roe deer, that were hunted on horseback
  even under the ramparts of the town. On the promenade of the court there
  circulated in a long file ceaselessly during fashionable hours five or
  six hundred carriages, the servants in showy liveries. In the numerous
  churches the music was renowned, the archduke Leopold being passionately
  given to the art, maintaining at his own cost forty or fifty musicians,
  the best of Italy and Germany. Under the windows of the palace stretched
  the same park that we admire to-day, open all the year to privileged
  persons and twice a year to the public, a park filled with trees of rare
  essences and the most delicious flowers so artistically disposed, and so
  refreshing to the eyes, that M. de la Serre declared that if he had seen
  there an apple tree he would assuredly have taken it for an earthly
  Paradise."</p>
      <p>(D. C. B.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>