<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e24937">
   <title>BROWNSVILLE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWNSVILLE,--> a city and the county-seat of Cameron county,
  Texas, U.S.A., situated near the S. extremity of the state, on the Rio
  Grande river about 22 m. above its mouth, and opposite Matamoras, Mexico.
  Pop. (1890) 6134; (1900) 6305, including 2462 foreign-born and 18
  negroes; (1910) 10,517. It is served by the St Louis, Brownsville &amp;
  Mexico, and the Rio Grande railways, being connected by the former with
  Houston and Galveston and by the latter with Point Isabel on the Gulf
  coast. Its chief importance lies in its being the commercial and
  distributing centre for a rich and extensive agricultural region in
  southern Texas and northern Mexico, and an important market for rice,
  sugar-cane, fruit, vegetables and live-stock. It has a United States
  custom house, the Cameron county court house, a Roman Catholic cathedral,
  St Joseph's College (Roman Catholic), and the Incarnate Word Academy
  (Roman Catholic). Before the Mexican War there was a small Mexican
  settlement on the site of Brownsville. In March 1846 General Zachary
  Taylor erected fortifications here, and upon his withdrawal to Point
  Isabel, left a small garrison in command of Major Jacob Brown. The fort
  was assaulted by General Arista and shelled by batteries from the Mexican
  shore, and at last on the 10th of May was relieved by General Taylor, who
  in advancing to its aid had won the battles of Palo Alto (8th of May) and
  Resaca de la Palma (9th of May). The fort, originally named Fort Taylor,
  was renamed Fort Brown, by order of General Taylor, in memory of Major
  Brown, who was mortally wounded during the bombardment. In 1859
  Brownsville was captured by a band of Mexican raiders under Juan
  Nepomuceno Cortina. During the Civil War, until its temporary occupation
  by Federal forces in 1863, and subsequent effective blockade, it was an
  active centre of operations of Confederate blockade runners. At Palmetto
  Ranch, near the battlefield of Palo Alto, took place (13th of May 1865),
  more than a month after General Lee's surrender, the last engagement
  between Federal and Confederate troops in the Civil War. In Brownsville,
  on the night of the 13th of August 1906, certain persons unknown fired
  into houses and at citizens on the streets, killing one man and injuring
  two. Suspicion pointed to negro soldiers of Companies B, C and D of the
  25th Infantry, stationed at Fort Brown, and as it appeared that the
  culprits were being shielded by their comrades by a "conspiracy of
  silence," President Roosevelt dismissed the 170 men of the three
  companies "without honor." Both in Congress and in the press a bitter
  attack was made on the president for his action. In 1907 the military
  reservation of Fort Brown was transferred to the Department of
  Agriculture. In March 1909 Congress provided for a commission of army
  officers to report as to the eligibility of members of the negro
  regiments for re-enlistment.</p>
   </body>
</topic>