<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e24250">
   <title>BROWNING, ELIZABETH BARRETT</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWNING, ELIZABETH BARRETT--> (1806-1861), English poet, wife of
  the poet Robert Browning, was born probably at Coxhoe Hall, Durham, for
  this was the home of her father and mother for some time after their
  marriage in 1805. Her baptismal register gives the date of her birth as
  the 6th of March 1806, and that of her christening as the 10th of
  February 1808. The long misunderstanding as to her age, whereby she was
  supposed to have been born three years later, was shared by her
  contemporaries and even for a time by her husband. She was the daughter
  and eldest child of Edward Barrett Moulton, who added the surname of
  Barrett on the death of his maternal grandfather, whose estates in
  Jamaica he inherited. His wife was Mary Graham-Clarke, daughter of J.
  Graham-Clarke of Fenham Hall, Newcastle-on-Tyne. She died when her
  illustrious daughter was twenty-two years old. Elizabeth's childhood was
  passed in the country, chiefly at Hope End, a house bought by her father
  in the beautiful country in sight of the Malvern Hills. "They seem to
  me," she wrote, "my native hills; for though I was born in the county of
  Durham, I was an infant when I went first into their neighbourhood, and
  lived there until I had passed twenty by several years." Her country
  poems, such as "The Lost Bower," "Hector in the Garden," and "The
  Deserted Garden," refer to the woods and gardens of Hope End. Elizabeth
  Barrett was much the companion of her father, who pleased himself with
  printing fifty copies of what she calls her "great epic of eleven or
  twelve years old, in four books"—<i>The Battle of Marathon</i>
  (sent to the printer in 1819). She owns this to have been "a curious
  production for a child," but disclaims for it anything more than "an
  imitative faculty." The love of Pope's Homer, she adds, led her to the
  study of Greek, and of Latin as a help to Greek, "and the influence of
  all those tendencies is manifest so long afterwards as in my <i>Essay on
  Mind</i> [<i>Essay on Mind and other Poems</i>, 1826], a didactic poem
  written when I was seventeen or eighteen, and long repented of." She was
  a keen student, and it is told of her that when her health failed she had
  her Greek books bound so as to look like novels, for fear her doctor
  should forbid her continuous study. At this time began her friendship
  with the blind scholar Hugh Stuart Boyd, with whom she read Greek
  authors, and especially the Greek Christian Fathers and Poets. To him she
  addressed later three of her sonnets, and he was one of her chief friends
  until his death in 1848. In 1832 Mr Barrett sold his house of Hope End,
  and brought his family to Sidmouth, Devon, for some three years. There
  Elizabeth made a translation of the <i>Prometheus Bound</i> of Aeschylus,
  published with some original poems (1833). After that time London became
  the home of the Barretts until the children married and the father died.
  The temporary dwelling was at 74 Gloucester Place, Portman Square, and in
  1838 the lease was taken of the final house, 50 Wimpole Street.</p>
      <p>It is in the middle of the year 1836 that Elizabeth Barrett's active
  literary life began. She then made the acquaintance of R.H. Horne,
  afterwards famous for a time as the author of <i>Orion</i>, but perhaps
  best remembered as her correspondent (<i>Letters to R.H. Horne</i>, 2
  vols. 1877), and this acquaintance led to the appearance of rather
  frequent poems by Miss Barrett in the <i>New Monthly Magazine</i>, edited
  by Bulwer (Lord Lytton), and in other magazines or annuals. But the
  publication of <i>The Seraphim and other Poems</i> (1838) was a graver
  step. "My present attempt," she writes in this year, "<i>is</i> actually,
  and will be considered by others, more a trial of strength than either of
  my preceding ones." There was at that date a lull in the production of
  conspicuous books of poetry. Wordsworth had ceased, Browning and Tennyson
  had hardly begun to write their best. Miss Barrett's volume was well
  reviewed, but not popular, and no second edition was required; of the
  poems afterwards famous it contained three, "Cowper's Grave," "My Doves,"
  and "The Sea-Mew," the first impassioned and the other two very quiet,
  which a fine taste must rank high among all her works. <i>The Quarterly
  Review</i> (September 1840), in an article on "Modern English Poetesses,"
  criticizes <i>The Seraphim</i> with <i>Prometheus</i>, and treats the
  former with respect, but does not lift the author out of the quite
  unequal company of Mrs Norton, "V," and other contemporary women. In the
  previous year Elizabeth had made the memorable acquaintance of
  Wordsworth. "No," she writes, "I was not at all disappointed in
  Wordsworth, although perhaps I should not have singled him from the
  multitude as a great man. There is a <i>reserve</i> even in his
  countenance; ... his eyes have more meekness than brilliancy; and in his
  slow, even articulation there is rather the solemnity and calmness of
  <i>truth</i> itself than the animation and energy of those who seek for
  it ... He was very kind, and sate near me and talked to me as long as he
  was in the room, and recited a translation by Cary of a sonnet of
  Dante's—and altogether it was a dream." With Landor, at the same
  date, a meeting took place that had long results. At this time, too,
  began another of Elizabeth's valued friendships—that with Miss
  Mitford, author of <i>Our Village</i> and other works less well
  remembered. Mr John Kenyon also became at about this time a dear and
  intimate friend. He was a distant cousin of the Barretts, had published
  some verse, and was a warm and generous friend to men of letters. From
  the date of the birth of their child (1849) he gave the Brownings a
  hundred pounds a year, and when he died in 1856 he bequeathed to them
  eleven thousand pounds. To him a great number of Elizabeth's letters are
  addressed, and to him in later years was <i>Aurora Leigh</i> dedicated.
  Elizabeth Barrett began also in London an acquaintance with Harriet
  Martineau.</p>
      <p>Full of the interest of friendship and literature, the residence in
  London was unfavourable to Elizabeth's health. In early girlhood she had
  a spinal affection, and her lungs became delicate. She broke a
  blood-vessel in the beginning of the Barretts' life in town, and was
  thereafter an invalid—by no means entirely confined to her room,
  but often imprisoned there, and generally a recluse, until her marriage.
  Her state was so threatening that in 1838 it was found necessary to
  remove her to Torquay, where she spent three years, accompanied by her
  brother Edward, the dearest of her eight brothers, the only one, she said
  many years later, who ever comprehended her, and for a time by her father
  and sisters. During this time of physical suffering she underwent the
  greatest grief of her life by the drowning of her beloved brother, who
  with two friends went sailing in a small boat and was lost in Babbacombe
  Bay. Rumours of the foundering reached the unhappy sister, who was
  assured of the worst after three days, when the bodies were found. The
  accident of Edward Barrett's meeting with his death through her residence
  at Torquay, and the minor accident of her having parted from him on the
  day of his death, as she said, "with pettish words," increased her
  anguish of heart to horror. A few days before she had written, "There are
  so many mercies close around me that God's being seems proved to me,
  <i>demonstrated</i> to me, by His manifested love." When the blow came,
  its heavy weight and closeness to her heart convinced her, she wrote,
  through an awful experience of suffering, of divine action. But many
  years later the mention of her brother's death was intolerable to her. At
  the time she only did not die. She had to remain for nearly a year day
  and night within hearing of the sea, of which the sound seemed to her the
  moan of a dying man.</p>
      <p>There is here an interval of silence in the correspondence which
  busied her secluded life at all ages; but with an impulse of
  self-protection she went to work as soon as her strength sufficed. One of
  her tasks was a part taken in the <i>Chaucer Modernized</i> (1841), a
  work suggested by Wordsworth, to which he, Leigh Hunt, Horne and others
  contributed. In 1841 she returned to Wimpole Street, and in that and the
  <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page669">[v.04
  p.0669]</ph>following year she was at work on two series of articles on
  the Greek Christian poets and on the English poets, written for the
  <i>Athenaeum</i> under the editorship of Mr C.W. Dilke. In work she found
  some interest and even some delight: "Once I wished not to live, but the
  faculty of life seems to have sprung up in me again from under the
  crushing foot of heavy grief. Be it all as God wills."</p>
      <p>It is in 1842 that we notice the name of Robert Browning in her
  letters: "Mr Horne the poet and Mr Browning the poet were not behind in
  approbation," she says in regard to her work on the poets. "Mr Browning
  is said to be learned in Greek, especially the dramatists." In this year
  also she declares her love for Tennyson. To Kenyon she writes, "I ought
  to be thanking you for your great kindness about this divine Tennyson."
  In 1842, moreover, she had the pleasure of a letter from Wordsworth, who
  had twice asked Kenyon for permission to visit her. The visit was not
  permitted on account of Miss Barrett's ill-health. Now Haydon sent her
  his unfinished painting of the great poet musing upon Helvellyn; she
  wrote her sonnet on the portrait, and Haydon sent it to Rydal Mount.
  Wordsworth's commendation is rather cool. In August 1843 "The Cry of the
  Children" appeared in <i>Blackwood's Magazine</i>, and during the year
  she was associated with her friend Horne in a critical work, <i>The New
  Spirit of the Age</i>, rather by advice than by direct contribution. Her
  two volumes of poems (1844) appeared, six years after her former book,
  under the title of <i>Poems, by Elizabeth Barrett Barrett</i>. The
  warmest praises that greeted the new poems were H.F. Chorley's in the
  <i>Athenaeum</i>, John Forster's in the <i>Examiner</i>, and those
  conveyed in <i>Blackwood</i>, the <i>Dublin Review</i>, the <i>New
  Quarterly</i> and the <i>Atlas</i>. Letters came from Carlyle and others.
  Both he and Miss Martineau selected as their favourite poem "Lady
  Geraldine's Courtship," a violent piece of work. In the beginning of the
  following year came the letter from a stranger that was to be so
  momentous to both. "I had a letter from Browning the poet last night,"
  she writes to her old friend Mrs Martin, "which threw me into
  ecstasies—Browning, the author of <i>Paracelsus</i>, the king of
  the mystics." She is flattered, though not to "ecstasies," at about the
  same time by a letter from E.A. Poe, and by the dedication to her, as
  "the noblest of her sex," of his own work. "What is to be said, I wonder,
  when a man calls you the 'noblest of your sex'? 'Sir, you are the most
  discerning of yours.'" America was at least as quick as England to
  appreciate her poetry; among other messages thence came in the spring
  letters from Lowell and from Mrs Sigourney. "She says that the sound of
  my poetry is stirring the 'deep green forests of the New World'; which
  sounds pleasantly, does it not?" It is in the same year that the letters
  first speak of the hope of a journey to Italy. The winters in London,
  with the imprisonment which—according to the medical practice of
  that day—they entailed, were lowering Elizabeth's strength of
  resistance against disease. She longed for the change of light, scene,
  manners and language, and the longing became a hope, until her father's
  prohibition put an end to it, and doomed her, as she and others thought,
  to death, without any perceptible reason for the denial of so reasonable
  a desire.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile the friendship with Browning had become the chief thing in
  Elizabeth Barrett's life. The correspondence, once begun, had not
  flagged. In the early summer they met. The allusion to his poetry in
  "Lady Geraldine's Courtship" had doubtless put an edge to his already
  keen wish to know her. He became her frequent visitor and kept her room
  fragrant with flowers. He never lagged, whether in friendship or in love.
  We have the strange privilege, since the publication of the letters
  between the two, of following the whole course of this noble love-story
  from beginning to end, and day by day. Browning was six years younger
  than the woman he so passionately admired, and he at first believed her
  to be confined by some hopeless physical injury to her sofa. But of his
  own wish and resolution he never doubted. Her hesitation, in her regard
  for his liberty and strength, to burden him with an ailing wife, she has
  recorded in the Sonnets afterwards published under a slight disguise as
  <i>Sonnets from the Portuguese</i>. She refused him once "with all her
  will, but much against her heart," and yielded at last for his sake
  rather than her own. Her father's will was that his children should not
  marry, and, kind and affectionate father though he was, the prohibition
  took a violent form and struck terror into the hearts of the three
  dutiful and sensitive girls. Robert Browning's addresses were, therefore,
  kept secret, for fear of scenes of anger which the most fragile of the
  three could not face. Browning was reluctant to practise the deception;
  Elizabeth alone knew how impossible it was to avoid it. When she was
  persuaded to marry, it was she who insisted, in mental and physical
  terror, upon a secret wedding. Throughout the summer of 1846 her health
  improved, and on the 12th of September the two poets were married in St
  Marylebone parish church. Browning visited it on his subsequent journeys
  to England to give thanks for what had taken place at its altar.
  Elizabeth's two sisters had been permitted to know of the engagement, but
  not of the wedding, so that their father's anger might not fall on them
  too heavily. For a week Mrs Browning remained in her father's house. On
  the 19th of September she left it, taking her maid and her little dog,
  joined her husband, and crossed to the Continent. She never entered that
  home again, nor did her father ever forgive her. Her letters, written
  with tears to entreat his pardon, were never answered. They were all
  subsequently returned to her unopened. Among them was one she had
  written, in the prospect of danger, before the birth of her child. With
  her sisters her relations were, as before, most affectionate. Her
  brothers, one at least of whom disapproved of her action, held for a time
  aloof. All others were taken entirely by surprise. Mrs Jameson, who had
  been one of the few intimate visitors to Miss Barrett's room, had offered
  to take her to Italy that year, but met her instead on her way thither
  with a newly-married husband. The poets' journey was full of delight.
  Where she could not walk, up long staircases or across the waters of the
  stream at Vaucluse, Browning carried her. In October they reached Pisa,
  and there they wintered, Mrs Jameson keeping them company for a time lest
  ignorance of practical things should bring them, in their poverty, to
  trouble. She soon found that they were both admirable economists; not
  that they gave time and thought to husbandry, but that they knew how to
  enjoy life without luxuries. So they remained to the end, frugal and
  content with little.</p>
      <p>For climate and cheapness they settled in Italy, choosing Florence in
  the spring of 1847, and remaining there, with the interruptions of a
  change to places in Italy such as Siena and Rome, and to Paris and
  England, until Mrs Browning's death. It was at Pisa that Robert Browning
  first saw the <i>Sonnets from the Portuguese</i>, poems which his wife
  had written in secret and had no thought of publishing. He, however,
  resolved to give them to the world. "I dared not," he said, "reserve to
  myself the finest sonnets written in any language since Shakespeare's."
  The judgment, which the existence of Wordsworth's sonnets renders
  obviously absurd, may be pardoned. The sonnets were sent to Miss Mitford
  and published at Reading, as <i>Sonnets by E.B.B.</i>, in 1847. In 1850
  they were included, under their final title, in a new issue of poems.
  During the Pisan autumn appeared in <i>Blackwood's Magazine</i> seven
  poems by Mrs Browning which she had sent some time before, and the
  publication of which at that moment disturbed her as likely to hurt her
  father by an apparent reference to her own story. At Pisa also she wrote
  and sent to America a poem, "The Runaway Slave at Pilgrim Point," which
  was published in Boston, in <i>The Liberty Bell</i>, in 1848, and
  separately in England in 1849. In the summer of 1847 the Brownings left
  their temporary dwelling in Florence and took the apartment in Casa
  Guidi, near the Pitti Palace, which was thenceforth their chief home.
  Early in their residence began that excited interest in Italian affairs
  which made so great a part of Mrs Browning's emotional life. The
  Florentines, under the government of the grand duke, were prosperous but
  disturbed by national aspirations. Mrs Browning, by degrees, wrote Casa
  Guidi Windows on their behalf and as an appeal to the always impulsive
  sympathies of England. In 1849 was born <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page670">[v.04 p.0670]</ph>the Brownings'
  only child, their beloved son Robert Wiedemann Barrett. After this event
  Mrs Browning resumed her literary activities, preparing a new issue, with
  some additions, of her poems (1850). A poem on the death of a friend's
  child appeared in the <i>Athenaeum</i> (1849), and there the new volumes
  were warmly praised. <i>Casa Guidi Windows</i> followed in 1851. Visiting
  England in that year, the Brownings saw much of the Procters, and
  something of Florence Nightingale, Kingsley, Ruskin, Rogers, Patmore and
  Tennyson, and also of Carlyle, with whom they went to Paris, where they
  saw George Sand, and where they passed the December days of the <i>coup
  d'état</i>. Mrs Browning happened to take a political fancy to Napoleon
  III., whom she would probably have denounced if a tithe of his tyrannies
  had occurred in Italy, and the fancy became more emotional in after
  years.</p>
      <p>A new edition of Mrs Browning's poems was called for in 1853, and at
  about this time, in Florence, she began to work on <i>Aurora Leigh</i>.
  She was still writing this poem when the Brownings were again in England,
  in 1855. Tennyson there read to them his newly-written <i>Maud</i>. After
  another interval in Paris they were in London again—Mrs Browning
  for the last time. She was with her dear cousin Kenyon during the last
  months of his life. In October 1856 the Brownings returned to their
  Florentine home, Mrs Browning leaving her completed <i>Aurora Leigh</i>
  for publication. The book had an immediate success; a second edition was
  required in a fortnight, a third a few months later. In the fourth
  edition (1859) several corrections were made. The review in
  <i>Blackwood</i> was written by W.E. Aytoun, that in the <i>North
  British</i> by Coventry Patmore.</p>
      <p>In 1857 Mrs Browning addressed a petition, in the form of a letter, to
  the emperor Napoleon begging him to remit the sentence of exile upon
  Victor Hugo. We do not hear of any reply. In 1857 Mrs Browning's father
  died, unreconciled. Henrietta Barrett had married, like her sister, and
  like her was unforgiven. In 1858 occurred another visit to Paris, and
  another to Rome, where Hawthorne and his family were among the Brownings'
  friends. In 1859 came the Italian war in which Mrs Browning's hasty
  sympathies were hotly engaged. Her admiration of Italy's champion,
  Napoleon III., knew no bounds, and did not give way when, by the peace of
  Villafranca, Venice and Rome were left unannexed to the kingdom of Italy,
  and the French frontiers were "rectified" by the withdrawal from that
  kingdom of Savoy and Nice. That peace, however, was a bitter
  disappointment, and her fragile health suffered. At Siena and Florence
  this year the Brownings were very kind to Landor, old, solitary, and ill.
  Mrs Browning's poem, "A Tale of Villafranca", was published in the
  <i>Athenaeum</i> in September, and afterwards included in <i>Poems before
  Congress</i> (1860). Then followed another long visit to Rome, and there
  Mrs Browning prepared for the press this, her last volume. The little
  book was judged with some impatience, <i>A Curse for a Nation</i> being
  mistaken for a denunciation of England, whereas it was aimed at America
  and her slavery. The <i>Athenaeum</i>, amongst others, committed this
  error. The <i>Saturday Review</i> was hard on the volume, so was
  <i>Blackwood</i>; the <i>Atlas</i> and <i>Daily News</i> favourable. In
  July 1860 was published "A Musical Instrument" in the young <i>Cornhill
  Magazine</i>, edited by the author's friend W.M. Thackeray. The last blow
  she had to endure was the death of her sister Henrietta, in the same
  year.</p>
      <p>On the 30th of June 1861 Elizabeth Barrett Browning died. Her husband,
  who tended her alone on the night of her decease, wrote to Miss Blagden:
  "Then came what my heart will keep till I see her again and
  longer—the most perfect expression of her love to me within my
  whole knowledge of her. Always smilingly, happily, and with a face like a
  girl's, and in a few minutes she died in my arms, her head on my cheek.
  ... There was no lingering, nor acute pain, nor consciousness of
  separation, but God took her to himself as you would lift a sleeping
  child from a dark uneasy bed into your arms and the light. Thank God."
  Her married life had been supremely happy. Something has been said of the
  difference between husband and wife in regard to "spiritualism", in which
  Mrs Browning had interest and faith, but no division ever interrupted
  their entirely perfect affection and happiness. Of her husband's love for
  her she wrote at the time of her marriage, "He preferred ... of free and
  deliberate choice, to be allowed to sit only an hour a day by my side, to
  the fulfilment of the brightest dream which should exclude me in any
  possible world." "I am still doubtful whether all the brightness can be
  meant for <i>me</i>. It is just as if the sun rose again at 7 o'clock
  <ph outputclass="scac">P.M.</ph>" "I take it for pure magic, this life of
  mine. Surely nobody was ever so happy before." "I must say to you [Mrs
  Jameson] who saw the beginning with us, that this end of fifteen months
  is just fifteen times better and brighter; the mystical 'moon' growing
  larger and larger till scarcely room is left for any stars at all: the
  only differences which have touched me being the more and more
  happiness." Browning buried his wife in Florence, under a tomb designed
  by their friend Frederick Leighton. On the wall of Casa Guidi is placed
  the inscription: "Qui scrisse e mori Elisabetta Barrett Browning, che in
  cuore di donna conciliava scienza di dotto e spirito di poeta, e face del
  suo verso aureo annello fra Italia e Inghilterra. Pone questa lapide
  Firenze grata 1861." In 1866 Robert Browning published a volume of
  selections from his wife's works.</p>
      <p>The place of Elizabeth Barrett Browning in English literature is high,
  if not upon the summits. She had an original genius, a fervent heart, and
  an intellect that was, if not great, exceedingly active. She seldom has
  composure or repose, but it is not true that her poetry is purely
  emotional. It is full of abundant, and even over-abundant, thoughts. It
  is intellectually restless. The impassioned peace of the greatest poetry,
  such as Wordsworth's, is not hers. Nor did she apparently seek to attain
  those heights. Her Greek training taught her little of the economy that
  such a poetic education is held to impose; she "dashed", not by reason of
  feminine weakness, but as it were to prove her possession of masculine
  strength. Her gentler work, as in the <i>Sonnets from the Portuguese</i>,
  is beyond praise. There is in her poetic personality a glory of
  righteousness, of spirituality, and of ardour that makes her name a
  splendid one in the history of an incomparable literature.</p>
      <p>See the <i>Letters of Elizabeth Barrett Browning addressed to R.H.
  Horne, with Comments on Contemporaries</i>, edited by S.R. Townshend
  Mayer (2 vols., 1877); <i>The Poetical Works of Elizabeth Barrett
  Browning from 1826 to 1844</i>, edited with memoir by J.H. Ingram (1887);
  <i>Elizabeth Barrett Browning</i> (Eminent Women series), by J.H. Ingram,
  1888); <i>Records of Tennyson, Ruskin and the Brownings</i>, by Anne
  Ritchie (1892); <i>The Letters of Elizabeth Barrett Browning</i>, edited
  with biographical additions by Frederick G. Kenyon (2 vols., 1897);
  <i>The Letters of Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Barrett</i> (2
  vols., 1899); <i>La Vie et l'œuvre d'Elizabeth Browning</i>, by
  Mdlle. Germaine-Marie Merlette (Paris, 1906)</p>
      <p>(<ph outputclass="sc">A. Me.</ph>)</p>
   </body>
</topic>