<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e26282">
   <title>BRUNSWICK</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNSWICK, KARL WILHELM FERDINAND,--> <ph outputclass="sc">Duke
  of</ph> (1735-1806), German general, was born on the 9th of October
  1735 at Wolfenbüttel. He received an unusually wide and thorough
  education, and travelled in his youth in Holland, France and various
  parts of Germany. His first military experience was in the North German
  campaign of 1757, under the duke of Cumberland. At the battle of
  Hastenbeck he won great renown by a gallant charge at the head of an
  infantry brigade; <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page688">[v.04 p.0688]</ph>and upon the capitulation of
  Kloster Zeven he was easily persuaded by his uncle Ferdinand of
  Brunswick, who succeeded Cumberland, to continue in the war as a general
  officer. The exploits of the hereditary prince, as he was called, soon
  gained him further reputation, and he became an acknowledged master of
  irregular warfare. In pitched battles, and in particular at Minden and
  Warburg, he proved himself an excellent subordinate. After the close of
  the Seven Years' War, the prince visited England with his bride, the
  daughter of Frederick, prince of Wales, and in 1766 he went to France,
  being received both by his allies and his late enemies with every token
  of respect. In Paris he made the acquaintance of Marmontel; in
  Switzerland, whither he continued his tour, that of Voltaire; and in Rome
  , where he remained for a long time, he explored the antiquities of the
  city under the guidance of Winckelmann. After a visit to Naples he
  returned to Paris, and thence, with his wife, to Brunswick. His services
  to the dukedom during the next few years were of the greatest value; with
  the assistance of the minister Féronce von Rotenkreuz he rescued the
  state from the bankruptcy into which the war had brought it. His
  popularity was unbounded, and when he succeeded his father, Duke Karl I.,
  in 1780, he soon became known as a model to sovereigns. He was perhaps
  the best representative of the benevolent despot of the 18th
  century—wise, economical, prudent and kindly. His habitual caution,
  if it induced him on some occasions to leave reforms uncompleted, at any
  rate saved him from the failures which marred the efforts of so many
  liberal princes of his time. He strove to keep his duchy from all foreign
  entanglements. At the same time he continued to render important services
  to the king of Prussia, for whom he had fought in the Seven Years' War;
  he was a Prussian field marshal, and was at pains to make the regiment of
  which he was colonel a model one, and he was frequently engaged in
  diplomatic and other state affairs. He resembled his uncle Frederick the
  Great in many ways, but he lacked the supreme resolution of the king, and
  in civil as in military affairs was prone to excessive caution. As an
  enthusiastic adherent of the Germanic and anti-Austrian policy of Prussia
  he joined the <i>Fürstenbund</i>, in which, as he now had the reputation
  of being the best soldier of his time, he was the destined
  commander-in-chief of the federal army.</p>
      <p>Between 1763 and 1787 his only military service had been in the brief
  War of the Bavarian Succession; in the latter year, however, the Duke, as
  a Prussian field marshal, led the army which invaded Holland. His success
  was rapid, complete and almost bloodless, and in the eyes of
  contemporaires the campaign appeared as an example of perfect
  generalship. Five years later Brunswick was appointed to the command of
  the allied Austrian and German army assembled to invade France and crush
  the Revolution. In this task he knew that he must encounter more than a
  formal resistance. He was so far in acknowledged sympathy with French
  hopes of reform, that when he gave an asylum in his duchy to the "comte
  de Lille" (Louis XVIII.) the revolutionary government made no protest.
  Indeed, earlier this year (1792) he had been offered supreme command of
  the French army. As the king of Prussia took the field with Brunswick's
  army, the duke felt bound as a soldier to treat his wishes as actual
  orders. (For the events of the Valmy campaign see <ph outputclass="sc">French
  Revolutionary Wars</ph>). The result of Brunswick's cautious advance on
  Paris was the cannonade of Valmy followed by a retreat of the allies. The
  following campaign of 1793 showed his perhaps at his best as a careful
  and exact general; even the fiery Hoche, with the "nation in arms" behind
  him, failed to make any impression on the veteran leader of the allies.
  But difficulties and disagreements at headquarters multiplied, and when
  Brunswick found himself unable to move or direct his army without
  interference from the king, he laid down his command and returned to
  govern his duchy. He did not, however, withdraw entirely from Prussian
  service, and in 1803 he carried out a successful and diplomatic mission
  to Russia. In 1806, at the personal request of Queen Louise of Prussia,
  he consented to command the Prussian army, but here again the presence of
  the king of Prussia and the conflicting views of numerous advisers of
  high rank proved fatal. At the battle of Auerstadt the old duke was
  mortally wounded. Carried for nearly a month in the midst of the routed
  Prussian army he died at last on the 10th of November 1806 at Ottensen
  near Hamburg.</p>
      <p>His son and successor, <ph outputclass="sc">Friedrich Wilhelm</ph>
  (1771-1815), who was one of the bitterest opponents of Napoleonic
  domination in Germany, took part in the war of 1809 at the head of a
  corps of partisans; fled to England after the battle of Wagram, and
  returned to Brunswick in 1813, where he raised fresh troops. He was
  killed at the battle of Quatre Bras on the 16th of June 1815.</p>
      <p>See Lord Fitzmaurice, <i>Charles W.F., duke of Brunswick</i> (London,
  1901); memoir in <i>Allgemeine deutsche Biographie</i>, vol. ii.
  (Leipzig, 1882); and, for an interesting sketch of his military
  character, A. Chuquet, <i>Les Guerres de la Révolution—La Premiére
  Invasion prussienne</i> (Paris, N.D.).</p>
   </body>
</topic>