<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e33348">
   <title>BUGEAUD DE LA PICONNERIE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUGEAUD DE LA PICONNERIE, THOMAS ROBERT,--> <ph outputclass="sc">duke
  of Isly</ph> (1784-1849), marshal of France, was born at Limoges on the
  15th of October 1784. He came of a noble family of Périgord, and was the
  youngest of his parents' thirteen children. Harsh treatment led to his
  flight from home, and for some years about 1800 he lived in the country,
  engaged in agriculture, to which he was ever afterwards devoted. At the
  age of twenty he became a private soldier in the <i>Vélites</i> of the
  Imperial Guard (1804), with which he took part in the Austerlitz campaign
  of the following year. Early in 1806 he was given a commission, and as a
  sub-lieutenant he served in the Jena and Eylau campaigns, winning his
  promotion to the rank of lieutenant at Pultusk (December 1806). In 1808
  he was in the first French corps which entered Spain, and was stationed
  in Madrid during the revolt of the <i>Dos Mayo</i>. At the second siege
  of Saragossa he won further promotion to the rank of captain, and in
  1809-1810 found opportunities for winning distinction under General
  (Marshal) Suchet in the eastern theatre of the Peninsular War, in which
  he rose to the rank of major and the command of a full regiment. At the
  first restoration he was made a colonel, but he rejoined Napoleon during
  the Hundred Days, and under his old chief Suchet distinguished himself
  greatly in the war in the Alps. For fifteen years after the fall of
  Napoleon he was not re-employed, and during this time he displayed great
  activity in agriculture and in the general development of his district of
  Périgord. The July revolution of 1830 reopened his military career, and
  after a short tenure of a regimental command he was in 1831 made a
  <i>maréchal de camp</i>. In the chamber <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page759">[v.04 p.0759]</ph>of deputies, to
  which he was elected in the same year, he showed himself to be an
  inflexible opponent of democracy, and in his military capacity he was
  noted for his severity in police work and the suppression of
  <i>émeutes</i>. His conduct as gaoler of the duchesse de Berry led to a
  duel between Bugeaud and the deputy Dulong, in which the latter was
  killed (1834); this affair and the incidents of another <i>émeute</i>
  exposed Bugeaud to ceaseless attacks in the Chamber and in the press, but
  his opinion was sought by all parties in matters connected with
  agriculture and industrial development. He was re-elected in 1834, 1837
  and 1839.</p>
      <p>About this time Bugeaud became much interested in the question of
  Algeria. At first he appears to have disapproved of the conquest, but his
  undeviating adherence to Louis Philippe brought him into agreement with
  the government, and with his customary decision he proposed to employ at
  once whatever forces were necessary for the swift, complete and lasting
  subjugation of Algeria. Later events proved the soundness of his views;
  in the meantime Bugeaud was sent to Africa in a subordinate capacity, and
  proceeded without delay to initiate his war of flying columns. He won his
  first victory on the 7th of July 1836, made a brilliant campaign of six
  weeks' duration, and returned home with the rank of lieutenant-general.
  In the following year he signed the treaty of Tafna (June 1st, 1837),
  with Abd-el-Kader, an act which, though justified by the military and
  political situation, led to a renewal of the attacks upon him in the
  chamber, to the refutation of which Bugeaud devoted himself in 1839.
  Finally, in 1840, he was nominated governor-general of Algeria, and early
  in 1841 he put into force his system of flying columns. His swiftness and
  energy drove back the forces of Abd-el-Kader from place to place, while
  the devotion of the rank and file to "Père Bugeaud" enabled him to carry
  all before him in action. In 1842 he secured the French positions by
  undertaking the construction of roads. In 1843 Bugeaud was made marshal
  of France, and in this and the following year he continued his operations
  with unvarying success. His great victory of Isly on the 14th of August
  1844 won for him the title of duke. In 1845, however, he had to take the
  field again in consequence of the disaster of Sidi Brahim (22nd of
  September 1845), and up to his final retirement from Algeria (July 1846)
  he was almost constantly employed in the field. His resignation was due
  to differences with the home government on the question of the future
  government of the province. Amidst his other activities he had found time
  to study the agricultural characteristics of the conquered country, and
  under his régime the number of French colonists had grown from 17,000 to
  100,000. In 1848 the marshal was in Paris during the revolution, but his
  orders prevented him from acting effectually to suppress it. He was
  asked, but eventually refused, to be a candidate for the presidency in
  opposition to Louis Napoleon. His last public service was the command of
  the army of the Alps, formed in 1848-1849 to observe events in Italy. He
  died in Paris on the 10th of June 1849.</p>
      <p>Bugeaud's writings were numerous, including his <i>Œuvres
  militaires</i>, collected by Weil (Paris, 1883), many official reports on
  Algeria and the war there, and some works on economics and political
  science. See Comte d'Ideville, <i>Le Maréchal Bugeaud</i> (Paris,
  1881-1882).</p>
   </body>
</topic>