<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25579">
   <title>BRUNEI</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNEI,--> a state situated in the north-west of Borneo. It has
  been so diminished in area since the beginning of the 19th century as to
  have become in comparison with the other states of Borneo territorially
  insignificant. It formerly included the whole of northern Borneo and
  southern Palawan, and stretched down the west coast as far as Sambas.
  What remains of this once powerful sultanate is a triangular-shaped
  territory, the base of the triangle being represented by 80 m. of
  coast-line, and the two sides by the frontiers of Sarawak. The area is
  calculated to be about 1700 sq. m. This great reduction of the extent of
  the territory has been brought about by the cession on successive
  occasions of strips of territory to Sarawak and to the British North
  Borneo Company on condition of annual payments of money. In 1888 the
  state was placed under British protection. On the 2nd of January 1906 a
  treaty was made whereby the sultan of Brunei agreed to hand over the
  general administration of his state to a British resident. The sultan
  Mahommed Jomal-ul-alam, born in 1889, succeeded his father in May 1906.
  He receives an allowance of 12,000 dollars a year from state funds, and
  his two principal ministers receive allowances of 6000 dollars a year
  each. The interior people have for centuries been subject to petty
  oppression, and there is too much of the old spirit left among the Malays
  to avoid acrimonious dispute and rebellion.</p>
      <p>The bulk of the inhabitants, who consist of Malays, Kadayans, Orang
  Bukits and a few Muruts, are to be found in and about the
  capital—also called Brunei—the population of the city being
  estimated at about 15,000, and the population of the whole territory
  being about 25,000. The city is prettily situated on the river, with a
  background of cleared hills, and in the distance heights clothed with
  magnificent forest. The dwelling-houses are built over the river on
  slender piles obtained from the Nibong palm which resists the action of
  the water for several years. Though there are practically no exports and
  imports, there is a certain amount of inland commerce, the Brunei Malay
  usually earning a living by trading with the interior tribes of Sarawak
  and British North Borneo. Some of them are skilled workers of brass, and
  the Brunei women make very beautiful cloth, interwoven and embroidered
  with gold thread. Sago is worked in the important river-valleys of the
  Tutong and the Balait, but only a small quantity of rice is
  cultivated.</p>
      <p>The history of this ancient and decaying sultanate is of some
  interest. Brunei, or, as it is called by the natives Bruni or
  Dar-ul-Salam (city of peace), possesses a historic tablet of stone upon
  which, in <ph outputclass="scac">A.H.</ph> 1221 (1804), was engraved in
  Malay characters the genealogy of the sovereigns who have ruled over the
  country. The engraving was the work of Datu Imaum Yakub, the high priest
  at the time, who received the genealogy from the lips of Merhoum Bongsu,
  otherwise Sultan Muadin, and Sultan Kemal-Udin, who ordered this record
  of their forefathers to be written. This stone tablet now stands on the
  tomb of Sultan Mahommed Jemal-ul-Alam at the foot of Panggal hill, in the
  city of Brunei. The Selesilah, or book of descent, is kept in the palace
  by the sultan. The other heirlooms, which are also kept in the sultan's
  palace, and which descend to each sultan in turn, are the "Nobab Nagara"
  (two royal drums) from Johore and Menang-Kabau, and the "Gunta Alamat"
  (bells), the gift of Sultan Bahkei of Johore or Malacca. The first sultan
  of Brunei was Alak-ber-Tata, who was probably of Bisaya stock, and
  governed the country before the introduction of Islam, in the 15th
  century. He assumed the name of Mahommed on his conversion to Islam,
  which was brought about during a visit to the Malay peninsula. Brunei, at
  this time, was a dependency of Majapahit (Java), and paid a yearly
  tribute of a jar of areca juice obtained from the young green nuts of the
  areca palm, and of no monetary value. The Hindu kingdom of Menjapahit was
  destroyed by the Mahommedans in 1478, and Brunei is mentioned in the
  history of Java as one of the countries conquered by Adaya Mingrat, the
  general of Angka Wijaya. Sultan Mahommed's only child was a daughter. His
  brother Akhmed married the daughter of Ong Chum Ping, a Chinese officer
  said to have been sent by his emperor to obtain a jewel from Mount
  Kinabalu in North Borneo, and was the successor of Sultan Mahommed in the
  sovereignty of Brunei. He was succeeded by Sultan Berkat, an Arab sherif
  of high rank, from the country of Taif in Arabia, who had married Sultan
  Akhmed's only child. Sultan Berkat built a mosque and enforced Mahommedan
  law, and with the assistance of the Chinese built the stone wall, which
  is still in existence between the islands of Kaya Orang and Chermin, by
  sinking forty junks filled with rock across the mouth of the Brunei
  river. This work was completed before the arrival of Pigafetta in 1521.
  In the reign of Sultan Bulkeiah Magellan's squadron anchored off the
  mouth of Brunei river in August 1521, and Pigafetta makes mention of the
  splendid court and the imperial magnificence of the Borneo capital.
  Sultan Bulkeiah was otherwise known as Nakoda Ragam; he was the greatest
  warrior of Brunei and made military expeditions to Java, Malacca, Luzon
  and all the coasts of Borneo. His tomb, which is handsomely built of
  stone, is still to be seen in Brunei, and is constantly visited by
  Malays, who leave money and various articles on the tomb as offerings to
  his memory. Others, again, come and take away anything they can find,
  which they keep as charms and mementoes. The Spaniards captured Brunei in
  1580, the reigning sultan and his court retiring to Suai in the Baram
  district. The invaders were compelled to evacuate the place, however, in
  consequence of the heavy losses they sustained in the numerous attempts
  made for its recovery. The golden age of Brunei was nevertheless at an
  end, and there is little more of importance to record. Disputed
  successions and civil war, maladministration and the untrustworthiness of
  the Malay character, caused a steady decline in prosperity. The East
  India Company started a factory in the town in the 18th century, but
  commerce had already decayed and the establishment was abandoned. In the
  early part of the 19th centuiy Brunei was but <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page682">[v.04 p.0682]</ph>a resort for
  pirates and a market for the slave trade. During the 'forties Admiral
  (then Captain) Keppel and other officers of the British navy suppressed
  piracy in the neighbourhood. Sarawak was handed over to Raja Brooke, and,
  after the capture and temporary occupation of Brunei by Sir Thomas
  Cochrane, Labuan was ceded to the British empire. From this island it was
  possible to exercise a certain control over the townspeople, and a consul
  was stationed there to watch affairs. Nowadays the political consequence
  of Brunei largely arises from the existence there of valuable seams of
  coal, leased to the Sarawak government.</p>
      <p>(C. H.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>