<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e21305">
   <title>BRONGNIART, ALEXANDRE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRONGNIART, ALEXANDRE--> (1770-1847), French mineralogist and
  geologist, son of the eminent architect who designed the Bourse and other
  public buildings of Paris, was born in that city on the 5th of February
  1770. At an early age he studied chemistry, under Lavoisier, and after
  passing through the École des Mines he took honours at the École de
  Médecine; subsequently he joined the army of the Pyrenees as
  <i>pharmacien</i>; but having committed some slight political offence, he
  was thrown into prison and detained there for some time. Soon after his
  release he was appointed professor of natural history in the Collège des
  Quatre Nations. In 1800 he was made director of the Sèvres porcelain
  factory, a post which he retained to his death, and in which he achieved
  his greatest work. In his hands Sèvres became the leading porcelain
  factory in Europe, and the researches of an able band of assistants
  enabled him to lay the foundations of ceramic chemistry. In addition to
  his work at Sèvres, quite enough to engross the entire energy of any
  ordinary man, he continued his more purely scientific work. He succeeded
  Haüy as professor of mineralogy in the Museum of Natural History; but he
  did not confine himself to mineralogy, for it is to him that we owe the
  division of Reptiles into the four orders of Saurians, Batrachians,
  Chelonians and Ophidians. Fossil as well as living animals engaged his
  attention, and in his studies of the strata around Paris he was
  instrumental in establishing the Tertiary formations. In 1816 he was
  elected to the Academy; and in the following year he visited the Alps of
  Switzerland and Italy, and afterwards Sweden and Norway. The result of
  his observations was published from time to time in the <i>Journal des
  Mines</i> and other scientific journals. Wide as was the range of his
  interests his most famous work was accomplished at Sèvres, and his most
  enduring monument is his classic <i>Traité des arts céramiques</i>
  (1844). He died in Paris on the 7th of October 1847.</p>
      <p>His other principal works are :—<i>Traité élémentaire de
  minéralogie, avec des applications aux arts</i> (2 vols., Paris, 1807);
  <i>Histoire naturelle des crustacés fossiles</i> (Paris, 1822);
  <i>Classification et caractères minéralogiques des roches homogènes et
  hétérogènes</i> (Paris, 1827); the <i>Tableau des terrains qui composent
  l'écorce du globe, ou Essai sur la structure de la partie connue de la
  terre</i> (Paris, 1829); and the <i>Traité des arts céramiques</i>
  (1844). Brongniart was also the coadjutor of Cuvier in the admirable
  <i>Essai sur la géographie minéralogique des environs de Paris</i>
  (Paris, 1811); originally published in <i>Ann. Mus. Hist. Nat.</i>
  (Paris, xi. 1808).</p>
   </body>
</topic>