<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e26247">
   <title>BRUNO</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNO--> (<ph outputclass="sc">Brun, Bruns</ph>) <b>OF QUERFURT,
  SAINT</b> (c. 975-1009), German missionary bishop and martyr, belonged to
  the family of the lords of Querfurt in Saxony. He was educated at the
  famous cathedral school at Magdeburg, and at the age of twenty was
  attached to the clerical household of the emperor Otto III. In 996 he
  accompanied the emperor to Rome, and there gave up his post and entered
  the monastery of SS. Alexius and Bonifacius on the Aventine, taking "in
  religion" the name of Bonifacius. When the news reached Rome of the
  martyrdom of Adalbert, bishop of Prague (997), Bruno determined to take
  his place, and in 1004, after being consecrated by the pope as archbishop
  of the eastern heathen, he set out for Germany to seek aid of the emperor
  Henry II. The emperor, however, being at war with Boleslaus of Poland,
  opposed his enterprise, and he went first to the court of St Stephen of
  Hungary, and, finding but slight encouragement there, to that of the
  grand prince Vladimir at Kiev. He made no effort to win over Vladimir to
  the Roman obedience, but devoted himself to the conversion of the pagan
  Pechenegs who inhabited the country between the Don and the Danube. In
  this he was so far successful that they made peace with the grand prince
  and were for a while nominally Christians. In 1008 Bruno went to the
  court of Boleslaus, and, after a vain effort to persuade the emperor to
  end the war between Germans and Poles, determined at all hazards to
  proceed with his mission to the Prussians. With eighteen companions he
  set out; but on the borders of the Russian (Lithuanian) country he and
  all his company were massacred by the heathens (February 14, 1009).</p>
      <p>During his stay in Hungary (1004) Bruno wrote a life of St Adalbert,
  the best of the three extant biographies of the saint (in Pertz, <i>Mon.
  Germ. Hist. Scriptores</i>, iv. pp. 577, 596-612), described by A.
  Potthast (<i>Bibliotheca hist. med. aev.</i>) as "in the highest degree
  attractive both in manner and matter."</p>
      <p>A life of St Bruno was written by Dietmar, bishop of Merseburg
  (976-1019). This, with additions from the life of St Romuald, is
  published in the Bollandist <i>Acta Sanctorum</i> (June 19), vi. 1, pp.
  223-225. See further U. Chevalier, <i>Répertoire des sources historiques,
  Bio-Bibliographie</i> (Paris, 1904), s.v. "Brunon de Querfurt."</p>
   </body>
</topic>