<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22946">
   <title>BROUGHAM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROUGHAM--> <ph outputclass="scac">AND</ph> 
         <b>VAUX, HENRY PETER
  BROUGHAM,</b> 
         <ph outputclass="sc">1st Baron</ph> (1778-1868), lord
  chancellor of England, was born at Edinburgh on the 19th of September
  1778. He was the eldest son of Henry Brougham and Eleanora, daughter of
  the Rev. James Syme. In his later years he was wont to trace his paternal
  descent to Uduardus de Broham, in the reign of Henry II., but no real
  connexion has been established between the ancient lords of Brougham
  castle, whose inheritance passed by marriage from the Viponts into the
  family of the De Cliffords, and the Broughams of Scales Hall, from whom
  the chancellor was really descended. Entering the high school of
  Edinburgh when barely seven, he left, having risen to be head of the
  school, in 1791. He entered the university of Edinburgh in 1792, and
  devoted himself chiefly to the study of natural science and mathematics,
  contributing in 1795 a paper to the Royal Society on some new phenomenon
  of light and colours, which was printed in the <i>Transactions</i> of
  that body. A paper on porisms was published in the same manner in 1798,
  and in 1803 his scientific <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page653">[v.04 p.0653]</ph>reputation was so far established
  that he was elected F.R.S., But in spite of his taste for mathematical
  reasoning, Brougham's mind was not an accurate or exact one; and his
  pursuit of physical science was rather a favourite recreation than a
  solid advantage to him.</p>
      <p>For two years of his university career he had attended lectures in
  civil law, and having adopted law as a profession he was admitted to the
  faculty of advocates in 1800. It does not appear that he ever held a
  brief in the court of session, but he went a circuit or two, where he
  defended or prosecuted a few prisoners, and played a series of tricks on
  the presiding judge, Lord Eskgrove, which almost drove that learned
  person to distraction. The Scottish bar, however, as he soon perceived,
  offered no field sufficiently ample for his talents and his ambition. He
  resolved to go to London, where he had already appeared as junior counsel
  in a Scottish appeal to the House of Lords. In 1803 he entered at
  Lincoln's Inn, and in 1808 he was called to the English bar. In the
  meantime he had turned to literature as a means of subsistence. When in
  1802 the <i>Edinburgh Review</i> was founded by the young and aspiring
  lights of the northern metropolis, Brougham was the most ready, the most
  versatile and the most satirical of all its contributors. To the first
  twenty numbers he contributed eighty articles, wandering through every
  imaginable subject,—science, politics, colonial policy, literature,
  poetry, surgery, mathematics and the fine arts. The prodigious success of
  the <i>Review</i>, and the power he was known to wield in it, made him a
  man of mark from his first arrival in London. He obtained the friendship
  of Lord Grey and the leading Whig politicians. His wit and gaiety made
  him an ornament of society, and he sought to extend his literary and
  political reputation by the publication of an elaborate work on the
  colonial policy of the empire. In 1806, Fox being then in office, he was
  appointed secretary to a mission of Lord Rosslyn and Lord St Vincent to
  the court of Lisbon, with a view to counteract the anticipated French
  invasion of Portugal. The mission lasted two or three months; Brougham
  came home out of humour and out of pocket; and meantime the death of Fox
  put an end to the hopes of the Whigs.</p>
      <p>Brougham was disappointed by the abrupt fall of the ministry, and
  piqued that his Whig friends had not provided him with a seat in
  parliament. Nevertheless, he exerted his pen with prodigious activity
  during the election of 1809; and Lord Holland declared that he had filled
  the booksellers' shops with articles and pamphlets. The result was small.
  No seat was placed at his disposal, and he was too poor to contest a
  borough. He was fortunate at this time to ally himself with the movement
  for the abolition of the slave-trade, and he remained through life not
  only faithful, but passionately attached to the cause. Indeed, one of the
  first measures he carried in the House of Commons was a bill to make the
  slave-trade felony, and he had the happiness, as chancellor of England,
  to take a part in the final measure of negro emancipation throughout the
  colonies.</p>
      <p>Previous to his entering on practice at the English bar, Brougham had
  acquired some knowledge of international law, and some experience of the
  prize courts. This circumstance probably led to his being retained as
  counsel for the Liverpool merchants who had petitioned both Houses of
  Parliament against the Orders in Council. Brougham conducted the
  lengthened inquiry which took place at the bar of the House, and he
  displayed on this occasion a mastery over the principles of political
  economy and international law which at that time was rare. Nevertheless,
  he was unsuccessful, and it was not until 1812, when he was himself in
  parliament, that he resumed his attack on the Orders in Council, and
  ultimately conquered. It was considered inexpedient and impossible that a
  man so gifted, and so popular as Brougham had now become, should remain
  out of parliament, and by the influence of Lord Holland the duke of
  Bedford was induced to return him to the House of Commons for the borough
  of Camelford. He took his seat early in 1810, having made a vow that he
  would not open his mouth for a month. The vow was kept, but kept for that
  month only. He spoke in March in condemnation of the conduct of Lord
  Chatham at Walcheren, and he went on speaking for the rest of his life.
  In four months, such was the position he had acquired in the House that
  he was regarded as a candidate for the leadership of the Liberal party,
  then in the feeble hands of George Ponsonby. However, the Tories
  continued in power. Parliament was dissolved. Camelford passed into other
  hands. Brougham was induced to stand for Liverpool, with Thomas Creevey
  against Canning and General Gascoyne. The Liberals were defeated by a
  large majority, and what made the sting of defeat more keen was that
  Creevey retained his old seat for Thetford, while Brougham was left out
  in the cold.</p>
      <p>He remained out of parliament during the four eventful years from 1812
  to 1816, which witnessed the termination of the war, and he did not
  conceal his resentment against the Whigs. But in the years he spent out
  of parliament occurrences took place which gave ample employment to his
  bustling activity, and led the way to one of the most important passages
  of his life. He had been introduced in 1809 to the princess of Wales
  (afterwards Queen Caroline). But it was not till 1812 that the princess
  consulted him on her private affairs, after the rupture between the
  prince regent and the Whigs had become more decided. From that time,
  Brougham, in conjunction with Samuel Whitbread, became one of the
  princess's chief advisers; he was attached to her service, not so much
  from any great liking or respect for herself, as from an indignant sense
  of the wrongs and insults inflicted upon her by her husband. Brougham
  strongly opposed her departure from England in 1814, as well as her
  return in 1820 on the accession of George IV.</p>
      <p>In 1816 he had again been returned to parliament for Winchelsea, a
  borough of the earl of Darlington, and he instantly resumed a commanding
  position in the House of Commons. He succeeded in defeating the
  continuance of the income-tax; he distinguished himself as an advocate
  for the education of the people; and on the death of Romilly he took up
  with ardour the great work of the reform of the law. Nothing exasperated
  the Tory party more than the select committee which sat, with Brougham in
  the chair, in 1816 and the three following years, to investigate the
  state of education of the poor in the metropolis. But he was as far as
  ever from obtaining the leadership of the party to which he aspired.
  Indeed, as was pointed out by Lord Lansdowne in 1817, the opposition had
  no recognized efficient leaders; their warfare was carried on in separate
  courses, indulging their own tastes and tempers, without combined action.
  Nor was Brougham much more successful at the bar. The death of George
  III. suddenly changed this state of things. Queen Caroline at once, in
  April 1820, appointed Brougham her attorney-general, and Denman her
  solicitor-general; and they immediately took their rank in court
  accordingly; this was indeed the sole act of royal authority on the part
  of the unhappy queen. In July Queen Caroline came from St Omer to
  England; ministers sent down to both Houses of Parliament the secret
  evidence which they had long been collecting against her; and a bill was
  brought into the House of Lords for the deposition of the queen, and the
  dissolution of the king's marriage. The defence of the queen was
  conducted by Brougham, assisted by Denman, Lushington and Wilde, with
  equal courage and ability. His conduct of the defence was most able, and
  he wound up the proceedings with a speech of extraordinary power and
  effect. The peroration was said to have been written and rewritten by him
  seventeen times. At moments of great excitement such declamation may be
  of value, and in 1820 it was both heard and read with enthusiasm. But to
  the calmer judgment of later generations this celebrated oration seems
  turgid and overstrained. Such immense popular sympathy prevailed on the
  queen's behalf, that the ministry did not proceed with the bill in the
  Commons, and the result was a virtual triumph for the queen.</p>
      <p>This victory over the court and the ministry raised Henry Brougham at
  once to the pinnacle of fame. He shared the triumph of the queen. His
  portrait was in every shop window. A piece of plate was presented to him,
  paid for by a penny subscription of peasants and mechanics. He refused to
  accept a sum of £4000 which the queen herself placed at his disposal;
  <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page654">[v.04
  p.0654]</ph>he took no more than the usual fees of counsel, while his
  salary as Her Majesty's attorney-general remained unpaid, until it was
  discharged by the treasury after her death. But from that moment his
  fortune was made at the bar. His practice on the northern circuit
  quintupled. One of his finest speeches was a defence of a Durham
  newspaper which had attacked the clergy for refusing to allow the bells
  of churches to be tolled on the queen's death; and by the admission of
  Lord Campbell, a rival advocate and an unfriendly critic, he rose
  suddenly to a position unexampled in the profession. The meanness of
  George IV. and of Lord Eldon refused him the silk gown to which his
  position at the bar entitled him, and for some years he led the circuit
  as an outer barrister, to the great loss of the senior members of the
  circuit, who could only be employed against him. His practice rose to
  about £7000 a year, but it was again falling off before he became
  chancellor.</p>
      <p>It may here be mentioned that in 1825 the first steps were taken,
  under the auspices of Brougham, for the establishment of a university in
  London, absolutely free from all religious or sectarian distinctions. In
  1827 he contributed to found the "Society for the Diffusion of Useful
  Knowledge"—an association which gave an immense impulse to sound
  popular literature. Its first publication was an essay on the "Pleasures
  and Advantages of Science" written by himself. In the following year
  (1828) he delivered his great speech on law reform, which lasted six
  hours, in a thin and exhausted House,—a marvellous effort,
  embracing every part of the existing system of judicature.</p>
      <p>The death of Canning, the failure of Lord Goderich, and the accession
  of the duke of Wellington to power, again changed the aspect of affairs.
  The progress of the movement for parliamentary reform had numbered the
  days of the Tory government. At the general election of 1830 the county
  of York spontaneously returned Brougham to the new House of Commons as
  their representative. The parliament met in November. Brougham's first
  act was to move for leave to bring in a bill to amend the representation
  of the people; but before the debate came on the government was defeated
  on another question; the duke resigned, and Earl Grey was commanded by
  William IV. to form an administration.</p>
      <p>Amongst the difficulties of the new premier and the Whig party were
  the position and attitude of Brougham. He was not the leader of any
  party, and had no personal following in the House of Commons. Moreover,
  he himself had repeatedly declared that nothing would induce him to
  exchange his position as an independent member of parliament for any
  office, however great. On the day following the resignation of the Tory
  government, he reluctantly consented to postpone for one week his motion
  on parliamentary reform. The attorney-generalship was offered to him and
  indignantly refused. He himself affirms that he desired to be master of
  the rolls, which would have left him free to sit in the House of Commons.
  But this was positively interdicted by the king, and objected to by Lord
  Althorp, who declared that he could not undertake to lead the House with
  so insubordinate a follower behind him. But as it was impossible to leave
  Brougham out of the ministry, it was determined to offer him the
  chancellorship. Brougham himself hesitated, or affected to hesitate, but
  finally yielded to the representations of Lord Grey and Lord Althorp. On
  the 22nd of November the great seal was delivered to him by the king, and
  he was raised to the peerage as Baron Brougham and Vaux. His
  chancellorship lasted exactly four years.</p>
      <p>Lord Brougham took a most active and prominent part in all the great
  measures promoted by Grey's government, and the passing of the Reform
  Bill was due in a great measure to the vigour with which he defended it.
  But success developed traits which had hitherto been kept in the
  background. His manner became dictatorial and he exhibited a restless
  eccentricity, and a passion for interfering with every department of
  state, which alarmed the king. By his insatiable activity he had
  contrived to monopolize the authority and popularity of the government,
  and notwithstanding the immense majority by which it was supported in the
  reformed parliament, a crisis was not long in arriving. Lord Grey
  resigned, but very much by Brougham's exertions the cabinet was
  reconstructed under Lord Melbourne, and he appeared to think that his own
  influence in it would be increased. But the irritability of his temper
  and the egotism of his character made it impossible for his colleagues to
  work with him, and the extreme mental excitement under which he laboured
  at this time culminated during a journey to Scotland in a behaviour so
  extravagant, that it gave the final stroke to the confidence of the king.
  At Lancaster he joined the bar-mess, and spent the night in an orgy. In a
  country house he lost the great seal, and found it again in a game of
  blindman's-buff. At Edinburgh, in spite of the coldness which had sprung
  up between himself and the Grey family, he was present at a banquet given
  to the late premier, and delivered a harangue on his own services and his
  public virtue. All this time he continued to correspond with the king in
  a strain which created the utmost irritation and amazement at
  Windsor.</p>
      <p>Shortly after the meeting of parliament in November the king dismissed
  his ministers. The chancellor, who had dined at Holland House, called on
  Lord Melbourne on his way home, and learned the intelligence. Melbourne
  made him promise that he would keep it a secret until the morrow, but the
  moment he quitted the ex-premier he sent a paragraph to <i>The Times</i>
  relating the occurrence, and adding that "the queen had done it all."
  That statement, which was totally unfounded, was the last act of his
  official life. The Peel ministry, prematurely and rashly summoned to
  power, was of no long duration, and Brougham naturally took an active
  part in overthrowing it. Lord Melbourne was called upon in April 1835 to
  reconstruct the Whig government with his former colleagues. But,
  formidable as he might be as an opponent, the Whigs had learned by
  experience that Brougham was even more dangerous to them as an ally, and
  with one accord they resolved that he should not hold the great seal or
  any other office. The great seal was put in commission, to divert for a
  time his resentment, and leave him, if he chose, to entertain hopes of
  recovering it. These hopes, however, were soon dissipated; and although
  the late chancellor assumed an independent position in the House of
  Lords, and even affected to protect the government, his resentment
  against his "noble friends" soon broke out with uncontrolled vehemence.
  Throughout the session of 1835 his activity was undiminished. Bills for
  every imaginable purpose were thrown by him on the table of the House,
  and it stands recorded in Hansard that he made no less than 221 reported
  speeches in parliament in that year. But in the course of the vacation a
  heavier blow was struck: Lord Cottenham was made lord chancellor.
  Brougham's daring and arrogant spirit sank for a time under the shock,
  and during the year 1836 he never spoke in parliament. Among the numerous
  expedients resorted to in order to keep his name before the public, was a
  false report of his death by a carriage accident, sent up from
  Westmorland in 1839. He was accused, with great probability, of being
  himself the author of the report. Such credence did it obtain that all
  the newspapers of October 22, excepting <i>The Times</i>, had obituary
  notices. However, for more than thirty years after his fall he continued
  to take an active part in the judicial business of the House of Lords,
  and in its debates; but it would have been better for his reputation if
  he had died earlier. His reappearance in parliament on the accession of
  Queen Victoria was marked by sneers at the court, and violent attacks on
  the Whigs for their loyal and enthusiastic attachment to their young
  sovereign; and upon the outbreak of the insurrection in Canada, and the
  miscarriage of Lord Durham's mission, he overwhelmed his former
  colleagues, and especially Lord Glenelg, with a torrent of invective and
  sarcasm, equal in point of oratory to the greatest of his earlier
  speeches. Indeed, without avowedly relinquishing his political
  principles, Brougham estranged himself from the whole party by which
  those principles were defended; and his conduct in general during the
  years following his loss of office revealed his character in a very
  unfavourable light. He continued, however, to render judicial services in
  the privy council, and the House of Lords. The privy council, especially
  when hearing appeals from the colonies, India, and the courts maritime
  and ecclesiastical was his favourite tribunal; its vast range of <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page655">[v.04
  p.0655]</ph>jurisdiction, varied by questions of foreign and
  international law, suited his discursive genius. He had remodelled the
  judicial committee in 1833, and it still remains one of the most useful
  of his creations.</p>
      <p>In the year 1860 a second patent was conferred upon him by Queen
  Victoria, with a reversion of his peerage to his youngest brother,
  William Brougham (d. 1886). The preamble of this patent stated that this
  unusual mark of honour was conferred upon him by the crown as an
  acknowledgment of the great services he had rendered, more especially in
  promoting the abolition of slavery, and the emancipation of the negro
  race. The peerage was thus perpetuated in a junior branch of the family,
  Lord Brougham himself being without an heir. He had married in 1821 Mrs
  Spalding (d. 1865), daughter of Thomas Eden, and had two daughters, the
  survivor of whom died in 1839. Brougham's last days were passed at
  Cannes, in the south of France. An accident having attracted his
  attention to the spot about the year 1838, when it was little more than a
  fishing village on a picturesque coast, he bought there a tract of land
  and built on it. His choice and his example made it the sanatorium of
  Europe. He died there on the 7th of May 1868, in the ninetieth year of
  his age.</p>
      <p>The verdict of the time has proved that there was nothing of
  permanence, and little of originality in the prodigious efforts of
  Brougham's genius. He filled the office of chancellor during times
  burning with excitement, and he himself embodied and expressed the
  fervour of the times. He affected at first to treat the business of the
  court of chancery as a light affair, though in truth he had to work hard
  to master the principles of equity, of which he had no experience. His
  manner in court was desultory and dictatorial. Sometimes he would crouch
  in his chair, muffled in his wig and robes, like a man asleep; at other
  times he would burst into restless activity, writing letters, working
  problems, interrupting counsel. But upon the whole Brougham was a just
  and able judge, though few of his decisions are cited as landmarks of the
  law.</p>
      <p>As a parliamentary figure Brougham's personality excited for many
  years an immense amount of public interest, now somewhat hard to
  comprehend. His boundless command of language, his animal spirits and
  social powers, his audacity and well-stored memory enabled him to
  dominate the situation. His striking and almost grotesque personal
  appearance, added to the effect of his voice and manner—a tall
  disjointed frame, with strong bony limbs and hands, that seemed to
  interpret the power of his address; strange angular motions of the arms;
  the incessant jerk of his harsh but expressive features; the modulations
  of his voice, now thundering in the loudest tones of indignation, now
  subdued to a whisper—all contributed to give him the magical
  influence such as is excited by a great actor. But his eccentricity rose
  at times to the verge of insanity; and with all his powers he lacked the
  moral elevation which inspires confidence and wins respect.</p>
      <p>The activity of Lord Brougham's pen was only second to the volubility
  of his tongue. He carried on a vast and incessant correspondence of
  incredible extent. For thirty years he contributed largely to the
  <i>Edinburgh Review</i>, and he continued to write in that journal even
  after he held the great seal. The best of his writings, entitled
  "Sketches of the Statesmen of the time of George III.", first appeared in
  the <i>Review</i>. These were followed by the "Lives of Men of Letters
  and Science," of the same period. Later in life he edited Paley's
  <i>Natural Theology</i>; and he published a work on political philosophy,
  besides innumerable pamphlets and letters to public men on the events of
  the day. He published an incorrect translation of Demosthenes' <i>De
  Corona</i>. A novel entitled <i>Albert Lunel</i> was attributed to him. A
  fragment of the <i>History of England under the House of Lancaster</i>
  employed his retirement. In 1838 was published an edition of his speeches
  in four volumes, elaborately corrected by himself. The last of his works
  was his posthumous <i>Autobiography</i>. Ambitious as he was of literary
  fame, and jealous of the success of other authors, he has failed to
  obtain any lasting place in English literature. His style was slovenly,
  involved and incorrect; and his composition bore marks of haste and
  carelessness, and nowhere shows any genuine originality of thought. The
  collected edition of his works and speeches carefully revised by himself
  (Edinburgh, 1857 and 1872) is the best. His <i>Autobiography</i> is of
  some value from the original letters with which it is interspersed. But
  Lord Brougham's memory was so much impaired when he began to write his
  recollections that no reliance can be placed on his statements, and the
  work abounds in manifest errors. Nor was his regard for truth at any time
  unimpeachable, and the accounts which he gave of more than one
  transaction in which he played a prominent part were found on
  investigation to be unfounded.</p>
      <p>The best modern account of Brougham is J.B. Atlay's, in his
  <i>Victorian Chancellors</i> (1906); Lord Campbell's, in <i>Lives of the
  Chancellors</i>, is spiteful, and by an unfriendly though well-informed
  critic; the Rev. W. Hunt's judicious and careful biography in the
  <i>D.N.B.</i> is somewhat lacking in colour; Henry Reeve's article in the
  9th ed. of the <i>Ency. Brit.</i>, which is frequently drawn upon above,
  now requires a good many corrections in points of fact and perspective,
  but gives a brilliant picture by an appreciative critic, much "behind the
  scenes." See also references in the <i>Greville Memoirs</i> and
  <i>Creevey Papers</i>; S. Walpole, <i>History of England</i> (1890); J.A.
  Roebuck, <i>History of the Whig Ministry</i> (1852); Lord Holland,
  <i>Memoirs of the Whig Party</i> (1854); <i>Brougham and his Early
  Friends: Letters to James Loch</i>, 1798-1809 (3 vols., London, 1908,
  privately printed).</p>
   </body>
</topic>