<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e27085">
   <title>BRYANT, WILLIAM CULLEN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRYANT, WILLIAM CULLEN--> (1794-1878), American poet and
  journalist, was born at Cummington, a farming village in the Hampshire
  hills of western Massachusetts, on the 3rd of November 1794. He was the
  second son of Peter Bryant, a physician and surgeon of no mean
  scholarship, refined in all his tastes, and a public-spirited citizen.
  Peter Bryant was the great-grandson of Stephen Bryant, an English Puritan
  emigrant to Massachusetts Bay about the year 1632. The poet's mother,
  Sarah Snell, was a descendant of "Mayflower" pilgrims. He was born in the
  log farmhouse built by his father two years before, at the edge of the
  pioneer settlement among those boundless forests, the deep stamp of whose
  beauty and majesty he carried on his own mind and reprinted upon the
  emotions of others throughout a long life spent mainly amid the
  activities of his country's growing metropolis. By parentage, by
  religious and political faith, and by hardness of fortune, the earliest
  of important American poets was appointed to a life typical of the first
  century of American national existence, and of the strongest single
  racial element by which that nation's social order has been moulded and
  promoted. Rated by the amount of time given to school books and college
  classes, Bryant's early education was limited. After the village school
  he received a year of exceptionally good training in Latin under his
  mother's brother, the Rev. Dr Thomas Snell, of Brookfield, followed by a
  year of Greek under the Rev. Moses Hallock, of Plainfield, and at sixteen
  entered the sophomore class of Williams College. Here he was an apt and
  diligent student through two sessions, and then, owing to the straitness
  of his father's means, he withdrew without graduating, and studied
  classics and mathematics for a year, in the vain hope that his father
  might yet be able to send him to Yale College. But the length of his
  school and college days would be a very misleading measure of his
  training. He was endowed by nature with many of those traits which it is
  often only the final triumph of books and institutional regimen to
  establish in character, and a double impulse toward scholarship and
  citizenship showed its ruling influence with a precocity and an ardour
  which gave every day of systematic schooling many times its ordinary
  value. It is his own word that, two months after beginning with the Greek
  alphabet, he had read the New Testament through. On abandoning his hope
  to enter Yale, the poet turned to and pursued, under private guidance at
  Worthington and at Bridgewater, the study of law. At twenty-one he was
  admitted to the bar, opened an office in Plainfield, presently withdrew
  from there, and at Great Barrington settled for nine years in the
  attorney's calling, with an aversion for it which he never lost. His
  first book of verse, <i>The Embargo, or Sketches of the Times; A Satire
  by a Youth of thirteen</i>, had been printed at Boston in 1808.</p>
      <p>At the age of twenty-six Bryant married, at Great Barrington, Miss
  Frances Fairchild, with whom he enjoyed a happy union until her death
  nearly half a century later. In the year of his marriage he suffered the
  bereavement of his father's death. In 1825 he ventured to lay aside the
  practice of law, and removed to New York City to assume a literary
  editorship. Here for some months his fortunes were precarious, until in
  the next year he became one of the editors of the <i>Evening Post</i>. In
  the third year following, 1829, he came into undivided editorial control,
  and became also chief owner. He enjoyed his occupation, fulfilling its
  duties with an unflagging devotion to every worthy public interest till
  he died in 1878, in the month of his choice, as indicated in his
  beautiful poem entitled "June."</p>
      <p>Though Bryant's retiring and contemplative nature could not overpower
  his warm human sympathies, it yet dominated them to an extent that made
  him always, even in his journalistic capacity and in the strenuous prose
  of daily debate, a councillor rather than a leader. It was after the
  manner of the poet, the seer, that he was a patriot, standing for
  principles much more than for measures, and, with an exquisite
  correctness which belonged to every phase of his being, never prevailing
  by the accommodation of himself to inferiors in foresight, insight or
  rectitude. His vigorous and stately mind found voice in one of the most
  admirable models of journalistic style known in America. He was founder
  of a distinct school of American journalism, characterized by an equal
  fidelity and temperance, energy and dignity. Though it is as a poet that
  he most emphatically belongs to history, his verse was the expression of
  only the gentler motions of his mind; and it gathers influence, if not
  lustre, when behind it is seen a life intrepid, upright, glad, and ever
  potent for the nobler choice in all the largest affairs of his time. His
  renown as a poet antedated the appearance of his first volume by some
  four or five years. "American poetry," says Richard Henry Stoddard, "may
  be said to have commenced in 1817 with ... (Bryant's) 'Thanatopsis' and
  'Inscription for the entrance of a wood.'" "Thanatopsis," which revealed
  a voice at once as new and as old as the wilderness out of which it
  reverberated, had been written at Cummington in the poet's eighteenth
  year, and was printed in 1817 in the <i>North American Review</i>; the
  "Inscription" was written in his nineteenth, and in his twenty-first,
  while a student of law at Bridgewater, he had composed his lines "To a
  Water-fowl," whose exquisite beauty and exalted faith his own pen rarely,
  if ever, surpassed. The poet's gift for language made him a frequent
  translator, and among his works of this sort his rendering of Homer is
  the most noted and most valuable. But the muse of Bryant, at her very
  best, is always brief-spoken and an interpreter initially of his own
  spirit. Much of the charm of his poems lies in the equal purity of their
  artistic and their moral beauty. On the ethical side they are more than
  pure, they are—it may be said without derogation—Puritan. He
  never commerces with unloveliness for any loveliness that may be plucked
  out of it, and rarely or never discovers moral beauty under any sort of
  mask. As free from effeminacy as from indelicacy, his highest and his
  deepest emotions are so dominated by a perfect self-restraint that they
  never rise (or stoop) to transports. There is scarcely a distempered
  utterance in the whole body of his poetical works, scarcely one
  passionate exaggeration. He faces life with an invincible courage, an
  inextinguishable hope and heavenward trust, and the dignity of a
  benevolent will which no compulsion can break or bend. The billows of his
  soul are not waves, but hills which tempests ruffle but can never heave.
  Even when he essays to speak for spirits unlike his own—characters
  of history or conceptions of his own imagination—he never with
  signal success portrays <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page699">[v.04 p.0699]</ph>them in the bonds, however
  transient, of any overmastering passion. For merriment he has a generous
  smile, for sorrow a royal one; but the nearest he ever comes to mirth is
  in his dainty rhyme, "Robert of Lincoln," and the nearest to a wail in
  those exquisite notes of grief for the loss of his young sister, "The
  Death of the Flowers," which only draw the tear to fill it with the light
  of a perfect resignation. As a seer of large and noble contemplation, in
  whose pictures of earth and sky the presence and care of the Divine mind,
  and every tender and beautiful relation of man to his Creator and to his
  fellow, are melodiously celebrated, his rank is among the master poets of
  America, of whom he is historically the first.</p>
      <p>Bryant published volumes of <i>Poems</i> in 1821 (Cambridge) and 1832
  (New York), and many other collections were issued under his supervision,
  the last being the <i>Poetical Works</i> (New York, 1876). Among his
  volumes of verse were "The Fountain" and other poems (New York, 1842);
  <i>The White-Footed Deer and Other Poems</i> (New York, 1844); <i>Thirty
  Poems</i> (New York, 1864); and blank-verse translations of <i>The Iliad
  of Homer</i> (Boston, 1870) and of <i>The Odyssey of Homer</i> (Boston,
  1871). His <i>Poetical Works</i> and his <i>Complete Prose Writings</i>
  (New York, 1883 and 1884) were edited by Parke Godwin, who also wrote
  <i>A Biography of William Cullen Bryant, with Extracts from his private
  Correspondence</i> (New York, 1883). See also J. Grant Wilson, <i>Bryant
  and his Friends</i> (New York, 1886); John Bigelow, <i>William Cullen
  Bryant</i> (Boston, 1890), in the "American Men of Letters" series; W.A.
  Bradley, <i>Bryant</i>, in the "English Men of Letters" series (1905);
  E.C. Stedman, <i>Poets of America</i> (1885); and biographical and
  bibliographical introductions by Henry C. Sturges and Richard Henry
  Stoddard to the "Roslyn edition" of his <i>Poetical Works</i> (New York,
  1903).</p>
      <p>(G. W. <ph outputclass="sc">Ca</ph>.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>