<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e34394">
   <title>BUKHĀRĪ</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUKHĀRĪ--> [Mahommed ibn Ismā'īl
  al-Bukhārī] (810-872), Arabic author of the most generally
  accepted collection of traditions (<ph outputclass="special">
            <i>ḥadīth</i>
         </ph>) from Mahomet, was born
  at Bokhara (<i>Bukhārā</i>), of an Iranian family, in <ph outputclass="scac">A.H.</ph> 194 (<ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 810). He
  early distinguished himself in the learning of traditions by heart, and
  when, in his sixteenth year, his family made the pilgrimage to Mecca, he
  gathered additions to his store from the authorities along the route.
  Already, in his eighteenth year, he had devoted himself to the
  collecting, sifting, testing and arranging of traditions. For that
  purpose he travelled over the Moslem world, from Egypt to Samarkand, and
  learned (as the story goes) from over a thousand men three hundred
  thousand traditions, true and false. He certainly became the acknowledged
  authority on the subject, and developed a power and speed of memory <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page771">[v.04
  p.0771]</ph>which seemed miraculous, even to his contemporaries. His
  theological position was conservative and anti-rationalistic; he enjoyed
  the friendship and respect of <ph outputclass="special">Aḥmad Ibn Ḥanbal</ph>. In law, he appears to have been a
  Shāfi'ite. After sixteen years' absence he returned to Bokhara, and
  there drew up his <ph outputclass="special">
            <i>Ṣaḥīḥ</i>
         </ph>, a
  collection of 7275 tested traditions, arranged in chapters so as to
  afford bases for a complete system of jurisprudence without the use of
  speculative law, the first book of its kind (see <ph outputclass="sc">Mahommedan Law</ph>). He died in <ph outputclass="scac">A.H.</ph> 256, in banishment at Kartank, a suburb of
  Samarkand. His book has attained a quasi-canonicity in Islām, being
  treated almost like the Koran, and to his grave solemn pilgrimages are
  made, and prayers are believed to be heard there.</p>
      <p>See F. Wüstenfeld, <i>Schāfi'iten</i>, 78 ff.; M<sup>c</sup>G.
  de Slane's transl. of Ibn Khallikan, i. 594 ff.; I. Goldziher,
  <i>Mohammedanische Studien</i>, ii. 157 ff.; Nawawi, <i>Biogr. Dict.</i>
  86 ff.</p>
      <p>(<ph outputclass="sc">D. B. Ma.</ph>)</p>
   </body>
</topic>