<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e26447">
   <title>BRUNSWICK</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNSWICK,--> a village of Cumberland county, Maine, U.S.A., in
  the township of Brunswick, on the Androscoggin river, 9 m. W. of Bath,
  and 27 m. N.N.E. of Portland. Pop. of the township (1900) 6806; (1910)
  6621; of the village (1900) 5210 (1704 foreign-born); (1910) 5341.
  Brunswick is served by the Maine Central railway, and by the Lewiston,
  Brunswick &amp; Bath, and the Portland &amp; Brunswick electric railways.
  Opposite Brunswick and connected with it by a bridge is the township of
  Topsham (pop. in 1910, 2016). The village of Brunswick lies only 63 ft.
  above sea-level, shut within rather narrow bounds by hills or bluffs,
  from which good views may be obtained of the island-dotted sea and
  deeply-indented coast to the south and east and of the White Mountains to
  the west. The river falls in three successive stages for a total distance
  of 41 ft., furnishing good water-power for paper and cotton mills and
  other manufactories; the first cotton-mill in Maine was built here about
  1809. The settlement of the site of Brunswick was begun by fishermen in
  1628 and the place was called Pejepscot; in 1717 Brunswick was
  constituted a township under its present name by the Massachusetts
  general court, and in 1739 the township was regularly incorporated. The
  village was incorporated in 1836.</p>
      <p>Brunswick is best known as the seat of Bowdoin College, a small
  institution of high educational rank. There are eleven buildings on a
  campus of about 40 acres, 1 m. from the riverbank at the end of the
  principal village thoroughfare. The chapel (King Chapel, named in honour
  of William King, the first governor of Maine), built of undressed
  granite, is of Romanesque style, and has twin towers and spires rising to
  a height of 120 ft.; the interior walls are beautifully decorated with
  frescoes and mural paintings. The Walker Art Building (built as a
  memorial to Theophilus W. Walker) is of Italian Renaissance style, has
  mural decorations by John la Farge, Elihu Vedder, Abbott H. Thayer and
  Kenyon Cox, and contains a good collection of paintings and other works
  of art. Among the paintings, many of which were given by the younger
  James Bowdoin, are examples of van Dyck, Titian, Poussin and Rembrandt.
  The library building is of Gothic style, and in 1908 contained 88,000
  volumes (including the private library of the younger James Bowdoin).
  Among the other buildings are an astronomical observatory, a science
  building, a memorial hall, a gymnasium and three dormitories. The
  building of the Medical School of Maine (1820), which is a department of
  the college, is on the same campus. Bowdoin was incorporated by the
  general court of Massachusetts in 1794, but was not opened until 1802. It
  was named in honour of James Bowdoin (1726-1790), whose son was a liberal
  benefactor. The college has been maintained as a non-sectarian
  institution largely by Congregationalists, and is governed by a board of
  trustees and a board of overseers. Among the distinguished alumni have
  been Nathaniel Hawthorne, Franklin Pierce, Henry W. Longfellow, John P.
  Hale, William P. Fessenden, Melville W. Fuller, and Thomas B. Reed.</p>
   </body>
</topic>