<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e20002">
   <title>BROCKES, BARTHOLD HEINRICH</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROCKES, BARTHOLD HEINRICH--> (1680-1747), German poet, was born
  at Hamburg on the 22nd of September 1680. He studied jurisprudence at
  Halle, and after extensive travels in Italy, France and Holland, settled
  in his native town in 1704. In 1720 he was appointed a member of the
  Hamburg senate, and entrusted with several important offices. Six years
  (from 1735 to 1741) he spent as <i>Amtmann</i> (magistrate) at
  Ritzebt端tel. He died in Hamburg on the 16th of January 1747. Brockes'
  poetic works were published in a series of nine volumes under the
  fantastic title <i>Irdisches Vergn端gen in Gott</i> (1721-1748); he also
  translated Marini's <i>La Strage degli innocenti</i> (1715), Pope's
  <i>Essay on Man</i> (1740) and Thomson's <i>Seasons</i> (1745). His
  poetry has small intrinsic value, but it is symptomatic of the change
  which came over German literature at the beginning of the 18th century.
  He was one of the first German poets to substitute for the bombastic
  imitations of Marini, to which he himself had begun by contributing, a
  clear and simple diction. He was also a pioneer in directing the
  attention of his countrymen to the new poetry of nature which originated
  in England. His verses, artificial and crude as they often are, express a
  reverential attitude towards nature and a religious interpretation of
  natural phenomena which was new to German poetry and prepared the way for
  Klopstock.</p>
      <p>Brockes' autobiography was published by J.M. Lappenberg in the
  <i>Zeitschrift des Vereins f端r Hamburger Geschichte,</i> ii. pp. 167 ff.
  (1847). See also A. Brandl, <i>B. H. Brockes</i> (1878), and D.F.
  Strauss, <i>Brockes und H.S. Reimarus</i> (<i>Gesammelte Schriften</i>,
  ii.). A short selection of his poetry will be found in vol. 39 (1883) of
  K端rschner's <i>Deutsche Nationalliteratur</i>.</p>
   </body>
</topic>