<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23328">
   <title>BROWN, GEORGE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWN, GEORGE--> (1818-1880), Canadian journalist and statesman,
  was born in Edinburgh on the 29th of November 1818, and was educated in
  his native city. With his father, Peter Brown (d. 1863), he emigrated to
  New York in 1838; and in 1843 they removed to Toronto, and began the
  publication of <i>The Banner</i>, a politico-religious paper in support
  of the newly formed Free Church of Scotland. In 1844 he began,
  independently of his father, the issue of the Toronto <i>Globe</i>. This
  paper, at first weekly, became in 1853 a daily, and through the ability
  and energy of Brown, came to possess an almost tyrannical influence over
  the political opinion of Ontario. In 1851 he entered the Canadian
  parliament as member for Kent county. Though giving at first a modified
  support to the Reform government, he soon broke with it and became leader
  of the Radical or "Clear Grit" party. His attacks upon the Roman Catholic
  church and on the supposed domination in parliament of the French
  Canadian section made him very unpopular in Lower Canada, but in Upper
  Canada his power was great. Largely owing to his attacks, the Clergy
  Reserves were secularized in 1854. He championed the complete laicization
  of the schools in Ontario, but unsuccessfully, the Roman Catholic church
  maintaining its right to separate schools. He also fought for the
  representation by population of the two provinces in parliament, the Act
  of Union (1841) having granted an equal number of representatives to
  each. This principle of "Rep. by Pop." was conceded by the British North
  America Act (1867). In 1858 Brown became premier of "The Short
  Administration," which was defeated and compelled to resign after an
  existence of two days.</p>
      <p>He was one of the earliest advocates of a federation of the British
  colonies in North America, and in 1864, to accomplish this end, entered
  into a coalition with his bitter personal and political opponent, Mr
  (afterwards Sir) John A. Macdonald. <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page659">[v.04 p.0659]</ph>Largely owing
  to Brown's efforts, Federation was carried through the House, but on the
  21st of December 1865 he resigned from the Coalition government, though
  continuing to support its Federation policy, and in 1867 he was defeated
  in South Ontario and never again sat in the House. In great measure owing
  to his energy, and in spite of much concealed opposition from the
  French-Canadians, the North-West Territories were purchased by the new
  Dominion. In December 1873 he was called to the Canadian senate, and in
  1874 was appointed by the imperial government joint plenipotentiary with
  Sir Edward Thornton to negotiate a reciprocity treaty between Canada and
  the United States. The negotiations were successful, but the draft treaty
  failed to pass the United States Senate. Soon afterwards Brown refused
  the lieutenant-governorship of Ontario, and on two subsequent occasions
  the offer of knighthood, devoting himself to the <i>Globe</i> and to a
  model farm at Bow Park near Brantford. On the 25th of March 1880 he was
  shot by a discharged employé, and died on the 9th of May.</p>
      <p>His candour, enthusiasm and open tolerance of the opinions of others
  made him many warm friends and many fierce enemies. He was at his best in
  his generous protests against all privileges, social, political and
  religious, and in the self-sacrificing patriotism which enabled him to
  fling aside his personal prejudices, and so to make Federation
  possible.</p>
      <p>See J. C. Dent, <i>Canadian Portrait Gallery</i> (Toronto, 1800). The
  official <i>Life</i>, by the Hon. Alexander Mackenzie, is decidedly
  partisan. A life by John Lewis is included in the <i>Makers of Canada</i>
  series (Toronto).</p>
      <p>(W. L. G.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>