<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e33908">
   <title>BUILDERS' RITES.</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUILDERS' RITES.--> Many people familiar with the ceremonies
  attendant on the laying of foundation stones, whether ecclesiastical,
  masonic or otherwise, may be at a loss to account for the actual origin
  of the custom in placing within a cavity beneath the stone, a few coins
  of the realm, newspapers, &amp;c. The ordinary view that by such means
  particulars may be found of the event on the removal of the stone
  hereafter, may suffice as respects latter-day motives, but such memorials
  are deposited in the hope that they will never be disturbed, and so
  another reason must be found for such an ancient survival. Whilst old
  customs continue, the reasons for them are ever changing, and certainly
  this fact applies to laying foundation stones. Originally, it appears
  that living victims were selected as "a sacrifice to the gods," and
  especially to ensure the stability of the building. Grimm<xref href="#d1e33908/Footnote_351" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> remarks "It
  was often thought necessary to immure live animals and even men in the
  foundation, on which the structure was to be raised, to secure immovable
  stability." There is no lack of evidence as to this gruesome practice,
  both in savage and civilized communities. "The old pagan laid the
  foundation of his house and fortress in blood."<xref href="#d1e33908/Footnote_352" type="fn"><!--[2]--></xref> Under the walls of two round
  towers in Ireland (the only ones examined) human skeletons have been
  discovered. In the 15th century, the wall of Holsworthy church was built
  over a living human being, and when this became unlawful, images of
  living beings were substituted (<i>Folk-Lore Journal</i>, i. 23-24).</p>
      <p>The best succinct account of these rites is to be obtained in G. W.
  Speth's <i>Builders' Rites and Ceremonies</i> (1893).</p>
      <p>(W. J. H.*)</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_351"> 
            <i>Teutonic
  Mythology</i> (1883-1884), (trans. Stalleybrass).</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_352"> Baring-Gould on
  "Foundations," <i>Murray's Mag.</i> (1887).</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>