<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e26477">
   <title>BRUSA</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUSA,--> or <ph outputclass="sc">Broussa</ph> (anc. <i>Prusa</i>),
  the capital of the Brusa (Khudavendikiar) vilayet of Asia Minor, which
  includes parts of ancient Mysia, Bithynia, and Phrygia, and extends in a
  southeasterly direction from Mudania, on the Sea of Marmora, to
  Afium-Kara-Hissar on the Smyrna-Konia railway. The vilayet is one of the
  most important in Asiatic Turkey, has great mineral and agricultural
  wealth, many mineral springs, large forests, and valuable industries. It
  exports cereals, silk, cotton, opium, tobacco, olive-oil, meerschaum,
  boracite, &amp;c. The Ismid-Angora and Eskishehr-Konia railways pass
  through the province. Population of the province, 1,600,000 (Moslems,
  1,280,000; Christians, 317,000; Jews, 3000).</p>
      <p>The city stretches along the lower slopes of the Mysian Olympus or
  Kechish Dagh, occupying a position above the valley of the Nilufer
  (<i>Odrysses</i>) not unlike that of Great Malvern above the vale of the
  Severn. It is divided by ravines into three quarters, and in the centre,
  on a bold terrace of rock, stood the ancient <i>Prusa</i>. The modern
  town has clean streets and good roads made by Ahmed Vefyk Pasha when
  Vali, and it contains mosques and tombs of great historic and
  architectural interest; the more important are those of the sultans Murad
  I., Bayezid (Bajazet) I., Mahommed I., and Murad II., 1403-1451, and the
  Ulu Jami'. The mosques show traces of Byzantine, Persian and Arab
  influence in their plan, architecture and decorative details. The
  circular church of St Elias, in which the first two sultans, Osman and
  Orkhan, were buried, was destroyed by fire and earthquake, and rebuilt by
  Ahmed Vefyk Pasha. There are in the town an American mission and school,
  and a British orphanage. Silk-spinning is an important industry, the
  export of silk in 1902 being valued at £620,000. There are also
  manufactories of silk stuffs, towels, burnús, carpets, felt
  prayer-carpets embroidered in silk and gold. The hot iron and sulphur
  springs near Brusa, varying in temperature from 112° to 178° F., are
  still much used. The town is connected with its port, Mudania, by a
  railway and a road. There is a British vice-consul. Pop. 75,000 (Moslems,
  40,000; Christians, 33,000; Jews, 2000).</p>
      <p>
         <i>Prusa</i>, founded, it is said, at the suggestion of Hannibal, was
  for a long time the seat of the Bithynian kings. It continued to flourish
  under the Roman and Byzantine emperors till the 10th century, when it was
  captured and destroyed by Saif-addaula of Aleppo. Restored by the
  Byzantines, it was again taken in 1327 by the Ottomans after a siege of
  ten years, and continued to be their capital till Murad I. removed to
  Adrianople. In 1402 it was pillaged by the Tatars; in 1413 it resisted an
  attack of the Karamanians; in 1512 it fell into the power of Ala ed-Din;
  and in 1607 it was burnt by the rebellious Kalenderogli. In 1883 it was
  occupied by the Egyptians under Ibrahim Pasha, and from 1852-1855
  afforded an asylum to Abd-el-Kader.</p>
      <p>See L. de Laborde, <i>Voyage de l'Asie Mineure</i> (Paris, 1838); C.
  Texier, <i>Asie Mineure</i> (Paris, 1839).</p>
   </body>
</topic>