<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12267">
   <title>BRIGHT, SIR CHARLES TILSTON</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIGHT, SIR CHARLES TILSTON--> (1832-1888), English telegraph
  engineer, who came of an old Yorkshire family, was born on the 8th of
  June 1832, at Wanstead, Essex. At the age of fifteen he became a clerk
  under the Electric Telegraph Company. His talent for electrical
  engineering was soon shown, and his progress was rapid; so that in 1852
  he was appointed engineer to the Magnetic Telegraph Company, and in that
  capacity superintended the laying of lines in various parts of the
  British Isles, including in 1853 the first cable between Great Britain
  and Ireland, from Portpatrick to Donaghadee. His experiments convinced
  him of the practicability of an electric submarine cable connexion
  between Ireland and America; and having in 1855 already discussed the
  question with Cyrus Field, who with J. W. Brett controlled the
  Newfoundland Telegraph Company on the other side of the ocean, Bright
  organized with them the Atlantic Telegraph Company in 1856 for the
  purpose of carrying out the idea, himself becoming engineer-in-chief. The
  story of the first Atlantic cable is told elsewhere (see <ph outputclass="sc">Telegraph</ph>), and it must suffice here to say that in
  1858, after two disappointments, Bright successfully accomplished what to
  many had seemed an impossible feat, and within a few days of landing the
  Irish end of the line at Valentia he was knighted in Dublin. Subsequently
  Sir Charles Bright supervised the laying of submarine cables in various
  regions of the world, and took a leading part as pioneer in other
  developments of the electrical industry. In conjunction with Josiah
  Latimer Clark, with whom he entered into partnership in 1861, he invented
  improved methods of insulating submarine cables, and a paper on
  electrical standards read by them before the British Association in the
  same year led to the establishment of the British Association committee
  on that subject, whose work formed the foundations of the system still in
  use. From 1865 to 1868 he was Liberal M.P. for Greenwich. He died on the
  3rd of May 1888, at Abbey Wood, near London.</p>
      <p>See <i>Life Story of Sir C. T. Bright</i>, by his son Charles Bright
  (revised ed. 1908).</p>
   </body>
</topic>