<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e27034">
   <title>BRYANT, JACOB</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRYANT, JACOB--> (1715-1804), English antiquarian and writer on
  mythological subjects, was born at Plymouth. His father had a place in
  the customs there, but was afterwards stationed at Chatham. The son was
  first sent to a school near <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page698">[v.04 p.0698]</ph>Rochester, whence he was removed
  to Eton. In 1736 he was elected to a scholarship at King's College,
  Cambridge, where he took his degrees of B.A. (1740) and M.A. (1744),
  subsequently being elected a fellow. He returned to Eton as private tutor
  to the duke of Marlborough, then marquess of Blandford; and in 1756 he
  accompanied the duke, then master-general of ordnance and
  commander-in-chief of the forces in Germany, to the continent as private
  secretary. He was rewarded by a lucrative appointment in the ordnance
  department, which allowed him ample leisure to indulge his literary
  tastes. He twice refused the mastership of the Charterhouse. Bryant died
  on the 14th of November 1804 at Cippenham near Windsor. He left his
  library to King's College, having, however, previously made some valuable
  presents from it to the king and the duke of Marlborough. He bequeathed
  £2000 to the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel, and £1000 for the
  use of the superannuated collegers of Eton.</p>
      <p>His principal works are: <i>Observations and Inquiries relating to
  various Parts of Ancient History</i> (1767); <i>A New System, or an
  Analysis, of Ancient Mythology, wherein an attempt is made to divest
  Tradition of Fable, and to reduce Truth to its original Purity</i>
  (1774-1776), which is fantastic and now wholly valueless; <i>Vindication
  of the Apamean Medal</i> (1775), which obtained the support of the great
  numismatist Eckhel; <i>An Address to Dr Priestley upon his Doctrine of
  Philosophical Necessity</i> (1780); <i>Vindiciae Flavianae, a Vindication
  of the Testimony of Josephus concerning Jesus Christ</i> (1780);
  <i>Observations on the Poems of Thomas Rowley, in which the Authenticity
  of those Poems is ascertained</i> (1781); <i>Treatise upon the
  Authenticity of the Scriptures, and the Truth of the Christian
  Religion</i> (1792); <i>Observations upon the Plagues inflicted upon the
  Egyptians</i> (1794); <i>Observations on a Treatise, entitled Description
  of the Plain of Troy, by Mr de Chevalier</i> (1795); <i>A Dissertation
  concerning the War of Troy, and the Expedition of the Grecians, as
  described by Homer, with the view of showing that no such expedition was
  ever undertaken, and that no such city as Phrygia existed</i> (1796);
  <i>The Sentiments of Philo Judaeus concerning the <ph outputclass="grk">Λόγος</ph> or Word of God</i>
  (1797).</p>
   </body>
</topic>