<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e262">
   <title>BRETEUIL</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRETEUIL, LOUIS CHARLES AUGUSTE LE TONNELIER,--> <ph outputclass="sc">Baron de</ph> (1730-1807), French diplomatist, was born at
  the chateau of Azay-le-Féron (Indre) on the 7th of March 1730. He was
  only twenty-eight when he was appointed by Louis XV. ambassador to the
  elector of Cologne, and two years later he was sent to St Petersburg. He
  arranged to be temporarily absent from his post at the time of the palace
  revolution by which Catherine II. was placed on the throne. In 1769 he
  was sent to Stockholm, and subsequently represented his government at
  Vienna, Naples, and again at Vienna until 1783, when he was recalled to
  become minister of the king's household. In this capacity he introduced
  considerable reforms in prison administration. A close friend of Marie
  Antoinette, he presently came into collision with Calonne, who demanded
  his dismissal in 1787. His influence with the king and queen, especially
  with the latter, remained unshaken, and on Necker's dismissal on the 11th
  of July 1789, Breteuil succeeded him as chief minister. The fall of the
  Bastille three days later put an end to the new ministry, and Breteuil
  made his way to Switzerland with the first party of <i>émigrés</i>. At
  Soleure, in November 1790, he received from Louis XVI. exclusive powers
  to negotiate with the European courts, and in his efforts to check the
  ill-advised diplomacy of the <i>émigré</i> princes, he soon brought
  himself into opposition with his old rival Calonne, who held a chief
  place in their councils. <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page501">[v.04 p.0501]</ph>After the failure of the flight to
  Varennes, in the arrangement of which he had a share, Breteuil received
  instructions from Louis XVI., designed to restore amicable relations with
  the princes. His distrust of the king's brothers and his defence of Louis
  XVI.'s prerogative were to some extent justified, but his intransigeant
  attitude towards these princes emphasized the dissensions of the royal
  family in the eyes of foreign sovereigns, who looked on the comte de
  Provence as the natural representative of his brother and found a pretext
  for non-interference on Louis's behalf in the contradictory statements of
  the negotiators. Breteuil himself was the object of violent attacks from
  the party of the princes, who asserted that he persisted in exercising
  powers which had been revoked by Louis XVI. After the execution of Marie
  Antoinette he retired into private life near Hamburg, only returning to
  France in 1802. He died in Paris on the 2nd of November 1807.</p>
      <p>See the memoirs of Bertrand de Molleville (2 vols., Paris, 1816) and
  of the marquis de Bouillé (2 vols., Paris, 1884); and E. Daudet,
  <i>Coblentz, 1789-1793</i> (1889), forming part of his <i>Hist. de
  l'émigration.</i>
      </p>
   </body>
</topic>