<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23947">
   <title>BROWNE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWNE, MAXIMILIAN ULYSSES,--> <ph outputclass="sc">Count von, Baron
  de Camus and Mountany</ph> (1705-1757), Austrian field marshal, was
  born at Basel on the 23rd of October 1705. His father (Ulysses Freiherr
  v. Browne, d. 1731) was an Irish exile of 1690, who entered the imperial
  service and in 1716 was made a count <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page665">[v.04 p.0665]</ph>of the Empire
  (<i>Reichsgraf</i>) by the emperor Charles VI. His uncle Georg,
  Reichsgraf von Browne (1698-1792), was a distinguished soldier, who rose
  to the rank of field marshal in the Russian army, and was made Reichsgraf
  by the emperor Joseph II. in 1779. The powerful influence which he
  commanded, through his father and his wife (<i>née</i> Countess Marie
  Philippine v. Martinitz), advanced the young officer through the
  subordinate grades so rapidly that at the age of twenty-nine he was
  colonel of an infantry regiment. But he justified his early promotion in
  the field, and in the Italian campaign of 1734 he greatly distinguished
  himself. In the Tirolese fighting of 1735, and in the unfortunate Turkish
  war, he won further distinction as a general officer. He was a lieutenant
  field marshal in command of the Silesian garrisons when in 1740 Frederick
  II. and the Prussian army overran the province. His careful employment of
  such resources as he possessed materially hindered the king in his
  conquest and gave time for Austria to collect a field army (see <ph outputclass="sc">Austrian Succession, War of the</ph>). He was present at
  Mollwitz, where he received a severe wound. His vehement opposition to
  all half-hearted measures brought him frequently into conflict with his
  superiors, but contributed materially to the unusual energy displayed by
  the Austrian armies in 1742 and 1743. In the following campaigns Browne
  exhibited the same qualities of generalship and the same impatience of
  control. In 1745 he served under Count Traun, and was promoted to the
  rank of Feldzeugmeister. In 1746 he was present in the Italian campaign
  and the battles of Piacenza and Rottofredo. Browne himself with the
  advanced guard forced his way across the Apennines and entered Genoa. He
  was thereafter placed in command of the army intended for the invasion of
  France, and early in 1747 of all the imperial forces in Italy. At the end
  of the war Browne was engaged in the negotiations which led to the
  convention of Nice (January 21st, 1749). He became commander-in-chief in
  Bohemia in 1751, and field marshal two years later. He was still in
  Bohemia when the Seven Years' War opened with Frederick's invasion of
  Saxony (1756). Browne's army, advancing to the relief of Pirna (see <ph outputclass="sc">Seven Years' War</ph>), was met, and, after a hard struggle,
  defeated by the king at Lobositz, but he drew off in excellent order, and
  soon made another attempt with a picked force to reach Pirna, by wild
  mountain tracks. The field marshal never spared himself, bivouacking in
  the snow with his men, and Carlyle records that private soldiers made
  rough shelters over him as he slept. He actually reached the Elbe at
  Schandau, but as the Saxons were unable to break out Browne retired,
  having succeeded, however, in delaying the development of Frederick's
  operations for a whole campaign. In the campaign of 1757 he voluntarily
  served under Prince Charles of Lorraine (<i>q.v.</i>) who was made
  commander-in-chief, and on the 6th of May in that year, while leading a
  bayonet charge at the battle of Prague, Browne, like Schwerin on the same
  day, met his death. He was carried mortally wounded into Prague, and
  there died on the 26th of June, his last days embittered by the knowledge
  that he was unjustly held responsible for the failure of the campaign.
  His name has been borne, since 1888, by the 36th Austrian infantry.</p>
      <p>See <i>Zuverlässige Lebensbeschreibung U.M. Reichsgrafen</i>, v. B.
  K.-K. Gen.-Feldmarschall (Frankfurt and Leipzig, 1757); Baron O'Cahill,
  <i>Gesch. der grossten Herrfuhrer</i> (Rastadt, 1785, v. ii. pp.
  264-316).</p>
   </body>
</topic>