<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22445">
   <title>BROOKS, CHARLES WILLIAM SHIRLEY</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROOKS, CHARLES WILLIAM SHIRLEY--> (1816-1874), English novelist,
  playwright and journalist, was born on the 29th of April 1816. He was the
  son of a London architect, and was articled in 1832 to a solicitor for
  five years. He became parliamentary reporter for the <i>Morning
  Chronicle</i>, and in 1853 was sent by that paper as special commissioner
  to investigate the subject of labour and the poor in southern Russia,
  Egypt and Syria; the result of his inquiries appearing first in the form
  of letters to the editor, and afterwards in a separate volume, under the
  title of <i>The Russians of the South</i> (1856). He wrote, sometimes
  alone, sometimes in conjunction with others, slight dramatic pieces of
  the burlesque kind, among which may be mentioned <i>Anything for a
  Change</i> (1848), <i>The Daughter of the Stars</i> (1850). Brooks was
  for many years on the staff of the <i>Illustrated London News</i>,
  contributing the weekly article on the politics of the day, and the two
  series entitled "Nothing in the Papers" and "By the Way." In 1851 he
  joined the staff of <i>Punch</i>, and noteworthy among his numerous
  contributions were the weekly satirical summaries of the parliamentary
  debates, entitled "The Essence of Parliament." His long service as
  newspaper reporter gave him special aptitude for this playful parody. In
  1870, on the death of Mark Lemon, "dear old Shirley," as his friends used
  to call him, was chosen to succeed to the editorial chair. His first
  novel, <i>Aspen Court</i>, was published in 1855. It was followed by
  <i>The Gordian Knot</i> (1860), <i>The Silver Cord</i> (1861) and
  <i>Sooner or Later</i> (1868). Brooks was a great letter-writer,
  deliberately cultivating the practice as an art, and imitating the style
  in vogue before newspapers and telegraphs suppressed private letters. He
  had an astonishing memory, was brilliant as an epigrammatist, was a great
  reader and a most genial companion. He was in his element with a group of
  children, reading to them, sharing their fun and always remembering the
  birthdays. He died in London, on the 23rd of February 1874, and was
  buried near his friends Leech and Thackeray, in Kensal Green
  cemetery.</p>
      <p>See G.S. Layard, <i>A Great "Punch" Editor: Being the Life, Letters
  and Diaries of Shirley Brooks</i> (1907.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>