<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12674">
   <title>BRISBANE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRISBANE,--> the capital of Queensland, Australia. It is situated
  in Stanley county, on the banks of the river Brisbane, 25 m. from its
  mouth in Moreton Bay. It is built on a series of hills rising from the
  river-banks, but some parts of it, such as Woollongabba and South
  Brisbane, occupy low-lying flats, which have sometimes been the scene of
  disastrous floods. The main streets and principal buildings of the city
  are situated on a tongue of land formed by a southward bend of the river.
  The extremity of the tongue, however, is open. Here, adjoining one
  another, are the botanical gardens, the grounds surrounding Government
  House, the official residence of the governor of the colony, and the
  Houses of Parliament, and Queen's Park, which is used as a recreation
  ground. From this park Albert Street runs for about three-quarters of a
  mile through the heart of the city, leading to Albert Park, in which is
  the observatory. Queen's Street, the main thoroughfare of Brisbane,
  crosses Albert Street midway between the two parks and leads across the
  Victoria Bridge to the separate city of South Brisbane on the other side
  of the river. The Victoria Bridge is a fine steel structure, which
  replaced the bridge swept away by floods in February 1893. Brisbane has a
  large number of buildings of architectural merit, though in some cases
  their effect is marred by the narrowness of the streets in which they
  stand. Among the most prominent are the Houses of Parliament, the great
  domed custom-house on the river-bank, the lands office, the general
  post-office, the town halls of Brisbane and South Brisbane, and the opera
  house. The Roman Catholic cathedral of St Stephen (Elizabeth Street) is
  an imposing building, having a detached campanile containing the largest
  bell in Australia. The foundation-stone of the Anglican cathedral, on an
  elevated site in Ann Street, was laid by the prince of Wales (as duke of
  York) in 1901. The city is the seat of a Roman Catholic archbishop and of
  an Anglican bishop. Many of the commercial and private buildings are also
  worthy of notice, especially the Queensland National Bank, a classic
  Italian structure, the massive treasury buildings, one of the largest
  erections in Australia, the Queensland Club with its wide colonnades in
  Italian Renaissance style, and the great buildings of the Brisbane
  Newspaper Company. Brisbane is well provided with parks and open spaces;
  the Victoria Park and Bowen Park are the largest; the high-lying Mount
  Coot-tha commands fine views, and there are other parks and numerous
  recreation grounds in various parts of the city, besides the admirable
  botanical gardens and the gardens of the Acclimatization Society.
  Electric tramways and omnibuses serve all parts of the city, and numerous
  ferries ply across the river. There is railway communication to north,
  south and west. By careful dredging, the broad river is navigable as far
  as Brisbane for ocean-going vessels, and the port is the terminal port
  for the Queensland mail steamers to Europe, and is visited by steamers to
  China, Japan and America, and for various inter-colonial lines. There is
  wharf accommodation on both banks of the river, a graving dock which can
  be used by vessels up to 5000 tons, and two patent slips which can take
  up ships of 1000 and 400 tons respectively. The exports are chiefly coal,
  sheep, tallow, wool, frozen meat and hides. The annual value of imports
  and exports exceeds seven and nine millions sterling respectively. There
  are boot factories, soap works, breweries, tanneries, tobacco works,
  &amp;c. The climate is on the whole dry and healthy, but during summer
  the temperature is high, the mean shade temperature being about 70°
  F.</p>
      <p>Brisbane was founded in 1825 as a penal settlement, taking its name
  from Sir Thomas Brisbane, then governor of Australia; in 1842 it became a
  free settlement and in 1859 capital of Queensland, the town up to that
  time having belonged to New South Wales. It was incorporated in the same
  year. South Brisbane became a separate city in 1903. The municipal
  government of the city, and also of South Brisbane, is in the hands of a
  mayor and ten alderman; the suburbs are controlled by shire councils and
  divisional boards. The chief suburbs are Kangaroo Point, Fortitude
  Valley, New Farm, Red Hill, Paddington, Milon, Toowong, Breakfast Creek,
  Bulimba, Woolongabba, Highgate and Indooroopilly. The population of the
  metropolitan area in 1901 was 119,907; of the city proper, 28,953; of
  South Brisbane, 25,481.</p>
   </body>
</topic>