<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12571">
   <title>BRINVILLIERS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRINVILLIERS, MARIE MADELEINE MARGUERITE D'AUBRAY,--> <ph outputclass="sc">Marquise de</ph> (<i>c.</i> 1630-1676), French poisoner,
  daughter of Dreux d'Aubray, civil lieutenant of Paris, was born in Paris
  about 1630. In 1651 she married the marquis de Brinvilliers, then serving
  in the regiment of Normandy. Contemporary evidence describes the marquise
  at this time as a pretty and much-courted little woman, with a
  fascinating air of childlike innocence. In 1659 her husband introduced
  her to his friend Godin de Sainte-Croix, a handsome young cavalry officer
  of extravagant tastes and bad reputation, whose mistress she became.
  Their relations soon created a public scandal, and as the marquis de
  Brinvilliers, who had left France to avoid his creditors, made no effort
  to terminate them, M. d'Aubray secured the arrest of Sainte-Croix on a
  <i>lettre de cachet</i>. For a year Sainte-Croix remained a prisoner in
  the Bastille, where he is popularly supposed to have acquired a knowledge
  of poisons from his fellow-prisoner, the Italian poisoner Exili. When he
  left the Bastille, he plotted with his willing mistress his revenge upon
  her father. She cheerfully undertook to experiment with the poisons which
  Sainte-Croix, possibly with the help of a chemist, Christopher Glaser,
  prepared, and found subjects ready to hand in the poor who sought her
  charity, and the sick whom she visited in the hospitals. Meanwhile
  Sainte-Croix, completely ruined financially, enlarged his original idea,
  and determined that not only M. Dreux d'Aubray but also the latter's two
  sons and other daughter should be poisoned, so that the marquise de
  Brinvilliers and himself might come into possession of the large family
  fortune. In February 1666, satisfied with the efficiency of
  Sainte-Croix's preparations and with the ease with which they could be
  administered without detection, the marquise poisoned her father, and in
  1670, with the connivance of their valet La Chaussée, her two brothers. A
  post-mortem examination suggested the real cause of death, but no
  suspicion was directed to the murderers. Before any attempt could be made
  on the life of Mlle Théresè d'Aubray, Sainte-Croix suddenly died. As he
  left no heirs the police were called in, and discovered among his
  belongings documents seriously incriminating the marquise and La
  Chaussée. The latter was arrested, tortured into a complete confession,
  and broken alive on the wheel (1673), but the marquise escaped, taking
  refuge first probably in England, then in Germany, and finally in a
  convent at Liége, whence she was decoyed by a police emissary disguised
  as a priest. A full account of her life and crimes was found among her
  papers. Her attempt to commit suicide was frustrated, and she was taken
  to Paris, where she was beheaded and her body burned on the 16th of July
  1676.</p>
      <p>See G. Roullier, <i>La Marquise de Brinvilliers</i> (Paris, 1883);
  Toiseleur, <i>Trois énigmes historiques</i> (Paris, 1882).</p>
   </body>
</topic>