<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e13028">
   <title>BRISTOL</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRISTOL, JOHN DIGBY,--> <ph outputclass="sc">1st Earl of</ph>
         <xref href="#d1e13028/Footnote_081" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> (1580-1653)
  English diplomatist, son of Sir George Digby of Coleshill, Warwickshire,
  and of Abigail, daughter of Sir Arthur Henningham, was born in <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page578">[v.04
  p.0578]</ph>1580, and entered Magdalen College, Oxford, in 1595 (M.A.
  1605), becoming a member of the Inner Temple in 1598. In 1605 he was sent
  to James to inform him of the safety of the princess Elizabeth at the
  time of the Gunpowder Plot. He gained his favour, was made a gentleman of
  the privy chamber and one of the king's carvers, and was knighted in
  1607. From 1610 to 1611 he was member of parliament for Heydon. In 1611
  he was sent as ambassador to Spain to negotiate a marriage between Prince
  Henry and the infanta Anne, and to champion the cause of the English
  merchants, for whom he obtained substantial concessions, and arranged the
  appointment of consuls at Lisbon and Seville. He also discovered a list
  of the English pensioners of the Spanish court, which included some of
  the ministers, and came home in 1613 to communicate this important
  intelligence to the king. In 1614 he again went to Spain to effect a
  union between the infanta Maria and Charles, though he himself was in
  favour of a Protestant marriage, and desired a political and not a
  matrimonial treaty. In 1616, on the disgrace of Somerset, he was recalled
  home to give evidence concerning the latter's connexions with Spain, was
  made vice-chamberlain and a privy councillor, and obtained from James the
  manor of Sherborne forfeited by the late favourite. In 1618 he went once
  more to Spain to reopen the negotiations, returning in May, and being
  created Baron Digby on the 25th of November. He endeavoured to avoid a
  breach with Spain on the election of the elector palatine, the king's
  son-in-law, to the Bohemian throne; and in March 1621, after the latter's
  expulsion from Bohemia, Digby was sent to Brussels to obtain a suspension
  of hostilities in the Palatinate. On the 4th of July he went to Vienna
  and drew up a scheme of pacification with the emperor, by which Frederick
  was to abandon Bohemia and be secured in his hereditary territories, but
  the agreement could never be enforced. After raising money for the
  defence of Heidelberg he returned home in October, and on the 21st of
  November explained his policy to the parliament, and asked for money and
  forces for its execution. The sudden dissolution of parliament, however,
  prevented the adoption of any measure of support, and entirely ruined
  Digby's plans. In 1622 he returned to Spain with nothing on which to rely
  but the goodwill of Philip IV., and nothing to offer but entreaties.</p>
      <p>On the 15th of September he was created earl of Bristol. He urged on
  the marriage treaty, believing it would include favourable conditions for
  Frederick, but the negotiations were taken out of his control, and
  finally wrecked by the arrival of Charles himself and Buckingham in March
  1623. He incurred their resentment, of which the real inspiration was
  Buckingham's implacable jealousy, by a letter written to James informing
  him of Buckingham's unpopularity among the Spanish ministers, and by his
  endeavouring to maintain the peace with Spain after their departure. In
  January 1624 he left Spain, and on arriving at Dover in March, Buckingham
  and Charles having now complete ascendancy over the king, he was
  forbidden to appear at court and ordered to confine himself at Sherborne.
  He was required by Buckingham to answer a series of interrogatories, but
  he refused to inculpate himself and demanded a trial by parliament. On
  the death of James he was removed by Charles I. from the privy council,
  and ordered to absent himself from his first parliament. On his demand in
  January 1626 to be present at the coronation Charles angrily refused, and
  accused him of having tried to pervert his religion in Spain. In March
  1626, after the assembling of the second parliament, Digby applied to the
  Lords, who supported his rights, and Charles sent him his writ
  accompanied by a letter from Lord Keeper Coventry desiring him not to use
  it. Bristol, however, took his seat and demanded justice against
  Buckingham (Thomason Tracts, E. 126 (20)). The king endeavoured to
  obstruct his attack by causing Bristol on the 1st of May to be himself
  brought to the bar, on an accusation of high treason by the
  attorney-general. The Lords, however, ordered that both charges should be
  investigated simultaneously. Further proceedings were stopped by the
  dissolution of parliament on the 15th of June; a prosecution was ordered
  by Charles in the Star Chamber, and Bristol was sent to the Tower, where
  he remained till the 17th of March 1628, when the peers, on the
  assembling of Charles's third parliament, insisted on his liberation and
  restoration to his seat in the Lords.</p>
      <p>In the discussions upon the Petition of Right, Bristol supported the
  use of the king's prerogative in emergencies, and asserted that the king
  besides his legal had a regal power, but joined in the demand for a full
  acceptance of the petition by the king after the first unsatisfactory
  answer. He was now restored to favour, but took no part in politics till
  the outbreak of the Scottish rebellion, when he warned Charles of the
  danger of attacking with inadequate forces. He was the leader in the
  Great Council held at York, was a commissioner to treat with the Scots in
  September 1640 at Ripon, and advised strongly the summoning of the
  parliament. In February 1641 he was one of the peers who advocated
  reforms in the administration and were given seats in the council. Though
  no friend to Strafford, he endeavoured to save his life, desiring only to
  see him excluded from office, and as a witness was excused from voting on
  the attainder. He was appointed gentleman of the bedchamber on the king's
  departure for Scotland, and on the 27th of December he was declared an
  evil counsellor by the House of Commons, Cromwell on the 28th moving an
  address to the king to dismiss him from his councils, on the plea that he
  had advocated the bringing up of the northern army to overawe parliament
  in the preceding spring. There is no evidence to support the charge, but
  Digby was regarded by the parliamentary party with special hatred and
  distrust, of which the chief causes were probably his Spanish
  proclivities and his indifference on the great matter of religion, to
  which was added the unpopularity reflected from his misguided son. On the
  28th of March 1642 he was sent to the Tower for having failed to disclose
  to parliament the Kentish petition. Liberated in April, he spoke in the
  Lords on the 20th of May in favour of an accommodation, and again in June
  in vindication of the king; but finding his efforts ineffectual, and
  believing all armed rebellion against the king a wicked violation of the
  most solemn oaths, he joined Charles at York, was present at Edgehill and
  accompanied him to Oxford. On the 1st of February 1643 he was named with
  Lord Herbert of Raglan for removal from the court and public office for
  ever, and in the propositions of November 1644 was one of those excepted
  from pardon. In January he had endeavoured to instigate a breach of the
  Independents with the Scots. Bristol, however, was not in favour of
  continuing the war, and withdrew to Sherborne, removing in the spring of
  1644 to Exeter, and after the surrender of the city retiring abroad on
  the 11th of July by order of the Houses, which rejected his petition to
  compound for his estate. He took up his residence at Caen, passing the
  rest of his life in exile and poverty, and occasionally attending the
  young king. In 1647 he printed at Caen <i>An Apology</i>, defending his
  support of the royal cause. This was reprinted in 1656 (Thomason Tracts,
  E. 897, 6). He died at Paris on the 16th of January 1653.</p>
      <p>He is described by Clarendon as "a man of grave aspect, of a presence
  that drew respect, and of great parts and ability, but passionate and
  supercilious and too voluminous a discourser in council." His aim was to
  effect a political union between England and Spain apart from the
  religious or marriage questions—a policy which would probably have
  benefited both English and European interests; but it was one understood
  neither in Spain nor in England, and proved impracticable. He was a man
  of high character, who refused to compound with falsehood and injustice,
  whose misfortune it was to serve two Stuart sovereigns, and whose firm
  resistance to the king's tyranny led the way to the great movement which
  finally destroyed it. Besides his <i>Apology</i>, he was the author of
  several printed speeches and poems, and translated <i>A Defence of the
  Catholic Faith</i> by Peter du Moulin (1610). He married Beatrix,
  daughter of Charles Walcot, and widow of Sir John Dyve, and besides two
  daughters left two sons, George, who succeeded him as 2nd earl of
  Bristol, and John, who died unmarried.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Bibliography</ph>.—The best account of
  Bristol will be found in the scattered notices of him in the <i>Hist. of
  England</i> and of the <i>Civil War</i>, by S. R. Gardiner, who also
  wrote the short sketch of his career in <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page579">[v.04 p.0579]</ph>the <i>Dict. of
  Nat. Biog.</i>, and who highly eulogizes his character and diplomacy. For
  lives, see <i>Biographia Britannica</i> (Kippis), v. 199; Wood's <i>Ath.
  Oxon.</i> (Bliss), iii. 338; D. Lloyd's <i>Memoires</i> (1668), 579;
  Collins's <i>Peerage</i> (Brydges, 1812), v. 362; Fuller's
  <i>Worthies</i> (Nichols, 1811), ii. 412; H. Walpole's <i>Royal and Noble
  Authors</i> (Park, 1806), iii. 49; also Clarendon's <i>Hist of the
  Rebellion</i>, esp. vi. 388; <i>Clarendon State Papers</i> and <i>Cal. of
  Cl. State Papers</i>; <i>Old Parliamentary History</i>; <i>Cabala</i>
  (1691; letters); Camden Soc., <i>Miscellany</i>, vol. vi. (1871);
  <i>Defence of his Spanish Negotiations</i>, ed. by S.R. Gardiner;
  <i>Somers Tracts</i> (1809), ii. 501; <i>Thomason Tracts</i> in Brit.
  Museum; <i>Hardwicke State Papers</i>, i. 494. The MSS. at Sherborne
  Castle, of which a selection was transcribed and deposited in the Public
  Record Office, were calendared by the Hist. MSS. Commission in
  <i>Rep.</i> viii. app. i. p. 213 and 10th <i>Rep.</i> app. i. p. 520;
  there are numerous references to Bristol in various collections
  calendared in the same publication and in the <i>Cal. of State Papers,
  Dom. Series</i>; see also <i>Harleian MSS.</i>, Brit. Mus. 1580, art.
  31-48, and <i>Add. MSS.</i> indexes and calendars.</p>
      <p>(P. C. Y.)</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_081"> 
            <i>I.e.</i> in the
  Digby line; for the Herveys see above.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>