<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e27175">
   <title>BRYCE, JAMES</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRYCE, JAMES--> (1838- ), British jurist, historian and
  politician, son of James Bryce (LL.D. of Glasgow, who had a school in
  Belfast for many years), was born at Belfast, Ireland, on the 10th of May
  1838. After going through the high school and university courses at
  Glasgow, he went to Trinity College, Oxford, and in 1862 was elected a
  fellow of Oriel. He went to the bar and practised in London for a few
  years, but he was soon called back to Oxford as regius professor of civil
  law (1870-1893). His reputation as a historian had been made as early as
  1864 by his <i>Holy Roman Empire</i>. He was an ardent Liberal in
  politics, and in 1880 he was elected to parliament for the Tower Hamlets
  division of London; in 1885 he was returned for South Aberdeen, where he
  was re-elected on succeeding occasions. His intellectual distinction and
  political industry made him a valuable member of the Liberal party. In
  1886 he was made under secretary for foreign affairs; in 1892 he joined
  the cabinet as chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster; in 1894 he was
  president of the Board of Trade, and acted as chairman of the royal
  commission on secondary education; and in Sir Henry Campbell-Bannerman's
  cabinet (1905) he was made chief secretary for Ireland; but in February
  1907 he was appointed British ambassador at Washington, and took leave of
  party politics, his last political act being a speech outlining what was
  then the government scheme for university reform in Dublin—a scheme
  which was promptly discarded by his successor Mr Birrell. As a man of
  letters Mr Bryce was already well known in America. His great work <i>The
  American Commonwealth</i> (1888; revised edition, 1910) was the first in
  which the institutions of the United States had been thoroughly discussed
  from the point of view of a historian and a constitutional lawyer, and it
  at once became a classic. His <i>Studies in History and Jurisprudence</i>
  (1901) and <i>Studies in Contemporary Biography</i> (1903) were
  republications of essays, and in 1897, after a visit to South Africa, he
  published a volume of <i>Impressions</i> of that country, which had
  considerable weight in Liberal circles when the Boer War was being
  discussed. Meanwhile his academic honours from home and foreign
  universities multiplied, and he became a fellow of the Royal Society in
  1894. In earlier life he was a notable mountain-climber, ascending Mount
  Ararat in 1876, and publishing a volume on <i>Transcaucasia and
  Ararat</i> in 1877; in 1899-1901 he was president of the Alpine Club.</p>
   </body>
</topic>