<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e29747">
   <title>BÜCHNER, FRIEDRICH KARL CHRISTIAN LUDWIG</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BÜCHNER, FRIEDRICH KARL CHRISTIAN LUDWIG--> (1824-1899), German
  philosopher and physician, was born at Darmstadt. He studied at Giessen,
  Strassburg, Würzburg and Vienna. In 1852 he became lecturer in medicine
  at the university of Tübingen, where he published his great work <i>Kraft
  und Stoff</i> (1855). In this work, the product, according to Lange, of a
  fanatical enthusiasm for humanity, he sought to demonstrate the
  indestructibility of matter and force, and the finality of physical
  force. The extreme materialism of this work excited so much opposition
  that he was compelled to give up his post at Tübingen. He retired to
  Darmstadt, where he practised as a physician and contributed regularly to
  pathological and physiological magazines. He continued his philosophical
  work in defence of materialism, and published <i>Natur und Geist</i>
  (1857), <i>Aus Natur und Wissenschaft</i> (vol. i., 1862; vol. ii.,
  1884), <i>Fremdes und Eigenes aus dem geistigen Leben der Gegenwart</i>
  (1890), <i>Darwinismus und Socialismus</i> (1894), <i>Im Dienste der
  Wahrheit</i> (1899). He died at Darmstadt on the 1st of May 1899. In
  estimating Büchner's philosophy it must be remembered that he was
  primarily a physiologist, not a metaphysician. Matter and force (or
  energy) are infinite; the conservation of force follows from the
  imperishability of matter, the ultimate basis of all science. Büchner is
  not always clear in his theory of the relation between matter and force.
  At one time he refuses to explain it, but generally he assumes that all
  natural and spiritual forces are indwelling in matter. "Just as a
  steam-engine," he says in <i>Kraft und Stoff</i> (7th ed., p. 130),
  "produces motion, so the intricate organic complex of force-bearing
  substance in an animal organism produces a total sum of certain effects,
  which, when bound together in a unity, are called by us mind, soul,
  thought." Here he postulates force and mind as emanating from original
  matter—a materialistic monism. But in other parts of his works he
  suggests that mind and matter are two different aspects of that which is
  the basis of all things—a monism which is not necessarily
  materialistic, and which, in the absence of further explanation,
  constitutes a confession of failure. Büchner was much less concerned to
  establish a scientific metaphysic than to protest against the romantic
  idealism of his predecessors and the theological interpretations of the
  universe. Nature according to him is purely physical; it has no purpose,
  no will, no laws imposed by extraneous authority, no supernatural ethical
  sanction.</p>
      <p>See Frauenstädt, <i>Der Materialismus</i> (Leipzig, 1856); Janet,
  <i>The Materialism of the Present Day: A Criticism of Dr Büchner's
  System</i>, trans. Masson (London, 1867).</p>
   </body>
</topic>