<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e20144">
   <title>BRODHEAD, JOHN ROMEYN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRODHEAD, JOHN ROMEYN--> (1814-1873), American historical scholar,
  was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, on the 2nd of January 1814, the
  son of Jacob Brodhead (1782-1855), a prominent clergyman of the Dutch
  Reformed Church. He graduated at Rutgers College in 1831, and in 1835 was
  admitted to the bar in New York City. After 1837, however, he devoted
  himself principally to the study of American colonial history, and in
  order to have access to the records of the early Dutch settlements in
  America he obtained in 1839 an appointment as attaché of the American
  legation at the Hague. His investigations here soon proved that the Dutch
  archives were rich in material on the early history of New York, and led
  the state legislature to appropriate funds for the systematic gathering
  from various European archives of transcripts of documents relating to
  New York. Brodhead was appointed (1841) by Governor William H. Seward to
  undertake the work, and within several years gathered from England,
  France and Holland some eighty manuscript volumes of transcriptions,
  largely of documents which had not hitherto been used by historians.
  These transcriptions were subsequently edited by Edward O'Callaghan
  (vols. i.-xi. incl.) and by Berthold Fernow (vols. xii.-xv., incl.), and
  published by the state under the title <i>Documents relating to the
  Colonial History of New York</i> (15 vols., 1853-1883). From 1846 to
  1849, while George Bancroft was minister to Great Britain, Brodhead held
  under him the post of secretary of legation. In 1853-1857 he was naval
  officer of the port of New York. He published several addresses and a
  scholarly <i>History of the State of New York</i> (2 vols., 1853-1871),
  generally considered the best for the brief period covered (1609-1690).
  He died in New York City on the 6th of May 1873.</p>
   </body>
</topic>