<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e24222">
   <title>BROWNE, WILLIAM GEORGE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWNE, WILLIAM GEORGE--> (1768-1813), English traveller, was born
  at Great Tower Hill, London, on the 25th of July 1768. At seventeen he
  was sent to Oriel College, Oxford. Having had a moderate competence left
  him by his father, on quitting the university he applied himself entirely
  to literary pursuits. But the fame of James Bruce's travels, and of the
  first discoveries made by the African Association, determined him to
  become an explorer of Central Africa. He went first to Egypt, arriving at
  Alexandria in January 1792. He spent some time in visiting the oasis of
  Siwa or Jupiter Ammon, and employed the remainder of the year in studying
  Arabic and in examining the ruins of ancient Egypt. In the spring of 1793
  he visited Sinai, and in May set out for Darfur, joining the great
  caravan which every year went by the desert route from Egypt to that
  country. This was his most important journey, in which he acquired a
  great variety of original information. He was forcibly detained by the
  sultan of Darfur and endured much hardship, being unable to effect his
  purpose of returning by Abyssinia. He was, however, allowed to return to
  Egypt with the caravan in 1796; after this he spent a year in Syria, and
  did not arrive in London till September 1798. In 1799 he published his
  <i>Travels in Africa, Egypt and Syria, from the year 1792 to 1798</i>.
  The work was full of valuable information; but, from the abruptness and
  dryness of the style, it never became popular. In 1800 Browne again left
  England, and spent three years in visiting Greece, some parts of Asia
  Minor and Sicily. In 1812 he once more set out for the East, proposing to
  penetrate to Samarkand and survey the most interesting regions of central
  Asia. He spent the winter in Smyrna, and in the spring of 1813 travelled
  through Asia Minor and Armenia, made a short stay at Erzerum, and arrived
  on the 1st of June at Tabriz. About the end of the summer of 1813 he left
  Tabriz for Teheran, intending to proceed thence into Tartary, but was
  shortly afterwards murdered. Some bones, believed to be his, were
  afterwards found and interred near the grave of Jean de Thevenot, the
  French traveller.</p>
      <p>Robert Walpole published, in the second volume of his <i>Memoirs
  relating to European and Asiatic Turkey</i> (1820), from papers left by
  Browne, the account of his journey in 1802 through Asia Minor to Antioch
  and Cyprus; also <i>Remarks written at Constantinople</i> (1802).</p>
   </body>
</topic>