<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22363">
   <title>BROOKLYN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROOKLYN,--> formerly a city of New York state, U.S.A., but since
  1898 a borough of New York City (<i>q.v.</i>), situated at the S.W.
  extremity of Long Island. It is conterminous with Kings county, and is
  bounded N. by the borough of Queens, from which it is in part separated
  by Newtown Creek; E. by the borough of Queens and Jamaica Bay; S. by the
  Atlantic Ocean; W. by Gravesend Bay, the Narrows, Upper New York Bay and
  East river, which separate it from Staten Island, Jersey City and the
  borough of Manhattan. It has a water-front of 33 m. and extends over an
  area of 77.62 sq. m. Pop. (1860) 279,122; (1870) 419,921; (1880) 599,495;
  (1890, then Kings county) 838,547; (1900) 1,166,582; (1905, state census)
  1,358,686; (1910) 1,634.351. In 1900 only 310,501, or 26.6%, were
  native-born of native white parents; 355,697 were foreign-born, 18,367
  were negroes, and 1206 were Chinese. Out of 332,715 males of voting age
  (21 years and over), 15,415 were illiterate (unable to write), and of
  these 14,159 were foreign-born.</p>
      <p>Brooklyn is connected with Manhattan by three bridges across the East
  river—the lowest, known as the Brooklyn, opened in 1883; another,
  known as the Williamsburg or East River bridge, opened in 1903; and a
  third, the Manhattan, was opened in 1909. And a tunnel directly across
  from the south terminus of Manhattan was completed in 1907. Ferries ply
  at frequent intervals between numerous points on its west water-front and
  points in Manhattan; there is also ferry connexion with Jersey City.
  Brooklyn is served directly by the Long Island railway; by about fifty
  regular coast-wise and trans-Atlantic steamship lines; and by elevated or
  surface car lines on a large number of its streets. Subway lines, begun
  in 1904, connect Brooklyn with the subway system of Manhattan.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Streets and Buildings.</i>—The surface of Brooklyn in the
  west section, from the lower course of the East river to Gravesend Bay,
  varies in elevation from a few inches to nearly 200 ft. above sea-level,
  the highest points being in Prospect Park; but steep street grades even
  in this section are rare, and elsewhere the surface is either only
  slightly undulating or, as in the east and south, flat. Most of the
  streets are from 60 to 100 ft. wide. The principal business thoroughfare
  is Fulton Street, which begins at Fulton ferry nearly under the Brooklyn
  bridge, runs to City Hall Park, and thence across the north central
  section of the borough. In the City Hall Park are the old city hall (now
  the borough hall), the hall of records, and the county court-house. Two
  blocks to the north (on Washington Street) is the post-office, a fine
  granite Romanesque building. The manufacturing and shipping districts are
  mostly along the west water-front. Here, on Wallabout Bay at the bend of
  the East river to the westward, is the New York navy yard, the principal
  navy yard of the United States, established in 1801, and commonly but
  incorrectly called the Brooklyn navy yard. It occupies altogether about
  144 acres, contains a trophy park, parade grounds, the United States
  Naval Lyceum (founded 1833), officers' quarters, barracks, and three
  large dry docks (respectively 564, 465 and 307 ft. long), foundries and
  machine shops. A naval hospital (having accommodation for about 500
  patients) to the east is separated from the navy yard by the largest and
  most interesting of Brooklyn's markets, the Wallabout (about 45 acres).
  The buildings of this market are Dutch in style and have a quaint clock
  tower. A little to the north of the navy yard are immense refineries of
  sugar. About 2 m. to the south, opposite Governor's Island, is the
  Atlantic Basin of 40 acres, with a wharfage of about 3 m. and brick and
  granite warehouses used largely for the storage of grain. A little
  farther south, on Gowanus Bay, is another basin, the Erie, of 161 acres,
  protected by a breakwater 1 m. in length, occupied by piers, warehouses,
  lumber depots and some of the largest dry docks in the United States; it
  also provides protection during winter to hundreds of canal boats. In
  this vicinity, too, are several yards for building yachts, launches and
  other boats. At the lower end of the west water-front, facing the
  Narrows, are a United States reservation and the harbour defences of Fort
  Hamilton.</p>
      <p>For a considerable portion of its inhabitants Brooklyn is only a place
  of residence, their business interests being in the borough of Manhattan;
  hence Brooklyn has been called the "city of homes" and the "dormitory of
  New York." Residential districts with social lines more or less
  distinctly drawn are numerous. The oldest is that on Brooklyn (or
  Columbia) Heights, west of City Hall Park, rising abruptly from the river
  to a height of from 70 to 100 ft., and commanding a delightful view of
  the harbour. Here are hotels, large apartment-houses, many private
  residences and a number of clubs, including the Brooklyn, the Crescent,
  the Hamilton, the Jefferson and the Germania. On Park Slope, immediately
  west of Prospect Park, and St Mark's Avenue, in another part of the
  borough, are also attractive residential districts. The south shore of
  the borough has various summer pleasure resorts, of which Coney Island is
  the most popular.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Parks and Cemeteries.</i>—One of the most attractive features
  of Brooklyn is Prospect Park, occupying about 516 acres of high ground in
  the west central part of the borough, on a site made memorable by the
  battle of Long Island. Its large variety of trees and shrubs, including
  oak, hickory, elm, maple, chestnut, birch, ash, cedar, pine, larch and
  sumach, its flower gardens, a palm house, ponds, a lake of 61 acres for
  boating, skating and curling, a parade ground of 40 acres for other
  athletic sports, a menagerie, and numerous pieces of statuary, are among
  its objects of interest or beauty. From the southern entrance to this
  park, Ocean Parkway, a fine boulevard, 210 ft. wide and planted with six
  rows of trees, extends 5½ m. south to Seaside Park (15 acres), on
  Brighton Beach, Coney Island. From the same entrance Fort Hamilton
  Parkway extends 4½ m. south-east to Fort Hamilton, and to Dyker Beach
  Park (144 acres) which face the lower end of the Narrows; and from Fort
  Hamilton, Shore Road and Bay Ridge Parkway extend north 4½ m. to Bay
  Ridge Park overlooking Upper New York Bay. From the northern entrance to
  Prospect Park, Eastern Parkway, another fine boulevard, 200 ft. wide,
  extends east 2½ m. to a point from which Rockaway Parkway runs 3 m.
  south-east to Canarsie Beach Park (40 acres), on Jamaica Bay; and
  extensions of Eastern Parkway run north-east through Highland Park (55
  acres), to Brooklyn Forest Park (535 acres, on the border of the borough
  of Queens), abounding in beautiful trees and delightful views. Half a
  mile east of the borough hall is Washington or Fort Greene Park (30
  acres), laid out on the site of earthworks (known as Fort Greene)
  constructed during the War of Independence, and commanding good
  views.</p>
      <p>Greenwood cemetery, one of the most beautiful cemeteries in the United
  States, ½ m. east of Prospect Park, occupies about 478 acres. Among the
  principal monuments are those erected to Roger Williams, S.F.B. Morse,
  Elias Howe, De Witt Clinton (colossal bronze statue by Henry Kirke
  Brown), Henry Ward Beecher, Peter Cooper, Horace Greeley, Henry Bergh,
  Henry George and James Gordon Bennett. At the main entrance is a
  beautiful gateway (of elaborately wrought brown stone), 142 ft. wide and
  having a central tower 100 ft. in height. Along the north-east border of
  the borough are Cypress Hills cemetery (400 acres), adjoining Brooklyn
  Forest Park, and the cemetery of the Evergreens (about 375 acres),
  adjoining Highland Park and partly in the borough of Queens.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page648">[v.04 p.0648]</ph>
      </p>
      <p>In the plaza at the northern entrance to Prospect Park is a soldiers'
  and sailors' memorial arch (80 ft. in width and 71 ft. in height),
  adorned with high-reliefs of Lincoln and Grant on horseback (by O'Donovan
  and Eakins) and with three large bronze groups (by Frederick MacMonnies).
  Immediately within the park there is a statue (also by MacMonnies) of
  J.S.T. Stranahan (1808-1898), who did more than any other man for the
  development of Brooklyn's system of parks and boulevards. On the slope of
  Lookout Hill (185 ft.) within the park is a shaft erected in 1895 to the
  memory of the Maryland soldiers who valiantly defended the rear of the
  American army at the battle of Long Island. A bronze statue of Abraham
  Lincoln overlooks the lake. In Fort Greene Park is a monument to the
  memory of the soldiers who died in the British prison ships during the
  War of Independence, many of them having been buried in a vault below.
  Facing the borough hall is a statue in bronze (by J.Q.A. Ward) of Henry
  Ward Beecher, mounted on a granite pedestal with a figure at one side to
  commemorate Beecher's sympathy for the slave. A fine bronze statue of
  Alexander Hamilton (by W.O. Partridge, b. 1861) stands at the entrance of
  the Hamilton Club in Clinton Street and one of U.S. Grant (also by
  Partridge) stands at the entrance of the Union League Club in Bedford
  Avenue.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Education</i>.—The Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences
  embraces twenty-six departments, of which those of music, philology and
  the fine arts have each more than 1000 members; the total membership of
  all departments in 1906 was 5894. The museum building of this institution
  is in Institute Park, which is separated from Prospect Park on the
  north-east by Flatbush Avenue. It contains, besides paintings and
  statuary, special collections for service in nearly all of the
  departments; among its purely art collections the most notable is that of
  J.J.J. Tissot's water-colour drawings, to illustrate the life of Christ.
  Since 1890 the Institute has received appropriations from the city, but
  it is maintained chiefly by private contributions. It is the outgrowth of
  the Apprentices' Library Association, founded in 1824, of which General
  Lafayette laid the corner-stone on the 4th of July of that year. In 1888
  Franklin W. Hooper (b. 1851), who did much to increase the efficiency of
  the work of the Institute, became director. Pratt Institute, founded in
  1887 by Charles Pratt (1830-1891), and the residuary legatee of his wife,
  who died in 1907, is one of the most successful manual and industrial
  training schools in the country, and its kindergarten normal is one of
  the best known in the United States. The Polytechnic Institute, opened in
  1855, is a high-grade school of science and liberal arts. It has two
  general departments, the college of arts and engineering and the
  preparatory school, which are conducted independently of one another. In
  connexion with the college there is provision for graduate study and for
  night courses, and there are teachers' courses to which women are
  admitted. The Packer Collegiate Institute, opened as the successor of the
  Brooklyn Female Academy, in 1854, and endowed by Mrs Harriet L. Packer,
  an institution for women, has primary, preparatory, academic and
  collegiate departments. Adelphi College, opened in 1896, is for both
  sexes and gives special attention to normal training; it is the outgrowth
  of Adelphi Academy, founded in 1869, now the preparatory department. St
  Francis' College, opened in 1858, and St John's College, opened in 1870,
  are institutions maintained by Roman Catholics. Here, too, are the law
  school of St Lawrence University, the Long Island Hospital Medical
  College, with a training school for nurses, the Brooklyn College of
  Pharmacy and several schools of music. Brooklyn's public schools rank
  especially high; among them there is a commercial high school and a
  manual training high school. Among the larger libraries of the borough
  are the Brooklyn public library, those of the Long Island Historical
  Society, on Brooklyn Heights, of Pratt Institute, and of the King's
  County Medical Society, and a good law library. The <i>Brooklyn Daily
  Eagle</i>, which occupies an attractive building near the borough hall,
  has been a newspaper of strong influence in the community. It was
  established in 1841 as a Democratic organ, and Walt Whitman was its
  editor for about a year during its early history.</p>
      <p>Brooklyn is well provided with charitable institutions, and has long
  been known as the "city of churches," probably from the famous clergymen
  who have lived there. Among them were Henry Ward Beecher, pastor of
  Plymouth church (Congregational) from 1847 to 1887; Lyman Abbott, pastor
  of the same church from 1887 to 1898; Thomas De Witt Talmage, pastor of
  the Brooklyn Tabernacle (Presbyterian) from 1869 to 1894; Richard Salter
  Storrs (1821-1900), pastor of the church of the Pilgrims (Congregational)
  from 1846 to 1899; and Theodore L. Cuyler (1822-1909), pastor of the
  Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian church from 1860 to 1890.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Manufactures and Commerce.</i>—The borough of Brooklyn is one
  of the most important manufacturing centres in the United States, most of
  the factories being located along or near the East river north of the
  Brooklyn bridge. The total value of the manufactured products in 1890 was
  $270,823,754 and in 1900, $342,127,124, an increase during the decade of
  26.3%. In 1905 the total value of the borough's manufactured product
  (under the factory system) was $373,462,930, or 15% of the total
  manufactured product of the state of New York. Brooklyn's largest
  manufacturing industry is the refining of sugar, about one-half of the
  sugar consumed in the United States being refined here; in 1900 the
  product of the sugar and molasses refining establishments was valued at
  $77,942,997. Brooklyn is also an important place for the milling of
  coffee and spices (the 1905 product was valued at $15,274,092), the
  building of small boats, and the manufacture of foundry and machine shop
  products, malt liquors, barrels, shoes, chemicals, paints, cordage,
  twine, and hosiery and other knitted goods. Of its large commerce, grain
  is the chief commodity; it is estimated that about four-fifths of that
  exported from the port of New York is shipped from here, and the
  borough's grain elevators have an estimated storage capacity of about
  20,000,000 bushels.</p>
      <p>The water-supply system is owned and operated by the borough; the
  water is derived from streams flowing southward in the sparsely settled
  area east of the borough, and also from driven wells in the same region;
  it is pumped by ten engines at Ridgewood to a reservoir having a capacity
  of about 300,000,000 gallons, while a part of it is re-pumped to a high
  service reservoir near the north entrance to Prospect Park for the
  service of the most elevated part of the borough. Besides this system
  some towns in the south section recently annexed have their own
  water-supply.</p>
      <p>
         <i>History.</i>—The first settlement within the present limits
  of Brooklyn was made in 1636, when some Dutch farmers took up their
  residence along the shore of Gowanus Bay. About the same time other Dutch
  farmers founded Flatlands (at first called Amersfoort), on Jamaica Bay,
  and a few Walloons founded Wallabout, where the navy yard now is. In 1642
  a ferry was established across East river from the present foot of Fulton
  Street, and a settlement grew up here which was known as The Ferry. The
  next year Lady Deborah Moody with some followers from New England founded
  Gravesend near the southern extremity of the borough. Finally, in the
  year 1645, a settlement was established near the site of the present
  borough hall, and was called Breuckelen (also spelled Breucklyn,
  Breuckland, Brucklyn, Broucklyn, Brookland and Brookline) until about the
  close of the 18th century, when its orthography became fixed as Brooklyn.
  The name, Breuckelen, meaning marsh land, seems to have been suggested by
  the resemblance of the situation of the settlement to that of Breuckelen,
  Holland. Of the other towns which were later united to form the borough,
  New Utrecht was settled about 1650, Flatbush (at first called Medwoud,
  Midwout or Midwood) about 1651, Bushwick and Williamsburg in 1660. All of
  the settlements were for a long time chiefly agricultural communities.
  Flatbush was for a few years immediately preceding 1675 the largest; but
  Brooklyn was the first (1646) to have a township organization, and within
  a few years Wallabout, Gowanus, The Ferry, and Bedford—a new
  settlement to the south-east of Wallabout, established in 1662—were
  included within its jurisdiction. In 1654 the municipal privileges of
  Brooklyn as well as of two of the other towns were enlarged, <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page649">[v.04
  p.0649]</ph>but with Dutch rule there was general discontent, and when,
  in 1664, Colonel Richard Nicolls came to overthrow it and establish
  English rule these towns offered no resistance. Nicolls erected the
  region composed of Long Island, Staten Island and Westchester into a
  county under the name of Yorkshire, and divided it into three ridings, of
  which Staten Island, the present county of Kings, and the town of Newtown
  in Queens, formed one. In 1683 the present county of Kings was organized
  by the first colonial legislature. During the War of Independence the
  chief event was the battle of Long Island, fought on the 27th of August
  1776. In 1816, when the population of the town of Brooklyn was about
  4500, its most populous section was incorporated as a village; and in
  1834, when its population had increased to 23,310, the whole town was
  incorporated as a city. By 1850 its population had increased to 138,882.
  In 1855 Williamsburg, which had been incorporated as a city in 1851, and
  the town of Bushwick were annexed. Other annexations followed until the
  city of Brooklyn was conterminous with Kings county; and finally, on the
  1st of January 1898, the city of Brooklyn became a borough of New York
  City.</p>
      <p>See S.M. Ostrander, <i>A History of Brooklyn and Kings County</i>
  (Brooklyn, 1894); H.W.B. Howard (ed.), <i>History of the City of
  Brooklyn</i> (Brooklyn, 1893); and H. Putnam, <i>Brooklyn</i>, in L.P.
  Powell's <i>Historic Towns of the Middle States</i> (New York, 1899).</p>
   </body>
</topic>