<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25359">
   <title>BRÜHL</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRÜHL, HEINRICH,--> <ph outputclass="sc">Count von</ph> (1700-1763),
  German statesman at the court of Saxony, was born on the 13th of August
  1700. He was the son of Johann Moritz von Brühl, a noble who held the
  office of <i>Oberhofmarschall</i> at the small court of
  Sachsen-Weissenfels. The father was ruined and compelled to part with his
  family estate, which passed into the hands of the prince. The son was
  first placed as page with the dowager duchess of Weissenfels, and was
  then received at her recommendation into the court of the elector of
  Saxony as <i>Silberpage</i> on the 16th of April 1719. He rapidly
  acquired the favour of the elector Frederick Augustus, surnamed the
  Strong, who had been elected to the throne of Poland in 1697. Brühl, who
  began as page and chamberlain, was largely employed in procuring money
  for his profuse master. He made himself useful in muzzling the Saxon
  states and was successively chief receiver of taxes and minister for the
  interior in 1731. He was at Warsaw when his master died in 1733, and he
  secured a hold on the confidence of the electoral prince, Frederick
  Augustus, who was at Dresden, by laying hands on the papers and jewels of
  the late ruler and bringing them promptly to his successor. During the
  whole of the thirty years of the reign of Frederick Augustus II. he was
  the real inspirer of his master and the practical chief of the Saxon
  court. He had for a time to put up with the presence of old servants of
  the electoral house, but after 1738 he was in effect sole minister. The
  title of prime minister was created for him in 1746, but he was not only
  a prime minister—he filled all the offices. His titles spread over
  several lines of print, and he drew the combined pay of the places
  besides securing huge grants of land. Brühl must therefore be held wholly
  responsible for the ruinous policy which destroyed the position of Saxony
  in Germany between 1733 and 1763; for the mistaken ambition which led
  Frederick Augustus II. to become a candidate for the throne of Poland;
  for the engagements into which he entered in order to secure the support
  of the emperor Charles VI.; for the shameless and ill-timed
  tergiversations of Saxony during the wars of the Austrian Succession; for
  the intrigues which entangled the electorate in the alliance against
  Frederick the Great, which led to the Seven Years' War; and for the waste
  and want of foresight which left the country utterly unprepared to resist
  the attack of the king of Prussia. He was not only without political or
  military capacity, but was so garrulous that he could not keep a secret.
  His indiscretion was repeatedly responsible for the king of Prussia's
  discoveries of the plans laid against him. Nothing could shake the
  confidence of his master, which survived the ignominious flight into
  Bohemia, into which he was trapped by Brühl at the time of the battle of
  Kesseldorf, and all the miseries of the Seven Years' War. The favourite
  abused the confidence of his master shamelessly. Not content with the
  67,000 talers a month which he drew as salary for his innumerable
  offices, he was found when an inquiry was held in the next reign to have
  abstracted more than five million talers of public money for his private
  use. He left the work of the government offices to be done by his
  lackeys, whom he did not even supervise. His profusion was boundless.
  Twelve tailors, it is said, were continually employed in making clothes
  for him, and he wore a new suit every day. His library of 70,000 volumes
  was one of his forms of ostentation, and so was his gallery of pictures.
  He died on the 28th of October 1763, having survived his master only for
  a few weeks. The new elector, Frederick Christian, dismissed him from
  office and caused an inquiry to be held into his administration. His
  fortune was found to amount to a million and a half of talers, and was
  sequestered but afterwards restored to his family. In 1736 he had been
  made a count of the Empire and had married the countess Franziska von
  Kolowrat-Kradowska, a favourite of the wife of Frederick Augustus. Four
  sons and a daughter survived him.</p>
      <p>His youngest son, Hans Moritz von Brühl (d. 1811), was before the
  Revolution of 1789 a colonel in the French service, and afterwards
  general inspector of roads in Brandenburg and Pomerania. By his wife
  Margarethe Schleierweber, the daughter of a French corporal, but renowned
  for her beauty and intellectual gifts, he was the father of Karl
  Friedrich Moritz Paul von Brühl (1772-1837), the friend of Goethe, who as
  intendant-general of the Prussian royal theatres was of some importance
  in the history of the development of the drama in Germany. In 1830 he was
  appointed intendant-general of the royal museums.</p>
      <p>See J. G. H. von Justi, <i>Leben und Charakter des Grafen von
  Brühl</i> (Göttingen, 1760-1761).</p>
   </body>
</topic>