<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" []>
<topic id="d1e31765">
  <title>BUDDHISM</title>
  <body>
    <p><!--BUDDHISM,--> the religion held by the followers of the Buddha
  (<i>q.v.</i>), and covering a large area in India and east and central
  Asia.</p>
    <p>
         <i>Essential Doctrines.</i>—We are fortunate in having preserved
  for us the official report of the Buddha&apos;s discourse, in which he
  expounded what he considered the main features of his system to the five
  men he first tried to win over to his new-found faith. There is no reason
  to doubt its substantial accuracy, not as to words, but as to purport. In
  any case it is what the compilers of the oldest extant documents believed
  their teacher to have regarded as the most important points in his
  teaching. Such a summary must be better than any that could now be made.
  It is incorporated into two divisions of their sacred books, first among
  the <i>suttas</i> containing the doctrine, and again in the rules of the
  society or order he founded (<i>Samyutta</i>, v. 421 = <i>Vinaya</i>, i.
  10). The gist of it, omitting a few repetitions, is as
  follows:—</p>
    <lq>
      <p>&quot;There are two aims which he who has given up the world ought not to
  follow after—devotion, on the one hand, to those things whose
  attractions depend upon the passions, a low and pagan ideal, fit only for
  the worldly-minded, ignoble, unprofitable, and the practice on the other
  hand of asceticism, which is painful, ignoble, unprofitable. There is a
  Middle Path discovered by the Tathāgata<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_301" type="fn">
<!--[1]-->        </xref>—a path which opens the
  eyes, and bestows understanding, which leads to peace, to insight, to the
  higher wisdom, to Nirvāna. Verily! it is this Noble Eightfold Path;
  that is to say, Right Views, Right Aspirations, Right Speech, Right
  Conduct, Right Mode of Livelihood, Right Effort, Right Mindfulness, and
  Right Rapture.</p>
      <p>&quot;Now this is the Noble Truth as to suffering. Birth is attended with
  pain, decay is painful, disease is painful, death is painful. Union with
  the unpleasant is painful, painful is separation from the pleasant; and
  any craving unsatisfied, that too is painful. In brief, the five
  aggregates of clinging (that is, the conditions of individuality) are
  painful.</p>
      <p>&quot;Now this is the Noble Truth as to the origin of suffering. Verily! it
  is the craving thirst that causes the renewal of becomings, that is
  accompanied by sensual delights, and seeks satisfaction now here, now
  there—that is to say, the craving for the gratification of the
  senses, or the craving for a future life, or the craving for
  prosperity.</p>
      <p>
            <ph id="page743" outputclass="pagenum">[v.04 p.0743]</ph>
         </p>
      <p>&quot;Now this is the Noble Truth as to the passing away of pain. Verily!
  it is the passing away so that no passion remains, the giving up, the
  getting rid of, the being emancipated from, the harbouring no longer of
  this craving thirst.</p>
      <p>&quot;Now this is the Noble Truth as to the way that leads to the passing
  away of pain. Verily! it is this Noble Eightfold Path, that is to say,
  Right Views, Right Aspirations, Right speech, conduct and mode of
  livelihood, Right Effort, Right Mindfulness and Right Rapture.&quot;</p>
    </lq>
    <p>A few words follow as to the threefold way in which the speaker
  claimed to have grasped each of these Four Truths. That is all. There is
  not a word about God or the soul, not a word about the Buddha or
  Buddhism. It seems simple, almost jejune; so thin and weak that one
  wonders how it can have formed the foundation for a system so mighty in
  its historical results. But the simple words are pregnant with meaning.
  Their implications were clear enough to the hearers to whom they were
  addressed. They were not intended, however, to answer the questionings of
  a 20th-century European questioner, and are liable now to be
  misunderstood. Fortunately each word, each clause, each idea in the
  discourse is repeated, commented on, enlarged upon, almost <i>ad nauseam</i>, in the <i>suttas</i>, and a short comment in the light of
  those explanations may bring out the meaning that was meant.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_302" type="fn">
<!--[2]-->      </xref>
      </p>
    <p>The passing away of pain or suffering is said to depend on an
  emancipation. And the Buddha is elsewhere (<i>Vinaya</i> ii. 239) made to
  declare: &quot;Just as the great ocean has one taste only, the taste of salt,
  just so have this doctrine and discipline but one flavour only, the
  flavour of emancipation&quot;; and again, &quot;When a brother has, by himself,
  known and realized, and continues to abide, here in this visible world,
  in that emancipation of mind, in that emancipation of heart, which is
  Arahatship; that is a condition higher still and sweeter still, for the
  sake of which the brethren lead the religious life under me.&quot;<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_303" type="fn">
<!--[3]-->      </xref> The
  emancipation is found in a habit of mind, in the being free from a
  specified sort of craving that is said to be the origin of certain
  specified sorts of pain. In some European books this is completely
  spoiled by being represented as the doctrine that existence is misery,
  and that desire is to be suppressed. Nothing of the kind is said in the
  text. The description of suffering or pain is, in fact, a string of
  truisms, quite plain and indisputable until the last clause. That clause
  declares that the <i>Upādāna Skandhas</i>, the five groups of
  the constituent parts of every individual, involve pain. Put into modern
  language this is that the conditions necessary to make an individual are
  also the conditions that necessarily give rise to sorrow. No sooner has
  an individual become separate, become an individual, than disease and
  decay begin to act upon it. Individuality involves limitation, limitation
  in its turn involves ignorance, and ignorance is the source of sorrow.
  Union with the unpleasant, separation from the pleasant, unsatisfied
  craving, are each a result of individuality. This is a deeper
  generalization than that which says, &quot;A man is born to trouble as the
  sparks fly upward.&quot; But it is put forward as a mere statement of fact.
  And the previous history of religious belief in India would tend to show
  that emphasis was laid on the fact, less as an explanation of the origin
  of evil, than as a protest against a then current pessimistic idea that
  salvation could not be reached on earth, and must therefore be sought for
  in a rebirth in heaven, in the <i>Brahmaloka</i>. For if the
  fact—the fact that the conditions of individuality are the
  conditions, also, of pain—were admitted, then the individual there
  would still not have escaped from sorrow. If the five ascetics to whom
  the words were addressed once admitted this implication, logic would
  drive them also to admit all that followed.</p>
    <p>The threefold division of craving at the end of the second truth might
  be rendered &quot;the lust of the flesh, the lust of life and the love of this
  present world.&quot; The two last are said elsewhere to be directed against
  two sets of thinkers called the Eternalists and the Annihilationists, who
  held respectively the everlasting-life-heresy and the
  let-us-eat-and-drink-for-tomorrow-we-die-heresy.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_304" type="fn">
<!--[4]-->      </xref> This may be so, but in any case
  the division of craving would have appealed to the five hearers as
  correct.</p>
    <p>The word translated &quot;noble&quot; in Noble Path, Noble Truth, is
  <i>ariya</i>, which also means Aryan.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_305" type="fn">
<!--[5]-->      </xref> The negative, un-Aryan, is used
  of each of the two low aims. It is possible that this rendering should
  have been introduced into the translation; but the ethical meaning,
  though still associated with the tribal meaning, had probably already
  become predominant in the language of the time.</p>
    <p>The details of the Path include several terms whose meaning and
  implication are by no means apparent at first sight. Right Views, for
  instance, means mainly right views as to the Four Truths and the Three
  Signs. Of the latter, one is identical, or nearly so, with the First
  Truth. The others are Impermanence and Non-soul (the absence of a
  soul)—both declared to be &quot;signs&quot; of every individual, whether god,
  animal or man. Of these two again the Impermanence has become an Indian
  rather than a Buddhist idea, and we are to a certain extent familiar with
  it also in the West. There is no Being, there is only a Becoming. The
  state of every individual is unstable, temporary, sure to pass away. Even
  in the lowest class of things, we find, in each individual, form and
  material qualities. In the higher classes there is a continually rising
  series of mental qualities also. It is the union of these that makes the
  individual. Every person, or thing, or god, is therefore a putting
  together, a compound; and in each individual, without any exception, the
  relation of its component parts is ever changing, is never the same for
  two consecutive moments. It follows that no sooner has separateness,
  individuality, begun, than dissolution, disintegration, also begins.
  There can be no individuality without a putting together: there can be no
  putting together without a becoming: there can be no becoming without a
  becoming different: and there can be no becoming different without a
  dissolution, a passing away, which sooner or later will inevitably be
  complete.</p>
    <p>Heracleitus, who was a generation or two later than the Buddha, had
  very similar ideas;<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_306" type="fn">
<!--[6]-->      </xref> and similar ideas are found in
  post-Buddhistic Indian works.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_307" type="fn">
<!--[7]-->      </xref> But in neither case are they
  worked out in the same uncompromising way. Both in Europe, and in all
  Indian thought except the Buddhist, souls, and the gods who are made in
  imitation of souls, are considered as exceptions. To these spirits is
  attributed a Being without Becoming, an individuality without change, a
  beginning without an end. To hold any such view would, according to the
  doctrine of the Noble (or Aryan) Path, be erroneous, and the error would
  block the way against the very entrance on the Path.</p>
    <p>So important is this position in Buddhism that it is put in the
  forefront of Buddhist expositions of Buddhism. The Buddha himself is
  stated in the books to have devoted to it the very first discourse he
  addressed to the first converts.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_308" type="fn">
<!--[8]-->      </xref> The first in the collection of
  the <i>Dialogues of Gotama</i> discusses, and completely, categorically,
  and systematically rejects, all the current theories about &quot;souls.&quot; Later
  books follow these precedents. Thus the <i>Kathā Vatthu</i>, the
  latest book included in the canon, discusses points of disagreement that
  had arisen in the community. It places this question of &quot;soul&quot; at the
  head of all the points it deals with, and devotes to it an amount of
  space quite overshadowing all the rest.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_309" type="fn">
<!--[9]-->      </xref> So also in the earliest Buddhist
  book later than the canon—the very interesting and suggestive
  series of conversations between the Greek king Menander and the Buddhist
  teacher Nāgasena. It is precisely this question of the &quot;soul&quot; that
  the unknown author takes up first, describing how Nāgasena
  convinces the king that there is no such thing as the <ph id="page744" outputclass="pagenum">[v.04 p.0744]</ph>&quot;soul&quot;
  in the ordinary sense, and he returns to the subject again and again.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3010" type="fn">
<!--[10]-->      </xref>
      </p>
    <p>After Right Views come Right Aspirations. It is evil desires, low
  ideals, useless cravings, idle excitements, that are to be suppressed by
  the cultivation of the opposite—of right desires, lofty
  aspirations. In one of the Dialogues<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3011" type="fn">
<!--[11]-->      </xref> instances are given—the
  desire for emancipation from sensuality, aspirations towards the
  attainment of love to others, the wish not to injure any living thing,
  the desire for the eradication of wrong and for the promotion of right
  dispositions in one&apos;s own heart, and so on. This portion of the Path is
  indeed quite simple, and would require no commentary were it not for the
  still constantly repeated blunder that Buddhism teaches the suppression
  of all desire.</p>
    <p>Of the remaining stages of the Path it is only necessary to mention
  two. The one is Right Effort. A constant intellectual alertness is
  required. This is not only insisted upon elsewhere in countless passages,
  but of the three cardinal sins in Buddhism (<i>rāga</i>,
  <i>dosa</i>, <i>moha</i>) the last and worst is stupidity or dullness,
  the others being sensuality and ill-will. Right Effort is closely
  connected with the seventh stage, Right Mindfulness. Two of the dialogues
  are devoted to this subject, and it is constantly referred to
  elsewhere.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3012" type="fn">
<!--[12]-->      </xref> The disciple, whatsoever he
  does—whether going forth or coming back, standing or walking,
  speaking or silent, eating or drinking—is to keep clearly in mind
  all that it means, the temporary character of the act, its ethical
  significance, and above all that behind the act there is no actor (goer,
  seer, eater, speaker) that is an eternally persistent unity. It is the
  Buddhist analogue to the Christian precept: &quot;Whether therefore ye eat or
  drink, or whatsoever ye do, do all to the glory of God.&quot;</p>
    <p>Under the head of Right Conduct the two most important points are Love
  and Joy. Love is in Pāli <i>Mettā</i>, and the <i>Metta Sutta</i>
         <xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3013" type="fn">
<!--[13]-->      </xref> says (no doubt with reference
  to the Right Mindfulness just described): &quot;As a mother, even at the risk
  of her own life, protects her son, her only son, so let him cultivate
  love without measure towards all beings. Let him cultivate towards the
  whole world—above, below, around—a heart of love unstinted,
  unmixed with the sense of differing or opposing interests. Let a man
  maintain this mindfulness all the while he is awake, whether he be
  standing, walking, sitting or lying down. This state of heart is the best
  in the world.&quot;</p>
    <p>Often elsewhere four such states are described, the Brahma
  Vihāras or Sublime Conditions. They are Love, Sorrow at the sorrows
  of others, Joy in the joys of others, and Equanimity as regards one&apos;s own
  joys and sorrows.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3014" type="fn">
<!--[14]-->      </xref> Each of these feelings was to
  be deliberately practised, beginning with a single object, and gradually
  increasing till the whole world was suffused with the feeling. &quot;Our mind
  shall not waver. No evil speech will we utter. Tender and compassionate
  will we abide, loving in heart, void of malice within. And we will be
  ever suffusing such a one with the rays of our loving thought. And with
  that feeling as a basis we will ever be suffusing the whole wide world
  with thought of love far-reaching, grown great, beyond measure, void of
  anger or ill-will.&quot;<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3015" type="fn">
<!--[15]-->      </xref>
      </p>
    <p>The relative importance of love, as compared with other habits, is
  thus described. &quot;All the means that can be used as bases for doing right
  are not worth the sixteenth part of the emancipation of the heart through
  love. That takes all those up into itself, outshining them in radiance
  and glory. Just as whatsoever stars there be, their radiance avails not
  the sixteenth part of the radiance of the moon. That takes all those up
  into itself, outshining them in radiance and glory—just as in the
  last month of the rains, at harvest time, the sun, mounting up on high
  into the clear and cloudless sky, overwhelms all darkness in the realms
  of space, and shines forth in radiance and glory—just as in the
  night, when the dawn is breaking, the morning star shines out in radiance
  and glory—just so all the means that can be used as helps towards
  doing right avail not the sixteenth part of the emancipation of the heart
  through love.&quot;<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3016" type="fn">
<!--[16]-->      </xref>
      </p>
    <p>The above is the positive side; the qualities (<i>dhammā</i>)
  that have to be acquired. The negative side, the qualities that have to
  be suppressed by the cultivation of the opposite virtues, are the Ten
  Bonds (<i>Samyojanas</i>), the Four Intoxications
  (<i>Āsavā</i>) and the Five Hindrances
  (<i>Nīvaranas</i>).</p>
    <p>The Ten Bonds are: (1) Delusion about the soul; (2) Doubt; (3)
  Dependence on good works; (4) Sensuality; (5) Hatred, ill-feeling; (6)
  Love of life on earth; (7) Desire for life in heaven; (8) Pride; (9)
  Self-righteousness; (10) Ignorance. The Four Intoxications are the mental
  intoxication arising respectively from (1) Bodily passions, (2) Becoming,
  (3) Delusion, (4) Ignorance. The Five Hindrances are (1) Hankering after
  worldly advantages, (2) The corruption arising out of the wish to injure,
  (3) Torpor of mind, (4) Fretfulness and worry, (5) Wavering of mind.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3017" type="fn">
<!--[17]-->      </xref> &quot;When
  these five hindrances have been cut away from within him, he looks upon
  himself as freed from debt, rid of disease, out of jail, a free man and
  secure. And gladness springs up within him on his realizing that, and joy
  arises to him thus gladdened, and so rejoicing all his frame becomes at
  ease, and being thus at ease he is filled with a sense of peace, and in
  that peace his heart is stayed.&quot;<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3018" type="fn">
<!--[18]-->      </xref>
      </p>
    <p>To have realized the Truths, and traversed the Path; to have broken
  the Bonds, put an end to the Intoxications, and got rid of the
  Hindrances, is to have attained the ideal, the Fruit, as it is called, of
  Arahatship. One might fill columns with the praises, many of them among
  the most beautiful passages in Pāli poetry and prose, lavished on
  this condition of mind, the state of the man made perfect according to
  the Buddhist faith. Many are the pet names, the poetic epithets bestowed
  upon it—the harbour of refuge, the cool cave, the island amidst the
  floods, the place of bliss, emancipation, liberation, safety, the
  supreme, the transcendent, the uncreated, the tranquil, the home of
  peace, the calm, the end of suffering, the medicine for all evil, the
  unshaken, the ambrosia, the immaterial, the imperishable, the abiding,
  the farther shore, the unending, the bliss of effort, the supreme joy,
  the ineffable, the detachment, the holy city, and many others. Perhaps
  the most frequent in the Buddhist text is Arahatship, &quot;the state of him
  who is worthy&quot;; and the one exclusively used in Europe is Nirvāna,
  the &quot;dying out&quot;; that is, the dying out in the heart of the fell fire of
  the three cardinal sins—sensuality, ill-will and stupidity.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3019" type="fn">
<!--[19]-->      </xref>
      </p>
    <p>The choice of this term by European writers, a choice made long before
  any of the Buddhist canonical texts had been published or translated, has
  had a most unfortunate result. Those writers did not share, could not be
  expected to share, the exuberant optimism of the early Buddhists.
  Themselves giving up this world as hopeless, and looking for salvation in
  the next, they naturally thought the Buddhists must do the same, and in
  the absence of any authentic scriptures, to correct the mistake, they
  interpreted Nirvāna, in terms of their own belief, as a state to be
  reached after death. As such they supposed the &quot;dying out&quot; must mean the
  dying out of a &quot;soul&quot;; and endless were the discussions as to whether
  this meant eternal trance, or absolute annihilation, of the &quot;soul.&quot; It is
  now thirty years since the right interpretation, founded on the canonical
  texts, has been given, but outside the ranks of Pāli scholars the
  old blunder is still often repeated. It should be added that the belief
  in salvation in this world, in this life, has appealed so strongly to
  Indian sympathies that from the time of the rise of Buddhism down to the
  present day it has been adopted as a part of general Indian belief, and
  <i>Jīvanmukti</i>, salvation during this life, has become a
  commonplace in the religious language of India.</p>
    <p>
         <i>Adopted Doctrines.</i>—The above are the essential doctrines
  of <ph id="page745" outputclass="pagenum">[v.04 p.0745]</ph>the original Buddhism. They are at the same time its
  distinctive doctrines; that is to say, the doctrines that distinguish it
  from all previous teaching in India. But the Buddha, while rejecting the
  sacrifices and the ritualistic magic of the brahmin schools, the
  animistic superstitions of the people, the asceticism and soul-theory of
  the Jains, and the pantheistic speculations of the poets of the
  pre-Buddhistic <i>Upanishads</i>, still retained the belief in
  transmigration. This belief—the transmigration of the soul, after
  the death of the body, into other bodies, either of men, beasts or
  gods—is part of the animistic creed so widely found throughout the
  world that it was probably universal. In India it had already, before the
  rise of Buddhism, been raised into an ethical conception by the
  associated doctrine of <i>Karma</i>, according to which a man&apos;s social
  position in life and his physical advantages, or the reverse, were the
  result of his actions in a previous birth. The doctrine thus afforded an
  explanation, quite complete to those who believed it, of the apparent
  anomalies and wrongs in the distribution here of happiness or woe. A man,
  for instance, is blind. This is owing to his lust of the eye in a
  previous birth. But he has also unusual powers of hearing. This is
  because he loved, in a previous birth, to listen to the preaching of the
  law. The explanation could always be exact, for it was scarcely more than
  a repetition of the point to be explained. It fits the facts because it
  is derived from them. And it cannot be disproved, for it lies in a sphere
  beyond the reach of human inquiry.</p>
    <p>It was because it thus provided a moral cause that it was retained in
  Buddhism. But as the Buddha did not acknowledge a soul, the link of
  connexion between one life and the next had to be found somewhere else.
  The Buddha found it (as Plato also found it)<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3020" type="fn">
<!--[20]-->      </xref> in the influence exercised upon
  one life by a desire felt in the previous life. When two thinkers of such
  eminence (probably the two greatest ethical thinkers of antiquity) have
  arrived independently at this strange conclusion, have agreed in
  ascribing to cravings, felt in this life, so great, and to us so
  inconceivable, a power over the future life, we may well hesitate before
  we condemn the idea as intrinsically absurd, and we may take note of the
  important fact that, given similar conditions, similar stages in the
  development of religious belief, men&apos;s thoughts, even in spite of the
  most unquestioned individual originality, tend though they may never
  produce exactly the same results, to work in similar ways.</p>
    <p>In India, before Buddhism, conflicting and contradictory views
  prevailed as to the precise mode of action of <i>Karma</i>; and we find
  this confusion reflected in Buddhist theory. The prevailing views are
  tacked on, as it were, to the essential doctrines of Buddhism, without
  being thoroughly assimilated to them, or logically incorporated with
  them. Thus in the story of the good layman Citta, it is an aspiration
  expressed on the deathbed;<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3021" type="fn">
<!--[21]-->      </xref> in the dialogue on the subject,
  it is a thought dwelt on during life,<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3022" type="fn">
<!--[22]-->      </xref> in the numerous stories in the
  <i>Peta</i> and <i>Vimāna Vatthus</i> it is usually some isolated
  act, in the discussions in the <i>Dhamma Sangani</i> it is some mental
  disposition, which is the <i>Karma</i> (doing or action) in the one life
  determining the position of the individual in the next. These are really
  conflicting propositions. They are only alike in the fact that in each
  case a moral cause is given for the position in which the individual
  finds himself now; and the moral cause is his own act.</p>
    <p>In the popular belief, followed also in the brahmin theology, the
  bridge between the two lives was a minute and subtle entity called the
  soul, which left the one body at death, through a hole at the top of the
  head, and entered into the new body. The new body happened to be there,
  ready, with no soul in it. The soul did not make the body. In the
  Buddhist adaptation of this theory no soul, no consciousness, no memory,
  goes over from one body to the other. It is the grasping, the craving,
  still existing at the death of the one body that causes the new set of
  <i>Skandhas</i>, that is, the new body with its mental tendencies and
  capacities, to arise. How this takes place is nowhere explained.</p>
    <p>The Indian theory of <i>Karma</i> has been worked out with many points
  of great beauty and ethical value. And the Buddhist adaptation of it,
  avoiding some of the difficulties common to it and to the allied European
  theories of fate and predestination, tries to explain the weight of the
  universe in its action on the individual, the heavy hand of the
  immeasurable past we cannot escape, the close connexion between all forms
  of life, and the mysteries of inherited character. Incidentally it held
  out the hope, to those who believed in it, of a mode of escape from the
  miseries of transmigration. For as the Arahat had conquered the cravings
  that were supposed to produce the new body, his actions were no longer
  <i>Karma</i>, but only <i>Kiriyā</i>, that led to no rebirth.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3023" type="fn">
<!--[23]-->      </xref>
      </p>
    <p>Another point of Buddhist teaching adopted from previous belief was
  the practice of ecstatic meditation. In the very earliest times of the
  most remote animism we find the belief that a person, rapt from all sense
  of the outside world, possessed by a spirit, acquired from that state a
  degree of sanctity, was supposed to have a degree of insight, denied to
  ordinary mortals. In India from the soma frenzy in the <i>Vedas</i>,
  through the mystic reveries of the <i>Upanishads</i>, and the hypnotic
  trances of the ancient Yoga, allied beliefs and practices had never lost
  their importance and their charm. It is clear from the <i>Dialogues</i>,
  and other of the most ancient Buddhist records,<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3024" type="fn">
<!--[24]-->      </xref> that the belief was in full
  force when Buddhism arose, and that the practice was followed by the
  Buddha&apos;s teachers. It was quite impossible for him to ignore the
  question; and the practice was admitted as a part of the training of the
  Buddhist Bhikshu. But it was not the highest or the most important part,
  and might be omitted altogether. The states of Rapture are called
  Conditions of Bliss, and they are regarded as useful for the help they
  give towards the removal of the mental obstacles to the attainment of
  Arahatship.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3025" type="fn">
<!--[25]-->      </xref> Of the thirty-seven constituent
  parts of Arahatship they enter into one group of four. To seek for
  Arahatship in the practice of the ecstasy alone is considered a deadly
  heresy.<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3026" type="fn">
<!--[26]-->      </xref>
  So these practices are both pleasant in themselves, and useful as one of
  the means to the end proposed. But they are not the end, and the end can
  be reached without them. The most ancient form these exercises took is
  recorded in the often recurring paragraphs translated in Rhys Davids&apos;
  <i>Dialogues of the Buddha</i> (i. 84-92). More modern, and much more
  elaborate, forms are given in the <i>Yogāvacaras Manual of Indian Mysticism as practised by Buddhists</i>, edited by Rhys Davids from a
  unique MS. for the Pāli Text Society in 1896. In the Introduction
  to this last work the various phases of the question are discussed at
  length.</p>
    <p>
         <i>Buddhist Texts. The Canonical Books.</i>—It is necessary to
  remember that the Buddha, like other Indian teachers of his period,
  taught by conversation only. A highly-educated man (according to the
  education current at the time), speaking constantly to men of similar
  education, he followed the literary habit of his day by embodying his
  doctrines in set phrases (<i>sūtras</i>), on which he enlarged, on
  different occasions, in different ways. Writing was then widely known.
  But the lack of suitable writing materials made any lengthy books
  impossible. Such sūtras were therefore the recognized form of
  preserving and communicating opinion. They were catchwords, as it were,
  <i>memoria technica</i>, which could easily be remembered, and would
  recall the fuller expositions that had been based upon them. Shortly
  after the Buddha&apos;s time the Brahmins had their sūtras in Sanskrit,
  already a dead language. He purposely put his into the ordinary
  conversational idiom of the day, that is to say, into Pāli. When
  the Buddha died these sayings were collected together by his disciples
  into what they call the Four Nikāyas, or &quot;collections.&quot; These
  cannot have reached their final form till about fifty or sixty years
  afterwards. Other sayings and verses, most of them ascribed, not to the
  Buddha, but to the disciples themselves, were put into a supplementary
  Nikāya. We know <ph id="page746" outputclass="pagenum">[v.04 p.0746]</ph>of slight additions made to this
  Nikāya as late as the time of Asoka, 3rd century <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph> And the developed doctrine, found in certain
  portions of it, shows that these are later than the four old
  Nikāyas. For a generation or two the books so put together were
  handed down by memory, though probably written memoranda were also used.
  And they were doubtless accompanied from the first, as they were being
  taught, by a running commentary. About one hundred years after the
  Buddha&apos;s death there was a schism in the community. Each of the two
  schools kept an arrangement of the canon—still in Pāli, or
  some allied dialect. Sanskrit was not used for any Buddhist works till
  long afterwards, and never used at all, so far as is known, for the
  canonical books. Each of these two schools broke up in the following
  centuries, into others. Several of them had their different arrangements
  of the canonical books, differing also in minor details. These books
  remained the only authorities for about five centuries, but they all,
  except only our extant Pāli Nikāyas, have been lost in India.
  These then are our authorities for the earliest period of Buddhism. Now
  what are these books?</p>
    <p>We talk necessarily of Pāli <i>books</i>. They are not books in
  the modern sense. They are memorial sentences or verses intended to be
  learnt by heart. And the whole style and method of arrangement is
  entirely subordinated to this primary necessity. Each sūtra
  (Pāli, <i>sutta</i>) is very short; usually occupying only a page,
  or perhaps two, and containing a single proposition. When several of
  these, almost always those that contain propositions of a similar kind,
  are collected together in the framework of one dialogue, it is called a
  <i>sullanta</i>. The usual length of such a suttanta is about a dozen
  pages; only a few of them are longer, and a collection of such suttantas
  might be called a book. But it is as yet neither narrative nor essay. It
  is at most a string of passages, drawn up in similar form to assist the
  memory, and intended, not to be read, but to be learnt by heart. The
  first of the four Nikāyas is a collection of the longest of these
  suttantas, and it is called accordingly the <i>Dīgha Nikāya</i>, that is &quot;the Collection of Long Ones&quot; (<i>sci.</i>
  Suttantas). The next is the <i>Majjhima Nikāya</i>, the &quot;Collection
  of the suttantas of Medium Length&quot;—medium, that is, as being
  shorter than the suttantas in the Dīgha, and longer than the
  ordinary suttas preserved in the two following collections. Between them
  these first two collections contain 186 dialogues, in which the Buddha,
  or in a few cases one of his leading disciples, is represented as engaged
  in conversation on some one of the religious, or philosophic, or ethical
  points in that system which we now call Buddhism. In depth of philosophic
  insight, in the method of Socratic questioning often adopted, in the
  earnest and elevated tone of the whole, in the evidence they afford of
  the most cultured thought of the day, these dialogues constantly remind
  the reader of the dialogues of Plato. But not in style. They have indeed
  a style of their own; always dignified, and occasionally rising into
  eloquence. But for the reasons already given, it is entirely different
  from the style of Western writings which are always intended to be read.
  Historical scholars will, however, revere this collection of dialogues as
  one of the most priceless of the treasures of antiquity still preserved
  to us. It is to it, above all, that we shall always have to go for our
  knowledge of the most ancient Buddhism. Of the 186, 175 had by 1907 been
  edited for the Pāli Text Society, and the remainder were either in
  the press or in preparation.</p>
    <p>A disadvantage of the arrangement in dialogues, more especially as
  they follow one another according to length and not according to subject,
  is that it is not easy to find the statement of doctrine on any
  particular point which is interesting one at the moment. It is very
  likely just this consideration which led to the compilation of the two
  following Nikāyas. In the first of these, called the <i>Anguttara Nikāya</i>, all those points of Buddhist doctrine capable of
  expression in classes are set out in order. This practically includes
  most of the psychology and ethics of Buddhism. For it is a distinguishing
  mark of the dialogues themselves that the results arrived at are arranged
  in carefully systematized groups. We are familiar enough in the West with
  similar classifications, summed up in such expressions as the Seven
  Deadly Sins, the Ten Commandments, the Thirty-nine Articles, the Four
  Cardinal Virtues, the Seven Sacraments and a host of others. These
  numbered lists (it is true) are going out of fashion. The aid which they
  afford to memory is no longer required in an age in which books of
  reference abound. It was precisely as a help to memory that they were
  found so useful in the early Buddhist times, when the books were all
  learnt by heart, and had never as yet been written. And in the Anguttara
  we find set out in order first of all the units, then all the pairs, then
  all the trios, and so on. It is the longest book in the Buddhist Bible,
  and fills 1840 pages 8vo. The whole of the Pāli text has been
  published by the Pāli Text Society, but only portions have been
  translated into English. The next, and last, of these four collections
  contains again the whole, or nearly the whole, of the Buddhist doctrine;
  but arranged this time in order of subjects. It consists of 55
  <i>Samyuttas</i> or groups. In each of these the suttas on the same
  subject, or in one or two cases the suttas addressed to the same sort of
  people, are grouped together. The whole of it has been published in five
  volumes by the Pāli Text Society. Only a few fragments have been
  translated.</p>
    <p>Many hundreds of the short suttas and verses in these two collections
  are found, word for word, in the dialogues. And there are numerous
  instances of the introductory story stating how, and when, and to whom
  the sutta was enunciated—a sort of narrative framework in which the
  sutta is set—recurring also. This is very suggestive as to the way
  in which the earliest Buddhist records were gradually built up. The
  suttas came first embodying, in set phrases, the doctrine that had to be
  handed down. Those episodes, found in two or three different places, and
  always embodying several suttas, came next. Then several of these were
  woven together to form a suttanta. And finally the suttantas were grouped
  together into the two Nikāyas, and the suttas and episodes
  separately into the two others. Parallel with this evolution, so to say,
  of the suttas, the short statements of doctrine, in prose, ran the
  treatment of the verses. There was a great love of poetry in the
  communities in which Buddhism arose. Verses were helpful to the memory.
  And they were adopted not only for this reason. The adherents of the new
  view of life found pleasure in putting into appropriate verse the
  feelings of enthusiasm and of ecstasy which the reforming doctrines
  inspired. When particularly happy in literary finish, or peculiarly rich
  in religious feeling, such verses were not lost. These were handed on,
  from mouth to mouth, in the small companies of the brethren or sisters.
  The oldest verses are all lyrics, expressions either of emotion, or of
  some deep saying, some pregnant thought. Very few of them have been
  preserved alone. And even then they are so difficult to understand, so
  much like puzzles, that they were probably accompanied from the first by
  a sort of comment in prose, stating when, and why, and by whom they were
  supposed to have been uttered. As a general rule such a framework in
  prose is actually preserved in the old Buddhist literature. It is only in
  the very latest books included in the canon that the narrative part is
  also regularly in verse, so that a whole work consists of a collection of
  ballads. The last step, that of combining such ballads into one long epic
  poem, was not taken till after the canon was closed. The whole process,
  from the simple anecdote in mixed prose and verse, the so-called
  <i>ākhyāna</i>, to the complete epic, comes out with striking
  clearness in the history of the Buddhist canon. It is typical, one may
  notice in passing, of the evolution of the epic elsewhere; in Iceland,
  for instance, in Persia and in Greece. And we may safely draw the
  conclusion that if the great Indian epics, the Mahā-bhārata
  and the Rāmāyana, had been in existence when the formation of
  the Buddhist canon began, the course of its development would have been
  very different from what it was.</p>
    <p>As will easily be understood, the same reasons which led to literary
  activity of this kind, in the earliest period, continued to hold good
  afterwards. A number of such efforts, after the Nikāyas had been
  closed, were included in a supplementary Nikāya called the
  <i>Khuddaka Nikāya</i>. It will throw very useful light upon the
  intellectual level in the Buddhist community just <ph id="page747" outputclass="pagenum">[v.04 p.0747]</ph>after the
  earliest period, and upon literary life in the valley of the Ganges in
  the 4th or 5th century <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>, if we briefly
  explain what the tractates in this collection contain. The first, the
  <i>Khuddaka Pātha</i>, is a little tract of only a few pages. After
  a profession of faith in the Buddha, the doctrine and the order, there
  follows a paragraph setting out the thirty-four constituents of the human
  body—bones, blood, nerves and so on—strangely incongruous
  with what follows. For that is simply a few of the most beautiful poems
  to be found in the Buddhist scriptures. There is no apparent reason,
  except their exquisite versification, why these particular pieces should
  have been here brought together. It is most probable that this tiny
  volume was simply a sort of first lesson book for young neophytes when
  they joined the order. In any case that is one of the uses to which it is
  put at present. The text book is the <i>Dhammapada</i>. Here are brought
  together from ten to twenty stanzas on each of twenty-six selected points
  of Buddhist self-training or ethics. There are altogether 423 verses,
  gathered from various older sources, and strung together without any
  other internal connexion than that they relate more or less to the same
  subject. And the collector has not thought it necessary to choose stanzas
  written in the same metre, or in the same number of lines. We know that
  the early Christians were accustomed to sing hymns, both in their homes
  and on the occasions of their meeting together. These hymns are now
  irretrievably lost. Had some one made a collection of about twenty
  isolated stanzas, chosen from these hymns, on each of about twenty
  subjects—such as Faith, Hope, Love, the Converted Man, Times of
  Trouble, Quiet Days, the Saviour, the Tree of Life, the Sweet Name, the
  Dove, the King, the Land of Peace, the Joy Unspeakable—we should
  have a Christian Dhammapada, and very precious such a collection would
  be. The Buddhist Dhammapada has been edited by Professor Fausböll (2nd
  ed., 1900), and has been frequently translated. Where the verses deal
  with those ideas that are common to Christians and Buddhists, the
  versions are easily intelligible, and some of the stanzas appeal very
  strongly to the Western sense of religious beauty. Where the stanzas are
  full of the technical terms of the Buddhist system of self-culture and
  self-control, it is often impossible, without expansions that spoil the
  poetry, or learned notes that distract the attention, to convey the full
  sense of the original. In all these distinctively Buddhist verses the
  existing translations (of which Professor Max Müller&apos;s is the best known,
  and Dr Karl Neumann&apos;s the best) are inadequate and sometimes quite
  erroneous. The connexion in which they were spoken is often apparent in
  the more ancient books from which these verses have been taken, and has
  been preserved in the commentary on the work itself.</p>
    <p>In the next little work the framework, the whole paraphernalia of the
  ancient akhyāna, is included in the work itself, which is called
  <i>Udāna</i>, or &quot;ecstatic utterances.&quot; The Buddha is represented,
  on various occasions during his long career, to have been so much moved
  by some event, or speech, or action, that he gave vent, as it were, to
  his pent-up feelings in a short, ecstatic utterance, couched, for the
  most part, in one or two lines of poetry. These outbursts, very terse and
  enigmatic, are charged with religious emotion, and turn often on some
  subtle point of Arahatship, that is, of the Buddhist ideal of life. The
  original text has been published by the Pāli Text Society. The
  little book, a garland of fifty of these gems, has been translated by
  General Strong. The next work is called the <i>Iti Vuttaka</i>. This
  contains 120 short passages, each of them leading up to a terse deep
  saying of the Buddha&apos;s, and introduced, in each case, with the words
  <i>Iti vuttam Bhagavalā</i>—&quot;thus was it spoken by the
  Exalted One.&quot; These anecdotes may or may not be historically accurate. It
  is quite possible that the memory of the early disciples, highly trained
  as it was, enabled them to preserve a substantially true record of some
  of these speeches, and of the circumstances in which they were uttered.
  Some or all of them may also have been invented. In either case they are
  excellent evidence of the sort of questions on which discussions among
  the earliest Buddhists must have turned. These ecstatic utterances and
  deep sayings are attributed to the Buddha himself, and accompanied by the
  prose framework. There has also been preserved a collection of stanzas
  ascribed to his leading followers. Of these 107 are brethren, and 73
  sisters, in the order. The prose framework is in this case preserved only
  in the commentary, which also gives biographies of the authors. This work
  is called the <i>Thera-therī-gāthā</i>.</p>
    <p>Another interesting collection is the <i>Jātaka</i> book, a set
  of verses supposed to have been uttered by the Buddha in some of his
  previous births. These are really 550 of the folk-tales current in India
  when the canon was being formed, the only thing Buddhist about them being
  that the Buddha, in a previous birth, is identified in each case with the
  hero in the little story. Here again the prose is preserved only in the
  commentary. And it is a most fortunate chance that this—the oldest,
  the most complete, and the most authentic collection of folklore
  extant—has thus been preserved intact to the present day. Many of
  these stories and fables have wandered to Europe, and are found in
  medieval homilies, poems and story-books. A full account of this curious
  migration will be found in the introduction to the present writer&apos;s
  <i>Buddhist Birth Stories</i>. A translation of the whole book is now
  published, under the editorship of Professor Cowell, at the Cambridge
  University Press. The last of these poetical works which it is necessary
  to mention is the <i>Sutta Nipāta</i>, containing fifty-five poems,
  all except the last merely short lyrics, many of great beauty. A very
  ancient commentary on the bulk of these poems has been included in the
  canon as a separate work. The poems themselves have been translated by
  Professor Fausböll in the <i>Sacred Books of the East</i>. The above
  works are our authority for the philosophy and ethics of the earliest
  Buddhists. We have also a complete statement of the rules of the order in
  the <i>Vinaya</i>, edited, in five volumes, by Professor Oldenberg. Three
  volumes of translations of these rules, by him and by the present writer,
  have also appeared in the <i>Sacred Books of the East</i>.</p>
    <p>There have also been added to the canonical books seven works on
  <i>Abhidhamma</i>, a more elaborate and more classified exposition of the
  Dhamma or doctrine as set out in the <i>Nikāyas</i>. All these
  works are later. Only one of them has been translated, the so-called
  Dhamma Sangani. The introduction to this translation, published under the
  title of <i>Buddhist Psychology</i>, contains the fullest account that
  has yet appeared of the psychological conceptions on which Buddhist
  ethics are throughout based. The translator, Mrs Caroline Rhys Davids,
  estimates the date of this ancient manual for Buddhist students as the
  4th century <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>
      </p>
    <p>
         <i>Later Works.</i>—So far the canon, almost all of which is now
  accessible to readers of Pāli. But a good deal of work is still
  required before the harvest of historical data contained in these texts
  shall have been made acceptable to students of philosophy and sociology.
  These works of the oldest period, the two centuries and a half, between
  the Buddha&apos;s time and that of Asoka, were followed by a voluminous
  literature in the following Periods—from Asoka to Kanishka, and
  from Kanishka to Buddhaghosa,—each of about three centuries. Many
  of these works are extant in MS.; but only five or six of the more
  important Have so far been published. Of these the most interesting is
  the Milinda, one of the earliest historical novels preserved to us. It is
  mainly religious and philosophical and purports to give the discussion,
  extending over several days, in which a Buddhist elder named
  Nāgasena succeeds in converting Milinda, that is Menander, the
  famous Greek king of Bactria, to Buddhism. The Pāli text has been
  edited and the work translated into English. More important historically,
  though greatly inferior in style and ability, is the Mahāvastu or
  <i>Sublime Story</i>, in Sanskrit. The story is the one of chief
  importance to the Buddhists—the story, namely, of how the Buddha
  won, under the Bo Tree, the victory over ignorance, and attained to the
  Sambodhi, &quot;the higher Wisdom,&quot; of Nirvāna. The story begins with
  his previous births, in which also he was accumulating the Buddha
  qualities. And as the Mahāvastu was a standard work of a particular
  sect, or rather school, called the Mahā-sanghikas, it has thus
  preserved for us the theory of the Buddha as held outside the followers
  of the cannon, by those whose views developed, in after centuries, into
  the Mahāyāna or modern form of Buddhism in India. But this
  book, like all the ancient books, was composed, not in the north, in
  Nepal, but in the valley of the Ganges, and it is partly <ph id="page748" outputclass="pagenum">[v.04 p.0748]</ph>in
  prose, partly in verse. Two other works, the <i>Lalita Vistara</i> and
  the <i>Buddha Carita</i>, give us—but this, of course, is
  later—Sanskrit poems, epics, on the same subject. Of these, the
  former may be as old as the Christian era; the latter belongs to the 2nd
  century after Christ. Both of them have been edited and translated. The
  older one contains still a good deal of prose, the gist of it being often
  repeated in the verses. The later one is entirely in verse, and shows off
  the author&apos;s mastery of the artificial rules of prosody and poetics,
  according to which a poem, a mahā-kāvya, ought, according to
  the later writers on the <i>Ars poetica</i>, to be composed.</p>
    <p>These three works deal only quite briefly and incidentally with any
  point of Buddhism outside of the Buddha legend. Of greater importance for
  the history of Buddhism are two later works, the <i>Netti Pakarana</i>
  and the <i>Saddharma Pundarīka</i>. The former, in Pāli,
  discusses a number of questions then of importance in the Buddhist
  community; and it relies throughout, as does the Milinda, on the
  canonical works, which it quotes largely. The latter, in Sanskrit, is the
  earliest exposition we have of the later Mahāyāna doctrine.
  Both these books may be dated in the 2nd or 3rd century of our era. The
  latter has been translated into English. We have now also the text of the
  <i>Prajnā Pāramitā</i>, a later treatise on the
  Mahāyāna system, which in time entirely replaced in India the
  original doctrines. To about the same age belongs also the
  <i>Divyāvadāna</i>, a collection of legends about the leading
  disciples of the Buddha, and important members of the order, through the
  subsequent three centuries. These legends are, however, of different
  dates, and in spite of the comparatively late period at which it was put
  into its present form, it contains some very ancient fragments.</p>
    <p>The whole of the above works were composed in the north of India; that
  is to say, either north or a few miles south of the Ganges. The record is
  at present full of gaps. But we can even now obtain a full and accurate
  idea of the earliest Buddhism, and are able to trace the main lines of
  its development through the first eight or nine centuries of its career.
  The Pāli Text Society is still publishing two volumes a year; and
  the Russian Academy has inaugurated a series to contain the most
  important of the Sanskrit works still buried in MS. We have also now
  accessible in Pāli fourteen volumes of the commentaries of the
  great 5th-century scholars in south India and Ceylon, most of them the
  works either of Buddhaghosa of Budh Gaya, or of Dhammapāla of
  Kāncipura (the ancient name of Conjeeveram). These are full of
  important historical data on the social, as well as the religious, life
  of India during the periods of which they treat.</p>
    <p>
         <i>Modern Research.</i>—The striking archaeological discoveries
  of recent years have both confirmed and added to our knowledge of the
  earliest period. Pre-eminent among these is the discovery, by Mr William
  Peppé, on the Birdpur estate, adjoining the boundary between English and
  Nepalese territory, of the stūpa, or cairn, erected by the
  Sākiya clan over their share of the ashes from the cremation pyre
  of the Buddha. About 12 m. to the north-east of this spot has been found
  an inscribed pillar, put up by Asoka as a record of his visit to the
  Lumbini Garden, as the place where the future Buddha had been born.
  Although more than two centuries later than the event to which it refers,
  this inscription is good evidence of the site of the garden. There had
  been no interruption of the tradition; and it is probable that the place
  was then still occupied by the descendants of the possessors in the
  Buddha&apos;s time. North-west of this another Asoka pillar has been
  discovered, recording his visit to the cairn erected by the Sakyas over
  the remains of Konāgamana, one of the previous Puddhas or teachers,
  whose follower Gotama the Buddha had claimed to be. These discoveries
  definitely determine the district occupied by the Sākiya republic
  in the 6th and 7th centuries <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph> The
  boundaries, of course, are not known; but the clan must have spread 30 m.
  or more along the lower slopes of the Himalayas and 30 m. or more
  southwards over the plains. It has been abandoned jungle since the 3rd
  century <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph>, or perhaps earlier, so that the
  ruined sites, numerous through the whole district, have remained
  undisturbed, and further discoveries may be confidently expected.</p>
    <p>The principal points on which this large number of older and better
  authorities has modified our knowledge are as follows:—</p>
    <p>1. We have learnt that the division of Buddhism, originating with
  Burnouf, into northern and southern, is misleading. He found that the
  Buddhism in his Pāli MSS., which came from Ceylon, differed from
  that in his Sanskrit MSS., which came from Nepal. Now that the works he
  used have been made accessible in printed editions, we find that,
  wherever the existing MSS. came from, the original works themselves were
  all composed in the same stretch of country, that is, in the valley of
  the Ganges. The difference of the opinions expressed in the MSS. is due,
  not to the place where they are now found, but <i>to the difference of time</i> at which they were originally composed. Not one of the books
  mentioned above is either northern or southern. They all claim, and
  rightly claim, to belong, so far as their place of origin is concerned,
  to the Majjhima Desa, the middle country. It is undesirable to base the
  main division of our subject on an adventitious circumstance, and
  especially so when the nomenclature thus introduced (it is not found in
  the books themselves) cuts right across the true line of division. The
  use of the terms northern and southern as applied, not to the existing
  MSS., but to the original books, or to the Buddhism they teach, not only
  does not help us, it is the source of serious misunderstanding. It
  inevitably leads careless writers to take for granted that we have,
  historically, two Buddhisms—one manufactured in Ceylon, the other
  in Nepal. Now this is admittedly wrong. What we have to consider is
  Buddhism varying through slight degrees, as the centuries pass by, in
  almost every book. We may call it one, or we may call it many. What is
  quite certain is that it is not two. And the most useful distinction to
  emphasize is, not the ambiguous and misleading geographical
  one—derived from the places where the modern copies of the MSS. are
  found; nor even, though that would be better, the linguistic
  one—but the chronological one. The use, therefore, of the
  inaccurate and misleading terms northern and southern ought no longer to
  be followed in scholarly works on Buddhism.</p>
    <p>2. Our ideas as to the social conditions that prevailed, during the
  Buddha&apos;s lifetime, in the eastern valley of the Ganges have been
  modified. The people were divided into clans, many of them governed as
  republics, more or less aristocratic. In a few cases several of such
  republics had formed confederations, and in four cases such
  confederations had already become hereditary monarchies. The right
  historical analogy is not the state of Germany in the middle ages, but
  the state of Greece in the time of Socrates. The Sākiyas were still
  a republic. They had republics for their neighbours on the east and
  south, but on the western boundary was the kingdom of Kosala, the modern
  Oudh, which they acknowledged as a suzerain power. The Buddha&apos;s father
  was not a king. There were rājas in the clan, but the word meant at
  most something like consul or archon. All the four real kings were called
  Mahā-rāja. And Suddhodana, the teacher&apos;s father, was not even
  rāja. One of his cousins, named Bhaddiya, is styled a rāja;
  but Suddhodana is spoken of, like other citizens, as Suddhodana the
  Sākiyan. As the ancient books are very particular on this question
  of titles, this is decisive.</p>
    <p>3. There was no caste—no caste, that is, in the modern sense of
  the term. We have long known that the connubium was the cause of a long
  and determined struggle between the patricians and the plebeians in Rome.
  Evidence has been yearly accumulating on the existence of restrictions as
  to intermarriage, and as to the right of eating together (commensality)
  among other Aryan tribes, Greeks, Germans, Russians and so on. Even
  without the fact of the existence now of such restrictions among the
  modern successors of the ancient Aryans in India, it would have been
  probable that they also were addicted to similar customs. It is certain
  that the notion of such usages was familiar enough to some at least of
  the tribes that preceded the Aryans in India. Rules of endogamy and
  exogamy; privileges, restricted to certain classes, of eating together,
  are not only Indian or Aryan, but world-wide phenomena. Both the spirit,
  and to a large degree the actual details, of modern Indian caste-usages
  are identical <ph id="page749" outputclass="pagenum">[v.04 p.0749]</ph>with these ancient, and no doubt
  universal, customs. It is in them that we have the key to the origin of
  caste.</p>
    <p>At any moment in the history of a nation such customs seem, to a
  superficial observer, to be fixed and immutable. As a matter of fact they
  are never quite the same in successive centuries, or even generations.
  The numerous and complicated details which we sum up under the
  convenient, but often misleading, single name of caste, are solely
  dependent for their sanction on public opinion. That opinion seems
  stable. But it is always tending to vary as to the degree of importance
  attached to some particular one of the details, as to the size and
  complexity of the particular groups in which each detail ought to be
  observed.</p>
    <p>Owing to the fact that the particular group that in India worked its
  way to the top, based its claims on religious grounds, not on political
  power, nor on wealth, the system has, no doubt, lasted longer in India
  than in Europe. But public opinion still insists, in considerable circles
  even in Europe, on restrictions of a more or less defined kind, both as
  to marriage and as to eating together. And in India the problem still
  remains to trace, in the literature, the gradual growth of the
  system—the gradual formation of new sections among the people, the
  gradual extension of the institution to the families of people engaged in
  certain trades, belonging to the same group, or sect, or tribe, tracing
  their ancestry, whether rightly or wrongly, to the same source. All these
  factors, and others besides, are real factors. But they are phases of the
  extension and growth, not explanations of the origin of the system.</p>
    <p>There is no evidence to show that at the time of the rise of Buddhism
  there was any substantial difference, as regards the barriers in
  question, between the peoples dwelling in the valley of the Ganges and
  their contemporaries, Greek or Roman, dwelling on the shores of the
  Mediterranean Sea. The point of greatest weight in the establishment of
  the subsequent development, the supremacy in India of the priests, was
  still being hotly debated. All the new evidence tends to show that the
  struggle was being decided rather against than for the Brahmins. What we
  find in the Buddha&apos;s time is caste in the making. The great mass of the
  people were distinguished quite roughly into four classes, social strata,
  of which the boundary lines were vague and uncertain. At one end of the
  scale were certain outlying tribes and certain hereditary crafts of a
  dirty or despised kind. At the other end the nobles claimed the
  superiority. But Brahmins by birth (not necessarily sacrificial priests,
  for they followed all sorts of occupations) were trying to oust the
  nobles from the highest grade. They only succeeded, long afterwards, when
  the power of Buddhism had declined.</p>
    <p>4. It had been supposed on the authority of late priestly texts, where
  boasts of persecution are put forth, that the cause of the decline of
  Buddhism in India had been Brahmin persecution. The now accessible older
  authorities, with one doubtful exception,<xref href="#d1e31765/Footnote_3027" type="fn">
<!--[27]-->      </xref> make no mention of persecution.
  On the other hand, the comparison we are now able to make between the
  canonical books of the older Buddhism and the later texts of the
  following centuries, shows a continual decline from the old standpoint, a
  continual approximation of the Buddhist views to those of the other
  philosophies and religions of India. We can see now that the very event
  which seemed, in the eyes of the world, to be the most striking proof of
  the success of the new movement, the conversion and strenuous support, in
  the 3rd century <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>, of Asoka, the most
  powerful ruler India had had, only hastened the decline. The adhesion of
  large numbers of nominal converts, more especially from the newly
  incorporated and less advanced provinces, produced weakness rather than
  strength in the movement for reform. The day of compromise had come.
  Every relaxation of the old thoroughgoing position was welcomed and
  supported by converts only half converted. And so the margin of
  difference between the Buddhists and their opponents gradually faded
  almost entirely away. The soul theory, step by step, gained again the
  upper hand. The popular gods and the popular superstitions are once more
  favoured by Buddhists themselves. The philosophical basis of the old
  ethics is overshadowed by new speculations. And even the old ideal of
  life, the salvation of the Arahat to be won in this world and in this
  world only, by self-culture and self-mastery, is forgotten, or mentioned
  only to be condemned. The end was inevitable. The need of a separate
  organization became less and less apparent. The whole pantheon of the
  Vedic gods, with the ceremonies and the sacrifices associated with them,
  passed indeed away. But the ancient Buddhism, the party of reform, was
  overwhelmed also in its fall; and modern Hinduism arose on the ruins of
  both.</p>
    <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Authorities</ph>.—The attention of the few
  scholars at work on the subject being directed to the necessary first
  step of publishing the ancient authorities, the work of exploring them,
  of analysing and classifying the data they contain, has as yet been very
  imperfectly done. The annexed list contains only the most important
  works.</p>
    <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_301"> That is by the Arahat, the title the Buddha always uses of himself. He does not call himself the Buddha, and his followers never address him as such.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_302"> One very ancient commentary on the Path has been preserved in three places in the canon: <i>Dīgha</i>, ii. 305-307 and 311-313, <i>Majjhima</i>, iii. 251, and <i>Samyutta</i>, v. 8.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_303"><i>Mahāli Suttanta</i>; translated in Rhys Davids&apos; <i>Dialogues of the Buddha</i>, vol. i. p. 201 (cf. p. 204).</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_304"> See <i>Iti-vuttaka</i>, p. 44; <i>Samyutta</i>, iii. 57.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_305"> See <i>Dīgha</i>, ii. 28; <i>Jāt</i>. v. 48, ii. 80.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_306"> Burnett, <i>Early Greek Philosophy</i>, p. 149.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_307"><i>Katha Up</i>. 2, 10; <i>Bhag. Gītā</i>, 2, 14; 9, 33.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_308"> The <i>Anatta-lakkhana Sutta</i> (<i>Vinaya</i>, i. 13 = <i>Samyutta</i>, iii. 66 and iv. 34), translated in <i>Vinaya Texts</i>, i. 100-102.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_309"> See article on &quot;Buddhist Schools of Thought,&quot; by Rhys Davids, in the <i>J.R.A.S.</i> for 1892.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3010"><i>Questions of King Milinda</i>, translated by Rhys Davids (Oxford, 1890-1894), vol. i. pp. 40, 41, 85-87; vol. ii. pp. 21-25, 86-89.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3011"><i>Majjhima</i>, iii. 251, cf. <i>Samyutta</i>, v. 8.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3012"><i>Dīgha</i>, ii. 290-315. <i>Majjhima</i>, i. 55 et seq. Cf. Rhys Davids&apos; <i>Dialogues of the Buddha</i>, i. 81.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3013"> No. 8 in the <i>Sutta Nipata</i> (p. 26 of Fausböll&apos;s edition). It is translated by Fausböll in vol. x. of the <i>S.B.E.</i>, and by Rhys Davids, <i>Buddhism</i>, p. 109.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3014"><i>Dīgha</i>, ii. 186-187.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3015"><i>Majjhima</i>, i. 129.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3016"><i>Iti-vuttaka</i>, pp. 19-21.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3017"> On the details of these see <i>Dīgha</i>, i. 71-73, translated by Rhys Davids in <i>Dialogues of the Buddha</i>, i. 82-84.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3018"><i>Dīgha</i>, i. 74.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3019"><i>Samyutta</i>, iv. 251, 261.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3020"><i>Phaedo</i>, 69 et seq. The idea is there also put forward in connexion with a belief in transmigration.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3021"><i>Samyutta</i>, iv. 302.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3022"><i>Majjhima</i>, iii. 99 et seq.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3023"> The history of the Indian doctrine of Karma has yet to be written. On the Buddhist side see Rhys Davids&apos; <i>Hibbert Lectures</i>, pp. 73-120, and Dahlke, <i>Aufsatze zum Verstandnis des Buddhismus</i> (Berlin, 1903), i. 92-106, and ii. l-11.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3024"> For instance, <i>Majjhima</i>, i. 163-166</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3025"><i>Anguttara</i>, iii. 119.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3026"><i>Dīgha</i>, i. 38.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3027"> See <i>Journal of the Pāli Text Society</i>, 1896, pp. 87-92.</fn>

      </p>
  </body>
</topic>
