<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e30632">
   <title>BUCKINGHAM AND NORMANBY</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCKINGHAM AND NORMANBY, JOHN SHEFFIELD,--> <ph outputclass="sc">1st
  Duke of</ph> (1648-1721), English statesman and poet, was born on <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page728">[v.04
  p.0728]</ph>the 7th of April 1648. He was the son of Edmund, 2nd earl
  of Mulgrave, and succeeded to that title on his father's death in 1658.
  At the age of eighteen he joined the fleet, to serve in the first Dutch
  war; on the renewal of hostilities in 1672 he was present at the battle
  of Southwold Bay, and in the next year received the command of a ship. He
  was also made a colonel of infantry, and served for some time under
  Turenne. In 1680 he was put in charge of an expedition sent to relieve
  the town of Tangier. It was said that he was provided with a rotten ship
  in the hope that he would not return, but the reason of this abortive
  plot, if plot there was, is not exactly ascertained. At court he took the
  side of the duke of York, and helped to bring about Monmouth's disgrace.
  In 1682 he was dismissed from the court, apparently for putting himself
  forward as a suitor for the princess Anne, but on the accession of King
  James he received a seat in the privy council, and was made lord
  chamberlain. He supported James in his most unpopular measures, and
  stayed with him in London during the time of his flight. He also
  protected the Spanish ambassador from the dangerous anger of the mob. He
  acquiesced, however, in the Revolution, and in 1694 was made marquess of
  Normanby. In 1696 he refused in company with other Tory peers to sign an
  agreement to support William as their "rightful and lawful king" against
  Jacobite attempts, and was consequently dismissed from the privy council.
  On the accession of Anne, with whom he was a personal favourite, he
  became lord privy seal and lord-lieutenant of the North Riding of
  Yorkshire, and in 1703 duke of Buckingham and Normanby. During the
  predominance of the Whigs between 1705 and 1710, Buckingham was deprived
  of his office as lord privy seal, but in 1710 he was made lord steward,
  and in 1711 lord president of the council. After the death of Anne he
  held no state appointment. He died on the 24th of February 1721 at his
  house in St James's Park, which stood on the site of the present
  Buckingham Palace. Buckingham was succeeded by his son, Edmund
  (1716-1735) on whose death the titles became extinct.</p>
      <p>Buckingham, who is better known by his inherited titles as Lord
  Mulgrave, was the author of "An Account of the Revolution" and some other
  essays, and of numerous poems, among them the <i>Essay on Poetry</i> and
  the <i>Essay on Satire</i>. It is probable that the <i>Essay on
  Satire</i>, which attacked many notable persons, "sauntering Charles"
  amongst others, was circulated in MS. It was often attributed at the time
  to Dryden, who accordingly suffered a thrashing at the hands of
  Rochester's bravoes for the reflections it contained upon the earl.
  Mulgrave was a patron of Dryden, who may possibly have revised it, but
  was certainly not responsible, although it is commonly printed with his
  works. Mulgrave adapted Shakespeare's <i>Julius Caesar</i>, breaking it
  up into two plays, <i>Julius Caesar</i> and <i>Marcus Brutus</i>. He
  introduced choruses between the acts, two of these being written by Pope,
  and an incongruous love scene between Brutus and Portia. He was a
  constant friend and patron of Pope, who expressed a flattering opinion of
  his <i>Essay on Poetry</i>. This, although smoothly enough written, deals
  chiefly with commonplaces.</p>
      <p>In 1721 Edmund Curll published a pirated edition of his works, and was
  brought before the bar of the House of Lords for breach of privilege
  accordingly. An authorized edition under the superintendence of Pope
  appeared in 1723, but the authorities cut out the "Account of the
  Revolution" and "The Feast of the Gods" on account of their alleged
  Jacobite tendencies. These were printed at the Hague in 1727. Pope
  disingenuously repudiated any knowledge of the contents. Other editions
  reappeared in 1723, 1726, 1729, 1740 and 1753. His <i>Poems</i> were
  included in Johnson's and other editions of the British poets.</p>
   </body>
</topic>