<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23728">
   <title>BROWN, THOMAS EDWARD</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWN, THOMAS EDWARD--> (1830-1897), British poet, scholar and
  divine, was born on the 5th of May 1830, at Douglas, Isle of Man. His
  father, the Rev. Robert Brown, held the living of St Matthew's—a
  homely church in a poor district. His mother came of Scottish parentage,
  though born in the island. Thomas, the sixth of ten children, was but two
  years old when the family removed to Kirk Braddan vicarage, a short
  distance from Douglas, where his father (a scholar of no university, but
  so fastidious about composition that he would have some sentences of an
  English classic read to him before answering an invitation) took share
  with the parish schoolmaster in tutoring the clever boy until, at the age
  of fifteen, he was entered at King William's College. Here his abilities
  soon declared themselves, and hence he proceeded to Christ Church,
  Oxford, where his position (as a servitor) cost him much humiliation,
  which he remembered to the end of his life. He won a double first,
  however, and was elected a fellow of Oriel in April 1854, Dean Gaisford
  having refused to promote him to a senior studentship of his own college,
  on the ground that no servitor had ever before attained to that honour.
  Although at that time an Oriel fellowship conferred a deserved
  distinction, Brown never took kindly to the life, but, after a few terms
  of private pupils, returned to the Isle of Man as vice-principal of his
  old school. He had been ordained deacon, but did not proceed to priest's
  orders for many years. In 1857 he married his cousin, Miss Stowell,
  daughter of Dr Stowell of Ramsey, and soon afterwards left the island
  once more to become headmaster of the Crypt school, Gloucester —a
  position which in no long time he found intolerable. From Gloucester he
  was summoned by the Rev. John Percival (afterwards bishop of Hereford),
  who had recently been appointed to the struggling young foundation of
  Clifton College, which he soon raised to be one of the great public
  schools. Percival wanted a master for the modern side, and made an
  appointment to meet Brown at Oxford; "and there," he writes, "as chance
  would have it, I met him standing at the corner of St Mary's <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page663">[v.04
  p.0663]</ph>Entry, in a somewhat Johnsonian attitude, four-square, his
  hands deep in his pockets to keep himself still, and looking decidedly
  volcanic. We very soon came to terms, and I left him there under promise
  to come to Clifton as my colleague at the beginning of the following
  term." At Clifton Brown remained from September 1863 to July 1892, when
  he retired—to the great regret of boys and masters alike, who had
  long since come to regard "T.E.B.'s" genius, and even his eccentricities,
  with a peculiar pride—to spend the rest of his days upon the island
  he had worshipped from childhood and often celebrated in song. His poem
  "Betsy Lee" appeared in <i>Macmillan's Magazine</i> (April and May 1873),
  and was published separately in the same year. It was included in
  <i>Fo'c's'le Yarns</i> (1881), which reached a second edition in 1889.
  This volume included at least three other notable poems—"Tommy
  Big-eyes," "Christmas Rose," and "Captain Tom and Captain Hugh." It was
  followed by <i>The Doctor and other Poems</i> (1887), <i>The Manx Witch
  and other Poems</i> (1889), and <i>Old John and other Poems</i>—a
  volume mainly lyrical (1893). Since his death all these and a few
  additional lyrics and fragments have been published in one volume by
  Messrs Macmillan under the title of <i>The Collected Poems of T.E.
  Brown</i> (1900). His familiar letters (edited in two volumes by an old
  friend, Mr S.T. Irwin, in 1900) bear witness to the zest he carried back
  to his native country, although his thoughts often reverted to Clifton.
  In October 1897 he returned to the school on a visit. He was the guest of
  one of the house-masters, and on Friday evening, 29th October, he gave an
  address to the boys of the house. He had spoken for some minutes with his
  usual vivacity, when his voice grew thick and he was seen to stagger. He
  died in less than two hours. Brown's more important poems are narrative,
  and written in the Manx dialect, with a free use of pauses, and sometimes
  with daring irregularity of rhythm. A rugged tenderness is their most
  characteristic note; but the emotion, while almost equally explosive in
  mirth and in tears, remains an educated emotion, disciplined by a
  scholar's sense of language. They breathe the fervour of an island
  patriotism (humorously aware of its limits) and of a simple natural
  piety. In his lyrics he is happiest when yoking one or the other of these
  emotions to serve a philosophy of life, often audacious, but always
  genial.</p>
      <p>(A. T. Q.-C.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>