<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e30282">
   <title>BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS-->, <ph outputclass="sc">2nd Duke
  of</ph>
         <xref href="#d1e30282/Footnote_261" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref>
  (1628-1687), English statesman, son of the 1st duke, was born on the 30th
  of January 1628. He was brought up, together with his younger brother
  Francis, by King Charles I. with his own children, and was educated at
  Trinity College, Cambridge, where he obtained the degree of M.A. in 1642.
  He fought for the king in the Civil War, and took part in the attack on
  Lichfield Close in April 1643. Subsequently, under the care of the earl
  of Northumberland, the two brothers travelled abroad and lived at
  Florence and Rome. When the Second Civil War broke out they joined the
  earl of Holland in Surrey, in July 1648. Lord Francis was killed near
  Kingston, and Buckingham and Holland were surprised at St Neots on the
  10th, the duke succeeding in escaping to Holland. In consequence of his
  participation in the rebellion, his lands, which had been restored to him
  in 1647 on account of his youth, were now again confiscated, a
  considerable portion passing into the possession of Fairfax; and he
  refused to compound. Charles II. conferred on him the Garter on the 19th
  of September 1649, and admitted him to the privy council on the 6th of
  April 1650. In opposition to Hyde he supported the alliance with the
  Scottish presbyterians, accompanied Charles to Scotland in June, and
  allied himself with Argyll, dissuading Charles from joining the royalist
  plot of October 1650, and being suspected of betraying the plan to the
  convenanting leaders. In May he had been appointed general of the eastern
  association in England, and was commissioned to raise forces abroad; and
  in the following year he was chosen to lead the projected movement in
  Lancashire and to command the Scottish royalists. He was present with
  Charles at the battle of Worcester on the 3rd of September 1651, and
  escaped safely <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page725">[v.04 p.0725]</ph>alone to Rotterdam in October. His
  subsequent negotiations with Cromwell's government, and his readiness to
  sacrifice the interests of the church, separated him from the rest of
  Charles's advisers and diminished his influence; while his estrangement
  from the royal family was completed by his audacious courtship of the
  king's sister, the widowed princess of Orange, and by a money dispute
  with Charles. In 1657 he returned to England, and on the 15th of
  September married Mary, daughter of Lord Fairfax, who had fallen in love
  with him although the banns of her intended marriage with the earl of
  Chesterfield had been twice called in church. Buckingham was soon
  suspected of organizing a presbyterian plot against the government, and
  in spite of Fairfax's interest with Cromwell an order was issued for his
  arrest on the 9th of October. He was confined at York House about April
  1658, and having broken bounds was rearrested on the 18th of August and
  imprisoned in the Tower, where he remained till the 23rd of February
  1659, being then liberated on his promise not to abet the enemies of the
  government, and on Fairfax's security of £20,000. He joined the latter in
  his march against Lambert in January 1660, and afterwards claimed to have
  gained Fairfax to the cause of the Restoration.</p>
      <p>On the king's return Buckingham, who met him at his landing at Dover,
  was at first received coldly; but he was soon again in favour, was
  appointed a gentleman of the bedchamber, carried the orb at the
  coronation on the 23rd of April 1661, and was made lord-lieutenant of the
  West Riding of Yorkshire on the 21st of September. The same year he
  accompanied the princess Henrietta to Paris on her marriage with the duke
  of Orleans, but made love to her himself with such imprudence that he was
  recalled. On the 28th of April 1662 he was admitted to the privy council.
  His confiscated estates amounting to £26,000 a year were restored to him,
  and he was reputed the king's richest subject. He took part in the
  suppression of the projected insurrection in Yorkshire in 1663, went to
  sea in the first Dutch war in 1665, and was employed in taking measures
  to resist the Dutch or French invasion in June 1666.</p>
      <p>He was, however, debarred from high office by Clarendon's influence.
  Accordingly Buckingham's intrigues were now directed to effect the
  chancellor's ruin. He organized parties in both houses of parliament in
  support of the bill of 1666 prohibiting the import of Irish cattle,
  partly to oppose Clarendon and partly to thwart the duke of Ormonde.
  Having asserted during the debates that "whoever was against the bill had
  either an Irish interest or an Irish understanding," he was challenged by
  Lord Ossory. Buckingham avoided the encounter, and Ossory was sent to the
  Tower. A short time afterwards, during a conference between the two
  houses on the 19th of December, he came to blows with the marquess of
  Dorchester, pulling off the latter's periwig, while Dorchester at the
  close of the scuffle "had much of the duke's hair in his hand."<xref href="#d1e30282/Footnote_262" type="fn"><!--[2]--></xref> According to
  Clarendon no misdemeanour so flagrant had ever before offended the
  dignity of the House of Lords. The offending peers were both sent to the
  Tower, but were released after apologizing; and Buckingham vented his
  spite by raising a claim to the title of Lord Roos held by Dorchester's
  son-in-law. His opposition to the government had forfeited the king's
  favour, and he was now accused of treasonable intrigues, and of having
  cast the king's horoscope. His arrest was ordered on the 25th of February
  1667, and he was dismissed from all his offices. He avoided capture till
  the 27th of June, when he gave himself up and was imprisoned in the
  Tower. He was released, however, by July 17th, was restored to favour and
  to his appointments on the 15 of September, and took an active part in
  the prosecution of Clarendon. On the latter's fall he became the chief
  minister, though holding no high office except that of master of the
  horse, bought from the duke of Albermarle in 1668. In 1671 he was elected
  chancellor of Cambridge, and in 1672 high steward of Oxford university.
  He favoured religious toleration, and earned the praise of Richard
  Baxter; he supported a scheme of comprehension in 1668, and advised the
  declaration of indulgence in 1672. He upheld the original jurisdiction of
  the Lords in Skinner's case. With these exceptions Buckingham's tenure of
  office was chiefly marked by scandals and intrigues. His illicit
  connexion with the countess of Shrewsbury led to a duel with her husband
  at Barn Elms on the 16th of January 1668, in which Shrewsbury was fatally
  wounded. The tale that the countess, disguised as a page, witnessed the
  encounter, appears to have no foundation; but Buckingham, by installing
  the "widow of his own creation" in his own and his wife's house, outraged
  even the lax opinion of that day. He was thought to have originated the
  project of obtaining the divorce of the childless queen. He intrigued
  against James, against Sir William Coventry—one of the ablest
  statesmen of the time, whose fall he procured by provoking him to send
  him a challenge—and against the great duke of Ormonde, who was
  dismissed in 1669. He was even suspected of having instigated Thomas
  Blood's attempt to kidnap and murder Ormonde, and was charged with the
  crime in the king's presence by Ormonde's son, Lord Ossory, who
  threatened to shoot him dead in the event of his father's meeting with a
  violent end. Arlington, next to Buckingham himself the most powerful
  member of the cabal and a favourite of the king, was a rival less easy to
  overcome; and he derived considerable influence from the control of
  foreign affairs entrusted to him. Buckingham had from the first been an
  adherent of the French alliance, while Arlington concluded through Sir
  William Temple in 1668 the Triple Alliance. But on the complete
  <i>volte-face</i> and surrender made by Charles to France in 1670,
  Arlington as a Roman Catholic was entrusted with the first treaty of
  Dover of the 20th of May—which besides providing for the united
  attack on Holland, included Charles's undertaking to proclaim himself a
  Romanist and to reintroduce the Roman Catholic faith into
  England,—While Buckingham was sent to France to carry on the sham
  negotiations which led to the public treaties of the 31st of December
  1670 and the 2nd of February 1672. He was much pleased with his reception
  by Louis XIV., declared that he had "more honours done him than ever were
  given to any subject," and was presented with a pension of 10,000 livres
  a year for Lady Shrewsbury. In June 1672 he accompanied Arlington to the
  Hague to impose terms on the prince of Orange, and with Arlington
  arranged the new treaty with Louis. After all this activity he suffered a
  keen disappointment in being passed over for the command of the English
  forces in favour of Schomberg. He now knew of the secret treaty of Dover,
  and towards the end of 1673 his jealousy of Arlington became open
  hostility. He threatened to impeach him, and endeavoured with the help of
  Louis to stir up a faction against him in parliament. This, however, was
  unsuccessful, and in January 1674 an attack was made upon Buckingham
  himself simultaneously in both houses. In the Lords the trustees of the
  young earl of Shrewsbury complained that Buckingham continued publicly
  his intimacy with the countess, and that a son of theirs had been buried
  in Westminster Abbey with the title of earl of Coventry; and Buckingham,
  after presenting an apology, was required, as was the countess, to give
  security for £10,000 not to cohabit together again. In the Commons he was
  attacked as the promoter of the French alliance, of "popery" and
  arbitrary government. He defended himself chiefly by endeavouring to
  throw the blame upon Arlington; but an address was voted petitioning the
  king to remove him from his councils, presence and from employment for
  ever. Charles, who had only been waiting for a favourable opportunity,
  and who was enraged at Buckingham's disclosures, consented with alacrity.
  Buckingham retired into private life, reformed his ways, attended church
  with his wife, began to pay his debts, became a "patriot," and was
  claimed by the country or opposition party as one of their leaders. In
  the spring of 1675 he was conspicuous for his opposition to the Test oath
  and for his abuse of the bishops, and on the 16th of November he
  introduced a bill for the relief of the nonconformists. On the 15th of
  February 1677 he was one of the four lords who endeavoured to embarrass
  the government by raising the question whether the parliament, not having
  assembled according to the act of Edward III. once in the year, had not
  been dissolved by <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page726">[v.04 p.0726]</ph>the recent prorogation. The motion
  was rejected and the four lords were ordered to apologize. On their
  refusing, they were sent to the Tower, Buckingham in particular
  exasperating the House by ridiculing its censure. He was released in
  July, and immediately entered into intrigues with Barillon, the French
  ambassador, with the object of hindering the grant of supplies to the
  king; and in 1678 he visited Paris to get the assistance of Louis XIV.
  for the cause of the opposition. He took an active part in the
  prosecution of those implicated in the supposed Popish Plot, and accused
  the lord chief justice (Sir William Scroggs) in his own court while on
  circuit of favouring the Roman Catholics. In consequence of his conduct a
  writ was issued for his apprehension, but it was never served. He
  promoted the return of Whig candidates to parliament, constituted himself
  the champion of the dissenters, and was admitted a freeman of the city of
  London. He, however, separated himself from the Whigs on the exclusion
  question, probably on account of his dislike of Monmouth and Shaftesbury,
  was absent from the great debate in the Lords on the 15th of November
  1680, and was restored to the king's favour in 1684.</p>
      <p>He took no part in public life after James's accession, but returned
  to his manor of Helmsley in Yorkshire, the cause of his withdrawal being
  probably exhausted health and exhausted finances. In 1685 he published a
  pamphlet, entitled <i>A short Discourse on the Reasonableness of Man's
  having a Religion</i> (reprinted in <i>Somers Tracts</i> (1813, ix. 13),
  in which after discussing the main subject he returned to his favourite
  topic, religious toleration. The tract provoked some rejoinders and was
  defended, amongst others, by William Penn, and by the author himself in
  <i>The Duke of Buckingham's Letter to the unknown author of a short
  answer to the Duke of Buckingham's Paper</i> (1685). In hopes of
  converting him to Roman Catholicism James sent him a priest, but
  Buckingham turned his arguments into ridicule. He died on the 16th of
  April 1687, from a chill caught while hunting, in the house of a tenant
  at Kirkby Moorside in Yorkshire, expressing great repentance and feeling
  himself "despised by my country and I fear forsaken by my God."<xref href="#d1e30282/Footnote_263" type="fn"><!--[3]--></xref> The miserable
  picture of his end drawn by Pope, however, is greatly exaggerated. He was
  buried on the 7th of June 1687 in Henry VII.'s chapel in Westminster
  Abbey, in greater state, it was said, than the late king, and with
  greater splendour. With his death the family founded by the extraordinary
  rise to power and influence of the first duke ended. As he left no
  legitimate children the title became extinct, and his great estate had
  been completely dissipated; of the enormous mansion constructed by him at
  Cliveden in Buckinghamshire not a stone remains.</p>
      <p>The ostentatious licence and the unscrupulous conduct of the
  Alcibiades of the 17th century have been deservedly censured. But even
  his critics agree that he was good-humoured, good-natured, generous, an
  unsurpassed mimic and the leader of fashion; and with his good looks, in
  spite of his moral faults and even crimes, he was irresistible to his
  contemporaries. Many examples of his amusing wit have survived. His
  portrait has been drawn by Burnet, Count Hamilton in the <i>Mémoires de
  Grammont</i>, Dryden, Pope in the <i>Epistle to Lord Bathurst</i>, and
  Sir Walter Scott in <i>Peveril of the Peak</i>. He is described by
  Reresby as "the first gentleman of person and wit I think I ever saw,"
  and Burnet bears the same testimony. Dean Lockier, after alluding to his
  unrivalled skill in riding, dancing and fencing, adds, "When he came into
  the presence-chamber it was impossible for you not to follow him with
  your eye as he went along, he moved so gracefully." Racing and hunting
  were his favourite sports, and his name long survived in the hunting
  songs of Yorkshire. He was the patron of Cowley, Sprat, Matthew Clifford
  and Wycherley. He dabbled in chemistry, and for some years, according to
  Burnet, "he thought he was very near the finding of the philosopher's
  stone." He set up glass works at Lambeth the productions of which were
  praised by Evelyn; and he spent much money, according to his biographer
  Brian Fairfax, in building <i>insanae substructions</i>. Dryden described
  him under the character of Zimri in the celebrated lines in <i>Absalom
  and Achitophel</i> (to which Buckingham replied in <i>Poetical
  Reflections on a late Poem ... by a Person of Honour,
  1682</i>):—</p>
      <fig outputclass="poem">
         <lines>
      "A man so various, that he seemed to be

      Not one, but all mankind's epitome;

      Stiff in opinions, always in the wrong,

      Was everything by starts and nothing long;

      But in the course of one revolving moon,

      Was chymist, fiddler, statesman and buffoon....

      Beggar'd by fools, whom still he found too late,

      He had his jest, but they had his estate."

    </lines>
      </fig>
      <p>Buckingham, however, cannot with any truth be called the "epitome of
  mankind." On the contrary, the distinguishing features of his life are
  its incompleteness, aimlessness, imperfection, insignificance, neglect of
  talents and waste of opportunities. "He saw and approved the best," says
  Brian Fairfax, "but did too often <i>deteriora sequi</i>." He is more
  severely but more justly judged by himself. In gay moments indeed he had
  written—</p>
      <fig outputclass="poem">
         <lines>
      "Methinks, I see the wanton houres flee,

      And as they passe, turne back and laugh at me,"<xref href="#d1e30282/Footnote_264" type="fn"><!--[4]--></xref>—

    </lines>
      </fig>
      <p>but his last recorded words on the approach of death, "O! what a
  prodigal have I been of that most valuable of all
  possessions—Time!" express with exact truth the fundamental flaw of
  his character and career, of which he had at last become conscious.</p>
      <p>Buckingham wrote occasional verses and satires showing undoubted but
  undeveloped poetical gifts, a collection of which, containing however
  many pieces not from his pen, was first published by Tom Brown in 1704;
  while a few extracts from a commonplace book of Buckingham of some
  interest are given in an article in the <i>Quarterly Review</i> of
  January 1898. He was the author of <i>The Rehearsal</i>, an amusing and
  clever satire on the heroic drama and especially on Dryden (first
  performed on the 7th of December 1671, at the Theatre Royal, and first
  published in 1672), a deservedly popular play which was imitated by
  Fielding in <i>Tom Thumb the Great</i>, and by Sheridan in the
  <i>Critic</i>. Buckingham also published two adapted plays, <i>The
  Chances</i>, altered from Fletcher's play of the same name (1682) and
  <i>The Restoration or Right will take place</i>, from Beaumont and
  Fletcher's <i>Philaster</i> (publ. 1714); and also <i>The Battle of
  Sedgmoor</i> and <i>The Militant Couple</i> (publ. 1704). The latest
  edition of his works is that by T. Evans (2 vols. 8vo, 1775). Another
  work is named by Wood <i>A Demonstration of the Deity</i>, of which there
  is now no trace.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Bibliography</ph>.—The life of Buckingham has
  been well and accurately traced and the chief authorities collected in
  the article in the <i>Dict, of Nat. Biography</i> (1899) by C.H. Firth,
  and in <i>George Villiers, 2nd Duke of Buckingham</i>, by Lady Burghclere
  (1903). Other biographies are in Wood's <i>Athenae Oxon</i> (Bliss), iv.
  207; in <i>Biographia Britannica</i>; by Brian Fairfax, printed in H.
  Walpole's <i>Catalogue of Pictures of George Duke of Buckingham</i>
  (1758); in Arber's edition of the <i>Rehearsal</i> (1868); and by the
  author of <i>Hudibras</i> in <i>The Genuine Remains of Mr Samuel
  Butler</i>, by R. Thyer (1759), ii. 72. The following may also be
  mentioned:—<i>Quarterly Review, Jan. 1898</i> (commonplace book);
  <i>A Conference on the Doctrine of Transubstantiation between ... the
  Duke of Buckingham and Father FitzGerald</i> (1714); <i>A Narrative of
  the Cause and Manner of the Imprisonment of the Lords</i> (1677); <i>The
  Declaration of the ... Duke of Buckingham and the Earls of Holland and
  Peterborough ... associated for the King</i> (1648); S.R. Gardiner's
  <i>Hist. of the Commonwealth</i> (1894-1901); <i>Hist. of Eng.
  Poetry</i>, by W.J. Courthope (1903), iii. 460; Horace Walpole's <i>Royal
  and Noble Authors</i>, iii. 304; <i>Miscellania Aulica</i>, by T. Brown
  (1702); and the <i>Fairfax Correspondence</i> (1848-1849). For the
  correspondence see <i>Charles II. and Scotland in 1650</i> (Scottish
  History Soc., vol. xvii., 1894); <i>Calendars of St. Pap. Dom.; Hist.
  MSS. Comm. Series, MSS. of Duke of Buccleuch at Montagu House, of Mrs
  Frankland-Russell-Astley</i>, of <i>Marq. of Ormonde</i>, and <i>Various
  Collections</i>; and <i>English Hist. Rev.</i> (April 1905), xx. 373.</p>
      <p>(P. C. Y.)</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_261"> i.e. in the
  Villiers line; see above.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_262"> Clarendon, <i>Life
  and Continuation</i>, 979.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_263"> 
            <i>Quarterly
  Review</i>, January 1898, p. 110.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_264"> From his Common
  place Book (<i>Quarterly Rev.</i> vol. 187, p. 87).</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>