<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" []>
<topic id="d1e34551">
  <title>BULGARIA</title>
  <body>
    <p><!--BULGARIA,--> a kingdom of south-eastern Europe, situated in the
  north-east of the Balkan Peninsula, and on the Black Sea. From 1878 until
  the 5th of October 1908, Bulgaria was an autonomous and tributary
  principality, under the suzerainty of the sultan of Turkey. The area of
  the kingdom amounts to 37,240 sq. m., and comprises the territories
  between the Balkan chain and the river Danube; the province of Eastern
  Rumelia, lying south of the Balkans; and the western highlands of
  Kiustendil, Samakov, Sofia and Trn. Bulgaria is bounded on the N. by the
  Danube, from its confluence with the Timok to the eastern suburbs of
  Silistria whence a line, forming the Rumanian frontier, is drawn to a
  point on the Black Sea coast 10 m. S. of Mangalia. On the E. it is washed
  by the Black Sea; on the S. the Turkish frontier, starting from a point
  on the coast about 12 m. S. of Sozopolis, runs in a south-westerly
  direction, crossing the river Maritza at Mustafa Pasha, and reaching the
  Arda at Adakali. The line laid down by the Berlin Treaty (1878) ascended
  the Arda to Ishiklar, thence following the crest of Rhodope to the
  westwards, but the cantons of Krjali and Rupchus included in this
  boundary were restored to Turkey in 1886. The present frontier, passing
  to the north of these districts, reaches the watershed of Rhodope a
  little north of the Dospat valley, and then follows the crest of the
  Rilska Planina to the summit of Tchrni Vrkh, where the Servian, Turkish
  and Bulgarian territories meet. From this point the western or Servian
  frontier passes northwards, leaving Trn to the east and Pirot to the
  west, reaching the Timok near Kula, and following the course of that
  river to its junction with the Danube. The Berlin Treaty boundary was far
  from corresponding with the ethnological limits of the Bulgarian race,
  which were more accurately defined by the abrogated treaty of San Stefano
  (see below, under <i>History</i>). A considerable portion of Macedonia,
  the districts of Pirot and Vranya belonging to Servia, the northern half
  of the vilayet of Adrianople, and large tracts of the Dobrudja, are,
  according to the best and most impartial authorities, mainly inhabited by
  a Bulgarian population.</p>
    <p>
         <i>Physical Features.</i>—The most striking physical features
  are two mountain-chains; the Balkans, which run east and west through the
  heart of the country; and Rhodope, which, for a considerable distance,
  forms its southern boundary. The Balkans constitute the southern half of
  the great semicircular range known as the anti-Dacian system, of which
  the Carpathians form the northern portion. This great chain is sundered
  at the Iron Gates by the passage of the Danube; its two component parts
  present many points of resemblance in their aspect and outline,
  geological formation and flora. The Balkans (ancient <i>Haemus</i>) run
  almost parallel to the Danube, ...</p>
    <p>
         <i>(continued in part 4)</i>
      </p>
  </body>
</topic>
