<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e30872">
   <title>BUCKLAND, WILLIAM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCKLAND, WILLIAM--> (1784-1856), English divine and geologist,
  eldest son of the Rev. Charles Buckland, rector of Templeton and Trusham,
  in Devon, was born at Axminster on the 12th of March 1784. He was
  educated at the grammar school of Tiverton, and at Winchester, and in
  1801 was elected a scholar of Corpus Christi College, Oxford, becoming
  B.A. in 1804. In 1809 he was elected a fellow of his college, and was
  admitted into holy orders. From early boyhood he had exhibited a strong
  taste for natural science, which was subsequently stimulated by the
  lectures of Dr John Kidd on mineralogy and chemistry; and his attention
  was especially drawn to the then infant science of geology. He also
  attended the lectures of Sir Christopher Pegge (1765-1822) on anatomy. He
  now devoted himself systematically to an examination of the geological
  structure of Great Britain, making excursions, and investigating the
  order of superposition of the strata and the characters of the organic
  remains which they contained. In 1813, on the resignation of Dr Kidd, he
  was appointed reader in mineralogy in Oxford; and the interest excited by
  his lectures was so great that in 1819 a readership in geology was
  founded and especially endowed by the treasury, Dr Buckland being the
  first holder of the new appointment. In 1818 Dr Buckland was elected a
  fellow of the Royal Society, and in 1824 and again in 1840 he was chosen
  president of the Geological Society of London. In 1825 he was presented
  by his college to the living of Stoke Charity, near Whitchurch, Hants,
  and in the same year he was appointed by Lord Liverpool to a canonry of
  the cathedral of Christ Church, Oxford, when the degree of D.D. was
  conferred upon him. In 1825, also, he married Mary, the eldest daughter
  of Mr Benjamin Morland of Sheepstead House, near Abingdon, Berks, by
  whose abilities and excellent judgment he was materially assisted in his
  literary labours. In 1832 he presided over the second meeting of the
  British Association, which was then held at Oxford. In 1845 he was
  appointed by Sir Robert Peel to the vacant deanery of Westminster, and
  was soon after inducted to the living of Islip, near Oxford, a preferment
  attached to the deanery. In 1847 he was appointed a trustee in the
  British Museum; and in 1848 he was awarded the Wollaston medal by the
  Geological Society of London. In 1849 his health began to give way under
  the increasing pressure of his multifarious duties; and the later years
  of his life were overshadowed by a serious illness, which compelled him
  to live in retirement. He died on the 24th of August 1856, and was buried
  in a spot which he had himself chosen, in Islip churchyard.</p>
      <p>Buckland was a man many-sided in his abilities, and of a singularly
  wide range of attainments. Apart from his published works and memoirs in
  connexion with the special department of geology, and in addition to the
  work entailed upon him by the positions which he at different times held
  in the Church of England, he entered with great enthusiasm into many
  practical questions connected with agricultural and sanitary science, and
  various social and even medical problems. As a teacher he possessed
  powers of the highest order; and the university of Oxford is enriched by
  the large and valuable private collections, illustrative of geology and
  mineralogy, which he amassed in the course of his active life. It is,
  however, upon his published scientific works that Dr Buckland's great
  reputation is mainly based. His first great work was the well-known
  <i>Reliquiae Diluvianae, or Observations on the Organic Remains contained
  in caves, fissures, and diluvial gravel attesting the Action of a
  Universal Deluge</i>, published in 1823 (2nd ed. 1824), in which he
  supplemented his former observations on the remains of extinct animals
  discovered in the cavern of Kirkdale in Yorkshire, and expounded his
  views as to the bearing of these and similar cases on the Biblical
  account of the Deluge. Thirteen years after the publication of the
  <i>Reliquiae</i>, Dr Buckland w as called upon, in accordance with the
  will of the earl of Bridgewater, to write one of the series of works
  known as the <i>Bridgewater Treatises</i>. The design of these treatises
  was to exhibit the "power, wisdom, and goodness of God, as manifested in
  the Creation," and none of them was of greater value, as evinced by its
  vitality, than that on "Geology and Mineralogy." Originally published in
  1836, it has gone through three editions, and though not a "manual" of
  geological science, it still possesses high value as a storehouse of
  geological and palaeontological facts bearing upon the particular
  argument which it was designed to illustrate. The third edition, issued
  in 1858, was edited by his son Francis T. Buckland, and is accompanied by
  a memoir of the author and a list of his publications.</p>
      <p>Of Dr Buckland's numerous original contributions to the sciences of
  Geology and Palaeontology, the following may be mentioned:—(1) "On
  the Structure of the Alps and adjoining parts of the Continent, and their
  relation to the Secondary and Transition Rocks of England" (<i>Annals of
  Phil.</i>, 1821); (2) "Account of an Assemblage of Fossil Teeth and Bones
  of Elephant, Rhinoceros, Hippopotamus, &amp;c., discovered in a cave at
  Kirkdale in Yorkshire in the year 1821" (<i>Phil. Trans.</i>); (3) "On
  the Quartz Rock of the Lickey Hill in Worcestershire" (<i>Trans. Geol.
  Soc.</i>); (4) "On the Megalosaurus or Great Fossil Lizard of
  Stonesfield" (Ibid.); (5) "On the Cycadeoideae, a Family of Plants found
  in the Oolite Quarries of the Isle of Portland" (Ibid.); (6) "On the
  Discovery of a New Species of Pterodactyle in the Lias of Lyme Regis"
  (Ibid.); (7) "On the Discovery of Coprolites or Fossil Faeces in the Lias
  of Lyme Regis, and in other Formations" (Ibid.); (8) "On the Evidences of
  Glaciers in Scotland and the North of England" (<i>Proc. Geol. Soc.
  Lond.</i>); (9) "On the South-Western Coal District of England" (joint
  paper with the Rev. W.D. Conybeare, <i>Trans. Geol. Soc. Lond.</i>); (10)
  "On the Geology of the neighbourhood of Weymouth, and the adjacent parts
  of the Coast of Dorset" (joint paper with Sir H. De la Beche, <i>Trans.
  Geol. Soc. Lond.</i>).</p>
      <p>With regard to the Glacial theory propounded by Agassiz, no one
  welcomed it with greater ardour than Buckland, and he zealously sought to
  trace out evidences of former glaciation in Britain. A record of the
  interesting discussion which took place at the Geological Society's
  meeting in London in November 1840, <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page732">[v.04 p.0732]</ph>after the
  reading of a paper by Buckland, was printed in the <i>Midland
  Naturalist</i>, October 1883.</p>
   </body>
</topic>