<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22117">
   <title>BROOKE, HENRY</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROOKE, HENRY--> (<i>c.</i> 1703-1783), Irish author, son of
  William Brooke, rector of Killinkere, Co. Cavan, was born at Rantavan in
  the same county, about 1703. His mother was a daughter of Simon Digby,
  bishop of Elphin. Dr Thomas Sheridan was one of his schoolmasters, and he
  was entered at Trinity College, Dublin, in 1720; in 1724 he was sent to
  London to study law. He married his cousin and ward, Catherine Meares,
  before she was fourteen. Returning to London he published a philosophical
  poem in six books entitled <i>Universal Beauty</i> (1735). He attached
  himself to the party of the prince of Wales, and took a small house at
  Twickenham near to Alexander Pope. In 1738 he translated the first and
  second books of Tasso's <i>Gerusalemme liberata</i>, and in the next year
  he produced a tragedy, <i>Gustavas Vasa, the Deliverer of his
  Country</i>. This play had been rehearsed for five weeks at Drury Lane,
  but at the last moment the performance was forbidden. The reason of this
  prohibition was a supposed portrait of Sir Robert Walpole in the part of
  Trollio. In any case the spirit of fervent patriotism which pervaded the
  play was probably disliked by the government. The piece was printed and
  sold largely, being afterwards put on the Irish stage under the title of
  <i>The Patriot</i>. This affair provoked a satirical pamphlet from Samuel
  Johnson, entitled "A Complete Vindication of the Licensers of the Stage
  from the malicious and scandalous Aspersions of Mr Brooke" (1739). His
  wife feared that his connexion with the opposition was imprudent, and
  induced him to return to Ireland. He interested himself in Irish history
  and literature, but a projected collection of Irish stories and a history
  of Ireland from the earliest times were abandoned in consequence of
  disputes about the ownership of the materials. During the Jacobite
  rebellion of 1745 Brooke issued his <i>Farmer's Six Letters to the
  Protestants of Ireland</i> (collected 1746) the form of which was
  suggested by Swift's <i>Drapier's Letters</i>. For this service he
  received from the government the post of barrack-master at Mullingar,
  which he held till his death. He wrote other pamphlets on the Protestant
  side, and was secretary to an association for promoting projects of
  national utility. About 1760 he entered into negotiations with leading
  Roman Catholics, and in 1761 he wrote a pamphlet advocating alleviation
  of the penal laws against them. He is said to have been the first editor
  of the <i>Freeman's Journal</i>, established at Dublin in 1763. Meanwhile
  he had been obliged to mortgage his property in Cavan, and had removed to
  Co. Kildare. Subsequently a bequest from Colonel Robert Brooke enabled
  him to purchase an estate near his old home, and he spent large sums in
  attempting to reclaim the waste-land. His best-known work is the novel
  entitled <i>The Fool of Quality; or the History of Henry Earl of
  Moreland</i>, the first part of which was published in 1765; and the
  fifth and last in 1770. The characters of this book, which relates the
  education of an ideal nobleman by an ideal merchant-prince, are gifted
  with a "passionate and tearful sensibility," and reflect the real humour
  and tenderness of the writer. Brooke's religious and philanthropic temper
  recommended the book to John Wesley, who edited (1780) an abridged
  edition, and to Charles Kingsley, who published it with a eulogistic
  notice in 1859. Brooke had a large family, but only two children survived
  him. His wife's death seriously affected him, and he died at Dublin in a
  state of mental infirmity on the 10th of October 1783.</p>
      <p>His daughter, Charlotte Brooke, published <i>The Poetical Works of
  Henry Brooke</i> in 1792, but was able to supply very little biographical
  material. Other sources for Brooke's biography are C. H. Wilson,
  <i>Brookiana</i> (2 vols., 1804), and a biographical preface by E. A.
  Baker prefixed to a new edition (1906) of <i>The Fool of Quality</i>.
  Brooke's other works include several tragedies, only some of which were
  actually staged. He also wrote: <i>Jack the Giant Queller</i> (1748), an
  operatic satire, the repetition of which was forbidden on account of its
  political allusions; "Constantia, or the Man of Lawe's Tale" (1741),
  contributed to George Ogle's <i>Canterbury Tales modernized; Juliet
  Grenville; or the History of the Human Heart</i> (1773), a novel; and
  some fables contributed to Edward Moore's <i>Fables for the Female
  Sex</i> (1744).</p>
   </body>
</topic>