<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25068">
   <title>BRUCE, MICHAEL</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUCE, MICHAEL--> (1746-1767), Scottish poet, was born at
  Kinnesswood in the parish of Portmoak, Kinross-shire, on the 27th of
  March 1746. His father, Alexander Bruce, was a weaver, and a man of
  exceptional ability. Michael was taught to read before he was four years
  old, and one of his favourite books was a copy of Sir David Lyndsay's
  works. He was early sent to school, but his attendance was often
  interrupted. He had frequently to herd cattle on the Lomond Hills in
  summer, and this early companionship with nature greatly influenced his
  poetic genius. He was a delicate child, and grew up contemplative,
  devotional and humorous, the pet of his family and his friends. His
  parents gave him an education superior to their position; he studied
  Latin and Greek, and at fifteen, when his school education was completed,
  a small legacy left to his mother, with some additions from kindly
  neighbours, provided means to send Michael to Edinburgh University, which
  he attended during the four winter sessions 1762-1765. In 1765 he taught
  during the summer months at Gairney Bridge, receiving about £11 a year in
  fees and free board in one or other of the homes of his pupils. He became
  a divinity student at Kinross of a Scottish sect known as the Burghers,
  and in the first summer (1766) of his divinity course accepted the charge
  of a new school at Forest Hill, near Clackmannan, where he led a
  melancholy life. Poverty, disease and want of companions depressed his
  spirits, but there he wrote "Lochleven," a poem inspired by the memories
  of his childhood. He had before been threatened with consumption, and now
  became seriously ill. During the winter he returned on foot to his
  father's house, where he wrote his last and finest poem, "Elegy written
  in Spring," and died on the 5th of July 1767.</p>
      <p>As a poet his reputation has been spread, first, through sympathy for
  his early death; and secondly, through the alleged theft by John Logan
  (<i>q.v.</i>) of several of his poems. Logan, who had been a
  fellow-student of Bruce, obtained Bruce's MSS. from his father, shortly
  after the poet's death. For the letters, poems, &amp;c., that he allowed
  to pass out of his hands, Alexander Bruce took no receipt, nor did he
  keep any list of the titles. Logan edited in 1770 <i>Poems on Several
  Occasions, by Michael Bruce</i>, in which the "Ode to the Cuckoo"
  appeared. In the preface he stated that "to make up a miscellany, some
  poems written by different authors are inserted." In a collection of his
  own poems in 1781, Logan printed the "Ode to the Cuckoo" as his own; of
  this the friends of Bruce were aware, but did not challenge its
  appropriation publicly. In a MS. <i>Pious Memorials of Portmoak</i>,
  drawn up by Bruce's friend, David Pearson, Bruce's authorship of the "Ode
  to the Cuckoo" is emphatically asserted. This book was in the possession
  of the Birrell family, and John Birrell, another friend of the poet, adds
  a testimony to the same effect. Pearson and Birrell also wrote to Dr
  Robert Anderson while he was publishing his <i>British Poets</i>,
  pointing out Bruce's claims. Their <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page677">[v.04 p.0677]</ph>communications
  were used by Anderson in the "Life" prefixed to Logan's works in the
  <i>British Poets</i> (vol. ii. p. 1029). The volume of 1770 had struck
  Bruce's friends as being incomplete, and his father missed his son's
  "Gospel Sonnets," which are supposed by the partisans of Bruce against
  Logan to have been the hymns printed in the 1781 edition of Logan's
  poems. Logan tried to prevent by law the reprinting of Bruce's poems (see
  James Mackenzie's <i>Life of Michael Bruce</i>, 1905, chap. xii.), but
  the book was printed in 1782, 1784, 1796 and 1807. Dr William
  M<sup>c</sup>Kelvie revived Bruce's claims in <i>Lochleven and Other
  Poems, by Michael Bruce, with a Life of the Author from Original
  Sources</i> (1837). Logan's authorship rests on the publication of the
  poems under his own name, and his reputation as author during his
  lifetime. His failure to produce the "poem book" of Bruce entrusted to
  him, and the fact that no copy of the "Ode to the Cuckoo" in his
  handwriting was known to exist during Bruce's lifetime, make it difficult
  to relieve him of the charge of plagiarism. Prof. John Veitch, in <i>The
  Feeling for Nature in Scottish Poetry</i> (1887, vol. ii. pp. 89-91),
  points out that the stanza known to be Logan's addition to this ode is
  out of keeping with the rest of the poem, and is in the manner of Logan's
  established compositions, in which there is nothing to suggest the direct
  simplicity of the little poem on the cuckoo.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Bibliography</ph>.—Additions to <i>Poems on
  Several Occasions</i> (1770) were made by Dr M<sup>c</sup>Kelvie in his
  1837 edition. He gives (p. 97) a list of the poems not printed in Logan's
  selection, and of those that are lost. See the "Lives" of Bruce and of
  Logan in Anderson's <i>British Poets</i> (1795); an admirable paper on
  Bruce in <i>The Mirror</i> (No. 36, 1779), said to be by William Craig,
  one of the lords of session; <i>The Poetical Works of Michael Bruce, with
  Life and Writings</i> (1895), by William Stephen, who, like Dr A.B.
  Grosart in his edition (1865) of <i>The Works of Michael Bruce</i>,
  adopts M<sup>c</sup>Kelvie's view. A restatement of the case for Bruce's
  authorship, coupled with a rather violent attack on Logan, is to be found
  in the <i>Life of Michael Bruce, Poet of Loch Leven, with Vindication of
  his Authorship of the "Ode to the Cuckoo" and other Poems, also Copies of
  Letters written by John Logan now first published</i> (1905), by James
  Mackenzie.</p>
   </body>
</topic>