<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e20402">
   <title>BROHAN, AUGUSTINE SUSANNE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROHAN, AUGUSTINE SUSANNE--> (1807-1887), French actress, was born
  in Paris on the 22nd of January 1807. She entered the Conservatoire at
  the age of eleven, and took the second prize for comedy in 1820, and the
  first in 1821. She served her apprenticeship in the provinces, making her
  first Paris appearance at the Odéon in 1832 as Dorine in <i>Tartuffe</i>.
  Her success there and elsewhere brought her a summons to the Comédie
  Française, where she made her <i>début</i> on the 15th of February 1834,
  as Madelon in <i>Les Précieuses ridicules</i>, and Suzanne in <i>Le
  Mariage de Figaro</i>. She retired in 1842, and died on the 16th of
  August 1887.</p>
      <p>Her elder daughter, <ph outputclass="sc">Josephine Félicité Augustine
  Brohan</ph> (1824-1893), was admitted to the Conservatoire when very
  young, twice taking the second prize for comedy. The soubrette part,
  entrusted for more than 150 years at the Comédie Française to a
  succession of artists of the first rank, was at the moment without a
  representative, and Mdlle Augustine Brohan made her <i>début</i> there on
  the 19th of May 1841, as Dorine in <i>Tartuffe</i>, and Lise in <i>Rivaux
  d'eux-mêmes</i>. She was immediately admitted <i>pensionnaire</i>, and at
  the end of eighteen months unanimously elected <i>sociétaire</i>. She
  soon became a great favourite, not only in the plays of Molière and de
  Regnard, but also in those of Marivaux. On her retirement from the stage
  in 1866, she made an unhappy marriage with Edmond David de Gheest (d.
  1885), secretary to the Belgian legation in Paris.</p>
      <p>Susanne Brohan's second daughter, <ph outputclass="sc">Émilie Madeleine
  Brohan</ph> (1833-1900), also took first prize for comedy at the
  Conservatoire (1850). She was engaged at once by the Comédie Française,
  but instead of making her <i>début</i> in some play of the
  <i>répertoire</i> of the theatre, the management put on for her benefit a
  new comedy by Scribe and Legouvé, <i>Les Contes de la reine de
  Navarre</i>, in which she created the part of Marguerite on the 1st of
  September 1850. Her talents and beauty made her a success from the first,
  and in less than two years from her <i>début</i> she was elected
  <i>sociétaire</i>. In 1853 she married Mario Uchard, from whom she was
  soon separated, and in 1858 she returned to the Comédie Française in
  leading parts, until her retirement in 1886. Her name is associated with
  a great number of plays, besides those in the classical
  <i>répertoire</i>, notably <i>Le Monde où l'on s'ennuie</i>, <i>Par droit
  de conquête</i>, <i>Les Deux Veuves</i>, and <i>Le Lion amoureux</i>, in
  which, as the "marquise de Maupas", she had one of her greatest
  successes.</p>
   </body>
</topic>