<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e30677">
   <title>BUCKINGHAMSHIRE, EARLS OF.</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCKINGHAMSHIRE, EARLS OF.--> The first earl of Buckinghamshire
  (to be distinguished from the earls of Buckingham, <i>q.v.</i>) was John
  Hobart (c. 1694-1756), a descendant of Sir Henry Hobart (d. 1625),
  attorney-general and chief justice of the common pleas under James I.,
  who was made a baronet in 1611, and who was the great-grandson of Sir
  James Hobart (d. 1507), attorney-general to Henry VII. The Hobarts had
  been settled in Norfolk and Suffolk for many years, when in 1728 John
  Hobart, who was a son of Sir Henry Hobart, the 4th baronet (d. 1698), was
  created Baron Hobart of Blickling. In 1740 Hobart became lord-lieutenant
  of Norfolk and in 1746 earl of Buckinghamshire, his sister, Henrietta
  Howard, countess of Suffolk, being the mistress of George II. He died on
  the 22nd of September 1756, and was succeeded as 2nd earl<xref href="#d1e30677/Footnote_281" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> by his eldest
  son John (1723-1793), who was member of parliament for Norwich and
  comptroller of the royal household before his accession to the title.
  From 1762 to 1766 he was ambassador to Russia, and from 1776 to 1780
  lord-lieutenant of Ireland, but he was hardly equal to the exceptional
  difficulties with which he had to deal in the latter position. He died
  without sons at Blickling Hall, Norfolk, on the 3rd of August 1793, when
  his half-brother George (c. 1730-1804), became 3rd earl. Blickling Hall
  and his Norfolk estates, however, passed to his daughter, Henrietta
  (1762-1805), the wife of William Kerr, afterwards 6th marquess of
  Lothian.</p>
      <p>Robert Hobart, 4th earl of Buckinghamshire (1760-1816), the eldest son
  of the 3rd earl, was born on the 6th of May 1760. He was a soldier, and
  then a member of both the English and the Irish Houses of Commons; from
  1789 to 1793 he was chief secretary to the lord-lieutenant of Ireland,
  exerting his influence in this country to prevent any concessions to the
  Roman Catholics. In 1793, being known by the courtesy title of Lord
  Hobart, he was sent to Madras as governor, but in 1798, after serious
  differences between himself and the governor-general of India, Sir John
  Shore, afterwards Lord Teignmouth, he was recalled. Returning to British
  politics, Hobart was called up to the House of Lords in 1798 (succeeding
  to the earldom of Buckinghamshire in 1804); he favoured the union between
  England and Ireland; from March 1801 to May 1804 he was secretary for war
  and the colonies (his family name being taken for Hobart Town in
  Tasmania), and in 1805 he became chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster
  under Pitt. For a short time he was joint postmaster-general, and from
  1812 until his death on the 4th of February 1816 he was president of the
  Board of Control, a post for which his Indian experience had fitted
  him.</p>
      <p>The 4th earl left no sons, and his titles passed to his nephew, George
  Robert Hobart (1789-1849), a son of George Vere Hobart (1761-1802),
  lieutenant-governor of Grenada. In 1824 the 5th earl inherited the
  Buckinghamshire estates of the Hampden family and took the name of
  Hampden, his ancestor, Sir John Hobart, 3rd baronet, having married Mary
  Hampden about 1655. On his death in February 1849 his brother, Augustus
  Edward Hobart (1793-1884), who took the name of Hobart-Hampden in 1878,
  became 6th earl. His two sons, Vere Henry, Lord Hobart (1818-1875),
  governor of Madras from 1872, and Frederick John Hobart (1821-1875),
  predeceased him, and when the 6th earl died he was succeeded by his
  grandson, Sidney Carr Hobart-Hampden (b. 1860), who became 7th earl of
  Buckinghamshire, and who added to his name that of Mercer-Henderson.
  Another of the 6th earl's sons was Augustus Charles Hobart-Hampden,
  generally known as Hobart Pasha (<i>q.v.</i>).</p>
      <p>See Lord Hobart's <i>Essays and Miscellaneous Writings</i>, edited
  with biography by Lady Hobart (1885).</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_281"> Until 1784, when
  George Grenville, Earl Temple, was created marquess of Buckingham, the
  2nd earl of Buckinghamshire always signed himself "Buckingham"; his
  contemporaries knew him by this name, and hence a certain amount of
  confusion has arisen.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>