<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23651">
   <title>BROWN, THOMAS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWN, THOMAS--> (1778-1820), Scottish philosopher, was born at
  Kirkmabreck, Kirkcudbright, where his father was parish clergyman. He was
  a boy of a refined nature, a wide reader and an eager student. Educated
  at several schools in London, he went to Edinburgh University in 1792,
  where he attended Dugald Stewart's moral philosophy class. His attendance
  was desultory, and he does not appear to have completed his arts course.
  After studying law for a time he took up medicine; his graduation thesis
  <i>De Somno</i> was well received. But his great strength lay in
  metaphysical analysis, as was shown in his answer to the objections
  raised against the appointment of Sir John Leslie to the mathematical
  professorship (1805). Leslie, a follower of Hume, was attacked by the
  clerical party as a sceptic and an infidel, and Brown took the
  opportunity to defend Hume's doctrine of causality as in no way inimical
  to religion. His defence, at first only a pamphlet, became in its third
  edition a lengthy treatise entitled <i>Inquiry into the Relation of Cause
  and Effect</i>, and is a fine specimen of Brown's analytical faculty. In
  1806 he became a medical practitioner in partnership with James Gregory,
  but, though successful in his profession, preferred literature and
  philosophy. After twice failing in the attempt to gain a professorship in
  the university, he was invited, during an illness of Dugald Stewart in
  the session of 1808-1809, to act as his substitute, and during the
  following session he undertook a great part of Stewart's work. The
  students received him with enthusiasm, due partly to his splendid
  rhetoric and partly to the novelty and ingenuity of his views. In 1810 he
  was appointed as colleague to Stewart, a position which he held for the
  rest of his life. He wrote his lectures at high pressure, and devoted
  much time to the editing and publication of the numerous poems which he
  had written at various times during his life. He was also engaged in
  preparing an abstract of his lectures as a handbook for his class. His
  health, never strong, gave way under the strain of his work. He was
  advised to take a voyage to London, where he died on the 2nd of April
  1820.</p>
      <p>His friend and biographer, David Welsh (1793-1845), superintended the
  publication of his text-book, the <i>Physiology of the Human Mind</i>,
  and his <i>Lectures on the Philosophy of the Human Mind</i> was published
  by his successors, John Stewart and the Rev. E. Milroy. The latter was
  received with great enthusiasm both in England (where it reached its 19th
  edition) and in America; but recent criticism has lessened its popularity
  and it is now almost forgotten.</p>
      <p>Brown's philosophy occupies an intermediate place between the earlier
  Scottish school and the later analytical or associational psychology. To
  the latter Brown really belonged, but he had preserved certain doctrines
  of the older school which were out of harmony with his fundamental view.
  He still retained a small quantum of intuitive beliefs, and did not
  appear to see that the very existence of these could not be explained by
  his theory of mental action. This intermediate or wavering position
  accounts for the comparative neglect into which his works have now
  fallen. They did much to excite thinking, and advanced many problems by
  more than one step, but they did not furnish a coherent system, and the
  doctrines which were then new have since been worked out with greater
  consistency and clearness.</p>
      <p>Brown wrote a criticism of Darwin's <i>Zoonomia</i> (1798), and was
  one of the first contributors to the <i>Edinburgh Review</i>, in the
  second number of which he published a criticism of the Kantian
  philosophy, based entirely on Villers's French account of it. Among his
  poems, which are modelled on Pope and Akenside and rather commonplace,
  may be mentioned: <i>Paradise of Coquettes</i> (1814); <i>Wanderer in
  Norway</i> (1815); <i>Warfiend</i> (1816); <i>Bower of Spring</i> (1817);
  <i>Agnes</i> (1818); <i>Emily</i> (1819); a collected edition in 4 vols.
  appeared in 1820.</p>
      <p>For a severe criticism of Brown's philosophy, see Sir W. Hamilton's
  <i>Discussions</i> and <i>Lectures on Metaphysics</i>; and for a high
  estimate of his merits, see J. S. Mill's <i>Examination of Hamilton</i>.
  See also D. Welsh's <i>Account of the Life and Writings, &amp;c.</i>
  (1825); M<sup>c</sup>Cosh's <i>Scottish Philosophy</i>, pp. 317-337. The
  only German writer who seems to have known anything of Brown is Beneke,
  who found in him anticipations of some of his own doctrines. See <i>Die
  neue Psychologie</i>, pp. 320-330.</p>
   </body>
</topic>