<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e26411">
   <title>BRUNSWICK</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNSWICK,--> a city of Germany, capital of the duchy of that
  name, situated in a fertile and undulating country, on the Oker, 37 m.
  S.E. from Hanover and 53 N.W. from Magdeburg, on the main line of railway
  from Berlin. Pop. (1900) 128,226; (1905) 136,423, of which number about
  9000 were Roman Catholics and 1000 Jews. Brunswick is an interesting
  place and retains much of its medieval character. The fortifications
  which formerly environed it were dismantled in 1797, and have given place
  to a regular circle of gardens and promenades, which rank among the
  finest in Germany. Within them lies the old town, with somewhat narrow
  and crooked streets, remarkable for its numerous ancient houses, with
  high gables and quaintly carved exteriors. In picturesqueness it vies
  with Lübeck and Lüneburg among North German towns. Among its churches,
  the cathedral, St Blasius, or Burgkirche, a Romanesque structure begun by
  Henry the Lion about 1173 and finished in 1194, is of interest. The
  chancel is decorated with 12th-century frescoes by Johannes Gallicus, and
  contains the tombs of the founder and his consort, with beautiful
  effigies in relief, and also that of the emperor Otto IV. In the vault
  beneath rest the remains of the Guelphs of the Brunswick line (since
  1681). Remarkable among other churches are the Magnikirche (consecrated
  in 1031; the present edifice being built between the 13th and 15th
  centuries and restored in 1877); the Martinikirche, with Romanesque
  towers, originally a Romanesque basilica (1180-1190), enlarged in the
  13th century in early Gothic by the addition of vaulted aisles and a
  choir (1490-1500), and remarkable further for the splendid late Gothic
  Annenkapelle (1434) and three magnificent portals; the Katharinenkirche,
  with a fine tower, begun by Henry the Lion in 1172, added to in 1252 and
  finished (choir) in 1500; the Brüderkirche (1361-1451, restored
  1869-1870), formerly the church of a Franciscan house, the refectory of
  which (1486) is now used for military stores; the Andreaskirche (1200,
  1360-1420), partly transitional, partly late Gothic, with a tower 318 ft.
  high; and the Aegidienkirche (1278-1434), now used for exhibitions and
  concerts.</p>
      <p>In secular buildings, both ancient and modern, Brunswick is also rich.
  The most noticeable of these is the town hall (14th and 15th centuries),
  a gem of Gothic architecture. In front of it is a beautiful Gothic leaden
  fountain of the early 15th century. Close by the cathedral is the
  Dankwarderode, a two-storeyed Romanesque building, erected in 1884 on the
  site of the ancient citadel of the same name which was destroyed by fire
  in 1873; the cloth merchants' hall (Gewandhaus) of the 13th century, with
  a richly ornamented facade in Renaissance style, now occupied by the
  chamber of commerce; the restored Huneborstelsche Haus with its curious
  and beautiful oak carving of the 16th century. The ducal palace is a fine
  modern structure, erected since 1865, when most of the previous building,
  which dated only from 1831, was destroyed by fire. The famous Quadriga of
  Rietschel, which perished at the same time, has been replaced by a copy
  by Georg Howaldt (1802-1883). The theatre lies on a spacious square close
  to the ducal gardens, and immediately outside the promenades; to the
  south is the handsome railway station. Among other numerous buildings of
  modern erection may be mentioned the new town hall (1895-1900) and the
  ministry of finance, both in early Gothic style. The scientific and art
  collections of Brunswick are numerous. The ducal museum contains a rich
  collection of antique and medieval curiosities, engravings and pictures.
  There are also a municipal museum, a museum of natural history, a
  mineralogical collection, a botanical garden and two libraries. The
  educational and charitable institutions of Brunswick are many. Of the
  former may be mentioned the Collegium Carolinum, founded in 1745, the
  technical high school, two gymnasia and an academy of forestry. Among the
  latter are a deaf and dumb institution, a blind asylum, an orphanage and
  various hospitals and infirmaries. A monument, 60 ft. high, to Duke
  Frederick William, who was slain at Quatre Bras, gives its name to the
  Monumentsplatz. Another to the south-east of the town perpetuates the
  memory of Schill Ferdinand (1776-1809) and his companions. There are also
  statues of Franz Abt, the composer, of Lessing and of the astronomer K.F.
  Gauss.</p>
      <p>The industries of the town are considerable. Especially important are
  the manufacture of machinery, boilers, gasometers, pianos, preserves,
  chemicals, beer and sausages. Brunswick is also a leading centre of the
  book trade. The communications between the inner town and the extensive
  suburbs are maintained by an excellent service of electric tramways.</p>
      <p>Brunswick is said to have been founded about 861 by Bruno, son of Duke
  Ludolf of Saxony, from whom it was named Brunswick (from the Old High
  German <i>Wich</i>, hamlet). Afterwards fortified and improved by Henry
  the Lion, it became one of the most important cities of northern Germany.
  For a long time its constitution was rather peculiar, as it consisted of
  five separate townlets, each with its own walls and gates, its own
  council and Rathaus—a condition traces of which are still evident.
  In the 13th century it ranked among the first cities of the Hanseatic
  League. After this era, however, it declined in prosperity, in
  consequence of the divisions of territory among the branches of the
  reigning house, the jealousy of the neighbouring states, the Thirty
  Years' War, and more recently the French occupation, under which it was
  assigned to the kingdom of Westphalia. During the time of the Reformation
  the sympathies of the citizens were with the new teaching, and the city
  was a member of the League of Schmalkalden. In 1830 it was the scene of a
  violent revolution, which led to the removal of the reigning duke. In
  1834 it attained municipal self-government.</p>
      <p>See F. Knoll, <i>Braunschweig und Umgebung</i> (1882); Sack, <i>Kurze
  Geschichte der Stadt Braunschweig</i> (1861); and H. Dürre, <i>Geschichte
  der Stadt Braunschweig im Mittelalter</i> (1875).</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page691">[v.04 p.0691]</ph>
      </p>
   </body>
</topic>