<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e24009">
   <title>BROWNE, ROBERT</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWNE, ROBERT--> (1550-1633), a leader among the early Separatist
  Puritans (hence sometimes called Brownists), was born about 1550 at
  Tolethorpe, near Stamford. He was of an ancient family, several members
  of which had been distinguished as merchants, county magnates and local
  benefactors. He was educated at Corpus Christi College, Cambridge,
  "commencing B.A." in 1572. For some years he was a schoolmaster, but in
  what place is uncertain. In 1579, on a brother's application and without
  his own consent, he was licensed to preach, and actually preached for
  some six months in Cambridge, where he gained considerable popularity;
  but impugning the episcopal order of the Established Church, he had his
  licence revoked early in the following year. He then went, on the
  invitation of Robert Harrison, "Maister in the Hospitall," to Norwich,
  where he soon gathered a numerous congregation, the members of which
  became associated in a religious "covenant," to the refusing of "all
  ungodlie communion with wicked persons." He seems also to have preached
  in various parts of Norfolk and Suffolk, especially at Bury St Edmunds,
  and vigorously denounced the form of government existing in the Church,
  which at this time he held incompatible with true "preaching of the
  word." Dr Freake, bishop of Norwich, caused him to be imprisoned early in
  1581, but he was ere long released through the influence of his remote
  kinsman, the Lord Treasurer Burghley. Before the end of 1581, however, he
  incurred two more imprisonments, and, apparently in January 1582,
  migrated with his whole company to Middelburg in Zealand. There they
  organized a church on what they conceived to be the New Testament model,
  but the community broke up within two years owing to internal
  dissensions.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, Browne issued two most important works, <i>A Treatise of
  Reformation without Tarying for Anie</i>, in which he asserts the
  inalienable right of the church to effect necessary reforms without the
  authorization or permission of the civil magistrate; and <i>A Booke which
  sheweth the life and manners of all True Christians</i>, in which he
  enunciates the theory of Congregational independency (see <ph outputclass="sc">Congregationalism</ph>). These, with a third tract (<i>A
  Treatise upon the 23. of Matthew</i>, see C. Burrage, as below, pp.
  21-25), making together a thin quarto, were published at Middelburg in
  1582. The following year two men were hanged at Bury St Edmunds for
  circulating them. In January 1584<xref href="#d1e24009/Footnote_181" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> Browne and some of his company
  came to Edinburgh, after visiting Dundee and St Andrews. He remained some
  months in Scotland, endeavouring to commend his ecclesiastical theories,
  but had no success. He then returned to Stamford, in which town or
  neighbourhood he seems to have resided chiefly for the next two years,
  his residence being broken by visits to London and probably to the
  continent (early in 1585), and by at least one imprisonment (summer,
  1585). His attitude to the lawfulness of occasional attendance at
  services in parish churches seems to have been changing about this time;
  on the <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page666">[v.04
  p.0666]</ph>7th of October 1585 he was induced to make a qualified
  submission to the established order. The story that this result was
  brought about by excommunication, actual or threatened, is very doubtful,
  and rests on late and questionable authority. A further submission
  prepared the way for his appointment, in November 1586, to the mastership
  of St Olave's grammar school, Southwark, which he held for more than two
  years. During part of this time he was much engaged in controversy, on
  the one hand with Stephen Bredwell, an uncompromising advocate of the
  established order, and on the other with some of those who more or less
  occupied his own earlier position, and now looked upon him as a renegade.
  In particular he several times replied to Barrowe and Greenwood; one of
  his replies, entitled <i>A Reproofe of certaine schismatical persons and
  their doctrine touching the hearing and preaching of the word of God</i>
  (1587-1588), has recently been recovered, and sheds a flood of light upon
  the development of Browne's later views (see Burrage, pp. 45-62, for this
  whole period).</p>
      <p>Before the 20th of June 1589 his mastership of St Olave's seems to
  have terminated, and after being rector of Little Casterton (in the gift
  of his eldest brother) for a month or two, he finally, in September 1591,
  accepted episcopal ordination and the rectory of Achurch-cum-Thorpe
  Waterville, in Northamptonshire. There he ministered for forty-two years,
  with one lengthy interval, 1617-1626, which is only partly accounted for
  (see Burrage, pp. 68-71). There is reason to believe that he never
  entirely abandoned his early ideal, but latterly thought it possible to
  maintain a spiritual fellowship within the framework of the Established
  Church. The closing years of his life seem to have been clouded, due
  partly to separation among his own flock, and partly to growing
  irritability in himself, a lonely and disappointed man. When over eighty
  years old he had a dispute with the parish constable about a rate, blows
  were struck, and before a magistrate he behaved so stubbornly that he was
  sent to Northampton gaol, where he died in October 1633. He was buried in
  St Giles's churchyard, Northampton. In spite of his later attitude of
  compromise with expediency, which he felt forced on him by external
  conditions too strong to defy or ignore, Robert Browne remains a pioneer
  in ecclesiastical theory in England, the first formulator of an ideal
  which subsequently became known as Congregationalism (<i>q.v.</i>). He
  rediscovered certain forgotten aspects of primitive church life, and did
  not shrink from suffering for the sake of what he held to be the truth.
  In addition to the works above-mentioned, Browne wrote several
  controversial and apologetic treatises, of which some remained in MS.
  until quite recently, and some are still missing.</p>
      <p>See H.M. Dexter, <i>The Congregationalism of the Last Three Hundred
  Years</i> (1880); C. Burrage, <i>The True Story of Robert Browne</i>
  (Oxford, 1906); <i>Congregational Historical Society's Transactions</i>,
  passim (1901-1906).</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_181"> Probably after
  writing <i>A True and Short Declaration</i>, the main source of our
  knowledge of his life hitherto.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>