<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22287">
   <title>BROOKITE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROOKITE,--> one of the three modifications in which titanium
  dioxide (TiO<sub>2</sub>) occurs in nature; the other minerals with the
  same chemical composition, but with different physical and
  crystallographic characters, being rutile (<i>q.v.</i>) and anatase
  (<i>q.v.</i>) The two latter are tetragonal in crystallization, whilst
  brookite is orthorhombic. The name was given by A. Lévy in 1825 in honour
  of the English mineralogist H.J. Brooke (1771-1857). Two types of
  brookite crystals may be distinguished. The commoner type of crystals are
  thin and tabular, and often terminated by numerous small and brilliant
  faces (fig. 1); the faces of the orthopinacoid (<i>a</i>) and of the
  prisms (<i>m</i>, <i>l</i>) are vertically striated. These crystals are
  of a rich reddish-brown colour and are often translucent. Crystals of the
  second type have the appearance of six-sided bipyramids (fig. 2) owing to
  the equal development of the prism <i>m</i> {110} and the pyramid
  <i>e</i> {122}; these crystals are black and opaque, and constitute the
  variety known as arkansite.</p>
      <p>The lustre of brookite is metallic-adamantine. There is no distinct
  cleavage (rutile and anatase have cleavages); hardness 5½-6; sp. gr. 4.0.
  The optical characters are interesting: the optic axes for red and for
  blue light lie in planes at right angles to each other, whilst for
  yellow-green light the crystals are uniaxial. The acute bisectrix of the
  optic axes is perpendicular to the orthopinacoid (<i>a</i>) for all
  colours, so that this phenomenon of the crossing of the optic axial
  planes may be readily observed in the thin tabular crystals of the
  first-mentioned type.</p>
      <p>Brookite occurs only as crystals, never in compact masses, and is
  usually associated with either anatase or rutile. The crystals are found
  attached to the walls of cavities in decomposed igneous rocks and
  crystalline schists; it is also found as minute isolated crystals in many
  sedimentary rocks. The best-known locality is Fronolen near Tremadoc in
  North Wales, where crystals of the thin tabular habit occur with
  crystallized quartz, albite and anatase on the walls of crevices in
  diabase. Similar crystals of relatively large size are found attached to
  gneiss at several places in the Swiss and Tirolese Alps. Thicker crystals
  of prismatic, rather than tabular, habit and of a rich red colour
  combined with considerable transparency and brilliancy are found in the
  gold-washings of the Sanarka river in the southern Urals. The arkansite
  variety occurs with rutile in the elaeolite-syenite of Magnet Cove in Hot
  Spring county, Arkansas. Minute crystals of brookite have been detected
  with anatase and rutile in the iron-ore of Cleveland in Yorkshire.</p>
      <p>Crystals of brookite, as well as of anatase and rutile, have been
  prepared artificially by the interaction of steam and titanium fluoride,
  the particular modification of titanium dioxide which results depending
  on the temperature at which the reaction takes place. Brookite is liable
  to become altered to rutile: aggregates of rutile needles with the form
  of brookite (arkansite) are not uncommon at Magnet Cove, Arkansas.</p>
      <p>(L. J. S.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>