<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e32706">
   <title>BUDÉ</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUDÉ--> [<ph outputclass="sc">Budaeus</ph>], <b>GUILLAUME</b>
  (1467-1540), French scholar, was born at Paris. He went to the university
  of Orleans to study law, but for several years, being possessed of ample
  means, he led an idle and dissipated life. When about twenty-four years
  of age he was seized with a sudden passion for study, and made rapid
  progress, particularly in the Latin and Greek languages. The work which
  gained him greatest reputation was his <i>De Asse et Partibus</i> (1514),
  a treatise on ancient coins and measures. He was held in high esteem by
  Francis I., who was persuaded by him, and by Jean du Bellay, bishop of
  Narbonne, to found the Collegium Trilingue, afterwards the Collège de
  France, and the library at Fontainebleau, which was removed to Paris and
  was the origin of the Bibliothèque Nationale. He also induced Francis to
  refrain from prohibiting printing in France, which had been advised by
  the Sorbonne in 1533. He was sent by Louis XII. to Rome as ambassador to
  Leo X., and in 1522 was appointed <i>maître des requêtes</i> and was
  several times <i>prévôt des marchands</i>. He died in Paris on the 23rd
  of August 1540.</p>
      <p>Budé was also the author of <i>Annotationes in XXIV. libros
  Pandectarum</i> (1508), which, by the application of philology and
  history, had a great influence on the study of Roman law, and of
  <i>Commentarii linguae Graecae</i> (1529), an extensive collection of
  lexicographical notes, which contributed greatly to the study of Greek
  literature in France. Budé corresponded with the most learned men of his
  time, amongst them Erasmus, who called him the marvel of France, and
  Thomas More. He wrote with equal facility in Greek and Latin, although
  his Latin is inferior to his Greek, being somewhat harsh and full of
  Greek constructions. His request that he should be buried at night, and
  his widow's open profession of Protestantism at Geneva (where she retired
  after his death), caused him to be suspected of leanings towards
  Calvinism. At the time of the massacre of St Bartholomew, the members of
  his family were obliged to flee from France. Some took refuge in
  Switzerland, where they worthily upheld the traditions of their house,
  while others settled in Pomerania under the name Budde or Buddeus.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page750">[v.04 p.0750]</ph>
      </p>
      <p>See Le Roy, <i>Vita G. Budaei</i> (1540); Rebitté, <i>G. Budé,
  restaurateur des études grecques en France</i> (1846); E. de Budé, <i>Vie
  de G. Budé</i> (1884), who refutes the idea of his ancestor's Protestant
  views; D'Hozier, <i>La Maison de Budé</i>; L. Delaruelle, <i>Études sur
  l'humanisme français</i> (1907).</p>
   </body>
</topic>