<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12796">
   <title>BRISTOL, EARLS AND MARQUESSES OF.</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRISTOL, EARLS AND MARQUESSES OF.--> This English title has been
  held in the Hervey family since 1714, though previously an earldom of
  Bristol, in the Digby family, is associated with two especially famous
  representatives, of whom separate biographies are given. The Herveys are
  mentioned during the 13th century as seated in Bedfordshire, and
  afterwards in Suffolk, where they have held the estate of Ickworth since
  the 15th century. John Hervey (1616-1679) was the eldest son of Sir
  William Hervey (d. 1660), and was born on the 18th of August 1616. He
  held a high position in the household of Catherine, wife of Charles II.,
  and was for many years member of parliament for Hythe. He married
  Elizabeth, the only surviving child of his kinsman, William, Lord Hervey
  of Kidbrooke (d. 1642), but left no children when he died on the 18th of
  January 1679, and his estates passed to his brother, Sir Thomas Hervey.
  Sir Thomas, who was member of parliament for Bury St Edmunds, died on the
  27th of May 1694, and was succeeded by his son, John, who became the 1st
  earl of Bristol.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">John Hervey</ph>, 1st earl of Bristol (1665-1751),
  born on the 27th of August 1665, was educated at Clare Hall, Cambridge,
  and became member of parliament for Bury St Edmunds in March 1694. In
  March 1703 he was created Baron Hervey of Ickworth, and in October 1714
  was made earl of Bristol as a reward for his zeal in promoting the
  principles of the revolution and supporting the Hanoverian succession. He
  died on the 20th of January 1751. By his first wife, Isabella (d. 1693),
  daughter of Sir Robert Carr, Bart., of Sleaford, he had one son, Carr,
  Lord Hervey (1691-1723), who was educated at Clare Hall, Cambridge, and
  was member for Bury St Edmunds from 1713 to 1722. (It has been suggested
  that Carr, who died unmarried on the 14th of November 1723, was the
  father of Horace Walpole.) He married secondly Elizabeth (d. 1741),
  daughter and co-heiress of Sir Thomas Felton, Bart., of Playford,
  Suffolk, by whom he had ten sons and six daughters. His eldest son, John
  (1696-1743), took the courtesy title of Lord Hervey on the death of his
  half-brother, Carr, in 1723, and gained some renown both as a writer and
  a politician (see <ph outputclass="sc">Hervey of Ickworth</ph>). Another
  son, Thomas (1699-1775), was one of the members for Bury from 1733 to
  1747; held various offices at court; and eloped with Elizabeth, wife of
  Sir Thomas Hanmer. He had very poor health, and his reckless life
  frequently brought him into pecuniary and other difficulties. He wrote
  numerous pamphlets, and when he died Dr Johnson said of him, "Tom Hervey,
  though a vicious man, was one of the genteelest men who ever lived."
  Another of the 1st earl's sons, Felton (1712-1773), was also member for
  the family borough of Bury St Edmunds. Having assumed the additional name
  of Bathurst, Felton's grandson, Felton Elwell Hervey-Bathurst
  (1782-1819), was created a baronet in 1818, and on his death a year later
  the title descended to his brother, Frederick Anne (1783-1824), the
  direct ancestor of the present baronet. The 1st earl died in January
  1751, the title and estates descending to his grandson.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">George William Hervey</ph>, 2nd earl of Bristol
  (1721-1775), the eldest son of John, Lord Hervey of Ickworth, by his
  marriage with Mary (1700-1768), daughter of Nicholas Lepell, was born on
  the 31st of August 1721. He served for some years in the army, and in
  1755 was sent to Turin as envoy extraordinary. He was ambassador at
  Madrid from 1758 to 1761, filling a difficult position with credit and
  dignity, and ranked among the followers of Pitt. Appointed
  lord-lieutenant of Ireland in 1766, he never visited that country during
  his short tenure of this office, and, after having served for a short
  time as keeper of the privy seal, became groom of the stole to George
  III. in January 1770. He died unmarried on the 18th or 20th of March
  1775, and was succeeded by his brother.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Augustus John Hervey</ph>, 3rd earl of Bristol
  (1724-1779), was born on the 19th of May 1724, and entered the navy,
  where his promotion was rapid. He distinguished himself in several
  encounters with the French, and was of great assistance to Admiral Hawke
  in 1759, although he had returned to England before the battle of
  Quiberon Bay in November 1759. Having served with distinction in the West
  Indies under Rodney, his active life at sea ceased when the peace of
  Paris was concluded in February 1763. He was, however, nominally
  commander-in-chief in the Mediterranean in this year, and was made
  vice-admiral of the blue in January 1778. Hervey was member of parliament
  for Bury from 1757 to 1763, and after being for a short time member for
  Saltash, again represented Bury from 1768 until he succeeded his brother
  in the peerage in 1775. He often took part in debates in parliament, and
  was a frequent contributor to periodical literature. Having served as a
  lord of the admiralty from 1771 to 1775 he won some notoriety as an
  opponent of the Rockingham ministry and a defender of Admiral Keppel. In
  August 1744 he had been secretly married to Elizabeth Chudleigh
  (1720-1788), afterwards duchess of Kingston (<i>q.v.</i>), but this union
  was dissolved in 1769. The earl died in London on the 23rd of December
  1779, leaving no legitimate issue, and having, as far as possible,
  alienated his property from the <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page576">[v.04 p.0576]</ph>title. He was succeeded by his
  brother. Many of his letters are in the Record Office, and his journals
  in the British Museum. Other letters are printed in the <i>Grenville
  Papers</i>, vols. iii. and iv. (London, 1852-1853), and the <i>Life of
  Admiral Keppel</i>, by the Hon. T. Keppel (London, 1852).</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Frederick Augustus Hervey</ph>, bishop of Derry
  (1730-1803), who now became 4th earl of Bristol, was born on the 1st of
  August 1730, and educated at Westminster school and Corpus Christi
  College, Cambridge, graduating in 1754. Entering the church he became a
  royal chaplain; and while waiting for other preferment spent some time in
  Italy, whither he was led by his great interest in art. In February 1767,
  while his brother, the 2nd earl, was lord-lieutenant of Ireland, he was
  made bishop of Cloyne, and having improved the property of the see he was
  translated to the rich bishopric of Derry a year later. Here again he was
  active and philanthropic. While not neglecting his luxurious personal
  tastes he spent large sums of money on making roads and assisting
  agriculture, and his munificence was shared by the city of Londonderry.
  He built splendid residences at Downhill and Ballyscullion, which he
  adorned with rare works of art. As a bishop, Hervey was industrious and
  vigilant; he favoured complete religious equality, and was opposed to the
  system of tithes. In December 1779 he became earl of Bristol, and in
  spite of his brother's will succeeded to a considerable property. Having
  again passed some time in Italy, he returned to Ireland and in 1782 threw
  himself ardently into the Irish volunteer movement, quickly attaining a
  prominent position among the volunteers, and in great state attending the
  convention held in Dublin in November 1783. Carried away by his position
  and his popularity he talked loudly of rebellion, and his violent
  language led the government to contemplate his arrest. Subsequently he
  took no part in politics, spending his later years mainly on the
  continent of Europe. In 1798 he was imprisoned by the French at Milan,
  remaining in custody for eighteen months. He died at Albano on the 8th of
  July 1803, and was buried in Ickworth church. Varying estimates have been
  found of his character, including favourable ones by John Wesley and
  Jeremy Bentham. He was undoubtedly clever and cultured, but licentious
  and eccentric. In later life he openly professed materialistic opinions;
  he fell in love with the countess Lichtenau, mistress of Frederick
  William II., king of Prussia; and by his bearing he gave fresh point to
  the saying that "God created men, women and Herveys." In 1752 he had
  married Elizabeth (d. 1800), daughter of Sir Jermyn Davers, Bart., by
  whom he had two sons and three daughters. His elder son, Augustus John,
  Lord Hervey (1757-1796), had predeceased his father, and he was succeeded
  in the title by his younger son.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Frederick William Hervey</ph>, 5th earl and 1st
  marquess of Bristol (1769-1859), was born on the 2nd of October 1769. He
  married Elizabeth Albana (d. 1844), daughter of Clotworthy, 1st Baron
  Templetown, by whom he had six sons and three daughters. In 1826 he was
  created marquess of Bristol and Earl Jermyn, and died on the 15th of
  February 1859. He was succeeded by his son Frederick William (1800-1864),
  M.P. for Bury St Edmunds 1830-1859, as 2nd marquess; and by the latter's
  son Frederick William John (1834-1907), M.P. for West Suffolk 1859-1864,
  as 3rd marquess. The latter's nephew, Frederick William Fane Hervey (b.
  1863), who succeeded as 4th marquess, served with distinction in the
  royal navy, and was M.P. for Bury St Edmunds from 1906 to 1907.</p>
      <p>See John, Lord Hervey, <i>Memoirs of the Reign of George II</i>.,
  edited by J.W. Croker (London, 1884); John Hervey, 1st earl of Bristol,
  <i>Diary</i> (Wells, 1894); and <i>Letter Books of Bristol; with Sir T.
  Hervey's Letters during Courtship and Poems during Widowhood</i> (Wells,
  1894). Also the articles in the <i>Dictionary of National Biography</i>,
  vol. xxvi. (London, 1891).</p>
   </body>
</topic>