<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23805">
   <title>BROWNE, HABLÔT KNIGHT</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWNE, HABLÔT KNIGHT--> (1815-1882), English artist, famous as
  "Phiz," the illustrator of the best-known books by Charles Dickens,
  Charles Lever and Harrison Ainsworth in their original editions. His
  talents in other directions of art were of a very ordinary kind. As an
  interpreter and illustrator of Dickens's characters, "Phiz," as he always
  signed his drawings, was in some respects the equal of his rivals
  Cruikshank and Leech, while, in his own way, he excelled them both. Of
  Huguenot extraction, he was born in Lambeth on the 11th of June 1815. His
  father died early and left the family badly off. Browne was apprenticed
  to Finden, the eminent engraver on steel, in whose studio he obtained his
  only artistic education. To engraving, however, he was entirely unsuited,
  and having in 1833 secured an important prize from the Society of Arts
  for a drawing of "John Gilpin," he abandoned engraving in the following
  year and took to other artistic work, with the ultimate object of
  becoming a painter. In the spring of 1836 he met Charles <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page664">[v.04
  p.0664]</ph>Dickens. It was at the moment when the serial publication
  of <i>Pickwick</i> was in danger from the want of a capable interpreter
  for the illustrations. Dickens knew Browne slightly as the illustrator of
  his little pamphlet <i>Sunday under Three Heads</i>, and probably this
  slight knowledge of his work stood the draughtsman in good stead. In the
  original edition of <i>Pickwick</i>, issued in shilling monthly parts
  from early in 1836 until the end of 1837, the first seven plates were
  drawn by Robert Seymour, a clever illustrator who committed suicide in
  April 1836. The next two plates were by R.W. Buss, an otherwise
  successful portrait-painter and lecturer, but they were so poor that a
  change was imperative. Browne and W.M. Thackeray called independently at
  the publishers' office with specimens of their powers for Dickens's
  inspection. The novelist preferred Browne. Browne's first two etched
  plates for <i>Pickwick</i> were signed "Nemo," but the third was signed
  "Phiz," a pseudonym which was retained in future. When asked to explain
  why he chose this name he answered that the change from "Nemo" to "Phiz"
  was made "to harmonize better with Dickens's Boz." Possibly Browne
  adopted it to conceal his identity, hoping one day to become famous as a
  painter. It is to be noted, however, that "Phiz" is usually attached to
  his better work and H.K.B. to his less successful drawings. "Phiz"
  undoubtedly created Sam Weller, so far as his well-known figure is
  concerned, as Seymour had created Pickwick. Dickens and "Phiz" were
  personally good friends in early days, and in 1838 travelled together to
  Yorkshire to see the schools of which Nicholas Nickleby became the hero;
  afterwards they made several journeys of this nature in company to
  facilitate the illustrator's work. The other Dickens characters which
  "Phiz" realized most successfully are perhaps Squeers, Micawber, Guppy,
  Major Bagstock, Mrs Gamp, Tom Pinch and, above all, David Copperfield. Of
  the books by Dickens which "Phiz" illustrated the best are <i>David
  Copperfield</i>, <i>Pickwick</i>, <i>Dombey and Son</i>, <i>Martin
  Chuzzlewit</i> and <i>Bleak House</i>. Browne made several drawings for
  <i>Punch</i> in early days and also towards the end of his life; his
  chief work in this direction being the clever design for the wrapper
  which was used for eighteen months from January 1842. He also contributed
  to <i>Punch's Pocket Books</i>. In addition to his work for Dickens,
  "Phiz" illustrated over twenty of Lever's novels (the most successful
  being <i>Harry Lorrequer</i>, <i>Charles O'Malley</i>, <i>Jack Hinton</i>
  and the <i>Knight of Gwynne</i>). He also illustrated Harrison
  Ainsworth's and Frank Smedley's novels. <i>Mervyn Clitheroe</i> by
  Ainsworth is one of the most admirable of the artist's Works. Browne was
  in continual employment by publishers until 1867, when he had a stroke of
  paralysis. Although he recovered slightly and made many illustrations on
  wood, they were by comparison inferior productions which the
  draughtsman's admirers would willingly ignore. In 1878 he was awarded an
  annuity by the Royal Academy. He gradually became worse in health, until
  he died on the 8th of July 1882.</p>
      <p>Most of Browne's work was etched on steel plates because these yielded
  a far larger edition than copper. Browne was annoyed at some of his
  etchings being transferred to stone by the publishers and printed as
  lithographic reproductions. Partly with the view to prevent this
  treatment of his work he employed a machine to rule a series of lines
  over the plate in order to obtain what appeared to be a tint; when
  manipulated with acid this tint gave an effect somewhat resembling
  mezzotint, which at that time it was found practically impossible to
  transfer to stone. The illustrations executed by Browne are particularly
  noteworthy because they realized exactly what the reader most desired to
  see represented. So skilful was he in drawing and composition that no
  part of the story was avoided by reason of the elaborateness of the
  subject. Whatever was the best incident for illustration was always the
  one selected.</p>
      <p>See D. Croal Thomson, <i>Hablôt Knight Browne, "Phiz": Life and
  Letters</i> (London, 1884); John Forster, <i>Life of Charles Dickens</i>
  (London, 1871-1874); F.G. Kitton, <i>"Phiz": A Memoir</i> (London, 1882);
  <i>Charles Dickens and his Illustrators</i> (London, 1899); M.H.
  Spielmann, <i>The History of Punch</i> (London, 1895).</p>
      <p>(D. C. T.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>