<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e19655">
   <title>BROACH</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROACH,--> or <ph outputclass="sc">Bharuch</ph>, an ancient city and
  modern district of British India, in the northern division of Bombay. The
  city is on the right bank of the Nerbudda, about 30 m. from the sea, and
  203 m. N. of Bombay. The area, including suburbs, occupies 2-1/6 sq. m.
  Pop. (1901) 42,896. The sea-borne trade is confined to a few coasting
  vessels. Handloom-weaving is almost extinct, but several cotton mills
  have been opened. There are also large flour-mills. Broach is the
  Barakacheva of the Chinese traveller Hsüan Tsang and the Barygaza of
  Ptolemy and Arrian. Upon the conquest of Gujarat by the Mahommedans, and
  the formation of the state of that name, Broach formed part of the new
  kingdom. On its overthrow by Akbar in 1572, it was annexed to the Mogul
  empire and governed by a Nawab. The Mahrattas became its masters in 1685,
  from which period it was held in subordination to the peshwa until 1772,
  when it was captured by a force under General Wedderburn (brother to Lord
  Loughborough), who was killed in the assault. In 1783 it was ceded by the
  British to Sindhia in acknowledgment of certain services. It was stormed
  in 1803 by a detachment commanded by Colonel Woodington, and was finally
  ceded to the East India Company by Sindhia under the treaty of Sarji
  Anjangaom.</p>
      <p>The <ph outputclass="sc">District of Broach</ph> contains an area of
  1467 sq. m. Consisting chiefly of the alluvial plain at the mouth of the
  river Nerbudda, the land is rich and highly cultivated, and though it is
  without forests it is not wanting in trees. The district is well supplied
  with rivers, having in addition to the Nerbudda the Mahi in the north and
  the Kim in the south. The population comprises several distinct races or
  castes, who, while speaking a common dialect, Gujarati, inhabit separate
  villages. Thus there are Koli, Kunbi or Voro (Bora) villages, and others
  whose lands are almost entirely held and cultivated by high castes, such
  as Rajputs, Brahmans or Parsees. In 1901 the population was 291,763,
  showing a decrease of 15%, compared with an increase of 5% in the
  preceding decade. The principal crops are cotton, millet, wheat and
  pulse. Dealing in cotton is the chief industry, the dealers being
  organized in a gild. Besides the cotton mills in Broach city there are
  several factories for ginning and pressing cotton, some of them on a very
  large scale. The district is traversed throughout its length by the
  Bombay &amp; Baroda railway, which crosses the Nerbudda opposite Broach
  city on an iron-girder bridge of 67 spans. The district suffered severely
  from the famine of 1899-1900.</p>
   </body>
</topic>