<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e31015">
   <title>BUCKTHORN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCKTHORN,--> known botanically as <i>Rhamnus cathartica</i>
  (natural order Rhamnaceae), a much-branched shrub reaching 10 ft. in
  height, with a blackish bark, spinous branchlets, and ovate,
  sharply-serrated leaves, 1 to 2 in. long, arranged several together at
  the ends of the shoots. The small green flowers are regular and have the
  parts in fours; male and female flowers are borne on different plants.
  The fruit is succulent, black and globose, and contains four stones. The
  plant is a native of England, occurring in woods and thickets chiefly on
  the chalk; it is rare in Ireland and not wild in Scotland. It is native
  in Europe, north Africa and north Asia, and naturalized in some parts of
  eastern North America. The fruit has strong purgative properties, and the
  bark yields a yellow dye.</p>
      <p>An allied species, <i>Rhamnus Frangula</i>, is also common in England,
  and is known as berry-bearing or black alder. It is distinguished from
  buckthorn by the absence of spiny branchlets, its non-serrated leaves,
  and bisexual flowers with parts in fives. The fruits are purgative and
  yield a green dye when unripe. The soft porous wood, called black
  dogwood, is used for gunpowder. Dyes are obtained from fruits and bark of
  other species of <i>Rhamnus</i>, such as <i>R. infectoria</i>, <i>R.
  tinctoria</i> and <i>R. davurica</i>—the two latter yielding the
  China green of commerce. Several varieties of <i>R. Alaternus</i>, a
  Mediterranean species, are grown in shrubberies.</p>
      <p>Sea-buckthorn is <i>Hippophae rhamnoides</i>, a willow-like shrub, 1
  to 8 ft. in height, with narrow leaves silvery on the underside, and
  globose orange-yellow fruits one-third of an inch in diameter. It occurs
  on sandy seashores from York to Kent and Sussex, but is not common.</p>
      <p>American buckthorns are: <i>Rhamnus purshiana</i> or <i>Cascara
  sagrada</i>, of the Pacific coast, producing cascara bark, and <i>R.
  Caroliniana</i>, the alder-buckthorn. <i>Bumelia lycioides</i> (or
  <i>lanuginosa</i>) is popularly called "southern buckthorn."</p>
   </body>
</topic>