<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12658">
   <title>BRISBANE, SIR THOMAS MAKDOUGALL</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRISBANE, SIR THOMAS MAKDOUGALL--> (1773-1860), Scottish soldier
  and astronomer, was born on the 23rd of July 1773 at Brisbane House, near
  Largs, in Ayrshire. He entered the army in 1789, and served in Flanders,
  the West Indies and the Peninsula. In 1814 he was sent to North America;
  on the return of Napoleon from Elba he was recalled, but did not arrive
  in time to take part in the battle of Waterloo. In 1821 he was appointed
  governor of New South Wales. During the four years for which he held that
  office, although he allowed the finances of the colony to get into
  confusion, he endeavoured to improve its condition by introducing the
  vine, sugar-cane and tobacco plant, and by encouraging the breeding of
  horses and the reclamation of land. At his instigation exploring parties
  were sent out, and one of these discovered the Brisbane river which was
  named after him. He established an astronomical observatory at Paramatta
  in 1822, and the <i>Brisbane Catalogue</i>, which was printed in 1835 and
  contained 7385 stars, was the result of observations made there in
  1822-1826. The observatory was discontinued in 1855. After his return to
  Scotland he resided chiefly at Makerstoun in Roxburghshire, where, as at
  Brisbane House, he had a large and admirably equipped observatory.
  Important magnetic observations were begun at Makerstoun in 1841, and the
  results gained him in 1848 the Keith prize of the Royal Society of
  Edinburgh, in whose <i>Transactions</i> they were published. In 1836 he
  was made a baronet, and G.C.B. in 1837; and in 1841 he became general. He
  was elected president of the Royal Society of Edinburgh after the death
  of Sir Walter Scott in 1833, and in the following year acted as president
  of the British Association. He died at Brisbane House on the 27th of
  January 1860. He founded two gold medals for the encouragement of
  scientific research, one in the <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page574">[v.04 p.0574]</ph>award of the Royal Society of
  Edinburgh, and the other in that of the Scottish Society of Arts.</p>
   </body>
</topic>