<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e20505">
   <title>BROKE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROKE, SIR PHILIP BOWES VERE,--> <ph outputclass="scac">BART.</ph>
  (1776-1841), British rear-admiral, was born at Broke Hall, near Ipswich,
  on the 9th of September 1776, a member of an old Suffolk family. Entering
  the navy in June 1792, he saw active service in the Mediterranean from
  1793 to 1795, and was with the British fleet at the battle of Cape St
  Vincent, 1797. In 1798 he was present at the defeat and capture of the
  French squadron off the north coast of Ireland. From 1799 to 1801 he
  served with the North Sea fleet, and in the latter year was made captain.
  Unemployed for the next four years, he commanded in 1805 a frigate in the
  English and Irish Channels. In 1806 he was appointed to the command of
  the "Shannon", 38-gun frigate, remaining afloat, principally in the Bay
  of Biscay, till 1811. The "Shannon" was then ordered to Halifax, Nova
  Scotia. For a year after the declaration of war between Great Britain and
  the United States in 1812, the frigate saw no important service, though
  she captured several prizes. Broke utilized this period of comparative
  inactivity to train his men thoroughly. He paid particular attention to
  gunnery, and the "Shannon" ere long gained a unique reputation for
  excellence of shooting. Broke's opportunity came in 1813. In May of that
  year the "Shannon" was cruising off Boston, watching the "Chesapeake", an
  American frigate of the same nominal force but heavier armament. On the
  1st of June Broke, finding his water supply getting low, wrote to
  Lawrence, the commander of the "Chesapeake", asking for a meeting between
  the two ships, stating the "Shannon's" force, and guaranteeing that no
  other British ship should take part in the engagement. Before this letter
  could be delivered, however, the "Chesapeake", under full sail, ran out
  of Boston harbour, crowds of pleasure-boats accompanying her to witness
  the engagement. Broke briefly addressed his men. "Don't cheer," he
  concluded, "go quietly to your quarters. I feel sure you will all do your
  duty." As the "Chesapeake" rounded to on the "Shannon's" weather quarter,
  at a distance of about fifty yards, the British frigate received her with
  a broadside. A hundred of the "Chesapeake's" crew were struck down at
  once, Lawrence himself being mortally wounded. A second broadside,
  equally well-aimed, increased the confusion, and, her tiller-ropes being
  shot away, the American frigate drifted foul of the "Shannon". Broke
  sprang on board with some sixty of his men following him. After a brief
  struggle <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page629">[v.04 p.0629]</ph>the fight was over. Within fifteen
  minutes of the firing of the first shot, the "Chesapeake" struck her
  flag, but Broke himself was seriously wounded. For his services he was
  rewarded with a baronetcy, and subsequently was made a K.C.B. His exploit
  captivated the public fancy, and his popular title of "Brave Broke" gives
  the standard by which his action was judged. Its true significance,
  however, lies deeper. Broke's victory was due not so much to courage as
  to forethought. "The 'Shannon,'" said Admiral Jurien de La Gravière,
  "captured the 'Chesapeake' on the 1st of June 1813; but on the 14th of
  September 1806, when he took command of his frigate, Captain Broke had
  begun to prepare the glorious termination to this bloody affair." Broke's
  wound incapacitated him from further service, and for the rest of his
  life caused him serious suffering. He died in London on the 2nd of
  January 1841.</p>
   </body>
</topic>