<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e33484">
   <title>BUGLE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUGLE,--> <ph outputclass="sc">Bugle-horn, Keyed Bugle, Kent Bugle or
  Regent's Bugle</ph> (Fr. <i>Bugle</i>, <i>Clairon</i>, <i>Cor à
  clefs</i>, <i>Bugle à clefs</i>; Ger. <i>Flügelhorn</i>,
  <i>Signalhorn</i>, <i>Bugelhorn</i>, <i>Klappenhorn</i>, <i>Kenthorn</i>;
  Ital. <i>Corna cromatica</i>), a treble brass wind instrument with
  cup-shaped mouthpiece and conical bore, used as a military duty and
  signal instrument. The bugle was originally, as its name denotes, a
  bull's horn,<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_341" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> of which it has preserved the
  characteristic conical bore of rapidly increasing diameter.</p>
      <p>Those members of the brass wind such as the horns, bugle, trumpet and
  tubas, which, in their simplest form, consist of tubes without lateral
  openings, depend for their scale on the harmonic series obtained by
  overblowing, i.e. by greater pressure of breath and by the increased
  tension of the lips, acting as reeds, across the mouthpiece. The harmonic
  series thus produced, which depends on the acoustic principles of the
  tube itself, and is absolutely uninfluenced by the manner in which the
  tube is bent, forms a natural subdivision in classifying these
  instruments:—(1) Those in which the lower harmonics from the second
  to the sixth or eighth are employed, such as the bugle, post-horn, the
  cornet à pistons, the trombone. (2) Those in which the higher harmonics
  from the third or fourth to the twelfth or sixteenth are mostly used,
  such as the French horn and trumpet. (3) Those which give out the
  fundamental tone and harmonics up to the eighth, such as the tubas and
  ophicleide.</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
  </title>
         <desc/>
         <image href="images/buglemusic1.png">
            <alt>Harmonic Series.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>We thus find a fundamental difference between the trumpet and the
  bugle as regards the harmonic series. But although, to the casual
  beholder, these instruments may present a general similarity, there are
  other important structural distinctions. The tube of the trumpet is
  cylindrical, widening only at the bell, whereas that of the bugle, as
  stated above, is conical. Both instruments have cup-shaped mouthpieces
  outwardly similar. The peculiar shape of the basins, however, at the
  place where they open into the tube, angular in the trumpet and bevelled
  in the bugle, taken in conjunction with the bore of the main tube, gives
  to the trumpet its brilliant blaring tone, and to the bugle its more
  veiled but penetrating quality, characteristic of the whole family.<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_342" type="fn"><!--[2]--></xref> Only five
  notes are required for the various bugle-calls, although the actual
  compass of the instrument consists of eight, of which the first or
  fundamental, however, being of poor quality, is never used. There are
  bugles in C and in E flat, but the bugle in B flat is most generally
  used; the key of C is used in notation.</p>
      <p>In order to increase the compass and musical possibilities of the
  bugle, two methods have been adopted, the use of (1) keys and (2) valves.
  The application of keys to the bugle produced the Kent bugle, and later
  the ophicleide. The application of valves produced the family of
  saxhorns. The use of keys for wood wind instruments was known early in
  the 15th century,<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_343" type="fn"><!--[3]--></xref> perhaps before. In 1438, the duke
  of Burgundy paid Hennequin Haulx, instrument-maker of Brussels, 4
  <i>ridres</i> a piece for three tenor bombards with keys. In the 16th
  century we find a key applied to the bass flûte-à-bec<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_344" type="fn"><!--[4]--></xref> and later to
  the large tenor cornetto.<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_345" type="fn"><!--[5]--></xref> In 1770 a horn-player named
  Kölbel, belonging to the imperial Russian band, experimented with keys on
  the trumpet, and in 1795 Weidinger of Vienna produced a trumpet with five
  keys. In 1810 Joseph Halliday, the bandmaster of the Cavan militia,
  patented the keyed bugle, with five keys and a compass of twenty-five
  notes, calling it the "Royal Kent Bugle" out of compliment to the duke of
  Kent, who was at the time commander-in-chief, and encouraged the
  introduction of the instrument into the regimental bands. A Royal Kent
  bugle in C, stamped with Halliday's name as inventor, and made by P.
  Turton, 5 Wormwood Gate, Dublin, was exhibited by Col. Shaw-Hellier at
  the Royal Military Exhibition in 1890.<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_346" type="fn"><!--[6]--></xref> The instrument measures 17 in.,
  and the total length of the tubing, including the mouthpiece, 50½ in. The
  diameter at the mouthpiece is ½ in. and at the bell 5¾ in. The instrument
  has a chromatic compass of two octaves, <xref href="images/zbuglemusic2.png" scope="external" format="html">
            <image href="images/buglemusic2.png">
               <alt>Chromatic compass.</alt>
            </image>
         </xref> the open notes being <xref href="images/zbuglemusic3.png" scope="external" format="html">
            <image href="images/buglemusic3.png">
               <alt>Open notes.</alt>
            </image>
         </xref>.</p>
      <p>Mahillon (op. cit. p. 117) points out that the tonality of the
  key-bugle and kindred instruments is determined by the second harmonic
  given out by the open tube, the first key remaining open. To the original
  instrument specified in the patent, Halliday added a sixth key, which
  became the first and was in the normal position open; this key when
  closed gave B flat, with the same series of harmonics as the open tube.
  The series, however, becomes shorter with each successive key. Thus, on
  being opened, the second key gives <xref href="images/zbuglemusic4.png" scope="external" format="html">
            <image href="images/buglemusic4.png">
               <alt>Second key.</alt>
            </image>
         </xref>, the
  third key <xref href="images/zbuglemusic5.png" scope="external" format="html">
            <image href="images/buglemusic5.png">
               <alt>Third key.</alt>
            </image>
         </xref>, the
  fourth key <xref href="images/zbuglemusic6.png" scope="external" format="html">
            <image href="images/buglemusic6.png">
               <alt>Fourth key.</alt>
            </image>
         </xref>, the
  fifth key <xref href="images/zbuglemusic7.png" scope="external" format="html">
            <image href="images/buglemusic7.png">
               <alt>Fifth key.</alt>
            </image>
         </xref>, the
  sixth key <xref href="images/zbuglemusic8.png" scope="external" format="html">
            <image href="images/buglemusic8.png">
               <alt>Sixth key.</alt>
            </image>
         </xref>. The
  bore of the instrument is just wide enough in proportion to its length to
  make possible the playing of the fundamental tones in the first two
  series, but these notes are never used, and the harmonics above the sixth
  are also avoided, being of doubtful intonation. In the ophicleide, the
  bass of the key-bugle, the bore is sufficiently wide to produce the
  fundamentals of a satisfactory quality.</p>
      <p>The keyed bugle was chiefly used in B flat, a crook for B flat being
  frequently added to the bugle in C; the soprano bugle in E flat was also
  much used in military bands.</p>
      <p>The origin of the bugle, in common with that of the hunting horn, is
  of the highest antiquity. During the middle ages, the word "bugle" was
  applied to the ox and also to its horns, whether used as musical
  instruments or for drinking. The <i>New English Dictionary</i> quotes a
  definition of bugle dating from c. 1398: "The Bugle ... is lyke to an oxe
  and is a fyers <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page761">[v.04 p.0761]</ph>beest."<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_347" type="fn"><!--[7]--></xref> In 1300 a romance<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_348" type="fn"><!--[8]--></xref> contains the
  word used in both acceptations, "A thousand bugles of Ynde," and "tweye
  bugle-hornes and a bowe." F. Godefroy<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_349" type="fn"><!--[9]--></xref> gives quotations from early
  French which show that, as in England, the word bugle was frequently used
  as an adjective, and as a verb:—"IIII cors buglieres fist soner de
  randon" (<i>Quatre fils Aymon</i>, ed. P. Tarbé, p. 32), and "I grant cor
  buglerenc fit en sa tor soner" (<i>Aiol</i>, 7457, <i>Société des anciens
  textes français</i>). Tubas, horns, cornets and bugles have as common
  archetype the horn of ram, bull or other animal, whose form was copied
  and modified in bronze, wood, brass, ivory, silver, &amp;c. Of all these
  instruments, the bugle has in the highest degree retained the acoustic
  properties and the characteristic scale of the prototype, and is still
  put to the original use for giving military signals. The shofar of the
  ancient Hebrews, used at the siege of Jericho, was a cow's horn (Josh.
  vi. 4, 5, 8, 13, &amp;c.), translated in the Vulgate <i>buccina</i>, in
  the paraphrase of the Chaldee <i>buccina ex cornu</i>. The directions
  given for sounding the trumpets of beaten silver described in Numbers x.
  form the earliest code of signals yet known; the narrative shows that the
  Israelites had metal wind instruments; if, therefore, they retained the
  more primitive cow's horn and ram's horn (shofar), it was from choice,
  because they attached special significance to them in connexion with
  their ritual. The trumpet of silver mentioned above was the
  <i>Khatsotsrah</i>, probably the long straight trumpet or tuba which also
  occurs among the instruments in the musical scenes of the ancient
  Egyptians and Assyrians. Gideon's use of a massed band of three hundred
  shofars to terrify and defeat the Midianites (Judges vii. 16), and Saul's
  call to arms (1 Sam. xiii. 3) show that the value of the shofar as a
  military instrument was well understood by the Jews. The cornu was used
  by the Roman infantry to sound the military calls, and Vegetius<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_3410" type="fn"><!--[10]--></xref> states
  that the tuba and buccina were also used for the same purpose. Mahillon
  possesses a facsimile of an ancient Etruscan cornu, the length of which
  is 1.40 m.; he gives its scale,<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_3411" type="fn"><!--[11]--></xref> pitched one tone below that of
  the bugle in E flat, as that of D flat, of which the harmonics <xref href="images/zbuglemusic9.png" scope="external" format="html">
            <image href="images/buglemusic9.png">
               <alt>Scale of Etruscan cornu.</alt>
            </image>
         </xref>, from the second to
  the sixth are available. The same department of the British Museum was
  enriched in 1904 with a terra-cotta model (fig. 2) of a late Roman bugle
  (<i>c.</i> 4th century <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph>), bent completely
  round upon itself to form a coil between the mouthpiece and the bell-end
  (the latter has been broken off). This precious relic was found at
  Ventoux in France and has been acquired from the collection of M. Morel.
  This is precisely the form of bugle now used as a badge by the first
  battalion of the King's Own Light Infantry.<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_3412" type="fn"><!--[12]--></xref> During the middle ages the use
  of the bugle-horn by knights and huntsmen, and perhaps also in naval
  warfare, was general in Europe, as the following additional quotations
  will show: "XXX cors bugleres, fait l'amirax soner" (<i>Conq. de
  Jérusalem</i>, 6811, Hippeau); "Two squyers blewe ... with ij grete
  bugles hornes" (Caxton, <i>Chron. Engl. ccix. 192</i>). The oliphant was
  a glorified bugle-horn made of rich material, such as ivory, carved and
  inlaid with designs in gold and silver.</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 2.—Terra Cotta Model
    of Roman Bugle, 4th cent. (British Museum).</p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/bugle_2.png">
            <alt>Model of Roman Bugle.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>The history of the bugle as a military instrument is in England
  closely connected with the creation of the light infantry, in which it
  gradually superseded the drum<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_3413" type="fn"><!--[13]--></xref> as a duty and signal
  instrument. It was during the 17th century that the change was
  inaugurated; improvements in firearms brought about the gradual
  abandonment of armour by the infantry, and the formation of the light
  infantry and the adoption of the bugle followed by degrees. One of the
  oldest light infantry regiments, Prince Albert's 1st Somerset Light
  Infantry, formed in 1685 by the earl of Huntingdon, employed a drummer at
  that date at a shilling per day.<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_3414" type="fn"><!--[14]--></xref> At the end of the 18th century
  we find the bugle the recognized signal instrument in the light infantry,
  while the trumpet remained that of the cavalry. The general order
  introducing the bugle as a minor badge for the light infantry is under
  date 28th of December 1814. In 1856 the popularity of the keyed or Royal
  Kent bugle in the army had reached its height. A bugle-band was formed in
  the Royal Artillery as a substitute for the drum and fife band.<xref href="#d1e33484/Footnote_3415" type="fn"><!--[15]--></xref> The
  organization and training of this bugle-band were entrusted to
  Trumpet-major James Lawson, who raised it to a very high standard of
  excellence. Major Lawson was a fine cornet player, and finding the scale
  of the service bugle too restricted he obtained permission to add to it a
  valve attachment, which made the bugle a chromatic instrument like the
  cornet, in fact practically a saxhorn. Before long, horns in E flat,
  tenor horns in B flat, euphoniums and bass tubas were added, all made of
  copper, and in 1869 the name of "bugle band" was changed to R.A. Brass
  Band, and in 1877 it was merged in the Mounted Band. The bugle with its
  double development by means of keys into Royal Kent bugle and ophicleide,
  and by means of valves into saxhorns and tubas, formed the nucleus of
  brass bands of all countries during the greater part of the 19th century.
  The Flügelhorn, as its name denotes, became the signal instrument of the
  infantry in Germany as in England, and still holds it own with the keyed
  bugle in the fine military bands of Austro-Hungary.</p>
      <p>There is in the department of prehistoric antiquities at the British
  Museum a fine bugle-horn belonging to the Bronze Age in Denmark; the
  tube, which has an accentuated conical bore, is bent in a semi-circle,
  and has on the inner bend a series of little rings from which were
  probably suspended ornaments or cords. An engraved design runs spirally
  round the whole length of the tube, which is in an excellent state of
  preservation.</p>
      <p>Meyerbeer introduced the bugle in B flat in his opera
  <i>Robert-le-Diable</i> in the scene of the resurrection of the nuns, and
  a bugle in A in the fifth act.</p>
      <p>See, for further information on the technique of the instrument,
  Logier's <i>Introduction to the Art of Playing on the Royal Kent
  Bugle</i> (London, Clementi, 1820); and for the use of the bugle in the
  French army, G. Kastner, <i>Le Manuel général de musique militaire</i>
  (with illustrations, Paris, 1848).</p>
      <p>(K. S.)</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_341"> The word is
  derived from Lat. <i>buculus</i>, a young bull. "Bugle," meaning a long
  jet or black glass bead, used in trimming ladies' dresses, is possibly
  connected with the Ger. <i>Bugel</i>, a bent piece of metal. The English
  name "bugle" is also given to a common labiate plant, the <i>Ajuga
  reptans</i>, not to be confused with the "Bugloss" or <i>Anchusa
  officinalis</i>.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_342"> For diagrams of
  these mouthpieces see V.C. Mahillon, <i>Éléments d'acoustique</i>
  (Brussels, 1874), p. 96.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_343"> See E. van der
  Straeten, <i>La Musique aux Pays-bas</i>, vol. vii. p. 38, where the
  instrument is not mentioned as a novelty; also Léon, comte de Laborde,
  <i>Les Ducs de Bourgogne</i>, pt. ii. (<i>Preuves</i>), (Paris, 1849),
  tom. i. p. 365, No. 1266.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_344"> Martin Agricola,
  <i>Musica Instrumentalis deudsch</i> (Wittenberg, 1528), f.
  viii<sup>b</sup>.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_345"> Michael
  Praetorius, <i>Syntagma Musicum</i> (Wolfenbüttel, 1618), pl. viii. No.
  5.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_346"> See Captain C.R.
  Day, <i>Descript. Catalogue</i> (London, 1891), pp. 168-169, and pl. xi.
  fig. D.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_347"> Barthol. Trevisa,
  <i>De Propr. Rebus</i>, xviii., xv., 1495, 774.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_348"> 
            <i>King
  Alisaunder</i>, 5112 and 5282.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_349"> 
            <i>Dictionnaire de
  l'ancienne langue française du IXe an XVe siècle.</i>
         </fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3410"> 
            <i>De re
  militari</i>, bk. iii. ch. v.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3411"> See <i>Catal.
  descriptif du musée instrumental du conservatoire de Bruxelles</i>, vol.
  i. (Ghent, 1880), p. 331. There are, in the department of Greek and Roman
  antiquities at the British Museum, two bronze Etruscan cornua, No. 2734,
  resembling the hunting horns of the middle ages and bent in a
  semicircular shape. They measure from end to end respectively 2 ft. 1 in.
  and 2 ft. 2 in.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3412"> Maj. J.H.L.
  Archer, <i>The British Army Records</i> (London, 1888), p. 402.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3413"> For the use of
  the drum in the 16th century, see Sir John Smyth, <i>Instructions and
  Observations for all Chieftaines, Captaines, &amp;c.</i> (London, 1595),
  pp. 158-159.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3414"> See Richard
  Cannon, <i>Historical Records</i> of the regiment (London, 1848), p.
  3.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_3415"> See H.G.
  Farmer, <i>Memoirs of the Royal Artillery Band</i> (London, 1904), p.
  183.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>