<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23453">
   <title>BROWN, JOHN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWN, JOHN--> (1784-1858), Scottish divine, grandson of the
  last-named, was born at Whitburn, Linlithgowshire, on the 12th of July
  1784. He studied at Glasgow university, and afterwards at the divinity
  hall of the "Burgher" branch of the "Secession" church at Selkirk, under
  the celebrated George Lawson. In 1806 he was ordained minister of the
  Burgher congregation at Biggar, Lanarkshire, where he laboured for
  sixteen years. While there he had an interesting controversy with Robert
  Owen the socialist. Transferred in 1822 to the charge of Rose Street
  church, Edinburgh, he at once took a high rank as a preacher. In 1829 he
  succeeded James Hall at Broughton Place church, Edinburgh. In 1835 he was
  appointed one of the professors in the theological hall of the Secession
  church, and, great as was his ability as a preacher and pastor, it was
  probably in this sphere that he rendered his most valuable service. He
  had been the first in Scotland to use in the pulpit the exegetical method
  of exposition of Scripture, and as a professor he illustrated the method
  and extended its use. To him chiefly is due the abandonment of the
  principle of interpretation according to the "analogy of faith," which
  practically subordinated the Bible to the creed. Brown's exegesis was
  marked by rare critical sagacity, exact and extensive scholarship,
  unswerving honesty, and a clear, logical style; and his expository works
  have thus a permanent value. He had a considerable share in the Apocrypha
  controversy, and he was throughout life a vigorous and consistent
  upholder of anti-state-church or "voluntary" views. His two sermons on
  <i>The Law of Christ respecting civil obedience, especially in the
  payment of tribute</i>, called forth by a local grievance from which he
  had personally suffered, were afterwards published with extensive
  additions and notes, and are still regarded as an admirable statement and
  defence of the voluntary principle. The part he took in the discussion on
  the Atonement, which agitated all the Scottish churches, led to a formal
  charge of heresy against him by those who held the doctrine of a limited
  atonement. In 1845, after a protracted trial, he was acquitted by the
  synod. From that time he enjoyed the thorough confidence of his
  denomination (after 1847 merged in "the United Presbyterian church"), of
  which in his later years he was generally regarded as the leading
  representative. He died on the 13th of October 1858. His chief works
  were: <i>Expository Discourses on First Peter</i> (1848); <i>Exposition
  of the Discourses and Sayings of our Lord</i> (1850); <i>Exposition of
  our Lord's Intercessory Prayer</i> (1850); <i>The Resurrection of
  Life</i> (1851); <i>Expository Discourses on Galatians</i> (1853); and
  <i>Analytical Exposition of the Epistle to the Romans</i> (1857).</p>
      <p>See <i>Memoir of John Brown, D.D.</i>, by John Cairns (1860).</p>
   </body>
</topic>