<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e2902">
   <title>BRIALMONT, HENRI ALEXIS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIALMONT, HENRI ALEXIS--> (1821-1903), Belgian general and
  military engineer, son of General Laurent Mathieu Brialmont (d. 1885),
  was born at Venlo in Limburg on the 25th of May 1821. Educated at the
  Brussels military school, he entered the army as sub-lieutenant of
  engineers in 1843, and became lieutenant in 1847. From 1847 to 1850 he
  was private secretary to the war minister, General Baron Chazal. In 1855
  he entered the staff corps, became major in 1861, lieutenant-colonel
  1864, colonel in 1868 and major-general 1874. In this rank he held at
  first the position of director of fortifications in the Antwerp district
  (December 1874), and nine months later he became inspector-general of
  fortifications and of the corps of engineers. In 1877 he became
  lieutenant-general. His far-reaching schemes for the fortification of the
  Belgian places met with no little opposition, and Brialmont seems to have
  felt much disappointment in this; at any rate he went in 1883 to Rumania
  to advise as to the fortification works required for the defence of the
  country, and presided over the elaboration of the scheme by which
  Bucharest was to be made a first-class fortress. He was thereupon placed
  <i>en disponibilité</i> in his own service, as having undertaken the
  Bucharest works without the authorization of his sovereign. This was due
  in part to the suggestion of Austria, which power regarded the Bucharest
  works as a menace to herself. His services were, however, too valuable to
  be lost, and on his return to Belgium in 1884 he resumed his command of
  the Antwerp military district. He had, further, while in eastern Europe,
  prepared at the request of the Hellenic government, a scheme for the
  defence of Greece. He retired in 1886, but continued to supervise the
  Rumanian defences. He died on the 21st of September 1903.</p>
      <p>In the first stage of his career as an engineer Brialmont's plans
  followed with but slight modification the ideas of Vauban; and his
  original scheme for fortifying Antwerp provided for both enceinte and
  forts being on a bastioned trace. But in 1859, when the great entrenched
  camp at Antwerp was finally taken in hand, he had already gone over to
  the school of polygonal fortification and the ideas of Montalembert.
  About twenty years later Brialmont's own types and plans began to stand
  out amidst the general confusion of ideas on fortification which
  naturally resulted from the introduction of long-range guns, and from the
  events of 1870-71. The extreme detached forts of the Antwerp region and
  the fortifications on the Meuse at Liége and Namur were constructed in
  accordance with Brialmont's final principles, viz. the lavish use of
  armour to protect the artillery inside the forts, the suppression of all
  artillery positions open to overhead fire, and the multiplication of
  intermediate batteries (see <ph outputclass="sc">Fortification and
  Siegecraft</ph>). In his capacity of inspector-general Brialmont
  drafted and carried out the whole scheme for the defences of Belgium. He
  was an indefatigable writer, and produced, besides essays, reviews and
  other papers in the journals, twenty-three important works and forty-nine
  pamphlets. In 1850 he originated the <i>Journal de l'armée Belge</i>. His
  most important publications were <i>La Fortification du temps présent</i>
  (Brussels, 1885); <i>Influence du tir plongeant et des obus-torpilles sur
  la fortification</i> (Brussels, 1888); <i>Les Régions fortifiées</i>
  (Brussels, 1890); <i>La Défense des états et la fortification à la fin du
  XIX<sup>e</sup> siècle</i> (Brussels, 1895); <i>Progrès de la défense des
  états et de la fortification permanente depuis Vauban</i> (Brussels,
  1898).</p>
   </body>
</topic>