<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e19566">
   <title>BRIXHAM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIXHAM,--> a seaport and market town in the Torquay parliamentary
  division of Devonshire, England, 33 m. S. of Exeter, on a branch of the
  Great Western railway. Pop. of urban district (1901) 8092. The town is
  irregularly built on the cliffs to the south of Torbay, and its harbour
  is sheltered by a breakwater. Early in the 19th century it was an
  important military post, with fortified barracks on Berry Head. It is the
  headquarters of the Devonshire sea-fisheries, having also a large
  coasting trade. Shipbuilding and the manufacture of ropes, paint and
  sails are industries. There is excellent bathing, and Brixham is in
  favour as a seaside resort. St Mary's, the ancient parish church, has an
  elaborate 14th-century font and some monuments of interest. At the
  British Seamen's Orphans' home boys are fed, clothed and trained as
  apprentices for the merchant service. A statue commemorates the landing,
  in 1688, of William of Orange.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Brixham Cave</i>, called also Windmill Hill Cavern, is a well-known
  ossiferous cave situated near Brixham, on the brow of a hill composed of
  Devonian limestone. It was discovered by chance in 1858, having been
  until then hermetically sealed by a mass of limestone breccia. Dr Hugh
  Falconer with the assistance of a committee of geologists excavated it.
  The succession of beds in descending order is as follows:—(1)
  Shingle consisting of pebbles of limestone, slate and other local rocks,
  with fragments of stalagmite and containing a few bones and worked
  flints. The thickness varies from five to sixteen feet. (2) Red cave
  earth with angular fragments of limestone, bones and worked flints, and
  having a thickness of 3 to 4 ft. (3) Remnants (<i>in situ</i>) of an old
  stalagmitic floor about nine inches thick. (4) Black peaty soil varying
  in thickness, the maximum being about a foot. (5) Angular debris fallen
  from above varying in thickness from one to ten feet. (6) Stalagmite with
  a few bones and antlers of reindeer, the thickness varying from one to
  fifteen inches. Of particular interest is the presence of patches or
  ledges of an old stalagmitic floor, three to four feet above the present
  floor. On the under-side, there are found attached fragments of limestone
  and quartz, showing that the shingle bed once extended up to it, and that
  it then formed the original floor. The shingle therefore stood some feet
  higher than it does now, and it is supposed that a shock or jar, such as
  that of an earthquake, broke up the stalagmite, and the pebbles and sand
  composing the shingle sunk deeper into the fissures in the limestone.
  This addition to the size of the cave was partially filled up by the cave
  earth. At a later period the fall of angular fragments at the entrance
  finally closed the cave, and it ceased to be accessible except to a few
  burrowing animals, whose remains are found above the second and newer
  stalagmite floor.</p>
      <p>The fauna of Brixham cavern closely resembles that of Kent's Hole. The
  bones of the bear, horse, rhinoceros, lion, elephant, hyena and of many
  birds and small rodents were unearthed. Altogether 1621 bones, nearly all
  broken and gnawed, were found; of these 691 belonged to birds and small
  rodents of more recent times. The implements are of a roughly-chipped
  type resembling those of the Mousterian period. From these structural and
  palaeontological evidences, geologists suppose that the formation of the
  cave was carried on simultaneously with the excavation of the valley;
  that the small streams, flowing down the upper ramifications of the
  valley, entered the western opening of the cave, and traversing the
  fissures in the limestone, escaped by the lower openings in the chief
  valley; and that the rounded pebbles found in the shingle bed were
  carried in by these streams. It would be only at times of drought that
  the cave was frequented by animals, a theory which explains the small
  quantity of animal remains in the shingle. The implements of man are
  relatively more common, seventeen chipped flints having been found. As
  the excavation of the valley proceeded, the level of the stream was
  lowered and its course diverted; the cave consequently became drier and
  was far more frequently inhabited by predatory animals. It was now
  essentially an animal den, the occasional visits of man being indicated
  by the rare occurrence of flint-implements. Finally, the cave became a
  resort of bears; the remains of 334 specimens, in all stages of growth,
  including even sucking cubs, being discovered.</p>
      <p>See Sir Joseph Prestwich, <i>Geology</i> (1888); Sir John Evans,
  <i>Ancient Stone Implements of Great Britain</i>, p. 512; Report on the
  Cave, <i>Phil. Trans.</i> (Royal Society, 1873).</p>
   </body>
</topic>