<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e11400">
   <title>BRIDGET</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIDGET,--> <ph outputclass="sc">Brigitta, Birgitta,</ph> 
         <b>OF
  SWEDEN, SAINT</b> (c. 1302-1373), the most celebrated saint of the
  northern kingdoms, was the daughter of Birger Persson, governor and
  <i>lagman</i> (provincial judge) of Uppland, and one of the richest
  landowners of the country. In 1316 she was married to Ulf Gudmarson, lord
  of Nericia, to whom she bore eight children, one of whom was afterwards
  honoured as St Catherine of Sweden. Bridget's saintly and charitable life
  soon made her known far and wide; she gained, too, great religious
  influence over her husband, with whom (1341-1343) she went on pilgrimage
  to St James of Compostella. In 1344, shortly after their return, Ulf died
  in the Cistercian monastery of Alvastra in East Gothland, and Bridget now
  devoted herself wholly to religion. As a child she had already believed
  herself to have visions; these now became more frequent, and her records
  of these "revelations," which were translated into Latin by Matthias,
  canon of Linköping, and by her confessor, Peter, prior of Alvastra,
  obtained a great vogue during the middle ages. It was about this time
  that she founded the order of St Saviour, or Bridgittines (<i>q.v.</i>),
  of which the principal house, at Vadstena, was richly endowed by King
  Magnus II. and his queen. About 1350 she went to Rome, partly to obtain
  from the pope the authorization of the new order, partly in pursuance of
  her self-imposed mission to elevate the moral tone of the age. It was not
  till 1370 that Pope Urban V. confirmed the rule of her order; but
  meanwhile Bridget had made herself universally beloved in Rome by her
  kindness and good works. Save for occasional pilgrimages, including one
  to Jerusalem in 1373, she remained in Rome till her death on the 23rd of
  July 1373. She was canonized in 1391 by Pope Boniface IX., and her feast
  is celebrated on the 9th of October.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Bibliography.</ph>—Cf. the Bollandist <i>Acta
  Sanctorum</i>, Oct. 8, iv. 368-560; the <i>Vita Sanctae Brigittae</i>,
  edited by C. Annerstedt in <i>Scriptores rerum Suedicarum medii aevi</i>,
  iii. 185-244 (Upsala, 1871). The best modern work on the subject is by
  the comtesse Catherine de Flavigny, entitled <i>Sainte Brigitte de Suède,
  sa vie, ses révélations et son œuvre</i> (Paris, 1892), which
  contains an exhaustive bibliography. The Revelations are contained in the
  critical edition of St Bridget's works published by the Swedish
  Historical Society and edited by G.E. Klemming (Stockholm, 1857-1884, II
  vols.). For full bibliography (to 1904) see Ulysse Chevalier,
  <i>Répertoire des sources hist. Bio.-Bibl.</i>, <i>s.v.</i>
  "Brigitte."</p>
   </body>
</topic>