<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25692">
   <title>BRUNETIÈRE, FERDINAND</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNETIÈRE, FERDINAND--> (1849-1906), French critic and man of
  letters, was born at Toulon on the 19th July 1849. After attending a
  school at Marseilles, he studied in Paris at the Lycée Louis-le-Grand.
  Desiring to follow the profession of teaching, he entered for examination
  at the École Normale Supérieure, but failed, and the outbreak of war in
  1870 debarred him from a second attempt. He turned to private tuition and
  to literary criticism. After the publication of successful articles in
  the <i>Revue Bleue</i>, he became connected with the <i>Revue des Deux
  Mondes</i>, first as contributor, then as secretary and sub-editor, and
  finally, in 1893, as principal editor. In 1886 he was appointed professor
  of French language and literature at the École Normale, a singular honour
  for one who had not passed through the academic mill; and later he
  presided with distinction over various <i>conférences</i> at the Sorbonne
  and elsewhere. He was decorated with the Legion of Honour in 1887, and
  became a member of the Academy in 1893. The published works of M.
  Brunetière consist largely of reprinted papers and lectures. They include
  six series of <i>Études critiques</i> (1880-1898) on French history and
  literature; <i>Le Roman naturaliste</i> (1883); <i>Histoire et
  Littérature</i>, three series (1884-1886); <i>Questions de critique</i>
  (1888; second series, 1890). The first volume of <i>L'Évolution de genres
  dans l'histoire de la littérature</i>, lectures in which a formal
  classification, founded on the Darwinian theory, is applied to the
  phenomena of literature, appeared in 1890; and his later works include a
  series of studies (2 vols., 1894) on the evolution of French lyrical
  poetry during the 19th century, a history of <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page684">[v.04 p.0684]</ph>French classic
  literature begun in 1904, a monograph on Balzac (1906), and various
  pamphlets of a polemical nature dealing with questions of education,
  science and religion. Among these may be mentioned <i>Discours
  académiques</i> (1901), <i>Discours de combat</i> (1900, 1903),
  <i>L'Action sociale du christianisme</i> (1904), <i>Sur les chemins de la
  croyance</i> (1905). M. Brunetière was an orthodox Roman Catholic, and
  his political sympathies were in the main reactionary. He possessed two
  prime qualifications of a great critic, vast erudition and unflinching
  courage. He was never afraid to diverge from the established critical
  view, his mind was closely logical and intensely accurate, and he rarely
  made a trip in the wide field of study over which it ranged. The most
  honest, if not the most impartial, of magisterial writers, he had a
  hatred of the unreal, and a contempt for the trivial; nobody was more
  merciless towards those who affected effete and decadent literary forms,
  or maintained a vicious standard of art. On the other hand, his
  intolerance, his sledge-hammer methods of attack and a certain dry
  pedantry alienated the sympathies of many who recognized the remarkable
  qualities of his mind. The application of universal principles to every
  question of letters is a check to dilettante habits of thought, but it is
  apt to detain the critic in a somewhat narrow and dusty path. M.
  Brunetière's influence, however, cannot be disputed, and it was in the
  main thoroughly sound and wholesome. He died on the 9th of December
  1906.</p>
      <p>His <i>Manual of the History of French Literature</i> was translated
  into English in 1898 by R. Derechef. Among critics of Brunetière see J.
  Lemaître, <i>Les Contemporains</i> (1887, &amp;c.), and J. Sargeret,
  <i>Les Grands Corvertis</i> (1906).</p>
   </body>
</topic>