<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25645">
   <title>BRUNELLESCHI</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNELLESCHI--> (or <ph outputclass="sc">Brunellesco</ph>),
  <b>FILIPPO</b> (1379-1446), Italian architect, the reviver in Italy of
  the Roman or Classic style, was born at Florence in 1379. His father, a
  notary, had destined him for his own profession, but observing the boy's
  talent for all sorts of mechanism, placed him in the gild of goldsmiths.
  Filippo quickly became a skilled workman, and perfected himself in the
  knowledge of sculpture, perspective and geometry. He designed some
  portions of houses in Florence, and in 1401 he was one of the competitors
  for the design of the gates of the baptistery of San Giovanni. He was
  unsuccessful, though his work obtained praise, and he soon afterwards set
  out for Rome. He studied hard, and resolved to do what he could to revive
  the older classical style, which had died out in Italy. Moreover, he was
  one of the first to apply the scientific laws of perspective to his work.
  In 1407 he returned to Florence, just at the time when it was resolved to
  attempt the completion of the cathedral church of Santa Maria del Fiore.
  Brunelleschi's plan for effecting this by a cupola was approved, but it
  was not till 1419, and after innumerable disputes, that the work was
  finally entrusted to him. At first he was hampered by his colleague
  Ghiberti, of whom he skilfully got rid. He did not live to see the
  completion of his great work, and the lantern on the summit was put up
  not altogether in accordance with the instructions and plans left by him.
  The great cupola, one of the triumphs of architecture, exceeds in some
  measurements that of St Peter's at Rome, and has a more massive and
  striking appearance. Besides this masterpiece Brunelleschi executed
  numerous other works, among the most remarkable of which are the Pitti
  palace at Florence, on the pattern of which are based the Tuscan palaces
  of the 15th century, the churches of San Lorenzo and Spirito Santo, and
  the still more elegant Capella del Pazza. The beautiful carved crucifix
  in the church of Santa Maria Novella in Florence is also the work of
  Brunelleschi. He died in Florence on the 16th of April 1446, and was
  buried in the cathedral church of his native city.</p>
      <p>See Manetti, <i>Vita di Brunelleschi</i> (Florence, 1812); Guasti,
  <i>La cupola di Santa Maria del Fiore</i> (Florence, 1857); von Fabriczy,
  <i>Filippo Brunelleschi</i> (Stuttgart, 1892).</p>
   </body>
</topic>