<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e11497">
   <title>BRIDGEWATER</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIDGEWATER, FRANCIS HENRY EGERTON,--> <ph outputclass="sc">8th Earl
  of</ph> (1756-1829), was educated at Eton and Christ Church, Oxford,
  and became fellow of All Souls in 1780, and F.R.S. in 1781. He held the
  rectories of Middle and Whitchurch in Shropshire, but the duties were
  performed by a proxy. He succeeded his brother (see above) in the earldom
  in 1823, and spent the latter part of his life in Paris. He was a fair
  scholar, and a zealous naturalist and antiquarian. When he died in
  February 1829 the earldom became extinct. He bequeathed to the British
  Museum the valuable Egerton MSS. dealing with the literature of France
  and Italy, and also £12,000. He also left £8000 at the disposal of the
  president of the Royal Society, to be paid to the author or authors who
  might be selected to write and publish 1000 copies of a treatise "On the
  Power, Wisdom and Goodness of God, as manifested in the Creation." Mr
  Davies Gilbert, who then filled the office, selected eight persons, each
  to undertake a branch of this subject, and each to receive £1000 as his
  reward, together with any benefit that might accrue from the sale of his
  work, according to the will of the testator.</p>
      <p>The Bridgewater treatises were published as follows:—1. <i>The
  Adaptation of External Nature to the Moral and Intellectual Condition of
  Man</i>, by Thomas Chalmers, D.D. 2. <i>The Adaptation of External Nature
  to the Physical Condition of Man</i>, by John Kidd, M.D. 3. <i>Astronomy
  and General Physics considered with reference to Natural Theology</i>, by
  William Whewell, D.D. 4. <i>The Hand, its Mechanism and Vital Endowments
  as evincing Design</i>, by Sir Charles Bell. 5. <i>Animal and Vegetable
  Physiology considered with reference to Natural Theology</i>, by Peter
  Mark Roget. 6. <i>Geology and Mineralogy considered with reference to
  Natural Theology</i>, by William Buckland, D.D. 7. <i>The Habits and
  Instincts of Animals with reference to Natural Theology</i>, by William
  Kirby. 8. <i>Chemistry, Meteorology, and the Function of Digestion,
  considered with reference to Natural Theology</i>, by William Prout, M.D.
  The works are of unequal merit; several of them took a high rank in
  apologetic literature. They first appeared during the years 1833 to 1840,
  and afterwards in Bohn's Scientific Library.</p>
   </body>
</topic>