<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25510">
   <title>BRUNE, GUILLAUME MARIE ANNE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNE, GUILLAUME MARIE ANNE--> (1763-1815), marshal of France, the
  son of an advocate, was born at Brives-la-Gaillarde (Corrèze), on the
  13th of March 1763. Before the Revolution he went to Paris to study law,
  and here he became a political journalist, a Jacobin and a friend of
  Danton. He was appointed <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page681">[v.04 p.0681]</ph>in 1793 to a superior command in
  the army direct from civil life, and as a general of brigade he took part
  in the fighting of the 13th Vendémiaire. In 1796 he fought under
  Bonaparte in Italy, and was promoted general of division for good service
  in the field. In 1798 he commanded the French army which occupied
  Switzerland, and in the following year he was in command of the French
  troops in Holland. His defence of Amsterdam against the Anglo-Russian
  expedition under the duke of York was completely successful; the invaders
  were defeated, and compelled, after a miserable retreat, to re-embark. He
  rendered further good service in Vendée and in Italy, and was made a
  marshal by Napoleon on the assumption by the latter of the imperial title
  in 1804. In 1807 Brune held a command in North Germany, but he was not
  afterwards employed during the First Empire. It is said that he was
  accused of venality, and on that account disgraced, but of this there is
  no proof. He was recalled to active service during the Hundred Days, and
  as commander of the army of the Var he defended the south of France
  against the Austrians. He was murdered by royalists during the White
  Terror at Avignon on the 2nd of August 1815.</p>
      <p>See <i>Notice historique sur la vie politique et militaire du maréchal
  Brune</i> (Paris, 1821), and Vermeil de Conchard, <i>L'Assassinat du
  maréchal Brune</i> (Paris, 1887).</p>
   </body>
</topic>