<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25342">
   <title>BRUGSCH, HEINRICH KARL</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUGSCH, HEINRICH KARL--> (1827-1894), German Egyptologist, was
  the son of a Prussian cavalry officer, and was born in the barracks at
  Berlin, on the 18th of February 1827. He early manifested a great
  inclination to Egyptian studies, in which, though encouraged by Humboldt,
  he was almost entirely self-taught. After completing his university
  course and visiting foreign museums he was sent to Egypt by the Prussian
  government in 1853, and contracted an intimate friendship with Mariette.
  On his return he received an appointment in the Berlin museum. In 1860 he
  was sent to Persia on a special mission under Baron Minutoli, travelled
  over the country, and after Minutoli's death discharged the functions of
  ambassador. In 1864 he was consul at Cairo, in 1868 professor at
  Gõttingen, and in 1870 director of the school of Egyptology, founded at
  Cairo by the khedive. From this post he was unceremoniously dismissed in
  1879 by the European controllers of the public revenues, determined to
  economize at all hazards; and French influence prevented his succeeding
  his friend Mariette at the Bulaq Museum in 1883. He afterwards resided
  principally in Germany until his death on the 9th of September 1894, but
  frequently visited Egypt, took part in another official mission to
  Persia, and organized an Egyptian exhibit at the Philadelphia Exposition
  in 1876. He had been made a pasha by the khedive in 1881. He published
  his autobiography in 1894, concluding with a warm panegyric upon British
  rule in Egypt. Brugsch's services to Egyptology are most important,
  particularly in the decipherment of demotic and the making of a vast
  hieroglyphic-demotic dictionary (1867-1882).</p>
      <p>See H. Brugsch, <i>Mein Leben und mein Wandern</i>, also art. <ph outputclass="sc">Egypt</ph>, section <i>Language and Writing</i>.</p>
   </body>
</topic>