<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e26641">
   <title>BRUTÉ, SIMON WILLIAM GABRIEL</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUTÉ, SIMON WILLIAM GABRIEL--> (1779-1839), American prelate,
  first Roman Catholic bishop of the diocese of Vincennes, Indiana, U.S.A.,
  was born at Rennes, France, on the 20th of March 1779, his father, Simon
  Gabriel Guillaume Bruté de Remur (1729-1786), being superintendent of the
  crown lands in Brittany. He was educated for the medical profession, but
  entered the Sulpician Seminary of Paris in November 1803, was ordained
  priest in 1808, refused the post of chaplain to Napoleon, was professor
  of theology in the Diocesan Seminary at Rennes in 1808-1810, and in
  August 1810 settled in Baltimore, Maryland, whither his long general
  interest in missions, and particularly his acquaintance with Bishop
  Flaget of Kentucky, had drawn him. After teaching for two years
  (1810-1812) in Baltimore, he was sent to Mount St Mary's College,
  Emmitsburg, Maryland, where he remained until 1815, acting both as
  teacher and as pastor. He next visited France in the interest of American
  missions, and on his return in November 1815, became president of St
  Mary's College, Baltimore. In 1818 he resumed his labours at Emmitsburg,
  and from this time until 1834 he held an almost unparalleled place in the
  American church, being constantly consulted by clergy throughout the
  country, besides lecturing, teaching, preaching and caring for his
  parish. The see of Vincennes was created in 1834; and Bruté, nominated
  its first bishop and consecrated in the same year, went to France for
  financial aid, with which he built his cathedral and several useful
  institutions. Here, too, he was professor of theology in his seminary,
  teacher in one of his academies, as well as pastor and bishop.
  Interesting stories are told of the high respect in which he was held by
  the neighbouring Indians, who called him "chief of the Black robes" and
  "man of the true prayer." He died in Vincennes, Indiana, on the 26th of
  June 1839. His great influence on the entire church, his wonderful
  success in planning, financing, and carrying out necessary ecclesiastical
  reforms, and the constructive and executive ability he displayed in his
  diocese, make him one of the foremost Catholic emigrants to the United
  States. He wrote <i>Brief Notes</i> on his experiences in France in 1793,
  in which he describes state persecution of Catholic priests.</p>
      <p>See James Roosevelt Bayley, <i>The Memoirs of the Rt. Rev. Simon
  William Gabriel Bruté, First Bishop of Vincennes</i> (New York, 1861),
  containing much autobiographical matter.</p>
   </body>
</topic>