<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e32976">
   <title>BUENOS AIRES</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUENOS AIRES,--> a city and port of Argentina, and capital of the
  republic, in 34° 36′ 21″ S. lat. and 58° 21′ 33″
  W. long., on the west shore of the La Plata estuary, about 155 m. above
  its mouth, and 127 m. W. by N. from Montevideo. The estuary at this point
  is 34 m. wide, and so shallow that vessels can enter the docks only
  through artificial channels kept open by constant dredging. Previously to
  the construction of the new port, ocean-going vessels of over 15 ft.
  draught were compelled to anchor in the outer roads some 12 m. from the
  city, and communication with the shore was effected by means of steam
  tenders and small boats, connecting with long landing piers, or with
  carts driven out from the beach. The city is built upon an open grassy
  plain extending inland from the banks of the estuary, and north from the
  Riachuelo or Matanzas river where the "Boca" port is located. Its average
  elevation is about 65 ft. above sea-level. The federal district, which
  includes the city and its suburbs and covers an area of 72 sq. m., was
  detached from the province of Buenos Aires by an act of congress in 1880.
  With the construction of the new port and reclamation of considerable
  areas of the shallow water frontage, the area of the city has been
  greatly extended below the line of the original estuary banks. The
  streets of the old city, which are narrow and laid out to enclose
  rectangular blocks of uniform size, run nearly parallel with the cardinal
  points of the compass, but this plan is not closely followed in the new
  additions and suburbs. This uniformity in plan, combined with the level
  ground and the style of buildings first erected, gave to the city an
  extremely monotonous and uninteresting appearance, but with its growth in
  wealth and population, greater diversity and better taste in architecture
  have resulted.</p>
      <p>The prevailing style of domestic architecture is that introduced from
  Spain and used throughout all the Spanish colonies—the grouping of
  one-storey buildings round one or two <i>patios</i>, which open on the
  street through a wide doorway. These residences have heavily barred
  windows on the street, and flat roofs with <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page753">[v.04 p.0753]</ph>parapets
  admirably adapted for defence. The domiciliation of wealthy foreigners,
  and the introduction of foreign customs and foreign culture, have
  gradually modified the style of architecture, both public and domestic,
  and modern Buenos Aires is adorned with many costly and attractive public
  edifices and residences. French renaissance, lavishly decorated, has
  become the prevailing style. The Avenida Alvear is particularly noted for
  the elegance of its private residences, and the new Avenida de Mayo for
  its display of elaborately ornamented public and business edifices, while
  the suburban districts of Belgrano and Flores are distinguished for the
  attractiveness of their country-houses and gardens. A part of the
  population is greatly overcrowded, one-fifth living in
  <i>conventillos</i>, or tenement-houses.</p>
      <p>Among the city's many <i>plazas</i>, or squares, twelve are especially
  worthy of mention, viz.: 25 de Mayo (formerly Victoria) on which face the
  Government-House and Cathedral, San Martin (or Retiro), Lavalle,
  Libertad, Lorea, Belgrano, 6 de Junio, Once de Setiembre, Independencia
  (formerly Conceptión), Constitución, Caridad and 29 de Deciembre. These
  vary in size from one to three squares, or 4 to 12 acres each, and are
  handsomely laid out with flowers, shrubbery, walks and shade trees. There
  are also two elaborately laid out <i>alamedas</i>, the Recoleta and the
  Paseo de Julio, the latter on the river front and partially absorbed by
  the new port works, and the great park at Palermo, officially called 3 de
  Febrero, which contains 840 acres, beautifully laid out in drives,
  footpaths, lawns, gardens and artificial lakes. In all, the <i>plazas</i>
  and parks of Buenos Aires cover an area of 960 acres.</p>
      <p>The cathedral, which is one of the largest in South America, dating
  from 1752, resembles the Madeleine of Paris in design, and its classical
  portico facing the Plaza 25 de Mayo has twelve stately Corinthian columns
  supporting an elaborately sculptured pediment. The archbishop's palace
  (Buenos Aires became an archiepiscopal see in 1866) adjoins the
  cathedral. There are about twenty-five Roman Catholic churches in the
  city, one of the richest and most popular of which is the Merced on Calle
  Reconquista, and four Protestant churches—English, Scottish
  Presbyterian, American Methodist and German Lutheran. Twenty asylums for
  orphans and indigent persons and one for lunatics are maintained at
  public expense and by private religious associations, while the demand
  for organized medical and surgical treatment is met by fifteen
  well-appointed hospitals, having an aggregate of 2600 beds, and treating
  17,000 patients annually. Of these, five belong to foreign nationalities.
  The city has six cemeteries covering 230 acres.</p>
      <p>Among the more noteworthy public buildings are the Casa Rosada
  (government-house), facing the Plaza 25 de Mayo and occupying in part the
  site of the fort built by Garay in 1580; the new congress hall on Calle
  Callao and Avenida de Mayo, finished in 1906 at a cost of about
  £1,300,000; the new municipal hall on Avenida de Mayo; the <i>bolsa</i>
  or exchange, distributing reservoir, mint, and some of the more modern
  educational buildings. Higher education is represented by the university
  of Buenos Aires, with its several faculties, including law and medicine,
  and 3562 students (1901), four national colleges, three normal schools
  and various technical schools. There are, also, a national library, a
  national museum, a zoological garden and an aquarium. The people are fond
  of music, the drama and amusements, and devote much time and expense to
  diversions of a widely varied character, from Italian opera to
  horse-racing and <i>pelota</i>. They have two or three large public
  baths, and a large number of social, sporting and athletic clubs. The
  Porteños, as the residents of Buenos Aires are called, are accustomed to
  call their city the "Paris of America," and not without reason. Buenos
  Aires has become the principal manufacturing centre of the republic, and
  its industrial establishments are numbered by thousands and their capital
  by hundreds of millions of dollars.</p>
      <p>The growth of Buenos Aires since settled conditions have prevailed,
  and especially since its federalization, has been very rapid, and the
  city has finally outstripped all rivals and become the largest city of
  South America. At the time of its first authentic census in 1869, it had
  a population of 177,767. In 1887, when the suburbs of Belgrano and Flores
  with an aggregate population of 28,000 were annexed, its population
  without this increment was estimated at 404,000. In 1895 the national
  census gave the population as 663,854, and in 1904 a municipal census
  increased it to 950,891. At the close of 1905 the national statistical
  office estimated it at 1,025,653. The excess of births over deaths is
  unusually large (about 14 per thousand in 1905). The city has about
  one-fifth of the population of the whole republic. The government is
  vested in an <i>intendente municipal</i> (mayor) appointed by the
  national executive with the approval of the senate, and a <i>concejo
  deliberante</i> (legislative council) elected by the people and composed
  of two councillors from each parish. The police force is a military
  organization under the control of the national executive, and the higher
  municipal courts are subject to the same authority. Every ratepayer,
  whether foreigner or native, has the right to vote in municipal elections
  and to serve in the municipal council.</p>
      <p>The water-supply is drawn from the estuary at Belgrano and conducted
  3½ m. to the Recoleta, where three great settling basins, with an
  aggregate capacity of 12,000,000 gallons, and six acres of covered
  filters, are located. It is then pumped to the great distributing
  reservoir at Calles Córdoba and Viamonte, which covers four acres and has
  a capacity of 13,500,000 gallons. These works were begun in 1873. Up to
  1873, when the water and drainage works were initiated by English
  engineers and contractors, there were no public sewers, and the sanitary
  state of the city was indescribably bad. The cholera epidemic of
  1867-1868, with 15,000 victims, and the yellow fever epidemic of 1871,
  with 26,000 victims, were greatly intensified by these insanitary
  conditions. The construction of the sewers lasted about 19 years, when in
  1892 the water and drainage works were taken over by the government, and
  are now administered at public expense and at a profit. The main sewer is
  16 m. long and extends southward beyond Quilmes. The total cost of the
  two systems exceeded six millions sterling. Buenos Aires is now provided
  with a good water-supply, and its sanitary condition compares favourably
  with that of other great cities, the annual death-rate being about 18 per
  thousand, against 27 per thousand in 1887. Its mean annual temperature is
  64° Fahr., and its annual rainfall 34 in.</p>
      <p>The lighting includes both gas and electricity, the former dating from
  1856. Previously to that time street lighting had been effected at first
  with lamps burning mares' grease, and then with tallow candles. The
  streets were at first paved with cobble-stones, then with dressed granite
  paving-stones (parallelepipedons), and finally with wood and asphalt. The
  tram service is in the hands of nine private companies, operating 313 m.
  of track (31st of December 1905), on almost five-sevenths of which
  electric traction is employed. The city is the principal terminus and
  port for nearly all the trunk railway lines of the republic, which have
  large passenger stations at the Retiro, Once de Setiembre, and
  Constitución plazas, and are connected with the central produce market
  and the new Madero port. The great central produce market at Barracas al
  Sud (<i>Mercado Central de Frutos</i>), whose lands, buildings, railway
  sidings, machinery and mole cost £750,000, is designed to handle the
  pastoral and agricultural products of the country on a large scale, while
  20 markets in the city meet the needs of local consumers.</p>
      <p>The most important feature of the port of Buenos Aires is the "Madero
  docks," constructed to enlarge and improve its shipping facilities.
  Improvements had been, begun in 1872 at the "Boca," as the port on the
  Riachuelo is called, and nearly £1,500,000 was spent there in landing
  facilities and dredging a channel 12 m. in length, to deep water. These
  improvements were found insufficient, and in 1887 work was begun on plans
  executed by Sir John Hawkshaw for a series of four docks and two basins
  in front of the city, occupying 3 m. of reclaimed shore-line, and
  connected with deep water by two dredged channels. The north basin is
  provided with two dry docks, and the new quays are equipped with 24
  warehouses, hydraulic cranes, and 28 m. of railway sidings and
  connexions. The total cost of the new port works <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page754">[v.04 p.0754]</ph>up to 1908 was
  about £8,000,000 sterling ($40,000,000 gold). In September of that year
  it was decided by congress to borrow £5,000,000 for still further
  extensions which were found to be required. The channels to deep water
  require constant dredging because of the great quantity of silt deposited
  by the river, and on this and allied purposes an expenditure of £560,000
  was voted in 1908. In 1907 there were 29,178 shipping entries in the
  port, with an aggregate of 13,335,737 tons, the merchandise movement
  being 4,360,000 tons imports and 2,900,000 tons of produce exports. The
  revenues for 1907 were $5,452,000 gold, and working expenses, $2,213,000
  gold, the profit ($3,229,000) being equal to about 8% on the cost of
  construction.</p>
      <p>
         <i>History.</i>—Three attempts were made to establish a colony
  where the city of Buenos Aires stands. The first was in 1535 by Don Pedro
  de Mendoza with a large and well-equipped expedition from Spain, which,
  through mismanagement and the hostility of the Indians, resulted in
  complete failure. An expedition sent up the river by Mendoza founded
  Asunción, and thither went the colonists from his "Santa Maria de Buenos
  Ayres" when that settlement was abandoned. The second was in 1542 by a
  part of the expedition from Spain under Cabeza de Vaca, but with as
  little success. The third was in 1580 by Don Juan de Garay, governor of
  Paraguay, who had already established a half-way post at Santa Fé in
  1573, and from this attempt dates the foundation of the city. The need of
  a port near the sea, where supplies from Spain could be received and
  ships provisioned, was keenly felt by the Spanish colonists at Asunción,
  and Garay's expedition down the Paraná in 1580 had that special object in
  view. Garay built a fort and laid out a town in the prescribed Spanish
  style above Mendoza's abandoned settlement, giving it the name of "Ciudad
  de la Santissima Trinidad," but retaining Mendoza's descriptive name for
  the port in appreciation of the agreeable and invigorating atmosphere of
  that locality. Buenos Aires remained a dependency of Asunción until 1620,
  when the Spanish settlements of the La Plata region were divided into
  three provinces, Paraguay, Tucuman and Buenos Aires, and Garay's "city"
  became the capital of the latter and also the seat of a new bishopric.
  The increasing population and trade of the La Plata settlements naturally
  contributed to the importance and prosperity of Buenos Aires, but Spain
  seems to have taken very little interest in the town at that time. Peru
  still dazzled the imagination with her stores of gold and silver, and the
  king and his councillors and merchants had no thought for the little
  trading station on the La Plata, for which one small shipment of supplies
  each year was at first thought sufficient. The proximity of the
  Portuguese settlements of Brazil and the unprotected state of the coast,
  however, made smuggling easy, and the colonists soon learned to supply
  their own needs in that way. The heavy seigniorage tax on gold and
  silver, and the costs of transportation by way of Panama, also sent a
  stream of contraband metal from Charcas to Buenos Aires, where it found
  eager buyers among the Portuguese traders from Brazil, who even founded
  the town of Colonia on the opposite bank of the estuary to facilitate
  their hazardous traffic. In time the magnitude of these operations
  attracted attention at Madrid and efforts were made to suppress them, but
  without complete success until more liberal provisions were made to
  promote trade between Spain and her colonies. In 1776 the Rio de la Plata
  provinces were erected into a vice-royalty, and Buenos Aires became its
  capital. Two years later the old commercial restrictions were abolished
  and a new code was promulgated, so liberal in character compared with the
  old that it was called the "free trade regulations." Under the old system
  all intercourse with foreign countries had been prohibited, with the
  exception of Great Britain and Portugal—the former having a
  contract (1715 to 1739) to introduce African slaves, and permission to
  send one shipload of merchandise each year to certain colonial ports, and
  the latter's Brazilian colonies having permission to import from Buenos
  Aires each year 2000 fanegas of wheat, 500 quintals of jerked beef and
  500 of tallow. The African slaves introduced into Buenos Aires in this
  way were limited to 800 a year, and were the only slaves of that
  character ever received except some from Brazil after 1778, when greater
  commercial activity in the port created a sudden demand for labourers.
  Under the new regulations 9 ports in Spain and 24 in the colonies were
  declared <i>puertos habilitados</i>, or ports of entry, and trade between
  them was permitted, though under many restrictions. The effect of this
  change may be seen in the exportation of hides to the mother country,
  which had been only 150,000 a year before 1778, but rose to 700,000 and
  800,000 a year after that date. (For the later history of the city see
  <ph outputclass="sc">Argentina.</ph>)</p>
      <p>(A. J. L.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>