<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e29694">
   <title>BUCHEZ, PHILIPPE JOSEPH BENJAMIN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCHEZ, PHILIPPE JOSEPH BENJAMIN--> (1796-1865), French author and
  politician, was born on the 31st of March 1796 at Matagne-la-Petite, now
  in Belgium, then in the French department of the Ardennes. He finished
  his general education in Paris, and afterwards applied himself to the
  study of natural science and medicine. In 1821 he co-operated with
  Saint-Amand Bazard and others in founding a secret association, modelled
  on that of the Italian Carbonari, with the object of organizing a general
  armed rising against the government. The organization spread rapidly and
  widely, and displayed itself in repeated attempts at revolution. In one
  of these attempts, the affair at Belfort, Buchez was gravely compromised,
  although the jury which tried him did not find the evidence sufficient to
  warrant his condemnation. In 1825 he graduated in medicine, and soon
  after he published with Ulisse Trélat a <i>Précis élémentaire
  d'hygiène</i>. About the same time he became a member of the
  Saint-Simonian Society, presided over by Bazard, Barthélemy Prosper
  Enfantin, and Olinde Rodrigues, and contributed to its organ, the
  <i>Producteur</i>. He left it in consequence of aversion to the strange
  religious ideas developed by its "Supreme Father," Enfantin, and began to
  elaborate what he regarded as a Christian socialism. For the exposition
  and advocacy of his principles he founded a periodical called
  <i>L'Européen</i>. In 1833 he published an <i>Introduction à la science
  de l'histoire</i>, which was received with considerable favour (2nd ed.,
  improved and enlarged, 2 vols., 1842). Notwithstanding its prolixity,
  this is an interesting work. The part which treats of the aim, foundation
  and methods of the science of history is valuable; but what is most
  distinctive in Buchez's theory—the division of historical
  development into four great epochs originated by four universal
  revelations, of each epoch into three periods corresponding to desire,
  reasoning and performance, and of each of these periods into a
  theoretical and practical age—is merely ingenious (see Flint's
  <i>Philosophy of History in Europe</i>, i. 242-252). Buchez next edited,
  along with M. Roux-Lavergne (1802-1874), the <i>Histoire parlementaire de
  la Révolution française</i> (1833-1838; 40 vols.). This vast and
  conscientious publication is a valuable store of material for the early
  periods of the first French Revolution. There is a review of it by
  Carlyle (<i>Miscellanies</i>), the first two parts of whose own history
  of the French Revolution are mainly drawn from it. The editors worked
  under the inspiration of a strong admiration of the principles of
  Robespierre and the Jacobins, and in the belief that the French
  Revolution was an attempt to realize Christianity. In the <i>Essai d'un
  traité complet de philosophie au point de vue du Catholicisme et du
  progrès</i> (1839-1840) Buchez endeavoured to co-ordinate in a single
  system the political, moral, religious and natural phenomena of
  existence. Denying the possibility of innate ideas, he asserted that
  morality comes by revelation, and is therefore not only certain, but the
  only real certainty.</p>
      <p>It was partly owing to the reputation which he had acquired by these
  publications, but still more owing to his connexion with the
  <i>National</i> newspaper, and with the secret societies hostile to the
  government of Louis Philippe, that he was raised, by the Revolution of
  1848, to the presidency of the Constituent Assembly. He speedily showed
  that he was not possessed of the qualities needed in a situation so
  difficult and in days so tempestuous. He retained the position only for a
  very short time. After the dissolution of the assembly he was not
  re-elected. Thrown back into private life, he resumed his studies, and
  added several works to those which have been already mentioned. A
  <i>Traité de politique</i> (published 1866), which may be considered as
  the completion of his <i>Traité de philosophie</i>, was the most
  important of the productions of the last period of his life. His
  brochures are very numerous and on a great variety of subjects, medical,
  historical, political, philosophical, &amp;c. He died on the 12th of
  August 1865. He found a disciple of considerable ability in M.A. Ott, who
  advocated and applied his principles in various writings.</p>
      <p>See also A. Ott, "P.B.J. Buchez," in <i>Journal des économistes</i>
  for 1865.</p>
   </body>
</topic>