<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e4425">
   <title>BRIDGES.</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIDGES.--> 1. <i>Definitions and General
  Considerations.</i>—Bridges (old forms, <i>brig</i>, <i>brygge</i>,
  <i>brudge</i>; Dutch, <i>brug</i>; German, <i>Brücke</i>; a common
  Teutonic word) are structures carrying roadways, waterways or railways
  across streams, valleys or other roads or railways, leaving a passage way
  below. Long bridges of several spans are often termed "viaducts," and
  bridges carrying canals are termed "aqueducts," though this term is
  sometimes used for waterways which have no bridge structure. A "culvert"
  is a bridge of small span giving passage to drainage. In railway work an
  "overbridge" is a bridge over the railway, and an "underbridge" is a
  bridge carrying the railway. In all countries there are legal regulations
  fixing the minimum span and height of such bridges and the width of
  roadway to be provided. Ordinarily bridges are fixed bridges, but there
  are also movable bridges with machinery for opening a clear and
  unobstructed passage way for navigation. Most commonly these are "swing"
  or "turning" bridges. "Floating" bridges are roadways carried on pontoons
  moored in a stream.</p>
      <p>In classical and medieval times bridges were constructed of timber or
  masonry, and later of brick or concrete. Then late in the 18th century
  wrought iron began to be used, at first in combination with timber or
  cast iron. Cast iron was about the same time used for arches, and some of
  the early railway bridges were built with cast iron girders. Cast iron is
  now only used for arched bridges of moderate span. Wrought iron was used
  on a large scale in the suspension road bridges of the early part of the
  19th century. The great girder bridges over the Menai Strait and at
  Saltash near Plymouth, erected in the middle of the 19th century, were
  entirely of wrought iron, and subsequently wrought iron girder bridges
  were extensively used on railways. Since the introduction of mild steel
  of greater tenacity and toughness than wrought iron (<i>i.e.</i> from
  1880 onwards) it has wholly superseded the latter except for girders of
  less than 100 ft. span. The latest change in the material of bridges has
  been the introduction of ferro-concrete, armoured concrete, or concrete
  strengthened with steel bars for arched bridges. The present article
  relates chiefly to metallic bridges. It is only since metal has been used
  that the great spans of 500 to 1800 ft. now accomplished have been made
  possible.</p>
      <p>2. In a bridge there may be distinguished the <i>superstructure</i>
  and the <i>substructure</i>. In the former the main supporting member or
  members may be an arch ring or arched ribs, suspension chains or ropes,
  or a pair of girders, beams or trusses. The bridge flooring rests on the
  supporting members, and is of very various types according to the purpose
  of the bridge. There is also in large bridges wind-bracing to stiffen the
  structure against horizontal forces. The <i>substructure</i> consists of
  (<i>a</i>) the piers and end piers or abutments, the former sustaining a
  vertical load, and the latter having to resist, in addition, the oblique
  thrust of an arch, the pull of a suspension chain, or the thrust of an
  embankment; and (<i>b</i>) the foundations below the ground level, which
  are often difficult and costly parts of the structure, because the
  position of a bridge may be fixed by considerations which preclude the
  selection of a site naturally adapted for carrying a heavy structure.</p>
      <p>3. <i>Types of Bridges</i>.—Bridges may be classed as <i>arched
  bridges</i>, in which the principal members are in compression;
  <i>suspension bridges</i>, in which the principal members are in tension;
  and <i>girder bridges</i>, in which half the components of the principal
  members are in compression and half in tension. But there are cases of
  bridges of mixed type. The choice of the type to be adopted depends on
  many and complex considerations:—(1) The cost, having regard to the
  materials available. For moderate spans brick, masonry or concrete can be
  used without excessive cost, but for longer spans steel is more
  economical, and for very long spans its use is imperative. (2) The
  importance of securing permanence and small cost of maintenance and
  repairs has to be considered. Masonry and concrete are more durable than
  metal, and metal than timber. (3) Aesthetic considerations sometimes have
  great weight, especially in towns. Masonry bridges are preferable in
  appearance to any others, and metal arch bridges are less objectionable
  than most forms of girder.</p>
      <p>Most commonly the engineer has to attach great importance to the
  question of cost, and to design his structure to secure the greatest
  economy consistent with the provision of adequate strength. So long as
  bridge building was an empirical art, great waste of material was
  unavoidable. The development of the theory of structures has been largely
  directed to determining the arrangements of material which are most
  economical, especially in the superstructure. In the case of bridges of
  large span the cost and difficulty of erection are serious, and in such
  cases facility of erection becomes a governing consideration in the
  choice of the type to be adopted. In many cases the span is fixed by
  local conditions, such as the convenient sites for piers, or the
  requirements of waterway or navigation. But here also the question of
  economy must be taken into the reckoning. The cost of the superstructure
  increases very much as the span increases, but the greater the cost of
  the substructure, the larger the span which is economical. Broadly, the
  least costly arrangement is that in which the cost of the superstructure
  of a span is equal to that of a pier and foundation.</p>
      <p>For masonry, brick or concrete the arch subjected throughout to
  compression is the most natural form. The arch ring can be treated as a
  blockwork structure composed of rigid voussoirs. The stability of such
  structures depends on the position of the line of pressure in relation to
  the extrados and intrados of the arch ring. Generally the line of
  pressure lies within the middle half of the depth of the arch ring. In
  finding the line of pressure some principle such as the principle of
  least action must be used in determining the reactions at the crown and
  springings, and some assumptions must be made of not certain validity.
  Hence to give a margin of safety to cover contingencies not calculable,
  an excess of material must be provided. By the introduction of hinges the
  position of the line of resistance can be fixed and the stress in the
  arch ring determined with less uncertainty. In some recent masonry arched
  bridges of spans up to 150 ft. built with hinges considerable economy has
  been obtained.</p>
      <p>For an elastic arch of metal there is a more complete theory, but it
  is difficult of application, and there remains some uncertainty unless
  (as is now commonly done) hinges are introduced at the crown and
  springings.</p>
      <p>In suspension bridges the principal members are in tension, and the
  introduction of iron link chains about the end of the 18th century, and
  later of wire ropes of still greater tenacity, permitted the construction
  of road bridges of this type with spans at that time impossible with any
  other system of construction. The suspension bridge dispenses with the
  compression member required in girders and with a good deal of the
  stiffening required in metal arches. On the other hand, suspension
  bridges require lofty towers and massive anchorages. The defect of the
  suspension bridge is its flexibility. It can be stiffened by girders and
  bracing and is then of mixed type, when it loses much of its advantage in
  economy. Nevertheless, the stiffened suspension bridge will probably be
  the type adopted in future for very great spans. A bridge on this system
  has been projected at New York of 3200 ft. span.</p>
      <p>The immense extension of railways since 1830 has involved the
  construction of an enormous number of bridges, and most of these are
  girder bridges, in which about half the superstructure is in tension and
  half in compression. The use of wrought iron and later of mild steel has
  made the construction of such bridges very convenient and economical. So
  far as superstructure is concerned, more material must be used than for
  an arch or chain, for the girder is in a sense a combination of arch and
  chain. On the other hand, a girder imposes only a vertical load on its
  piers and abutments, and not a horizontal thrust, as in the case of an
  arch or suspension chain. It is also easier to erect.</p>
      <p>A fundamental difference in girder bridges arises from the mode of
  support. In the simplest case the main girders are supported at the ends
  only, and if there are several spans they are <i>discontinuous</i> or
  <i>independent</i>. But a main girder may be supported at two or more
  points so as to be <i>continuous</i> over two <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page534">[v.04 p.0534]</ph>or more spans.
  The continuity permits economy of weight. In a three-span bridge the
  theoretical advantage of continuity is about 49% for a dead load and 16%
  for a live load. The objection to continuity is that very small
  alterations of level of the supports due to settlement of the piers may
  very greatly alter the distribution of stress, and render the bridge
  unsafe. Hence many multiple-span bridges such as the Hawkesbury, Benares
  and Chittravatti bridges have been built with independent spans.</p>
      <p>Lastly, some bridges are composed of cantilevers and suspended
  girders. The main girder is then virtually a continuous girder hinged at
  the points of contrary flexure, so that no ambiguity can arise as to the
  stresses.</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
            <ph outputclass="sc">Fig</ph>. 1.—Trajan's Bridge.
  </title>
         <desc/>
         <image href="images/bridges_1.png">
            <alt>Fig. 1.--Trajan's Bridge.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>Whatever type of bridge is adopted, the engineer has to ascertain the
  loads to be carried, and to proportion the parts so that the stresses due
  to the loads do not exceed limits found by experience to be safe. In many
  countries the limits of working stress in public and railway bridges are
  prescribed by law. The development of theory has advanced <i>pari
  passu</i> with the demand for bridges of greater strength and span and of
  more complex design, and there is now little uncertainty in calculating
  the stresses in any of the types of structure now adopted. In the modern
  metal bridge every member has a definite function and is subjected to a
  calculated straining action. Theory has been the guide in the development
  of bridge design, and its trustworthiness is completely recognized. The
  margin of uncertainty which must be met by empirical allowances on the
  side of safety has been steadily diminished.</p>
      <p>The larger the bridge, the more important is economy of material, not
  only because the total expenditure is more serious, but because as the
  span increases the dead weight of the structure becomes a greater
  fraction of the whole load to be supported. In fact, as the span
  increases a point is reached at which the dead weight of the
  superstructure becomes so large that a limit is imposed to any further
  increase of span.</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
            <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 2.—Bridge of Alcantara.
  </title>
         <desc/>
         <image href="images/bridges_2.png">
            <alt>Fig. 2.--Bridge of Alcantara.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <section>
         <title>History of Bridge Building</title>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 3.—Ponte Salario.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_3.png">
               <alt>Fig. 3.--Ponte Salario.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>4. <i>Roman Bridges</i>.—The first bridge known to have been
  constructed at Rome over the Tiber was the timber Pons Sublicius, the
  bridge defended by Horatius. The Pons Milvius, now Ponte Molle, was
  reconstructed in stone by M. Aemilius Scaurus in 109 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>, and some portions of the old bridge are
  believed to exist in the present structure. The arches vary from 51 to 79
  ft. span. The Pons Fabricius (mod. Ponte dei Quattro Capi), of about 62
  <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>, is practically intact; and the Pons
  Cestius, built probably in 46 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>, retains
  much of the original masonry. The Pons Aelius, built by Hadrian <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 134 and repaired by Pope Nicholas II. and
  Clement IX., is now the bridge of St Angelo. It had eight arches, the
  greatest span being 62 ft.<xref href="#d1e4553/Footnote_061" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> Dio Cassius mentions a bridge,
  possibly 3000 to 4000 ft. in length, built by Trajan over the Danube in
  <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 104. Some piers are said still to exist. A
  bas-relief on the Trajan column shows this bridge with masonry piers and
  timber arches, but the representation is probably conventional (fig. 1).
  Trajan also constructed the bridge of Alcantara in Spain (fig. 2), of a
  total length of 670 ft., at 210 ft. above the stream. This had six arches
  and was built of stone blocks without cement. The bridge of Narses, built
  in the 6th century (fig. 3), carried the Via Salaria over the Anio. It
  was destroyed in 1867, during the approach of Garibaldi to Rome. It had a
  fortification such as became usual in later bridges for defence or for
  the enforcement of tolls. The great lines of aqueducts built by Roman
  engineers, and dating from 300 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph> onwards,
  where they are carried above ground, are arched bridge structures of
  remarkable magnitude (see <ph outputclass="sc">Aqueducts</ph>, §
  <i>Roman</i>). They are generally of brick and concrete.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 4.—First Span of Schaffhausen
    Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_4.png">
               <alt>Fig. 4.--First Span of Schaffhausen Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>5. <i>Medieval and other Early Bridges</i>.—Bridges with stone
  piers and timber superstructures were no doubt constructed from Roman
  times onward, but they have perished. Fig. 4 shows a timber bridge
  erected by the brothers Grubenmann at Schaffhausen about the middle of
  the 18th century. It had spans of 172 and 193 ft., and may be taken as a
  representative type of bridges of this kind. The Wittingen bridge by the
  same engineers had a span of 390 ft., probably the longest timber <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page535">[v.04
  p.0535]</ph>span ever constructed. Of stone bridges in Great Britain,
  the earliest were the cyclopean bridges still existing on Dartmoor,
  consisting of stone piers bridged by stone slabs. The bridge over the
  East Dart near Tavistock had three piers, with slabs 15 ft. by 6 ft.
  (Smiles, <i>Lives of the Engineers,</i> ii. 43). It is reputed to have
  lasted for 2000 years.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 5.—Crowland Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_5.png">
               <alt>Fig. 5.--Crowland Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The curious bridge at Crowland near Peterborough (fig. 5) which now
  spans roadways, the streams which formerly flowed under it having been
  diverted, is one of the earliest known stone bridges in England. It is
  referred to in a charter of the year 943. It was probably built by the
  abbots. The first bridges over the Thames at London were no doubt of
  timber. William of Malmesbury mentions the existence of a bridge in 994.
  J. Stow (<i>Survey of the Cities of London and Westminster</i>) describes
  the building of the first stone bridge commonly called Old London Bridge:
  "About the year 1176, the stone bridge was begun to be founded by Peter
  of Colechurch, near unto the bridge of timber, but more towards the
  west." It carried timber houses (fig. 6) which were frequently burned
  down, yet the main structure existed till the beginning of the 19th
  century. The span of the arches ranged from 10 to 33 ft., and the total
  waterway was only 337 ft. The waterway of the present London Bridge is
  690 ft., and the removal of the obstruction caused by the old bridge
  caused a lowering of the low-water level by 5 ft., and a considerable
  deepening of the river-bed. (See Smiles, <i>Lives of the Engineers</i>,
  "Rennie.")</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 6.—Old London Bridge, <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 1600. From a Drawing in the Pepysian Library
    Magdalene College, Cambridge.

    
  </title>
            <desc>
               <p>From J. R Green's <i>A Short History of the English
    People</i>, by permission of Macmillan &amp; Co., Ltd.</p>
            </desc>
            <image href="images/bridges_6.png">
               <alt>Fig. 6.--Old London Bridge, A.D. 1600.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The architects of the Renaissance showed great boldness in their
  designs. A granite arch built in 1377 over the Adda at Trezzo had a span
  at low water of 251 ft. This noble bridge was destroyed for military
  reasons by Carmagnola in 1416. The Rialto bridge at Venice, with a span
  of 91 ft., was built in 1588 by Antonio da Ponte. Fig. 7 shows the
  beautiful Ponte dellà Trinità erected at Florence in 1566 from the design
  of B. Ammanati.</p>
         <p>6. <i>Modern Bridges.</i>—(<i>a</i>) <i>Timber.</i>—In
  England timber bridges of considerable span, either braced trusses or
  laminated arches (<i>i.e.</i> arches of planks bolted together), were
  built for some of the earlier railways, particularly the Great Western
  and the Manchester, Sheffield &amp; Lincolnshire. They have mostly been
  replaced, decay having taken place at the joints. Timber bridges of large
  span were constructed in America between the end of the 18th and the
  middle of the 19th century. The Amoskeag bridge over the Merrimac at
  Manchester, N.H., U.S.A., built in 1792, had 6 spans of 92 ft. The
  Bellows Falls bridge over the Connecticut (built 1785-1792) had 2 spans
  of 184 ft. The singular Colossus bridge, built in 1812 over the
  Schuylkill, a kind of flat arched truss, had a span of 340 ft. Some of
  these timber bridges are said to have lasted ninety years with ordinary
  repairs, but they were road bridges not heavily loaded. From 1840,
  trusses, chiefly of timber but with wrought-iron tension-rods and
  cast-iron shoes, were adopted in America. The Howe truss of 1830 and the
  Pratt truss of 1844 are examples. The Howe truss had timber chords and a
  lattice of timber struts, with vertical iron ties. In the Pratt truss the
  struts were vertical and the ties inclined. Down to 1850 such bridges
  were generally limited to 150 ft. span. The timber was white pine. As
  railway loads increased and greater spans were demanded, the Howe truss
  was stiffened by timber arches on each side of each girder. Such a
  composite structure is, however, fundamentally defective, the
  distribution of loading to the two independent systems being
  indeterminate. Remarkably high timber piers were built. The Genesee
  viaduct, 800 ft. in length, built in 1851-1852 in 10 spans, had timber
  trestle piers 190 ft. in height. (See Mosse, "American Timber Bridges,"
  <i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i> xxii. p. 305, and for more modern examples,
  cxlii. p. 409; and clv. p. 382; Cooper, "American Railroad Bridges,"
  <i>Trans. Am. Soc. C.E.</i> vol. xxi pp. 1-28.) These timber framed
  structures served as models for the earlier metal trusses which began to
  be used soon after 1850, and which, except in a few localities where iron
  is costly, have quite superseded them.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 7.—Ponte della Trinità, Florence.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_7.png">
               <alt>Fig. 7.--Ponte della Trinità, Florence.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>7. (<i>b</i>) <i>Masonry.</i>—The present London Bridge, begun
  in 1824 and completed in 1831, is as fine an example of a masonry arch
  structure as can be found (figs. 8 and 9). The design was made by John
  Rennie the elder, and the acting engineer was his son, Sir John Rennie.
  The semi-elliptical shape of the arches the variation of span, the slight
  curvature of the roadway, and the simple yet bold architectural details,
  combine to make it a singularly beautiful bridge. The centre arch has a
  span of 152 ft., and rises 29 ft. 6 in above Trinity high-water mark; the
  arches on each side of the centre have a span of 140 ft. and the abutment
  arches 130 ft. The total length of the bridge is 1005 ft., its width from
  outside to outside 56 ft., and height above low <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page536">[v.04 p.0536]</ph>water 60 ft.
  The two centre piers are 24 ft. thick, the exterior stones are granite,
  the interior, half Bramley Fall and half from Painshaw, Derbyshire. The
  voussoirs of the centre arch (all of granite) are 4 ft. 9 in. deep at the
  crown, and increase to not less than 9 ft. at the springing. The general
  depth at which the foundations are laid is about 29 ft. 6 in. below low
  water. The total cost was £1,458,311, but the contractor's tender for the
  bridge alone was £425,081.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 8.—London New Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_8.png">
               <alt>Fig. 8.--London New Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Since 1867 it had been recognized that London Bridge was inadequate to
  carry the traffic passing over it, and a scheme for widening it was
  adopted in 1900. This was carried out in 1902-1904, the footways being
  carried on granite corbels, on which are mounted cornices and open
  parapets. The width between parapets is now 65 ft., giving a roadway of
  35 ft. and two footways of 15 ft. each. The architect was Andrew Murray
  and the engineer, G. E. W. Cruttwell. (Cole, <i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i>
  clxi. p. 290.)</p>
         <p>The largest masonry arch is the Adolphe bridge in Luxemburg, erected
  in 1900-1903. This has a span of 278 ft., 138 ft. rise above the river,
  and 102 ft. from foundation to crown. The thickness of the arch is 4 ft.
  8 in. at the crown and 7 ft. 2 in. where it joins the spandrel masonry.
  The roadway is 52 ft. 6 in. wide. The bridge is not continuous in width,
  there are arch rings on each face, each 16.4 ft. wide with a space
  between of 19.7 ft. This space is filled with a flooring of reinforced
  concrete, resting on the two arches, and carrying the central roadway. By
  the method adopted the total masonry has been reduced one-third. One
  centering was used for the two arch rings, supported on dwarf walls which
  formed a slipway, along which it was moved after the first was built.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 9.—Half Elevation and Half Section
    of Arch of London Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_9.png">
               <alt>Fig. 9.--Half Elevation and Half Section of Arch of London Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Till near the end of the 19th century bridges of masonry or brickwork
  were so constructed that they had to be treated as rigid blockwork
  structures. The stability of such structures depends on the position of
  the line of pressure relatively to the intrados and extrados of the arch
  ring. Generally, so far as could be ascertained, the line of pressure
  lies within the middle half of the depth of the voussoirs. In finding the
  abutment reactions some principle such as the principle of least action
  must be used, and some assumptions of doubtful validity made. But if
  hinges are introduced at crown and springings, the calculation of the
  stresses in the arch ring becomes simple, as the line of pressures must
  pass through the hinges. Such hinges have been used not only for metal
  arches, but in a modified form for masonry and concrete arches. Three
  cases therefore arise: (<i>a</i>) The arch is rigid at crown and
  springings; (<i>b</i>) the arch is two-hinged (hinges at springings);
  (<i>c</i>) the arch is three-hinged (hinges at crown and springings). For
  an elementary account of the theory of arches, hinged or not, reference
  may be made to a paper by H. M. Martin (<i>Proc. Inst. C. E.</i> vol.
  xciii. p. 462); and for that of the elastic arch, to a paper by A.E.Young
  (<i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i> vol. cxxxi. p. 323).</p>
         <p>In Germany and America two- and three-hinged arches of masonry and
  concrete have been built, up to 150 ft. span, with much economy, and the
  calculations being simple, an engineer can venture to work closely to the
  dimensions required by theory. For hinges, Leibbrand, of Stuttgart, uses
  sheets of lead about 1 in. thick extending over the middle third of the
  depth of the voussoir joints, the rest of the joints being left open. As
  the lead is plastic this construction is virtually an articulation. If
  the pressure on the lead is uniformly varying, the centre of pressure
  must be within the middle third of the width of the lead; that is, it
  cannot deviate from the centre of the voussoir joint by more than
  one-eighteenth of its depth. In any case the position of the line of
  pressures is confined at the lead articulations within very narrow
  limits, and ambiguity as to the stresses is greatly diminished. The
  restricted area on which the pressure acts at the lead joints involves
  greater intensity of stress than has been usual in arched bridges. In the
  Württemberg hinged arches a limit of stress of 110 tons per sq. ft. was
  allowed, while in the unhinged arches at Cologne and Coblentz the limit
  was 50 to 60 tons per sq. ft. (<i>Annales des Fonts et Chaussées</i>,
  1891). At Rechtenstein a bridge of two concrete arches has been
  constructed, span 75½ ft., with lead articulations: width of arch 11 ft.;
  depth of arch at crown and springing 2.1 and 2.96 ft. respectively. The
  stresses were calculated to be 15, 17 and 12 tons per sq. ft. at crown,
  joint of rupture, and springing respectively. At Cincinnati a concrete
  arch of 70 ft. span has been built, with a rise of 10 ft. The concrete is
  reinforced by eleven 9-in. steel-rolled joists, spaced 3 ft. apart and
  supported by a cross-channel joist at each springing. The arch is 15 in.
  thick at the crown and 4 ft. at the abutments. The concrete consisted of
  1 cement, 2 sand and 3 to 4 broken stone. An important series of
  experiments on the strength of masonry, brick and concrete structures
  will be found in the <i>Zeitschr. des österreichen Ing. und Arch.
  Vereines</i> (1895).</p>
         <p>The thermal coefficient of expansion of steel and concrete is nearly
  the same, otherwise changes of temperature would cause shearing stress at
  the junction of the two materials. If the two materials are disposed
  symmetrically, the amount of load carried by each would be in direct
  proportion to the coefficient of elasticity and inversely as the moment
  of inertia of the cross section. But it is usual in many cases to provide
  a sufficient section of steel to carry all the tension. For concrete the
  coefficient of elasticity E varies with the amount of stress and
  diminishes as the ratio of sand and stone to cement increases. Its value
  is generally taken at 1,500,000 to 3,000,000 lb per sq. in. For steel E =
  28,000,000 to 30,000,000, or on the average about twelve times its value
  for concrete. The maximum compressive working stress on the concrete may
  be 500 lb per sq. in., the tensile working stress 50 lb per sq. in., and
  the working shearing stress 75 lb per sq. in. The tensile stress on the
  steel may be 16,000 lb per sq. in. The amount of steel in the structure
  may vary from 0.75 to 1.5%. The concrete not only affords much of the
  strength to resist compression, but effectively protects the steel from
  corrosion.</p>
         <p>8. (<i>c</i>) <i>Suspension Bridges.</i>—A suspension bridge
  consists of two or more chains, constructed of links connected by pins,
  or of twisted wire strands, or of wires laid parallel. The chains pass
  over lofty piers on which they usually rest on saddles carried by
  rollers, and are led down on either side to anchorages in rock chambers.
  A level platform is hung from the chains by suspension rods. In the
  suspension bridge iron or steel can be used in its strongest form, namely
  hard-drawn wire. Iron suspension bridges began to be used at the end of
  the 18th century for road bridges with spans unattainable at that time in
  any other system. In 1819 T. Telford began the construction of the Menai
  bridge (fig. 10), the span being 570 ft. and the dip 43 ft. This bridge
  suffered some injury in a storm, but it is still in good condition and
  one of the most graceful of bridges. Other bridges built soon after were
  the Fribourg bridge of 870 ft. span, the Hammersmith bridge of 422 ft.
  span, and the Pest bridge of 666 ft. span. The merit of the simple
  suspension bridge is its cheapness, and its defect is its flexibility.
  This last becomes less <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page537">[v.04 p.0537]</ph>serious as the dead weight of the
  structure becomes large in proportion to the live or temporary load. It
  is, therefore, a type specially suited for great spans. Some suspension
  bridges have broken down in consequence of the oscillations produced by
  bodies of men marching in step. In 1850 a suspension bridge at Angers
  gave way when 487 soldiers were marching over it, and 226 were
  killed.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 10.—Menai Suspension Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_10.png">
               <alt>Fig. 10.--Menai Suspension Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>To obtain greater stiffness various plans have been adopted. In the
  Ordish system a certain number of intermediate points in the span are
  supported by oblique chains, on which girders rest. The Ordish bridge
  built at Prague in 1868 had oblique chains supporting the stiffening
  girders at intermediate points of the span. A curved chain supported the
  oblique chains and kept them straight. In 1860 a bridge was erected over
  the Danube canal at Vienna, of 264 ft. span which had two parallel chains
  one above the other and 4 ft. apart on each side of the bridge. The
  chains of each pair were connected by bracing so that they formed a stiff
  inverted arch resisting deformation under unequal loading. The bridge
  carried a railway, but it proved weak owing to errors of calculation, and
  it was taken down in 1884. The principle was sound and has been proposed
  at various times. About 1850 it was perceived that a bridge stiff enough
  to carry railway trains could be constructed by combining supporting
  chains with stiffening girders suspended from them. W. J. M. Rankine
  proved (<i>Applied Mechanics</i>, p. 370) that the necessary strength of
  a stiffening girder would be only one-seventh part of that of an
  independent girder of the same span as the bridge, suited to carry the
  same moving load (not including the dead weight of the girder which is
  supported by the chain). (See "Suspension Bridge with Stiffened Roadway,"
  by Sir G. Airy, and the discussion, <i>Proc. Inst, C.E.</i>, 1867, xxvi.
  p. 258; also "Suspension Bridges with Stiffening Girders," by Max am
  Ende, <i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i> cxxxvii. p. 306.)</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 11.—Niagara Suspension Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_11.png">
               <alt>Fig. 11.--Niagara Suspension Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The most remarkable bridge constructed on this system was the Niagara
  bridge built by J. A. Roebling in 1852-1855 (fig. 11). The span was 821
  ft., much the largest of any railway bridge at that time, and the height
  above the river 245 ft. There were four suspension cables, each 10 in. in
  diameter; each was composed of seven strands, containing 520 parallel
  wires, or 3640 wires in each cable. Each cable was carried on a separate
  saddle on rollers on each pier. The stiffening girder, constructed
  chiefly of timber, was a box-shaped braced girder 18 ft. deep and 25 ft.
  wide, carrying the railway on top and a roadway within. After various
  repairs and strengthenings, including the replacement of the timber
  girder by an iron one in 1880, this bridge in 1896-1897 was taken down
  and a steel arch built in its place. It was not strong enough to deal
  with the increasing weight of railway traffic. In 1836 I. K. Brunei
  constructed the towers and abutments for a suspension bridge of 702 ft.
  span at Clifton over the Avon, but the project was not then carried
  further; in 1860, however, the link chains of the Hungerford suspension
  bridge which was being taken down were available at small cost, and these
  were used to complete the bridge. There are three chains on each side, of
  one and two links alternately, and these support wrought iron stiffening
  girders. There are wrought iron saddles and steel rollers on the piers.
  At 196 ft. on either side from the towers the chains are carried over
  similar saddles without rollers, and thence at 45° with the horizontal
  down to the anchorages. Each chain has an anchor plate 5 ft. by 6 ft. The
  links are 24 ft. long at the centre of the bridge, and longer as they are
  more inclined, so that their horizontal projection is 24 ft. The chains
  are so arranged that there is a suspending rod at each 8 ft., attached at
  the joint of one of the three chains. For erection a suspended platform
  was constructed on eight wire ropes, on which the chains were laid out
  and connected. Another wire rope with a travelling carriage took out the
  links. The sectional area of the chains is 481 sq. in. at the piers and
  440 sq. in. at the centre. The two stiffening girders are plate girders 3
  ft. deep with flanges of 11 sq. in. area. In addition, the hand railing
  on each side forms a girder 4 ft. 9 in. deep, with flanges 4½ sq. in.
  area.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 12.—Williamsburg Suspension Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_12.png">
               <alt>Fig. 12.--Williamsburg Suspension Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Of later bridges of great span, perhaps the bridges over the East
  river at New York are the most remarkable. The Brooklyn bridge, begun in
  1872, has a centre span of 1595½ and side spans of 930 ft. The Brooklyn
  approach being 971 ft., and the New York approach 1562½ ft., the total
  length of the bridge is 5989 ft. There are four cables which carry a
  promenade, a roadway and an electric railway. The stiffening girders of
  the main span are 40 ft. deep and 67 ft. apart. The saddles for the
  chains are 329 ft. above high water. The cables are 15¾ in. in diameter.
  Each cable has 19 strands of 278 parallel steel wires, 7 B.W.G. Each wire
  is taken separately across the river and its length adjusted. Roebling
  preferred parallel wires as 10 % stronger than twisted wires. Each strand
  when made up and clamped was lowered to its position. The Williamsburg
  bridge (fig. 12), begun in 1897 and opened for traffic in 1903, has a
  span of 1600 ft., a versed sine of 176 ft., and a width of 118 ft. It has
  two decks, and carries two elevated railway tracks, four electric tramcar
  lines, two carriageways, two footways and two <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page538">[v.04 p.0538]</ph>bicycle paths.
  There are four cables, one on each side of the two main trusses or
  stiffening girders. These girders are supported by the cables over the
  centre span but not in the side spans. Intermediate piers support the
  trusses in the side spans. The cables are 18¾ in. in diameter; each
  weighs about 1116 tons, and has a nominal breaking strength of 22,320
  tons, the actual breaking strength being probably greater. The saddles
  are 332 ft. above the water. The four cables support a dead load of 7140
  tons and a live load of 4017 tons. Each cable is composed of 37 strands
  of 208 wires, or 7696 parallel steel wires, No. 8 B.W.G., or about 3/16
  in. in diameter. The wire was required to have a tensile strength of 89
  tons per sq. in., and 2½% elongation in 5 ft. and 5% in 8 in. Cast steel
  clamps hold the cable together, and to these the suspending rods are
  attached. The cables are wrapped in cotton duck soaked in oxidized oil
  and varnish, and are sheathed in sheet iron. A later bridge, the
  Manhattan, is designed to carry four railway tracks and four tramway
  lines, with a wide roadway and footpaths, supported by cables 21¼ in. in
  diameter, each composed of 9472 galvanized steel wires 3/16 in. in
  diameter.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 13.—Tower Bridge, London.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_13.png">
               <alt>Fig. 13.--Tower Bridge, London.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The Tower Bridge, London (fig. 13), is a suspension bridge with a
  secondary bascule bridge in the centre span to permit the passage of
  ships. Two main towers in the river and two towers on the shore abutments
  carry the suspension chains. The opening bridge between the river towers
  consists of two leaves or bascules, pivoted near the faces of the piers
  and rotating in a vertical plane. When raised, the width of 200 ft.
  between the main river piers is unobstructed up to the high-level
  foot-bridge, which is 141 ft. above Trinity H.W. The clear width of the
  two shore spans is 270 ft. The total length of the bridge is 940 ft., and
  that of the approaches 1260 ft. on the north and 780 ft. on the south.
  The width of the bridge between parapets is 60 ft., except across the
  centre span, where it is 49 ft. The main towers consist of a skeleton of
  steel, enclosed in a facing of granite and Portland stone, backed with
  brickwork. There are two high-level footways for use when the bascules
  are raised, the main girders of which are of the cantilever and suspended
  girder type. The cantilevers are fixed to the shore side of the towers.
  The middle girders are 120 ft. in length and attached to the cantilevers
  by links. The main suspension chains are carried across the centre span
  in the form of horizontal ties resting on the high-level footway girders.
  These ties are jointed to the hanging chains by pins 20 in. in diameter
  with a ring in halves surrounding it 5 in. thick. One half ring is
  rigidly attached to the tie and one to the hanging chain, so that the
  wear due to any movement is distributed over the length of the pin. A
  rocker bearing under these pins transmits the load at the joint to the
  steel columns of the towers. The abutment towers are similar to the river
  towers. On the abutment towers the chains are connected by horizontal
  links, carried on rockers, to anchor ties. The suspension chains are
  constructed in the form of braced girders, so that they are stiff against
  unsymmetrical loading. Each chain over a shore span consists of two
  segments, the longer attached to the tie at the top of the river tower,
  the shorter to the link at the top of the abutment tower, and the two
  jointed together at the lowest point. Transverse girders are hung from
  the chains at distances of 18 ft. There are fifteen main transverse
  girders to each shore span, with nine longitudinal girders between each
  pair. The trough flooring, ⅜ in. thick and 6 in. deep, is riveted
  to the longitudinals. The anchor ties are connected to girders embedded
  in large concrete blocks in the foundations of the approach viaducts.</p>
         <p>The two bascules are each constructed with four main girders. Over the
  river these are lattice girders, with transverse girders 12 ft. apart,
  and longitudinal and subsidiary transverse girders dividing the floor
  into rectangles 3 ft. by 3½ ft. covered with buckled plates. The roadway
  is of pine blocks dowelled. The bascules rotate through an angle of 82°,
  and their rear ends in the bascule chambers of the piers carry 365 tons
  of counterweight, the total weight of each being 1070 tons. They rotate
  on steel shafts 21 in. in diameter and 48 ft. long, and the bascules can
  be lifted or lowered in one minute, but usually the time taken is one and
  a half minutes. They are worked by hydraulic machinery.</p>
         <p>9. (<i>d</i>) <i>Iron and Steel Girder Bridges.</i>—The main
  supporting members are two or more horizontal beams, girders or trusses.
  The girders carry a floor or platform either on top (<i>deck</i> bridges)
  or near the bottom (<i>through</i> bridges). The platform is variously
  constructed. For railway bridges it commonly consists of cross girders,
  attached to or resting on the main girders, and longitudinal rail girders
  or stringers carried by the cross girders and directly supporting the
  sleepers and rails. For spans over 75 ft., expansion due to change of
  temperature is provided for by carrying one end of each chain girder on
  rollers placed between the bearing-plate on the girder and the bed-plate
  on the pier or abutment.</p>
         <p>Fig. 14 shows the roller bed of a girder of the Kuilenburg bridge of
  490 ft. span. It will be seen that the girder directly rests on a
  cylindrical pin or rocker so placed as to distribute the load uniformly
  to all the rollers. The pressure on the rollers is limited to about
  <i>p</i> = 600 <i>d</i> in lb per in. length of roller, where <i>d</i> is
  the diameter of the roller in inches.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 14.—Roller Bed of a Girder.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_14.png">
               <alt>Fig. 14.--Roller Bed of a Girder.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>In the girders of bridges the horizontal girder is almost exclusively
  subjected to vertical loading forces. Investigation of the internal
  stresses, which balance the external forces, shows that most of the
  material should be arranged in a top flange, boom or chord, subjected to
  compression, and a bottom flange or chord, subjected to tension. (See
  <ph outputclass="sc">Strength of Materials</ph>.) Connecting the flanges is
  a vertical web which may be a solid plate or a system of bracing bars. In
  any case, though the exact form of cross section of girders varies very
  much, it is virtually an I section (fig. 15). The function of the flanges
  is to resist a horizontal tension and compression distributed practically
  uniformly on their cross sections. The web resists forces equivalent <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page539">[v.04
  p.0539]</ph>to a shear on vertical and horizontal planes. The inclined
  tensions and compressions in the bars of a braced web are equivalent to
  this shear. The horizontal stresses in the flanges are greatest at the
  centre of a span. The stresses in the web are greatest at the ends of the
  span. In the most numerous cases the flanges or chords are parallel. But
  girders may have curved chords and then the stresses in the web are
  diminished.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 15.—Flanged Girder.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_15.png">
               <alt>Fig. 15.--Flanged Girder.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>At first girders had solid or plate webs, but for spans over 100 ft.
  the web always now consists of bracing bars. In some girder bridges the
  members are connected entirely by riveting, in others the principal
  members are connected by pin joints. The pin system of connexion used in
  the Chepstow, Saltash, Newark Dyke and other early English bridges is now
  rarely used in Europe. But it is so commonly used in America as to be
  regarded as a distinctive American feature. With pin connexions some
  weight is saved in the girders, and erection is a little easier. In early
  pin bridges insufficient bearing area was allowed between the pins and
  parts connected, and they worked loose. In some cases riveted covers had
  to be substituted for the pins. The proportions are now better
  understood. Nevertheless the tendency is to use riveted connexions in
  preference to pins, and in any case to use pins for tension members
  only.</p>
         <p>On the first English railways cast iron girder bridges for spans of 20
  to 66 ft. were used, and in some cases these were trussed with wrought
  iron. When in 1845 the plans for carrying the Chester and Holyhead
  railway over the Menai Straits were considered, the conditions imposed by
  the admiralty in the interests of navigation involved the adoption of a
  new type of bridge. There was an idea of using suspension chains combined
  with a girder, and in fact the tower piers were built so as to
  accommodate chains. But the theory of such a combined structure could not
  be formulated at that time, and it was proved, partly by experiment, that
  a simple tubular girder of wrought iron was strong enough to carry the
  railway. The Britannia bridge (fig. 16) has two spans of 460 and two of
  230 ft. at 104 ft. above high water. It consists of a pair of tubular
  girders with solid or plate sides stiffened by angle irons, one line of
  rails passing through each tube. Each girder is 1511 ft. long and weighs
  4680 tons. In cross section (fig. 17), it is 15 ft. wide and varies in
  depth from 23 ft. at the ends to 30 ft. at the centre. Partly to
  counteract any tendency to buckling under compression and partly for
  convenience in assembling a great mass of plates, the top and bottom were
  made cellular, the cells being just large enough to permit passage for
  painting. The total area of the cellular top flange of the large-span
  girders is 648 sq. in., and of the bottom 585 sq. in. As no scaffolding
  could be used for the centre spans, the girders were built on shore,
  floated out and raised by hydraulic presses. The credit for the success
  of the Conway and Britannia bridges must be divided between the
  engineers. Robert Stephenson and William Fairbairn, and Eaton Hodgkinson,
  who assisted in the experimental tests and in formulating the imperfect
  theory then available. The Conway bridge was first completed, and the
  first train passed through the Britannia bridge in 1850. Though each
  girder has been made continuous over the four spans it has not quite the
  proportions over the piers which a continuous girder should have, and
  must be regarded as an imperfectly continuous girder. The spans were in
  fact designed as independent girders, the advantage of continuity being
  at that time imperfectly known. The vertical sides of the girders are
  stiffened so that they amount to 40% of the whole weight. This was partly
  necessary to meet the uncertain conditions in floating when the
  distribution of supporting forces was unknown and there were chances of
  distortion.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 16.—Britannia Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_16.png">
               <alt>Fig. 16.--Britannia Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 17.—Britannia Bridge (Cross Section
    of Tubular Girder).
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_17.png">
               <alt>Fig. 17.--Britannia Bridge (Cross Section of Tubular Girder).</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Wrought iron and, later, steel plate web girders were largely used for
  railway bridges in England after the construction of the Conway and Menai
  bridges, and it was in the discussions arising during their design that
  the proper function of the vertical web between the top and bottom
  flanges of a girder first came to be understood. The proportion of depth
  to span in the Britannia bridge was 1/16. But so far as the flanges are
  concerned the stress <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page540">[v.04 p.0540]</ph>to be resisted varies inversely as
  the depth of the girder. It would be economical, therefore, to make the
  girder very deep. This, however, involves a much heavier web, and
  therefore for any type of girder there must be a ratio of depth to span
  which is most economical. In the case of the plate web there must be a
  considerable excess of material, partly to stiffen it against buckling
  and partly because an excess of thickness must be provided to reduce the
  effect of corrosion. It was soon found that with plate webs the ratio of
  depth to span could not be economically increased beyond 1/15 to 1/12. On
  the other hand a framed or braced web afforded opportunity for much
  better arrangement of material, and it very soon became apparent that
  open web or lattice or braced girders were more economical of material
  than solid web girders, except for small spans. In America such girders
  were used from the first and naturally followed the general design of the
  earlier timber bridges. Now plate web girders are only used for spans of
  less than 100 ft.</p>
         <p>Three types of bracing for the web very early developed—the
  Warren type in which the bracing bars form equilateral triangles, the
  Whipple Murphy in which the struts are vertical and the ties inclined,
  and the lattice in which both struts and ties are inclined at equal
  angles, usually 45° with the horizontal. The earliest published
  theoretical investigations of the stresses in bracing bars were perhaps
  those in the paper by W.T. Doyne and W.B. Blood (<i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i>,
  1851, xi. p. 1), and the paper by J. Barton, "On the economic
  distribution of material in the sides of wrought iron beams" (<i>Proc.
  Inst. C.E.</i>, 1855, xiv. p. 443).</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 18.—Span of Saltash Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_18.png">
               <alt>Fig. 18.--Span of Saltash Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The Boyne bridge, constructed by Barton in Ireland, in 1854-1855, was
  a remarkable example of the confidence with which engineers began to
  apply theory in design. It was a bridge for two lines of railway with
  lattice girders continuous over three spans. The centre span was 264 ft.,
  and the side spans 138 ft. 8 in.; depth 22 ft. 6 in. Not only were the
  bracing bars designed to calculated stresses, and the continuity of the
  girders taken into account, but the validity of the calculations was
  tested by a verification on the actual bridge of the position of the
  points of contrary flexure of the centre span. At the calculated position
  of one of the points of contrary flexure all the rivets of the top boom
  were cut out, and by lowering the end of the girder over the side span
  one inch, the joint was opened 1/32 in. Then the rivets were cut out
  similarly at the other point of contrary flexure and the joint opened.
  The girder held its position with both joints severed, proving that, as
  should be the case, there was no stress in the boom where the bending
  moment changes sign.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 19.—Newark Dyke Bridge and Section
    of Newark Dyke Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_19.png">
               <alt>Fig. 19.--Newark Dyke Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>By curving the top boom of a girder to form an arch and the bottom
  boom to form a suspension chain, the need of web except for non-uniform
  loading is obviated. I.K. Brunel adopted this principle for the Saltash
  bridge near Plymouth, built soon after the Britannia bridge. It has two
  spans of 455 ft. and seventeen smaller spans, the roadway being 100 ft.
  above high water. The top boom of each girder is an elliptical wrought
  iron tube 17 ft. wide by 12 ft. deep. The lower boom is a pair of chains,
  of wrought-iron links, 14 in each chain, of 7 in. by 1 in. section, the
  links being connected by pins. The suspending rods and cross bracing are
  very light. The depth of the girder at the centre is about one-eighth of
  the span.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 20.—Fink Truss.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_20.png">
               <alt>Fig. 20.--Fink Truss.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>In both England and America in early braced bridges cast iron,
  generally in the form of tubes circular or octagonal in section, was used
  for compression members, and wrought iron for the tension members. Fig.
  19 shows the Newark Dyke bridge on the Great Northern railway over the
  Trent. It was a pin-jointed Warren girder bridge erected from designs by
  C.M. Wild in 1851-1853. The span between supports was 259 ft., the clear
  span 240½ ft.; depth between joint pins 16 ft. There were four girders,
  two to each line of way. The top flange consisted of cast iron hollow
  castings butted end to end, and the struts were of cast iron. The lower
  flange and ties were flat wrought iron links. This bridge has now been
  replaced by a stronger bridge to carry the greater loads imposed by
  modern traffic. Fig. 20 shows a Fink truss, a characteristic early
  American type, with cast iron compression and wrought iron tension
  members. The bridge is a deck bridge, the railway being carried on top.
  The transfer of the loads to the ends of the bridge by <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page541">[v.04 p.0541]</ph>long
  ties is uneconomical, and this type has disappeared. The Warren type,
  either with two sets of bracing bars or with intermediate verticals,
  affords convenient means of supporting the floor girders. In 1869 a
  bridge of 390 ft. span was built on this system at Louisville.</p>
         <p>Amongst remarkable American girder bridges may be mentioned the Ohio
  bridge on the Cincinnati &amp; Covington railway, which is probably the
  largest girder span constructed. The centre span is 550 ft. and the side
  spans 490 ft.—centre to centre of piers. The girders are
  independent polygonal girders. The centre girder has a length of 545 ft.
  and a depth of 84 ft. between pin centres. It is 67 ft. between parapets,
  and carries two lines of railway, two carriageways, and two footways. The
  cross girders, stringers and wind-bracing are wrought iron, the rest of
  mild steel. The bridge was constructed in 1888 by the Phoenix Bridge
  Company, and was erected on staging. The total weight of iron and steel
  in three spans was about 5000 tons.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 21.—Typical Cantilever Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_21.png">
               <alt>Fig. 21.--Typical Cantilever Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 22.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_22.png">
               <alt>Fig. 22.--Cantilever Bridge converted to independent spans.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>10. (<i>e</i>) <i>Cantilever Bridges.</i>—It has been stated
  that if in a girder bridge of three or more spans, the girders were made
  continuous there would be an important economy of material, but that the
  danger of settlement of the supports, which would seriously alter the
  points of contrary flexure or points where the bending moment changes
  sign, and therefore the magnitude and distribution of the stresses,
  generally prevents the adoption of continuity. If, however, hinges or
  joints are introduced at the points of contrary flexure, they become
  necessarily points where the bending moment is zero and ambiguity as to
  the stresses vanishes. The exceptional local conditions at the site of
  the Forth bridge led to the adoption there of the cantilever system, till
  then little considered. Now it is well understood that in many positions
  this system is the simplest and most economical method of bridging. It is
  available for spans greater than those practicable with independent
  girders; in fact, on this system the spans are virtually reduced to
  smaller spans so far as the stresses are concerned. There is another
  advantage which in many cases is of the highest importance. The
  cantilevers can be built out from the piers, member by member, without
  any temporary scaffolding below, so that navigation is not interrupted,
  the cost of scaffolding is saved, and the difficulty of building in deep
  water is obviated. The centre girder may be built on the cantilevers and
  rolled into place or lifted from the water-level. Fig. 21 shows a typical
  cantilever bridge of American design. In this case the shore ends of the
  cantilevers are anchored to the abutments. J.A.L. Waddell has shown that,
  in some cases, it is convenient to erect simple independent spans, by
  building them out as cantilevers and converting them into independent
  girders after erection. Fig. 22 shows girders erected in this way, the
  dotted lines being temporary members during erection, which are removed
  afterwards. The side spans are erected first on staging and anchored to
  the piers. From these, by the aid of the temporary members, the centre
  span is built out from both sides. The most important cantilever bridges
  so far erected or projected are as follows:—</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig. 23.</ph>—Forth Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_23.png">
               <alt>Fig. 23.--Forth Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>(1) The Forth bridge (fig. 23). The original design was for a
  stiffened suspension bridge, but after the fall of the Tay bridge in 1879
  this was abandoned. The bridge, which was begun in 1882 and completed in
  1889, is at the only narrowing of the Forth in a distance of 50 m., at a
  point where the channel, about a mile in width, is divided by the island
  of Inchgarvie. The length of the cantilever bridge is 5330 ft., made up
  thus: central tower on Inchgarvie 260 ft.; Fife and Queensferry piers
  each 145 ft.; two central girders between cantilevers each 350 ft.; and
  six cantilevers each 680 ft. The two main spans are each 1710 ft. The
  clear headway is 157 ft., and the extreme height of the towers above high
  water 361 ft. The outer ends of the shore cantilevers are loaded to
  balance half the weight of the central girder, the rolling load, and 200
  tons in addition. An internal viaduct of lattice girders carries a double
  line of rails. Provision is made for longitudinal expansion due to change
  of temperature, for distortion due to the sun acting on one side of the
  structure, and for the wind acting on one side of the bridge. The amount
  of steel used was 38,000 tons exclusive of approach viaducts. (See <i>The
  Forth Bridge</i>, by W. Westhofen; <i>Reports of the British
  Association</i> (1884 and 1885); <i>Die Forth Brücke</i>, von G.
  Barkhausen (Berlin, 1889); <i>The Forth Bridge</i>, by Philip Phillips
  (1890); Vernon Harcourt, <i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i> cxxi. p. 309.)</p>
         <p>(2) The Niagara bridge of a total length of 910 ft., for two lines of
  railway. Clear span between towers 495 ft. Completed in 1883, and more
  recently strengthened (<i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i> cvii. p. 18, and cxliv. p.
  331).</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 24.—Lansdowne Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_24.png">
               <alt>Fig. 24.--Lansdowne Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>(3) The Lansdowne bridge (completed 1889) at Sukkur, over the Indus.
  The clear span is 790 ft., and the suspended girder 200 ft. in length.
  The span to the centres of the end uprights is 820 ft.; width between
  centres of main uprights at bed-plate 100 ft., and between centres of
  main members at end of <ph outputclass="correction">cantilevers</ph> 20 ft. The bridge is for a single line of railway of
  5 ft. 6 in. gauge. The back guys are the most heavily strained part of
  the structure, the stress provided for being 1200 tons. This is due to
  the half weight of centre girder, the weight of the cantilever itself,
  the rolling load on half the bridge, and the wind pressure. The anchors
  are built up of steel plates and angle, bars, and are buried in a large
  mass of concrete. The area of each anchor plate, normal to the line of
  stress, is 32 ft. by 12 ft. The bridge was designed by Sir A. Rendel, the
  consulting engineer to the Indian government (<i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i>
  ciii. p. 123).</p>
         <p>(4) The Red Rock cantilever bridge over the Colorado river, with a
  centre span of 660 ft.</p>
         <p>(5) The Poughkeepsie bridge over the Hudson, built 1886-1887. There
  are five river and two shore spans. The girders over the second and
  fourth spans are extended as cantilevers over the adjoining spans. The
  shore piers carry cantilevers projecting one way over the river openings
  and the other way over a shore span where it is secured to an anchorage.
  The girder spans are 525 ft., the cantilever spans 547 ft., and the shore
  spans 201 ft.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 25.—Quebec Bridge (original design)
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_25.png">
               <alt>Fig. 25.--Quebec Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>(6) The Quebec bridge (fig. 25) over the St Lawrence, which collapsed
  while in course of construction in 1907. This bridge, connecting very
  important railway systems, was designed to carry two lines of rails, a
  highway and electric railway on each side, all between the main trusses.
  Length between abutments 3240 ft.; <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page542">[v.04 p.0542]</ph>channel span
  1800 ft.; suspended span 675 ft.; shore spans 562½ ft. Total weight of
  metal about 32,000 tons.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 26.—Jubilee Bridge over the Hugli.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_26.png">
               <alt>Fig. 26.--Jubilee Bridge over the Hugli.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>(7) The Jubilee bridge over the Hugli, designed by Sir Bradford
  Leslie, is a cantilever bridge of another type (fig. 26). The girders are
  of the Whipple Murphy type, but with curved top booms. The bridge carries
  a double line of railway, between the main girders. The central double
  cantilever is 360 ft. long. The two side span girders are 420 ft long.
  The cantilever rests on two river piers 120 ft. apart, centre to centre.
  The side girders rest on the cantilevers on 15 in. pins, in pendulum
  links suspended from similar pins in saddles 9 ft. high.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 27.—Coalbrookdale Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_27.png">
               <alt>Fig. 27.--Coalbrookdale Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>11. (<i>f</i>) <i>Metal Arch Bridges.</i>—The first iron bridge
  erected was constructed by John Wilkinson (1728-1808) and Abraham Darby
  (1750-1791) in 1773-1779 at Coalbrookdale over the Severn (fig. 27). It
  had five cast iron arched ribs with a centre span of 100 ft. This curious
  bridge is still in use. Sir B. Baker stated that it had required patching
  for ninety years, because the arch and the high side arches would not
  work together. Expansion and contraction broke the high arch and the
  connexions between the arches. When it broke they fished it. Then the
  bolts sheared or the ironwork broke in a new place. He advised that there
  was nothing unsafe; it was perfectly strong and the stress in vital parts
  moderate. All that needed to be done was to fish the fractured ribs of
  the high arches, put oval holes in the fishes, and not screw up the bolts
  too tight.</p>
         <p>Cast iron arches of considerable span were constructed late in the
  18th and early in the 19th century. The difficulty of casting heavy arch
  ribs led to the construction of cast iron arches of cast voussoirs,
  somewhat like the voussoirs of masonry bridges. Such a bridge was the
  Wearmouth bridge, designed by Rowland Burdon and erected in 1793-1796,
  with a span of 235 ft. Southwark bridge over the Thames, designed by John
  Rennie with cast iron ribs and erected in 1814-1819, has a centre span of
  240 ft. and a rise of 24 ft. In Paris the Austerlitz (1800-1806) and
  Carrousel (1834-1836) bridges had cast iron arches. In 1858 an aqueduct
  bridge was erected at Washington by M.C. Meigs (1816-1892). This had two
  arched ribs formed by the cast iron pipes through which the water passed.
  The pipes were 4 ft. in diameter inside, 1½ in. thick, and were lined
  with staves of pine 3 in. thick to prevent freezing. The span was 200
  ft.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 28.—Arch of Bridge at Coblenz
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_28.png">
               <alt>Fig. 28.--Arch of Bridge at Coblenz.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Fig. 28 shows one of the wrought iron arches of a bridge over the
  Rhine at Coblenz. The bridge consists of three spans of about 315 ft.
  each.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 29.—St Louis Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_29.png">
               <alt>Fig. 29.--St Louis Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Of large-span bridges with steel arches, one of the most important is
  the St Louis bridge over the Mississippi, completed in 1874 (fig. 29).
  The river at St Louis is confined to a single channel, 1600 ft. wide, and
  in a freshet in 1870 the scour reached a depth of 51 ft. Captain J.B.
  Eads, the engineer, determined to establish the piers and abutments on
  rock at a depth for the east pier and east abutment of 136 ft. below high
  water. This was effected by caissons with air chambers and air locks, a
  feat unprecedented in the annals of engineering. The bridge has three
  spans, each formed of arches of cast steel. The centre span is 520 ft.
  and the side spans 502 ft. in the clear. The rise of the centre arch is
  47½ ft., and that of the side arches 46 ft. Each span has four steel
  double ribs of steel tubes butted and clasped by wrought iron couplings.
  The vertical bracing between the upper and lower members of each rib,
  which are 12 ft. apart, centre to centre, consolidates them into a single
  arch. The arches carry a double railway track and above this a roadway 54
  ft. wide.</p>
         <p>The St Louis bridge is not hinged, but later bridges have been
  constructed with hinges at the springings and sometimes with hinges at
  the crown also.</p>
         <p>The Alexander III. bridge over the Seine has fifteen steel ribs hinged
  at crown and springings with a span of 353 ft. between centres of hinges
  and 358 ft. between abutments. The rise from side to centre hinges is 20
  ft. 7 in. The roadway is 65½ ft. wide and footways 33 ft. (<i>Proc. Inst.
  C.E.</i> cxxx. p. 335).</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 30.—Viaur Viaduct.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_30.png">
               <alt>Fig. 30.--Viaur Viaduct.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The largest three-hinged-arch bridge constructed is the Viaur viaduct
  in the south of France (fig. 30). The central span is 721 ft. 9 in. and
  the height of the rails above the valley 380 ft. It has a very fine
  appearance, especially when seen in perspective and not merely in
  elevation.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 31.—Douro Viaduct.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_31.png">
               <alt>Fig. 31.--Douro Viaduct.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Fig. 31 shows the Douro viaduct of a total length of 1158 ft. carrying
  a railway 200 ft. above the water. The span of the central opening is 525
  ft. The principal rib is crescent-shaped 32.8 ft. deep <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page543">[v.04 p.0543]</ph>at the
  crown. Rolling load taken at 1.2 ton per ft. Weight of centre span 727
  tons. The Luiz I. bridge is another arched bridge over the Douro, also
  designed by T. Seyrig. This has a span of 566 ft. There are an upper and
  lower roadway, 164 ft. apart vertically. The arch rests on rollers and is
  narrowest at the crown. The reason given for this change of form was that
  it more conveniently allowed the lower road to pass between the
  springings and ensured the transmission of the wind stresses to the
  abutments without interrupting the cross-bracing. Wire cables were used
  in the erection, by which the members were lifted from barges and
  assembled, the operations being conducted from the side piers.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 32.—Niagara Falls and Clifton
    Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_32.png">
               <alt>Fig. 32.--Niagara Falls and Clifton Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The Niagara Falls and Clifton steel arch (fig. 32) replaces the older
  Roebling suspension bridge. The centre span is a two-hinged parabolic
  braced rib arch, and there are side spans of 190 and 210 ft. The bridge
  carries two electric-car tracks, two roadways and two footways. The main
  span weighed 1629 tons, the side spans 154 and 166 tons (Buck, <i>Proc.
  Inst. C.E.</i> cxliv. p. 70). Prof. Claxton Fidler, speaking of the
  arrangement adopted for putting initial stress on the top chord, stated
  that this bridge marked the furthest advance yet made in this type of
  construction. When such a rib is erected on centering without initial
  stress, the subsequent compression of the arch under its weight inflicts
  a bending stress and excess of compression in the upper member at the
  crown. But the bold expedients adopted by the engineer annulled the
  bending action.</p>
         <p>The Garabit viaduct carries the railway near St Flour, in the Cantal
  department, France, at 420 ft. above low water. The deepest part of the
  valley is crossed by an arch of 541 ft. span, and 213 ft. rise. The
  bridge is similar to that at Oporto, also designed by Seyrig. It is
  formed by a crescent-shaped arch, continued on one side by four, on the
  other side by two lattice girder spans, on iron piers. The arch is formed
  by two lattice ribs hinged at the abutments. Its depth at the crown is 33
  ft., and its centre line follows nearly the parabolic line of pressures.
  The two arch ribs are 65½ ft. apart at the springings and 20½ ft. at the
  crown. The roadway girders are lattice, 17 ft. deep, supported from the
  arch ribs at four points. The total length of the viaduct is 1715 ft. The
  lattice girders of the side spans were first rolled into place, so as to
  project some distance beyond the piers, and then the arch ribs were built
  out, being partly supported by wire-rope cables from the lattice girders
  above. The total weight of ironwork was 3200 tons and the cost £124,000
  (<i>Annales des travaux publiques</i>, 1884).</p>
         <p>The Victoria Falls bridge over the Zambezi, designed by Sir Douglas
  Fox, and completed in 1905, is a combination of girder and arch having a
  total length of 650 ft. The centre arch is 500 ft. span, the rise of the
  crown 90 ft., and depth at crown 15 ft. The width between centres of ribs
  of main arch is 27½ ft. at crown and 53 ft. 9 in at springings. The curve
  of the main arch is a parabola. The bridge has a roadway of 30 ft. for
  two lines of rails. Each half arch was supported by cables till joined at
  the centre. An electric cableway of 900 ft. span capable of carrying 10
  tons was used in erection.</p>
         <p>12. (g) <i>Movable Bridges</i> can be closed to carry a road or
  railway or in some cases an aqueduct, but can be opened to give free
  passage to navigation. They are of several types:—</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 33.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_33.png">
               <alt>Fig. 33.--Moving bridges.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>(1) <i>Lifting Bridges.</i>—The bridge with its platform is
  suspended from girders above by chains and counterweights at the four
  corners (fig. 33 a). It is lifted vertically to the required height when
  opened. Bridges of this type are not very numerous or important.</p>
         <p>(2) <i>Rolling Bridges.</i>—The girders are longer than the span
  and the part overhanging the abutment is counter-weighted so that the
  centre of gravity is over the abutment when the bridge is rolled forward
  (fig. 33 b). To fill the gap in the approaches when the bridge is rolled
  forward a frame carrying that part of the road is moved into place
  sideways. At Sunderland, the bridge is first lifted by a hydraulic press
  so as to clear the roadway behind, and is then rolled back.</p>
         <p>(3) <i>Draw or Bascule Bridges.</i>—The fortress draw-bridge is
  the original type, in which a single leaf, or bascule, turns round a
  horizontal hinge at one abutment. The bridge when closed is supported on
  abutments at each end. It is raised by chains and counterweights. A more
  common type is a bridge with two leaves or bascules, one hinged at each
  abutment. When closed <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page544">[v.04 p.0544]</ph>the bascules are locked at the
  centre (see fig. 13). In these bridges each bascule is prolonged
  backwards beyond the hinge so as to balance at the hinge, the
  prolongation sinking into the piers when the bridge is opened.</p>
         <p>(4) <i>Swing or Turning Bridges.</i>—The largest movable bridges
  revolve about a vertical axis. The bridge is carried on a circular base
  plate with a central pivot and a circular track for a live ring and
  conical rollers. A circular revolving platform rests on the pivot and
  rollers. A toothed arc fixed to the revolving platform or to the live
  ring serves to give motion to the bridge. The main girders rest on the
  revolving platform, and the ends of the bridge are circular arcs fitting
  the fixed roadway. Three arrangements are found: (a) the axis of rotation
  is on a pier at the centre of the river and the bridge is equal armed
  (fig. 33 c), so that two navigation passages are opened simultaneously.
  (b) The axis of rotation is on one abutment, and the bridge is then
  usually unequal armed (fig. 33 d), the shorter arm being over the land.
  (c) In some small bridges the shorter arm is vertical and the bridge
  turns on a kind of vertical crane post at the abutment (fig. 33 e).</p>
         <p>(5) <i>Floating Bridges</i>, the roadway being carried on pontoons
  moored in the stream.</p>
         <p>The movable bridge in its closed position must be proportioned like a
  fixed bridge, but it has also other conditions to fulfil. If it revolves
  about a vertical axis its centre of gravity must always lie in that axis;
  if it rolls the centre of gravity must always lie over the abutment. It
  must have strength to support safely its own overhanging weight when
  moving.</p>
         <p>At Konigsberg there is a road bridge of two fixed spans of 39 ft., and
  a central span of 60 ft. between bearings, or 41 ft. clear, with balanced
  bascules over the centre span. Each bascule consists of two main girders
  with cross girders and stringers. The main girders are hung at each side
  on a horizontal shaft 8⅝ in. in diameter, and are 6 ft. deep at
  the hinge, diminishing to 1 ft. 7 in. at the centre of the span. The
  counterweight is a depressed cantilever arm 12 ft. long, overlapped by
  the fixed platform which sinks into a recess in the masonry when the
  bridge opens. In closed position the main girders rest on a bed plate on
  the face of the pier 4 ft. 3 in. beyond the shaft bearings. The bridge is
  worked by hydraulic power, an accumulator with a load of 34 tons
  supplying pressure water at 630 lb per sq. in. The bridge opens in 15
  seconds and closes in 25 seconds.</p>
         <p>At the opening span of the Tower bridge (fig. 13) there are four main
  girders in each bascule. They project 100 ft. beyond and 62 ft. 6 in.
  within the face of the piers. Transverse girders and bracings are
  inserted between the main girders at 12 ft. intervals. The floor is of
  buckled plates paved with wood blocks. The arc of rotation is 82°, and
  the axis of rotation is 13 ft. 3 in. inside the face of the piers, and 5
  ft. 7 in. below the roadway. The weight of ballast in the short arms of
  the bascules is 365 tons. The weight of each leaf including ballast is
  about 1070 tons. The axis is of forged steel 21 in. in diameter and 48
  ft. long. The axis has eight bearings, consisting of rings of live
  rollers 4-7/16 in. in diameter and 22 in. long. The bascules are rotated
  by pinions driven by hydraulic engines working in steel sectors 42 ft.
  radius (<i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i> cxxvii. p. 35).</p>
         <p>As an example of a swing bridge, that between Duluth and Superior at
  the head of Lake Superior over the St Louis river may be described. The
  centre opening is 500 ft., spanned by a turning bridge, 58 ft. wide. The
  girders weighing 2000 tons carry a double track for trains between the
  girders and on each side on cantilevers a trolley track, roadway and
  footway. The bridge can be opened in 2 minutes, and is operated by two
  large electric motors. These have a speed reduction from armature shaft
  to bridge column of 1500 to 1, through four intermediate spur gears and a
  worm gear. The end lifts which transfer the weight of the bridge to the
  piers when the span is closed consist of massive eccentrics having a
  throw of 4 in. The clearance is 2 in., so that the ends are lifted 2 in.
  This gives a load of 50 tons per eccentric. One motor is placed at each
  end of the span to operate the eccentrics and also to release the latches
  and raise the rails of the steam track.</p>
         <p>At Riga there is a floating pontoon bridge over the Duna. It consists
  of fourteen rafts, 105 ft. in length, each supported by two pontoons
  placed 64 ft. apart. The pairs of rafts are joined by three baulks 15 ft.
  long laid in parallel grooves in the framing. Two spans are arranged for
  opening easily. The total length is 1720 ft. and the width 46 ft. The
  pontoons are of iron, 85½ ft. in length, and their section is elliptical,
  10½ ft. horizontal and 12 ft. vertical. The displacement of each pontoon
  is 180 tons and its weight 22 tons. The mooring chains, weighing 22 lb
  per ft., are taken from the upstream end of each pontoon to a downstream
  screw pile mooring and from the downstream end to an upstream screw
  pile.</p>
         <p>13. <i>Transporter Bridges.</i>—This new type of bridge consists
  of a high level bridge from which is suspended a car at a low level. The
  car receives the traffic and conveys it across the river, being caused to
  travel by electric machinery on the high level bridge. Bridges of this
  type have been erected at Portugalete, Bizerta, Rouen, Rochefort and more
  recently across the Mersey between the towns of Widnes and Runcorn.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 34.—Widnes and Runcorn Transporter
    Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_34.png">
               <alt>Fig. 34.--Widnes and Runcorn Transporter Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The Runcorn bridge crosses the Manchester Ship Canal and the Mersey in
  one span of 1000 ft., and four approach spans of 55½ ft. on one side and
  one span on the other. The low-level approach roadways are 35 ft. wide
  with footpaths 6 ft. wide on each side. The supporting structure is a
  cable suspension bridge with stiffening girders. A car is suspended from
  the bridge, carried by a trolley running on the underside of the
  stiffening girders, the car being <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page545">[v.04 p.0545]</ph>propelled
  electrically from one side to the other. The underside of the stiffening
  girder is 82 ft. above the river. The car is 55 ft. long by 24½ ft. wide.
  The electric motors are under the control of the driver in a cabin on the
  car. The trolley is an articulated frame 77 ft. long in five sections
  coupled together with pins. To this are fixed the bearings of the running
  wheels, fourteen on each side. There are two steel-clad series-wound
  motors of 36 B.H.P. For a test load of 120 tons the tractive force is 70
  lb per ton, which is sufficient for acceleration, and maintaining speed
  against wind pressure. The brakes are magnetic, with auxiliary
  handbrakes. Electricity is obtained by two gas engines (one spare) each
  of 75 B.H.P.</p>
         <p>On the opening day passengers were taken across at the rate of more
  than 2000 per hour in addition to a number of vehicles. The time of
  crossing is 3 or 4 minutes. The total cost of the structure was
  £133,000.</p>
         <p>14. In the United States few railway companies design or build their
  own bridges. General specifications as to span, loading, &amp;c., are
  furnished to bridge-building companies, which make the design under the
  direction of engineers who are experts in this kind of work. The design,
  with strain sheets and detail drawings, is submitted to the railway
  engineer with estimates. The result is that American bridges are
  generally of well-settled types and their members of uniform design,
  carefully considered with reference to convenient and accurate
  manufacture. Standard patterns of details are largely adopted, and more
  system is introduced in the workshop than is possible where the designs
  are more varied. Riveted plate girders are used up to 50 ft. span,
  riveted braced girders for spans of 50 ft. to 75 ft., and pin-connected
  girders for longer spans. Since the erection of the Forth bridge,
  cantilever bridges have been extensively used, and some remarkable steel
  arch and suspension bridges have also been constructed. Overhead railways
  are virtually continuous bridge constructions, and much attention has
  been given to a study of the special conditions appertaining to that
  case.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Substructure.</title>
         <p>15. The substructure of a bridge comprises the piers, abutments and
  foundations. These portions usually consist of masonry in some form,
  including under that general head stone masonry, brickwork and concrete.
  Occasionally metal work or woodwork is used for intermediate piers.</p>
         <p>When girders form the superstructure, the resultant pressure on the
  piers or abutments is vertical, and the dimensions of these are simply
  regulated by the sufficiency to bear this vertical load.</p>
         <p>When arches form the superstructure, the abutment must be so designed
  as to transmit the resultant thrust to the foundation in a safe
  direction, and so distributed that no part may be unduly compressed. The
  intermediate piers should also have considerable stability, so as to
  counterbalance the thrust arising when one arch is loaded while the other
  is free from load.</p>
         <p>For suspension bridges the abutment forming the anchorage must be so
  designed as to be thoroughly stable under the greatest pull which the
  chains can exert. The piers require to be carried above the platform, and
  their design must be modified according to the type of suspension bridge
  adopted. When the resultant pressure is not vertical on the piers these
  must be constructed to meet the inclined pressure. In any stiffened
  suspension bridge the action of the pier will be analogous to that of a
  pier between two arches.</p>
         <p>
            <i>Concrete in a shell</i> is a name which might be applied to all the
  methods of founding a pier which depend on the very valuable property
  which strong hydraulic concrete possesses of setting into a solid mass
  under water. The required space is enclosed by a wooden or iron shell;
  the soil inside the shell is removed by dredging, or some form of
  mechanical excavator, until the formation is reached which is to support
  the pier; the concrete is then shot into the enclosed space from a height
  of about 10 ft., and rammed down in layers about 1 ft. thick; it soon
  consolidates into a permanent artificial stone.</p>
         <p>
            <i>Piles</i> are used as foundations in compressible or loose soil.
  The heads of the piles are sawn off, and a platform of timber or concrete
  rests on them. Cast iron and concrete reinforced piles are now used.
  <i>Screw piles</i> are cast iron piles which are screwed into the soil
  instead of being driven in. At their end is fixed a blade of cast iron
  from two to eight times the diameter of the shaft of the pile; the pitch
  of the screw varies from one-half to one-fourth of the external diameter
  of the blade.</p>
         <p>
            <i>Disk piles</i> have been used in sand. These piles have a flat
  flange at the bottom, and water is pumped in at the top of the pile,
  which is weighted to prevent it from rising. Sand is thus blown or pumped
  from below the piles, which are thus easily lowered in ground which
  baffles all attempts to drive in piles by blows. In ground which is of
  the nature of quicksand, piles will often slowly rise to their original
  position after each blow.</p>
         <p>
            <i>Wells.</i>—In some soils foundations may be obtained by the
  device of building a masonry casing like that of a well and excavating
  the soil inside; the casing gradually sinks and the masonry is continued
  at the surface. This method is applicable in running sands. The interior
  of the well is generally filled up with concrete or brick when the
  required depth has been reached.</p>
         <p>
            <i>Piers and Abutments.</i>—Piers and abutments are of masonry,
  brickwork, or cast or wrought iron. In the last case they consist of any
  number of hollow cylindrical pillars, vertical or raking, turned and
  planed at the ends and united by a projection or socket and by flanges
  and bolts. The pillars are strengthened against lateral yielding by
  horizontal and diagonal bracing. In some cases the piers are cast iron
  cylinders 10 ft. or more in diameter filled with concrete.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 35.—Cylinder, Charing Cross Bridge.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_35.png">
               <alt>Fig. 35.--Cylinder, Charing Cross Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>
            <i>Cylinder Foundations.</i>—Formerly when bridge piers had to
  be placed where a firm bearing stratum could only be reached at a
  considerable depth, a timber cofferdam was used in which piles were
  driven down to the firm stratum. On the piles the masonry piers were
  built. Many bridges so constructed have stood for centuries. A great
  change of method arose when iron cylinders and in some cases brick
  cylinders or wells were adopted for foundations. These can be sunk to
  almost any depth or brought up to any height, and are filled with
  Portland cement concrete. They are sometimes excavated by grabs.
  Sometimes they are closed in and kept free of water by compressed air so
  that excavation work can be carried on inside them (fig. 35). Sometimes
  in silty river beds they are sunk 100 ft. or more, for <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page546">[v.04
  p.0546]</ph>security against deep scouring of the river-bed in floods.
  In the case of the Empress bridge over the Sutlej each pier consisted of
  three brick wells, 19 ft. in diameter, sunk 110 ft. The piers of the
  Benares bridge were single iron caissons, 65 ft. by 28 ft., sunk about
  100 ft., lined with brick and filled with concrete. At the Forth bridge
  iron caissons 70 ft. in diameter were sunk about 40 ft. into the bed of
  the Forth. In this case the compressed air process was used.</p>
         <p>16. <i>Erection.</i>—Consideration of the local conditions
  affecting the erection of bridges is always important, and sometimes
  becomes a controlling factor in the determination of the design. The
  methods of erection may be classed as—(1) erection on staging or
  falsework; (2) floating to the site and raising; (3) rolling out from one
  abutment; (4) building out member by member, the completed part forming
  the stage from which additions are handled.</p>
         <p>(1) In erection on staging, the materials available determine the
  character of the staging; stacks of timber, earth banks, or built-up
  staging of piles and trestles have all been employed, also iron staging,
  which can be rapidly erected and moved from site to site. The most
  ordinary type of staging consists of timber piles at nearly equal
  distances of 20 ft. to 30 ft., carrying a timber platform, on which the
  bridge is erected. Sometimes a wide space is left for navigation, and the
  platform at this part is carried by a timber and iron truss. When the
  headway is great or the river deep, timber-braced piers or clusters of
  piles at distances of 50 ft. to 100 ft. may be used. These carry
  temporary trusses of timber or steel. The Kuilenburg bridge in Holland,
  which has a span of 492 ft., was erected on a timber staging of this
  kind, containing 81,000 cub. ft. of timber and 5 tons of bolts. The
  bridge superstructure weighed 2150 tons, so that 38 cub. ft. of timber
  were used per ton of superstructure.</p>
         <p>(2) The Britannia and Conway bridges were built on staging on shore,
  lifted by pontoons, floated out to their position between the piers, and
  lastly lifted into place by hydraulic presses. The Moerdyk bridge in
  Holland, with 14 spans of 328 ft., was erected in a similar way. The
  convenience of erecting girders on shore is very great, but there is some
  risk in the floating operations and a good deal of hauling plant is
  required.</p>
         <p>(3) If a bridge consists of girders continuous over two or more spans,
  it may be put together on the embankment at one end and rolled over the
  piers. In some cases hauling tackle is used, in others power is applied
  by levers and ratchets to the rollers on which the girders travel. In
  such rolling operations the girder is subjected to straining actions
  different from those which it is intended to resist, and parts intended
  for tension may be in compression; hence it may need to be stiffened by
  timber during rolling. The bending action on the bottom boom in passing
  over the rollers is also severe. Modifications of the system have been
  adopted for bridges with discontinuous spans. In narrow ravines a bridge
  of one span may be rolled out, if the projecting end is supported on a
  temporary suspension cable anchored on each side. The free end is slung
  to a block running on the cable. If the bridge is erected when the river
  is nearly dry a travelling stage may be constructed to carry the
  projecting end of the girder while it is hauled across, the other end
  resting on one abutment. Sometimes a girder is rolled out about one-third
  of its length, and then supported on a floating pontoon.</p>
         <p>(4) Some types of bridge can be built out from the abutments, the
  completed part forming an erecting stage on which lifting appliances are
  fixed. Generally, in addition, wire cables are stretched across the span,
  from which lifting tackle is suspended. In bridges so erected the
  straining action during erection must be studied, and material must be
  added to resist erecting stresses. In the case of the St Louis bridge,
  half arches were built out on either side of each pier, so that the load
  balanced. Skeleton towers on the piers supported chains attached to the
  arched ribs at suitable points. In spite of careful provision, much
  difficulty was experienced in making the connexion at the crown, from the
  expansion due to temperature changes. The Douro bridge was similarly
  erected. The girders of the side spans were rolled out so as to overhang
  the great span by 105 ft., and formed a platform from which parts of the
  arch could be suspended. Dwarf towers, built on the arch ring at the
  fifth panel from either side, helped to support the girder above, in
  erecting the centre part of the arch (Seyrig, <i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i>
  lxiii. p. 177). The great cantilever bridges have been erected in the
  same way, and they are specially adapted for erection by building
  out.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Straining Actions and Working Stresses.</title>
         <p>17. In metal bridges wrought iron has been replaced by mild
  steel—a stronger, tougher and better material. Ingot metal or mild
  steel was sometimes treacherous when first introduced, and accidents
  occurred, the causes of which were obscure. In fact, small differences of
  composition or variations in thermal treatment during manufacture involve
  relatively large differences of quality. Now it is understood that care
  must be taken in specifying the exact quality and in testing the material
  supplied. Structural wrought iron has a tenacity of 20 to 22½ tons per
  sq. in. in the direction of rolling, and an ultimate elongation of 8 or
  10% in 8 in. Across the direction of rolling the tenacity is about 18
  tons per sq. in., and the elongation 3% in 8 in. Steel has only a small
  difference of quality in different directions. There is still controversy
  as to what degree of hardness, or (which is nearly the same thing) what
  percentage of carbon, can be permitted with safety in steel for
  structures.</p>
         <p>The qualities of steel used may be classified as
  follows:—(<i>a</i>) Soft steel, having a tenacity of 22½ to 26 tons
  per sq. in., and an elongation of 32 to 24% in 8 in. (<i>b</i>) Medium
  steel, having a tenacity of 26 to 34 tons per sq. in., and 28 to 25%
  elongation. (<i>c</i>) Moderately hard steel, having a tenacity of 34 to
  37 tons per sq. in., and 17% elongation, (<i>d</i>) Hard steel, having a
  tenacity of 37 to 40 tons per sq. in., and 10% elongation. Soft steel is
  used for rivets always, and sometimes for the whole superstructure of a
  bridge, but medium steel more generally for the plates, angle bars,
  &amp;c., the weight of the bridge being then reduced by about 7% for a
  given factor of safety. Moderately hard steel has been used for the
  larger members of long-span bridges. Hard steel, if used at all, is used
  only for compression members, in which there is less risk of flaws
  extending than in tension members. With medium or moderately hard steel
  all rivet holes should be drilled, or punched ⅛ in. less in
  diameter than the rivet and reamed out, so as to remove the ring of
  material strained by the punch.</p>
         <p>In the specification for bridge material, drawn up by the British
  Engineering Standards Committee, it is provided that the steel shall be
  acid or basic open-hearth steel, containing not more than 0.06% of
  sulphur or phosphorus. Plates, angles and bars, other than rivet bars,
  must have a tensile strength of 28 to 32 tons per sq. in., with an
  elevation of 20% in 8 in. Rivet bars tested on a gauge length eight times
  the diameter must have a tensile strength of 26 to 30 tons per sq. in.
  and an elongation of 25%.</p>
         <p>18. <i>Straining Actions.</i>—The external forces acting on a
  bridge may be classified as follows:—</p>
         <p>(1) The <i>live</i> or <i>temporary load</i>, for road bridges the
  weight of a dense crowd uniformly distributed, or the weight of a heavy
  wagon or traction engine; for railway bridges the weight of the heaviest
  train likely to come on the bridge. (2) An allowance is sometimes made
  for <i>impact</i>, that is the dynamical action of the live load due to
  want of vertical balance in the moving parts of locomotives, to
  irregularities of the permanent way, or to yielding of the structure. (3)
  The <i>dead load</i> comprises the weight of the main girders, flooring
  and wind bracing, or the total weight of the superstructure exclusive of
  any part directly carried by the piers. This is usually treated as
  uniformly distributed over the span. (4) The <i>horizontal pressure</i>
  due to a wind blowing transversely to the span, which becomes of
  importance in long and high bridges. (5) The <i>longitudinal drag</i> due
  to the friction of a train when braked, about one-seventh of the weight
  of the train. (6) On a curved bridge the <i>centrifugal load</i> due to
  the radical acceleration of the train. If <i>w</i> is the weight of a
  locomotive in tons, <i>r</i> the radius of curvature of the track,
  <i>v</i> the velocity in feet per sec.; then the horizontal force exerted
  on the bridge is <i>wv</i>
            <sup>2</sup>/<i>gr</i> tons. (7) In some cases,
  especially in arch and suspension bridges, changes of temperature set up
  stresses equivalent to those produced by an external load. In Europe a
  variation of temperature of 70° C. or 126° F. is commonly assumed. For
  this the expansion is about 1 in. in 100 ft. Generally a structure should
  be anchored at one point and free to move if possible in other
  directions. Roughly, if expansion is prevented, a stress of one ton per
  sq. in. is set up in steel structures for each 12° change of
  temperature.</p>
         <p>i. <i>Live Load on Road Bridges.</i>—A dense crowd of people may
  be taken as a uniform load of 80 to 120 lb per sq. ft. But in recent
  times the weight of traction engines and wagons which pass over bridges
  has increased, and this kind of load generally produces greater straining
  action than a crowd of people. In manufacturing districts and near large
  towns loads of 30 tons may come on road bridges, and county and borough
  authorities insist on provision being made for such loads. In Switzerland
  roads are divided into three classes according to their importance, and
  the following loads are prescribed, the designer having to provide
  sufficient strength either for a uniformly distributed crowd, or for a
  heavy wagon anywhere on the roadway:— <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page547">[v.04 p.0547]</ph>
         </p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:33%">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:22%">
                        <p>Crowd, lb per sq. ft.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:44%">
                        <p>Wagon, tons per axle.</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Main Roads</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>92</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>10 with 13 ft. wheel base</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Secondary Roads</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>72</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>6  with 10 ft. wheel base</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Other Roads</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>51</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>3  with 8 ft. wheel base</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>In England still larger loads are now provided for. J.C. Inglis
  (<i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i> cxli. p. 35) has considered two
  cases—(<i>a</i>) a traction engine and boiler trolley, and
  (<i>b</i>) a traction engine and trucks loaded with granite. He has
  calculated the equivalent load per foot of span which would produce the
  same maximum bending moments. The following are some of the
  results:—</p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:90%">
                        <p>Span Ft.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:1%">
                        <p>10.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:1%">
                        <p>20.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:1%">
                        <p>30.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:1%">
                        <p>40.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:1%">
                        <p>50.</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Equivalent load in tons per ft. run, Case <i>a</i>
                        </p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>1.75</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>0.95</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>0.70</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>0.73</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>0.72</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Do. Case <i>b</i>
                        </p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>3.25</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>1.7</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>1.3</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>1.2</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>1.15</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>Large as these loads are on short spans, they are not more than must
  often be provided for.</p>
         <p>
            <i>Live Load on Railway Bridges.</i>—The live load is the weight
  of the heaviest train which can come on the bridge. In the earlier girder
  bridges the live load was taken to be equivalent to a uniform load of 1
  ton per foot run for each line of way. At that time locomotives on
  railways of 4 ft. 8½ in. gauge weighed at most 35 to 45 tons, and their
  length between buffers was such that the average load did not exceed 1
  ton per foot run. Trains of wagons did not weigh more than three-quarters
  of a ton per foot run when most heavily loaded. The weights of engines
  and wagons are now greater, and in addition it is recognized that the
  concentration of the loading at the axles gives rise to greater straining
  action, especially in short bridges, than the same load uniformly
  distributed along the span. Hence many of the earlier bridges have had to
  be strengthened to carry modern traffic. The following examples of some
  of the heaviest locomotives on English railways is given by W.B. Farr
  (<i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i> cxli. p. 12):—</p>
         <p>
            <i>Passenger Engines.</i>
         </p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:71%">
                        <p>Total weights, tons</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p>84.35</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p>98.90</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p>91.90</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p>85.48</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Tons per ft. over all</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.58</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.71</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.62</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.61</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Tons per ft. of wheel base</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.92</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>2.04</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.97</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.95</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Maximum axle load, tons</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>19.00</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>16.00</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>18.70</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>18.50</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>
            <i>Goods Engines.</i>
         </p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:71%">
                        <p>Total weight, tons</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p>77.90</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p>78.80</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p>76.46</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p>75.65</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Tons per ft. over all</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.54</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.50</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.54</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.51</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Tons per ft. of wheel base</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>2.02</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p> 2.02</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p> 2.03</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>2.00</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Maximum axle load, tons</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>15.90</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>16.00</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>13.65</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>15.50</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>
            <i>Tank Engines.</i>
         </p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:71%">
                        <p>Total weight, tons</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p>53.80</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p>58.61</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p> 60.80</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right; width:7%">
                        <p>47.00</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Tons per ft. over all</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.60</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.68</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.70</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>1.55</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Tons per ft. of wheel base</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>2.45</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>2.52</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>2.23</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>3.03</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Maximum axle load, tons</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>17.54</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>15.29</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>17.10</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:right">
                        <p>15.77</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>Farr has drawn diagrams of bending moment for forty different very
  heavy locomotives on different spans, and has determined for each case a
  uniform load which at every point would produce as great a bending moment
  as the actual wheel loads. The following short abstract gives the
  equivalent uniform load which produces bending moments as great as those
  of any of the engines calculated:—</p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:top; text-align:center; width:42%">
                        <p>Span in Ft.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:57%">
                        <p>Load per ft. run equivalent to actual Wheel Loads in Tons, for
      each Track.</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>5.0</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>7.6</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>10.0</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>4.85</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>20.0</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>3.20</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>30.0</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>2.63</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>50.0</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>2.24</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>100.0</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1.97</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>Fig. 36 gives the loads per axle and the distribution of loads in some
  exceptionally heavy modern British locomotives.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
    Express Passenger Engine, G.N. Ry.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_36a.png">
               <alt>Express Passenger Engine, G.N. Ry.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
    Goods Engine, L. &amp; Y. Ry.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_36b.png">
               <alt>Goods Engine, L. &amp; Y. Ry.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
    Passenger Engine, Cal. Ry.<ph outputclass="br"/> 
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph>
    36.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_36c.png">
               <alt>Passenger Engine, Cal. Ry.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page548">[v.04 p.0548]</ph>
         </p>
         <p>In Austria the official regulations require that railway bridges shall
  be designed for at least the following live loads per foot run and per
  track:—</p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>Span.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>Live Load in Tons.</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:top; text-align:center; width:17%">
                        <p>Metres.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:top; text-align:center; width:17%">
                        <p>Ft.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:top; text-align:center; width:32%">
                        <p>Per metre run.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:top; text-align:center; width:32%">
                        <p>Per ft. run.</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>3.3</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>20</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>6.1</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>2</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>6.6</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>15</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>4.6</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>5</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>16.4</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>10</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>3.1</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>20</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>65.6</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>5</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1.5</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>30</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>98.4</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>4</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1.2</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>It would be simpler and more convenient in designing short bridges if,
  instead of assuming an equivalent uniform rolling load, agreement could
  be come to as to a typical heavy locomotive which would produce stresses
  as great as any existing locomotive on each class of railway. Bridges
  would then be designed for these selected loads, and the process would be
  safer in dealing with flooring girders and shearing forces than the
  assumption of a uniform load.</p>
         <p>Some American locomotives are very heavy. Thus a consolidation engine
  may weigh 126 tons with a length over buffers of 57 ft., corresponding to
  an average load of 2.55 tons per ft. run. Also long ore wagons are used
  which weigh loaded two tons per ft. run. J.A.L. Waddell (<i>De
  Pontibus</i>, New York, 1898) proposes to arrange railways in seven
  classes, according to the live loads which may be expected from the
  character of their traffic, and to construct bridges in accordance with
  this classification. For the lightest class, he takes a locomotive and
  tender of 93.5 tons, 52 ft. between buffers (average load 1.8 tons per
  ft. run), and for the heaviest a locomotive and tender weighing 144.5
  tons, 52 ft. between buffers (average load 2.77 tons per ft. run). Wagons
  he assumes to weigh for the lightest class 1.3 tons per ft. run and for
  the heaviest 1.9 tons. He takes as the live load for a bridge two such
  engines, followed by a train of wagons covering the span. Waddell's tons
  are short tons of 2000 lb.</p>
         <p>ii. <i>Impact.</i>—If a vertical load is imposed suddenly, but
  without velocity, work is done during deflection, and the deformation and
  stress are momentarily double those due to the same load at rest on the
  structure. No load of exactly this kind is ever applied to a bridge. But
  if a load is so applied that the deflection increases with speed, the
  stress is greater than that due to a very gradually applied load, and
  vibrations about a mean position are set up. The rails not being
  absolutely straight and smooth, centrifugal and lurching actions occur
  which alter the distribution of the loading. Again, rapidly changing
  forces, due to the moving parts of the engine which are unbalanced
  vertically, act on the bridge; and, lastly, inequalities of level at the
  rail ends give rise to shocks. For all these reasons the stresses due to
  the live load are greater than those due to the same load resting quietly
  on the bridge. This increment is larger on the flooring girders than on
  the main ones, and on short main girders than on long ones. The impact
  stresses depend so much on local conditions that it is difficult to fix
  what allowance should be made. E.H. Stone (<i>Trans. Am. Soc. of C.E.</i>
  xli. p. 467) collated some measurements of deflection taken during
  official trials of Indian bridges, and found the increment of deflection
  due to impact to depend on the ratio of dead to live load. By plotting
  and averaging he obtained the following results:—</p>
         <p>
            <i>Excess of Deflection and straining Action of a moving Load over
  that due to a resting Load.</i>
         </p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:76%">
                        <p>Dead load in per cent of total load</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center; width:3%">
                        <p>10</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center; width:3%">
                        <p>20</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center; width:3%">
                        <p>30</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center; width:3%">
                        <p>40</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center; width:3%">
                        <p>50</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center; width:3%">
                        <p>70</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center; width:3%">
                        <p>90</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Live load in per cent of total load</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>90</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>80</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>70</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>60</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>50</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>30</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>10</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Ratio of live to dead load</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>9</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>4</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>2.3</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>1.5</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>1.0</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>0.43</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>0.10</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Excess of deflection and stress due to moving load per cent</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p> 23</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>13</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p> 8</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>5.5</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>4.0</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>1.6</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="vertical-align:bottom; text-align:center">
                        <p>0.3</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>These results are for the centre deflections of main girders, but
  Stone infers that the augmentation of stress for any member, due to
  causes included in impact allowance, will be the same percentage for the
  same ratios of live to dead load stresses. Valuable measurements of the
  deformations of girders and tension members due to moving trains have
  been made by S.W. Robinson (<i>Trans. Am. Soc. C.E.</i> xvi.) and by F.E.
  Turneaure (<i>Trans. Am. Soc. C.E.</i> xli.). The latter used a recording
  deflectometer and two recording extensometers. The observations are
  difficult, and the inertia of the instrument is liable to cause error,
  but much care was taken. The most striking conclusions from the results
  are that the locomotive balance weights have a large effect in causing
  vibration, and next, that in certain cases the vibrations are cumulative,
  reaching a value greater than that due to any single impact action.
  Generally: (1) At speeds less than 25 m. an hour there is not much
  vibration. (2) The increase of deflection due to impact at 40 or 50 m. an
  hour is likely to reach 40 to 50% for girder spans of less than 50 ft.
  (3) This percentage decreases rapidly for longer spans, becoming about
  25% for 75-ft. spans. (4) The increase per cent of boom stresses due to
  impact is about the same as that of deflection; that in web bracing bars
  is rather greater. (5) Speed of train produces no effect on the mean
  deflection, but only on the magnitude of the vibrations.</p>
         <p>A purely empirical allowance for impact stresses has been proposed,
  amounting to 20% of the live load stresses for floor stringers; 15% for
  floor cross girders; and for main girders, 10% for 40-ft. spans, and 5%
  for 100-ft. spans. These percentages are added to the live load
  stresses.</p>
         <p>iii. <i>Dead Load.</i>—The dead load consists of the weight of
  main girders, flooring and wind-bracing. It is generally reckoned to be
  uniformly distributed, but in large spans the distribution of weight in
  the main girders should be calculated and taken into account. The weight
  of the bridge flooring depends on the type adopted. Road bridges vary so
  much in the character of the flooring that no general rule can be given.
  In railway bridges the weight of sleepers, rails, &amp;c., is 0.2 to 0.25
  tons per ft. run for each line of way, while the rail girders, cross
  girders, &amp;c., weigh 0.15 to 0.2 tons. If a footway is added about 0.4
  ton per ft. run may be allowed for this. The weight of main girders
  increases with the span, and there is for any type of bridge a limiting
  span beyond which the dead load stresses exceed the assigned limit of
  working stress.</p>
         <p>Let W<sub>
               <i>l</i>
            </sub> be the total live load, W<sub>
               <i>f</i>
            </sub>
  the total flooring load on a bridge of span <i>l</i>, both being
  considered for the present purpose to be uniform per ft. run. Let
  <i>k</i>(W<sub>
               <i>l</i>
            </sub>+W<sub>
               <i>f</i>
            </sub>) be the weight of main
  girders designed to carry W<sub>
               <i>l</i>
            </sub>+W<sub>
               <i>f</i>
            </sub>, but
  not their own weight in addition. Then</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      W<sub>
                  <i>g</i>
               </sub> = (W<sub>
                  <i>l</i>
               </sub>+W<sub>
                  <i>f</i>
               </sub>)(<i>k</i>+<i>k</i>
               <sup>2</sup>+<i>k</i>
               <sup>3</sup> ...)

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>will be the weight of main girders to carry
  W<sub>
               <i>l</i>
            </sub>+W<sub>
               <i>f</i>
            </sub> and their own weight (Buck,
  <i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i> lxvii. p. 331). Hence,</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      W<sub>
                  <i>g</i>
               </sub> = (W<sub>
                  <i>l</i>
               </sub>+W<sub>
                  <i>f</i>
               </sub>)<i>k</i>/(1-<i>k</i>).

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>Since in designing a bridge W<sub>
               <i>l</i>
            </sub>+W<sub>
               <i>f</i>
            </sub>
  is known, <i>k</i>(W<sub>
               <i>l</i>
            </sub>+W<sub>
               <i>f</i>
            </sub>) can be
  found from a provisional design in which the weight W<sub>
               <i>g</i>
            </sub>
  is neglected. The actual bridge must have the section of all members
  greater than those in the provisional design in the ratio
  <i>k</i>/(1-<i>k</i>).</p>
         <p>Waddell (<i>De Pontibus</i>) gives the following convenient empirical
  relations. Let <i>w</i>
            <sub>1</sub>, <i>w</i>
            <sub>2</sub> be the weights
  of main girders per ft. run for a live load <i>p</i> per ft. run and
  spans <i>l</i>
            <sub>1</sub>, <i>l</i>
            <sub>2</sub>. Then</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>w</i>
               <sub>2</sub>/<i>w</i>
               <sub>1</sub> = ½ [<i>l</i>
               <sub>2</sub>/<i>l</i>
               <sub>1</sub>+(<i>l</i>
               <sub>2</sub>/<i>l</i>
               <sub>1</sub>)<sup>2</sup>].

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>Now let <i>w</i>
            <sub>1</sub>′, <i>w</i>
            <sub>2</sub>′ be
  the girder weights per ft. run for spans <i>l</i>
            <sub>1</sub>,
  <i>l</i>
            <sub>2</sub>, and live loads <i>p</i>′ per ft. run.
  Then</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>w</i>
               <sub>2</sub>′/<i>w</i>
               <sub>2</sub> = 1/5(1+4<i>p</i>′/<i>p</i>)

    </lines>

            <lines>
               <i>w</i>
               <sub>2</sub>′/<i>w</i>
               <sub>1</sub> = 1/10[<i>l</i>
               <sub>2</sub>/<i>l</i>
               <sub>1</sub>+(<i>l</i>
               <sub>2</sub>/<i>l</i>
               <sub>1</sub>)<sup>2</sup>](1+4<i>p</i>′/<i>p</i>)

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>A partially rational approximate formula for the weight of main
  girders is the following (Unwin, <i>Wrought Iron Bridges and Roofs</i>,
  1869, p. 40):—</p>
         <p>Let <i>w</i> = total live load per ft. run of girder;
  <i>w</i>
            <sub>2</sub> the weight of platform per ft. run;
  <i>w</i>
            <sub>3</sub> the weight of main girders per ft. run, all in tons;
  <i>l</i> = span in ft.; <i>s</i> = average stress in tons per sq. in. on
  gross section of metal; <i>d</i> = depth of girder at centre in ft.;
  <i>r</i> = ratio of span to depth of girder so that <i>r</i> =
  <i>l</i>/<i>d</i>. Then</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>w</i>
               <sub>3</sub> = (<i>w</i>
               <sub>1</sub>+<i>w</i>
               <sub>2</sub>)<i>l</i>
               <sup>2</sup>/(C<i>ds</i>-<i>l</i>
               <sub>2</sub>) = (<i>w</i>
               <sub>1</sub>+<i>w</i>
               <sub>2</sub>)<i>lr</i>/(C<i>s</i>-<i>lr</i>),

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>where C is a constant for any type of girder. It is not easy to fix
  the average stress <i>s</i> per sq. in. of gross section. Hence the
  formula is more useful in the form</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>w</i> = (<i>w</i>
               <sub>1</sub>+<i>w</i>
               <sub>2</sub>)<i>l</i>
               <sup>2</sup>/(K<i>d</i>-<i>l</i>
               <sup>2</sup>) = (<i>w</i>
               <sub>1</sub>+<i>w</i>
               <sub>2</sub>)<i>lr</i>/(K-<i>lr</i>)

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>where K =
  (<i>w</i>
            <sub>1</sub>+<i>w</i>
            <sub>2</sub>+<i>w</i>
            <sub>3</sub>)<i>lr</i>/<i>w</i>
            <sub>3</sub>
  is to be deduced from the data of some bridge previously designed with
  the same working stresses. From some known examples, C varies from 1500
  to 1800 for iron braced parallel or bowstring girders, and from 1200 to
  1500 for similar girders of steel. K = 6000 to 7200 for iron and = 7200
  to 9000 for steel bridges.</p>
         <p>iv. <i>Wind Pressure.</i>—Much attention has been given to wind
  action since the disaster to the Tay bridge in 1879. As to the maximum
  wind pressure on small plates normal to the wind, there is not much
  doubt. Anemometer observations show that pressures of 30 lb per sq. ft.
  occur in storms annually in many localities, and that occasionally higher
  pressures are recorded in exposed positions. Thus at Bidstone, Liverpool,
  where the gauge has an exceptional exposure, a pressure of 80 lb per sq.
  ft. has been observed. In tornadoes, such as that at St Louis in 1896, it
  has been calculated, from the stability of structures overturned, that
  pressures of 45 to 90 lb per sq. ft. must have been reached. As to
  anemometer pressures, it should be observed that the recorded pressure is
  made up of a positive front and negative (vacuum) back pressure, but in
  structures the latter must be absent or only partially developed. Great
  difference of opinion exists as to whether on large surfaces the average
  pressure per sq. ft. is as great as on small surfaces, such as anemometer
  plates. The experiments of Sir B. Baker at the Forth bridge showed that
  on a surface 30 ft. × 15 ft. the intensity of pressure was less than on a
  similarly exposed anemometer plate. In the case of bridges there is the
  further difficulty that some surfaces partially <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page549">[v.04 p.0549]</ph>shield other
  surfaces; one girder, for instance, shields the girder behind it (see
  <i>Brit. Assoc. Report</i>, 1884). In 1881 a committee of the Board of
  Trade decided that the maximum wind pressure on a vertical surface in
  Great Britain should be assumed in designing structures to be 56 lb per
  sq. ft. For a plate girder bridge of less height than the train, the wind
  is to be taken to act on a surface equal to the projected area of one
  girder and the exposed part of a train covering the bridge. In the case
  of braced girder bridges, the wind pressure is taken as acting on a
  continuous surface extending from the rails to the top of the carriages,
  plus the vertical projected area of so much of one girder as is exposed
  above the train or below the rails. In addition, an allowance is made for
  pressure on the leeward girder according to a scale. The committee
  recommended that a factor of safety of 4 should be taken for wind
  stresses. For safety against overturning they considered a factor of 2
  sufficient. In the case of bridges not subject to Board of Trade
  inspection, the allowance for wind pressure varies in different cases. C.
  Shaler Smith allows 300 lb per ft. run for the pressure on the side of a
  train, and in addition 30 lb per sq. ft. on twice the vertical projected
  area of one girder, treating the pressure on the train as a travelling
  load. In the case of bridges of less than 50 ft. span he also provides
  strength to resist a pressure of 50 lb per sq. ft. on twice the vertical
  projection of one truss, no train being supposed to be on the bridge.</p>
         <p>19. <i>Stresses Permitted.</i>—For a long time engineers held
  the convenient opinion that, if the total dead and live load stress on
  any section of a structure (of iron) did not exceed 5 tons per sq. in.,
  ample safety was secured. It is no longer possible to design by so simple
  a rule. In an interesting address to the British Association in 1885, Sir
  B. Baker described the condition of opinion as to the safe limits of
  stress as chaotic. "The old foundations," he said, "are shaken, and
  engineers have not come to an agreement respecting the rebuilding of the
  structure. The variance in the strength of existing bridges is such as to
  be apparent to the educated eye without any calculation. In the present
  day engineers are in accord as to the principles of estimating the
  magnitude of the stresses on the members of a structure, but not so in
  proportioning the members to resist those stresses. The practical result
  is that a bridge which would be passed by the English Board of Trade
  would require to be strengthened 5% in some parts and 60% in others,
  before it would be accepted by the German government, or by any of the
  leading railway companies in America." Sir B. Baker then described the
  results of experiments on repetition of stress, and added that "hundreds
  of existing bridges which carry twenty trains a day with perfect safety
  would break down quickly under twenty trains an hour. This fact was
  forced on my attention nearly twenty-five years ago by the fracture of a
  number of girders of ordinary strength under a five-minutes' train
  service."</p>
         <p>Practical experience taught engineers that though 5 tons per sq. in.
  for iron, or 6½ tons per sq. in. for steel, was safe or more than safe
  for long bridges with large ratio of dead to live load, it was not safe
  for short ones in which the stresses are mainly due to live load, the
  weight of the bridge being small. The experiments of A. Wöhler, repeated
  by Johann Bauschinger, Sir B. Baker and others, show that the breaking
  stress of a bar is not a fixed quantity, but depends on the range of
  variation of stress to which it is subjected, if that variation is
  repeated a very large number of times. Let K be the breaking strength of
  a bar per unit of section, when it is loaded once gradually to breaking.
  This may be termed the statical breaking strength. Let
  <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> be the breaking strength of the same bar
  when subjected to stresses varying from <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> to
  <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>min.</i>
            </sub> alternately and repeated an indefinitely
  great number of times; <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>min.</i>
            </sub> is to be reckoned +
  if of the same kind as <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> and - if of the
  opposite kind (tension or thrust). The range of stress is therefore
  <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub>-<i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>min.</i>
            </sub>, if the
  stresses are both of the same kind, and
  <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub>+<i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>min.</i>
            </sub>, if they
  are of opposite kinds. Let <ph outputclass="grk">Δ</ph> =
  <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> ± <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>min.</i>
            </sub> = the
  range of stress, where <ph outputclass="grk">Δ</ph> is always
  positive. Then Wöhler's results agree closely with the rule,</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>k</i>
               <sub>
                  <i>max.</i>
               </sub> = ½<ph outputclass="grk">Δ</ph>+√(K²-<i>n</i>
               <ph outputclass="grk">Δ</ph>K),

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>where n is a constant which varies from 1.3 to 2 in various qualities
  of iron and steel. For ductile iron or mild steel it may be taken as 1.5.
  For a statical load, range of stress nil, <ph outputclass="grk">Δ</ph> = 0, <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> = K, the
  statical breaking stress. For a bar so placed that it is alternately
  loaded and the load removed, <ph outputclass="grk">Δ</ph> =
  <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> and <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> = 0.6
  K. For a bar subjected to alternate tension and compression of equal
  amount, <ph outputclass="grk">Δ</ph> = 2
  <i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> and <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> = 0.33
  K. The safe working stress in these different cases is
  <i>k</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> divided by the factor of safety. It is
  sometimes said that a bar is "fatigued" by repeated straining. The real
  nature of the action is not well understood, but the word fatigue may be
  used, if it is not considered to imply more than that the breaking stress
  under repetition of loading diminishes as the range of variation
  increases.</p>
         <p>It was pointed out as early as 1869 (Unwin, <i>Wrought Iron Bridges
  and Roofs</i>) that a rational method of fixing the working stress, so
  far as knowledge went at that time, would be to make it depend on the
  ratio of live to dead load, and in such a way that the factor of safety
  for the live load stresses was double that for the dead load stresses.
  Let A be the dead load and B the live load, producing stress in a bar;
  <ph outputclass="grk">ρ</ph> = B/A the ratio of live to dead load;
  <i>f</i>
            <sub>1</sub> the safe working limit of stress for a bar subjected
  to a dead load only and <i>f</i> the safe working stress in any other
  case. Then</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>f</i>
               <sub>1</sub> (A+B)/(A+2B) = <i>f</i>
               <sub>1</sub>(1+<ph outputclass="grk">ρ</ph>)/(1+2<ph outputclass="grk">ρ</ph>).

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>The following table gives values of <i>f</i> so computed on the
  assumption that <i>f</i>
            <sub>1</sub> = 7½ tons per sq. in. for iron and 9
  tons per sq. in. for steel.</p>
         <p>
            <i>Working Stress for combined Dead and Live Load. Factor of Safety
  twice as great for Live Load as for Dead Load.</i>
         </p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:55%">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:7%">
                        <p>Ratio<ph outputclass="br"/> 
                           <ph outputclass="grk">ρ</ph>
                        </p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:7%">
                        <p>1+<ph outputclass="grk">ρ</ph>
                           <ph outputclass="br"/> ——<ph outputclass="br"/>
      1+2<ph outputclass="grk">ρ</ph>
                        </p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Values of <i>f</i>, tons per sq. in.</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>Iron.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>Mild Steel.</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>All dead load</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1.00</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:14%">
                        <p>7.5</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:14%">
                        <p>9.0</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>.25</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.83</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>6.2</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>7.5</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>.50</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.75</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>5.6</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>6.8</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p> .66</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.71</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>5.3</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>6.4</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Live load = Dead load</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1.00</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.66</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>4.9</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>5.9</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>2.00</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.60</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>4.5</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>5.4</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>4.00</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.56</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>4.2</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>5.0</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>All live load</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>∞</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.50</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>3.7</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>4.5</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>Bridge sections designed by this rule differ little from those
  designed by formulae based directly on Wöhler's experiments. This rule
  has been revived in America, and appears to be increasingly relied on in
  bridge-designing. (See <i>Trans. Am. Soc. C.E.</i> xli. p. 156.)</p>
         <p>The method of J.J. Weyrauch and W. Launhardt, based on an empirical
  expression for Wöhler's law, has been much used in bridge designing (see
  <i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i> lxiii. p. 275). Let <i>t</i> be the <i>statical
  breaking strength</i> of a bar, loaded once gradually up to fracture
  (<i>t</i> = breaking load divided by original area of section); <i>u</i>
  the breaking strength of a bar loaded and unloaded an indefinitely great
  number of times, the stress varying from <i>u</i> to 0 alternately (this
  is termed the <i>primitive strength</i>); and, lastly, let <i>s</i> be
  the breaking strength of a bar subjected to an indefinitely great number
  of repetitions of stresses equal and opposite in sign (tension and
  thrust), so that the stress ranges alternately from <i>s</i> to
  -<i>s</i>. This is termed the <i>vibration strength</i>. Wöhler's and
  Bauschinger's experiments give values of <i>t</i>, <i>u</i>, and
  <i>s</i>, for some materials. If a bar is subjected to alternations of
  stress having the range <ph outputclass="grk">Δ</ph> =
  <i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub>-<i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>min.</i>
            </sub>, then, by
  Wöhler's law, the bar will ultimately break, if</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>f</i>
               <sub>
                  <i>max.</i>
               </sub> = F<ph outputclass="grk">Δ</ph>, . . . (1)

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>where F is some unknown function. Launhardt found that, for stresses
  always of the same kind, F =
  (<i>t</i>-<i>u</i>)/(<i>t</i>-<i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub>)
  approximately agreed with experiment. For stresses of different kinds
  Weyrauch found F =
  (<i>u</i>-<i>s</i>)/(2<i>u</i>-<i>s</i>-<i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub>)
  to be similarly approximate. Now let
  <i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub>/<i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>min.</i>
            </sub> = <ph outputclass="grk">φ</ph>, where <ph outputclass="grk">φ</ph> is + or -
  according as the stresses are of the same or opposite signs. Putting the
  values of F in (1) and solving for <i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub>, we get
  for the breaking stress of a bar subjected to repetition of varying
  stress,</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>f</i>
               <sub>
                  <i>max.</i>
               </sub> = <i>u</i>(1+(<i>t</i>-<i>u</i>)<ph outputclass="grk">φ</ph>/<i>u</i>)   [Stresses of same sign.]

      <i>f</i>
               <sub>
                  <i>max.</i>
               </sub> = <i>u</i>(1+(<i>u</i>-<i>s</i>)<ph outputclass="grk">φ</ph>/<i>u</i>)   [Stresses of opposite sign.]

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>The working stress in any case is <i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub>
  divided by a factor of safety. Let that factor be 3. Then Wöhler's
  results for iron and Bauschinger's for steel give the following equations
  for tension or thrust:—</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      Iron, working stress, <i>f</i> = 4.4 (1+½<ph outputclass="grk">φ</ph>)

      Steel, working stress, <i>f</i> = 5.87 (1+½<ph outputclass="grk">φ</ph>).

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>In these equations <ph outputclass="grk">φ</ph> is to have its + or
  - value according to the case considered. For shearing stresses the
  working stress may have 0.8 of its value for tension. The following table
  gives values of the working stress calculated by these
  equations:—</p>
         <p>
            <i>Working Stress for Tension or Thrust by Launhardt and Weyrauch
  Formula.</i>
         </p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:35%">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:14%">
                        <p>
                           <ph outputclass="grk">φ</ph>
                        </p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:21%">
                        <p>1+<ph outputclass="grk">φ</ph>/2</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>Working Stress <i>f</i>, tons per sq. in.</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>Iron.</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>Steel.</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>All dead load</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1.0</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1.5</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:14%">
                        <p>6.60</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:14%">
                        <p>8.80</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.75</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1.375</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p> 6.05</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p> 8.07</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.50</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1.25</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>5.50</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>7.34</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.25</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1.125</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>4.95</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>6.60</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>All live load</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.00</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>1.00</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>4.40</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>5.87</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>-0.25</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.875</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>3.85</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>5.14</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>-0.50</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p> 0.75</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>3.30</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>4.40</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>-0.75</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.625</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>2.75</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>3.67</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left">
                        <p>Equal stresses + and -</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>-1.00</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>0.500</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>2.20</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>2.93</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page550">[v.04 p.0550]</ph>
         </p>
         <p>To compare this with the previous table, <ph outputclass="grk">φ</ph> = (A+B)/A = 1+<ph outputclass="grk">ρ</ph>.
  Except when the limiting stresses are of opposite sign, the two tables
  agree very well. In bridge work this occurs only in some of the bracing
  bars.</p>
         <p>It is a matter of discussion whether, if fatigue is allowed for by the
  Weyrauch method, an additional allowance should be made for impact. There
  was no impact in Wöhler's experiments, and therefore it would seem
  rational to add the impact allowance to that for fatigue; but in that
  case the bridge sections become larger than experience shows to be
  necessary. Some engineers escape this difficulty by asserting that
  Wöhler's results are not applicable to bridge work. They reject the
  allowance for fatigue (that is, the effect of repetition) and design
  bridge members for the total dead and live load, plus a large allowance
  for impact varied according to some purely empirical rule. (See Waddell,
  <i>De Pontibus</i>, p.7.) Now in applying Wöhler's law,
  <i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> for any bridge member is found for the
  maximum possible live load, a live load which though it may sometimes
  come on the bridge and must therefore be provided for, is not the usual
  live load to which the bridge is subjected. Hence the range of stress,
  <i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub>-<i>f</i>
            <sub>
               <i>min.</i>
            </sub>, from which
  the working stress is deduced, is not the ordinary range of stress which
  is repeated a practically infinite number of times, but is a range of
  stress to which the bridge is subjected only at comparatively long
  intervals. Hence practically it appears probable that the allowance for
  fatigue made in either of the tables above is sufficient to cover the
  ordinary effects of impact also.</p>
         <p>English bridge-builders are somewhat hampered in adopting rational
  limits of working stress by the rules of the Board of Trade. Nor do they
  all accept the guidance of Wöhler's law. The following are some examples
  of limits adopted. For the Dufferin bridge (steel) the working stress was
  taken at 6.5 tons per sq. in. in bottom booms and diagonals, 6.0 tons in
  top booms, 5.0 tons in verticals and long compression members. For the
  Stanley bridge at Brisbane the limits were 6.5 tons per sq. in. in
  compression boom, 7.0 tons in tension boom, 5.0 tons in vertical struts,
  6.5 tons in diagonal ties, 8.0 tons in wind bracing, and 6.5 tons in
  cross and rail girders. In the new Tay bridge the limit of stress is
  generally 5 tons per sq. in., but in members in which the stress changes
  sign 4 tons per sq. in. In the Forth bridge for members in which the
  stress varied from 0 to a maximum frequently, the limit was 5.0 tons per
  sq. in., or if the stress varied rarely 5.6 tons per sq. in.; for members
  subjected to alternations of tension and thrust frequently 3.3 tons per
  sq. in. or 5 tons per sq. in. if the alternations were infrequent. The
  shearing area of rivets in tension members was made 1½ times the useful
  section of plate in tension. For compression members the shearing area of
  rivets in butt-joints was made half the useful section of plate in
  compression.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 37.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_37.png">
               <alt>Fig. 37.--Beam loading.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>20. <i>Determination of Stresses in the Members of
  Bridges.</i>—It is convenient to consider beam girder or truss
  bridges, and it is the stresses in the main girders which primarily
  require to be determined. A main girder consists of an upper and lower
  flange, boom or chord and a vertical web. The loading forces to be
  considered are vertical, the horizontal forces due to wind pressure are
  treated separately and provided for by a horizontal system of bracing.
  For practical purposes it is accurate enough to consider the booms or
  chords as carrying exclusively the horizontal tension and compression and
  the web as resisting the whole of the vertical and, in a plate web, the
  equal horizontal shearing forces. Let fig. 37 represent a beam with any
  system of loads W<sub>1</sub>, W<sub>2</sub>, ...
  W<sub>
               <i>n</i>
            </sub>.</p>
         <p>The reaction at the right abutment is</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      R<sub>2</sub> = W<sub>1</sub>
               <i>x</i>
               <sub>1</sub>/<i>l</i>+W<sub>2</sub>
               <i>x</i>
               <sub>2</sub>/<i>l</i>+...

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>That at the left abutment is</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      R<sub>1</sub> = W<sub>1</sub>+W<sub>2</sub>+...-R<sub>2</sub>.

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>Consider any section <i>a b</i>. The total shear at <i>a b</i> is</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      S = R-∑(W<sub>1</sub>+W<sub>2</sub> ...)

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>where the summation extends to all the loads to the left of the
  section. Let <i>p</i>
            <sub>1</sub>, <i>p</i>
            <sub>2</sub> ... be the
  distances of the loads from <i>a b</i>, and <i>p</i> the distance of
  R<sub>1</sub> from <i>a b</i>; then the bending moment at <i>a b</i>
  is</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      M = R<sub>1</sub>
               <i>p</i>-∑(W<sub>1</sub>
               <i>p</i>
               <sub>1</sub>+W<sub>2</sub>
               <i>p</i>
               <sub>2</sub> ...)

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>where the summation extends to all the loads to the left of <i>a
  b</i>. If the loads on the right of the section are considered the
  expressions are similar and give the same results.</p>
         <p>If A<sub>
               <i>t</i>
            </sub> A<sub>
               <i>c</i>
            </sub> are the cross sections of
  the tension and compression flanges or chords, and <i>h</i> the distance
  between their mass centres, then on the assumption that they resist all
  the direct horizontal forces the total stress on each flange is</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      H<sub>
                  <i>t</i>
               </sub> = H<sub>
                  <i>c</i>
               </sub> = M/<i>h</i>

            </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>and the intensity of stress of tension or compression is</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>f</i>
               <sub>
                  <i>t</i>
               </sub> = M/A<sub>
                  <i>t</i>
               </sub>
               <i>h</i>,

      <i>f</i>
               <sub>
                  <i>c</i>
               </sub> = M/A<sub>
                  <i>c</i>
               </sub>
               <i>h</i>.

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>If A is the area of the plate web in a vertical section, the intensity
  of shearing stress is</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>f</i>
               <sub>
                  <i>x</i>
               </sub> = S/A

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>and the intensity on horizontal sections is the same. If the web is a
  braced web, then the vertical component of the stress in the web bars cut
  by the section must be equal to S.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 38.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_38.png">
               <alt>Fig. 38.--Ritter's Method.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>21. <i>Method of Sections. A. Ritter's Method.</i>—In the case
  of braced structures the following method is convenient: When a section
  of a girder can be taken cutting only three bars, the stresses in the
  bars can be found by taking moments. In fig. 38 <i>m n</i> cuts three
  bars, and the forces in the three bars cut by the section are C, S and T.
  There are to the left of the section the external forces, R,
  W<sub>1</sub>, W<sub>2</sub>. Let <i>s</i> be the perpendicular from O,
  the join of C and T on the direction of S; <i>t</i> the perpendicular
  from A, the join of C and S on the direction of T; and <i>c</i> the
  perpendicular from B, the join of S and T on the direction of C. Taking
  moments about O,</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      R<sub>
                  <i>x</i>
               </sub>-W<sub>1</sub>(<i>x</i>+<i>a</i>)-W<sub>2</sub>(<i>x</i>+2<i>a</i>) = S<i>s</i>;

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>taking moments about A,</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      R3<i>a</i>-W<sub>1</sub>2<i>a</i>-W<sub>2</sub>
               <i>a</i> = T<i>t</i>;

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>and taking moments about B,</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      R2<i>a</i>-W<sub>1</sub>
               <i>a</i> = C<i>c</i>

            </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>Or generally, if M<sub>1</sub> M<sub>2</sub> M<sub>3</sub> are the
  moments of the external forces to the left of O, A, and B respectively,
  and <i>s</i>, <i>t</i> and <i>c</i> the perpendiculars from O, A and B on
  the directions of the forces cut by the section, then</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      S<i>s</i> = M<sub>1</sub>; T<i>t</i> = M<sub>2</sub> and C<i>c</i> = M<sub>3</sub>.

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>Still more generally if H is the stress on any bar, <i>h</i> the
  perpendicular distance from the join of the other two bars cut by the
  section, and M is the moment of the forces on one side of that join,</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      H<i>h</i> = M.

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 40.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_40.png">
               <alt>Fig. 40.--Uniform load on girder.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 39.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_39.png">
               <alt>Fig. 39.--Single load on girder.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>22. <i>Distribution of Bending Moment and Shearing
  Force.</i>—Let a girder of span <i>l</i>, fig. 39, supported at the
  ends, carry a fixed load W at m from the right abutment. The reactions at
  the abutments are R<sub>1</sub> = W<i>m</i>/<i>l</i> and R<sub>2</sub> =
  W(<i>l</i>-<i>m</i>)/<i>l</i>. The shears on vertical sections to the
  left and right of the load are R<sub>1</sub> and -R<sub>2</sub>, and the
  distribution of shearing force is given by two rectangles. Bending moment
  increases uniformly from either abutment to the load, at which the
  bending moment is M = R<sub>2</sub>
            <i>m</i> =
  R<sub>1</sub>(<i>l</i>-<i>m</i>). The distribution of bending moment is
  given by the ordinates of a triangle. Next let the girder carry a uniform
  load <i>w</i> per ft. run (fig. 40). The total load <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page551">[v.04 p.0551]</ph>is
  <i>wl</i>; the reactions at abutments, R<sub>1</sub> = R<sub>2</sub> =
  ½<i>wl</i>. The distribution of shear on vertical sections is given by
  the ordinates of a sloping line. The greatest bending moment is at the
  centre and = M<sub>
               <i>c</i>
            </sub> = ⅛<i>wl</i>
            <sup>2</sup>. At any
  point <i>x</i> from the abutment, the bending moment is M =
  ½<i>wx</i>(<i>l</i>-<i>x</i>), an equation to a parabola.</p>
         <p>23. <i>Shear due to Travelling Loads.</i>—Let a uniform train
  weighing <i>w</i> per ft. run advance over a girder of span 2<i>c</i>,
  from the left abutment. When it covers the girder to a distance <i>x</i>
  from the centre (fig. 41) the total load is <i>w</i>(<i>c</i>+<i>x</i>);
  the reaction at B is</p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry>R<sub>2</sub> = <i>w</i>(<i>c</i>+<i>x</i>)×</entry>
                     <entry>
                        <i>c</i>+<i>x</i>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>4<i>c</i>
                     </entry>
                     <entry> = </entry>
                     <entry>
                        <i>w</i>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>4<i>c</i>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>(<i>c</i>+<i>x</i>)²,</entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 42.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_42.png">
               <alt>Fig. 42.--Shear from dead load and travelling load.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 41.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_41.png">
               <alt>Fig. 41.--Load caused by train advancing over girder.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>which is also the shearing force at C for that position of the load.
  As the load travels, the shear at the head of the train will be given by
  the ordinates of a parabola having its vertex at A, and a maximum
  F<sub>
               <i>max.</i>
            </sub> = -½<i>wl</i> at B. If the load travels the
  reverse way, the shearing force at the head of the train is given by the
  ordinates of the dotted parabola. The greatest shear at C for any
  position of the load occurs when the head of the train is at C. For any
  load <i>p</i> between C and B will increase the reaction at B and
  therefore the shear at C by part of <i>p</i>, but at the same time will
  diminish the shear at C by the whole of <i>p</i>. The web of a girder
  must resist the maximum shear, and, with a travelling load like a railway
  train, this is greater for partial than for complete loading. Generally a
  girder supports both a dead and a live load. The distribution of total
  shear, due to a dead load <i>w</i>
            <sub>
               <i>l</i>
            </sub> per ft. run and a
  travelling load <i>w</i>
            <sub>
               <i>l</i>
            </sub> per ft. run, is shown in fig.
  42, arranged so that the dead load shear is added to the maximum
  travelling load shear of the same sign.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 43.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_43.png">
               <alt>Fig. 43.--Maximum shear at vertical sections due to dead and travelling load.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>24. <i>Counterbracing.</i>—In the case of girders with braced
  webs, the tension bars of which are not adapted to resist a thrust,
  another circumstance due to the position of the live load must be
  considered. For a train advancing from the left, the travelling load
  shear in the left half of the span is of a different sign from that due
  to the dead load. Fig. 43 shows the maximum shear at vertical sections
  due to a dead and travelling load, the latter advancing (fig. 43,
  <i>a</i>) from the left and (fig. 43, <i>b</i>) from the right abutment.
  Comparing the figures it will be seen that over a distance x near the
  middle of the girder the shear changes sign, according as the load
  advances from the left or the right. The bracing bars, therefore, for
  this part of the girder must be adapted to resist either tension or
  thrust. Further, the range of stress to which they are subjected is the
  sum of the stresses due to the load advancing from the left or the
  right.</p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="br"/>
         </p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 46.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_46.png">
               <alt>Fig. 46.--Advancing loads.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 45.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_45.png">
               <alt>Fig. 45.--Action distributed by flooring.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 44.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_44.png">
               <alt>Fig. 44.--Shear when concentrated loads travel over the Bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="br"/>
         </p>
         <p>25. <i>Greatest Shear when concentrated Loads travel over the
  Bridge.</i>—To find the greatest shear with a set of concentrated
  loads at fixed distances, let the loads advance from the left abutment,
  and let C be the section at which the shear is required (fig. 44). The
  greatest shear at C may occur with W<sub>1</sub> at C. If W<sub>1</sub>
  passes beyond C, the shear at C will probably be greatest when
  W<sub>2</sub> is at C. Let R be the resultant of the loads on the bridge
  when W<sub>1</sub> is at C. Then the reaction at B and shear at C is
  R<i>n</i>/<i>l</i>. Next let the loads advance a distance a so that
  W<sub>2</sub> comes to C. Then the shear at C is
  R(<i>n</i>+<i>a</i>)/<i>l</i>-W<sub>1</sub>, plus any reaction <i>d</i>
  at B, due to any additional load which has come on the girder during the
  movement. The shear will therefore be increased by bringing W<sub>2</sub>
  to C, if R<i>a</i>/<i>l</i>+<i>d</i> &gt; W<sub>1</sub> and <i>d</i> is
  generally small and negligible. This result is modified if the action of
  the load near the section is distributed to the bracing intersections by
  rail and cross girders. In fig. 45 the action of W is distributed to A
  and B by the flooring. Then the loads at A and B are
  W(<i>p</i>-<i>x</i>)/<i>p</i> and W<i>x</i>/<i>p</i>. Now let C (fig. 46)
  be the section at which the greatest shear is required, and let the loads
  advance from the left till W<sub>1</sub> is at C. If R is the resultant
  of the loads then on the girder, the reaction at B and shear at C is
  R<i>n</i>/<i>l</i>. But the shear may be greater when W<sub>2</sub> is at
  C. In that case the shear at C becomes
  R(<i>n</i>+<i>a</i>)/<i>l</i>+<i>d</i>-W<sub>1</sub>, if <i>a</i> &gt;
  <i>p</i>, and
  R(<i>n</i>+<i>a</i>)/<i>l</i>+<i>d</i>-W<sub>1</sub>
            <i>a</i>/<i>p</i>, if
  <i>a</i> &lt; <i>p</i>. If we neglect <i>d</i>, then the shear increases
  by moving W<sub>2</sub> to C, if R<i>a</i>/<i>l</i> &gt; W<sub>1</sub> in
  the first case, and if R<i>a</i>/<i>l</i> &gt;
  W<sub>1</sub>
            <i>a</i>/<i>p</i> in the second case.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 48.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_48.png">
               <alt>Fig. 48.--Series of travelling loads.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 47.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_47.png">
               <alt>Fig. 47.--Travelling live load.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="br"/>
         </p>
         <p>26. <i>Greatest Bending Moment due to travelling concentrated
  Loads.</i>—For the greatest bending moment due to a travelling live
  load, let a load of <i>w</i> per ft. run advance from the left abutment
  (fig. 47), and let its centre be at <i>x</i> from the left abutment. The
  reaction at B is 2<i>wx</i>²/<i>l</i> and the bending moment at any
  section C, at <i>m</i> from the left abutment, is
  2<i>wx</i>²/(<i>l</i>-<i>m</i>)/<i>l</i>, which increases as <i>x</i>
  increases till the span is covered. Hence, for uniform travelling loads,
  the bending moments are greatest when the loading is complete. In that
  case the loads on either side of C are proportional to <i>m</i> and
  <i>l</i>-<i>m</i>. In the case of a series of travelling loads at fixed
  distances apart passing over the girder from the left, let W<sub>1</sub>,
  W<sub>2</sub> (fig. 48), at distances <i>x</i> and <i>x</i>+<i>a</i> from
  the left abutment, be their resultants on either side of C. Then the
  reaction at B is
  W<sub>1</sub>
            <i>x</i>/<i>l</i>+W<sub>2</sub>(<i>x</i>+<i>a</i>)/<i>l</i>.
  The bending moment at C is</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      M = W<sub>1</sub>
               <i>x</i>(<i>l</i>-<i>m</i>)/<i>l</i>+W<sub>2</sub>
               <i>m</i>{1-(<i>x</i>+<i>a</i>)/<i>l</i>}.

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>If the loads are moved a distance ∆<i>x</i> to the right, the
  bending moment becomes</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      M+∆M = W<sub>1</sub>(<i>x</i>+∆<i>x</i>)(<i>l</i>-<i>m</i>)/<i>l</i>+W<sub>2</sub>
               <i>m</i>{1-(<i>x</i>+∆<i>x</i>+<i>a</i>)/<i>l</i>}

      ∆<i>m</i> = W<sub>1</sub>∆<i>x</i>(<i>l</i>-<i>m</i>)/<i>l</i>-W<sub>2</sub>∆<i>xm</i>/<i>l</i>,

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>and this is positive or the bending moment increases, if
  W<sub>1</sub>(<i>l</i>-<i>m</i>) &gt; W<sub>2</sub>
            <i>m</i>, or if
  W<sub>1</sub>/<i>m</i> &gt; W<sub>2</sub>/(<i>l</i>-<i>m</i>). But these are
  the average loads per ft. run to the left and right of C. Hence, if the
  average load to the left of a section is greater than that to the right,
  the bending moment at the section will be increased by moving the loads
  to the right, and vice versa. Hence the maximum bending moment at C for a
  series of travelling loads will occur when the average load is the same
  on either side of C. If one of the loads is at C, spread over a very
  small distance in the neighbourhood of C, then a very small displacement
  of the loads will permit the fulfilment of the condition. Hence the
  criterion for the position of the loads which makes the moment at C
  greatest is this: one load must be at C, and the other loads must be
  distributed, so that the average loads per ft. on either side of C (the
  load at C being neglected) are nearly equal. If the loads are very
  unequal in magnitude or distance this condition may be satisfied for more
  than one position of the loads, but it is not difficult to ascertain
  which position gives the maximum moment. Generally one of the largest of
  the loads must be at C with as many others to right and left as is
  consistent with that condition.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 49.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_49.png">
               <alt>Fig. 49.--Beam with series of travelling loads.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>This criterion may be stated in another way. The greatest bending
  moment will occur with one of the greatest loads at the section, and when
  this further condition is satisfied. Let fig. 49 represent a beam with
  the series of loads travelling from the right. Let <i>a b</i> be <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page552">[v.04
  p.0552]</ph>the section considered, and let W<sub>
               <i>x</i>
            </sub> be the
  load at <i>a b</i> when the bending moment there is greatest, and
  W<sub>
               <i>n</i>
            </sub> the last load to the right then on the bridge. Then
  the position of the loads must be that which satisfies the condition</p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <i>x</i>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <i>l</i>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>greater than</entry>
                     <entry>W<sub>1</sub>+W<sub>2</sub>+... W<sub>
                           <i>x</i>-1</sub>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>W<sub>1</sub>+W<sub>2</sub>+... W<sub>
                           <i>n</i>
                        </sub>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <i>x</i>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <i>l</i>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>less than</entry>
                     <entry>W<sub>1</sub>+W<sub>2</sub>+... W<sub>
                           <i>x</i>
                        </sub>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>W<sub>1</sub>+W<sub>2</sub>+... W<sub>
                           <i>n</i>
                        </sub>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 50.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_50.png">
               <alt>Fig. 50.--Curve of bending moment.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Fig. 50 shows the curve of bending moment under one of a series of
  travelling loads at fixed distances. Let W<sub>1</sub>, W<sub>2</sub>,
  W<sub>3</sub> traverse the girder from the left at fixed distances
  <i>a</i>, <i>b</i>. For the position shown the distribution of bending
  moment due to W<sub>1</sub> is given by ordinates of the triangle
  A′CB′; that due to W<sub>2</sub> by ordinates of
  A′DB′; and that due to W<sub>3</sub> by ordinates
  A′EB′. The total moment at W<sub>1</sub>, due to three loads,
  is the sum <i>m</i>C+<i>mn</i>+<i>mo</i> of the intercepts which the
  triangle sides cut off from the vertical under W<sub>1</sub>. As the
  loads move over the girder, the points C, D, E describe the parabolas
  M<sub>1</sub>, M<sub>2</sub>, M<sub>3</sub>, the middle ordinates of
  which are ¼W<sub>1</sub>
            <i>l</i>, ¼W<sub>2</sub>
            <i>l</i>, and
  ¼W<sub>3</sub>
            <i>l</i>. If these are first drawn it is easy, for any
  position of the loads, to draw the lines B′C, B′D, B′E,
  and to find the sum of the intercepts which is the total bending moment
  under a load. The lower portion of the figure is the curve of bending
  moments under the leading load. Till W<sub>1</sub> has advanced a
  distance a only one load is on the girder, and the curve A″F gives
  bending moments due to W<sub>1</sub> only; as W<sub>1</sub> advances to a
  distance <i>a</i>+<i>b</i>, two loads are on the girder, and the curve FG
  gives moments due to W<sub>1</sub> and W<sub>2</sub>. GB″ is the
  curve of moments for all three loads
  W<sub>1</sub>+W<sub>2</sub>+W<sub>3</sub>.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 51.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_51.png">
               <alt>Fig. 51.--Short bridge with very unequal loads.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Fig. 51 shows maximum bending moment curves for an extreme case of a
  short bridge with very unequal loads. The three lightly dotted parabolas
  are the curves of maximum moment for each of the loads taken separately.
  The three heavily dotted curves are curves of maximum moment under each
  of the loads, for the three loads passing over the bridge, at the given
  distances, from left to right. As might be expected, the moments are
  greatest in this case at the sections under the 15-ton load. The heavy
  continuous line gives the last-mentioned curve for the reverse direction
  of passage of the loads.</p>
         <p>With short bridges it is best to draw the curve of maximum bending
  moments for some assumed typical set of loads in the way just described,
  and to design the girder accordingly. For longer bridges the funicular
  polygon affords a method of determining maximum bending moments which is
  perhaps more convenient. But very great accuracy in drawing this curve is
  unnecessary, because the rolling stock of railways varies so much that
  the precise magnitude and distribution of the loads which will pass over
  a bridge cannot be known. All that can be done is to assume a set of
  loads likely to produce somewhat severer straining than any probable
  actual rolling loads. Now, except for very short bridges and very unequal
  loads, a parabola can be found which includes the curve of maximum
  moments. This parabola is the curve of maximum moments for a travelling
  load uniform per ft. run. Let <i>w</i>
            <sub>
               <i>e</i>
            </sub> be the load per
  ft. run which would produce the maximum moments represented by this
  parabola. Then <i>w</i>
            <sub>
               <i>e</i>
            </sub> may be termed the uniform load
  per ft. equivalent to any assumed set of concentrated loads. Waddell has
  calculated tables of such equivalent uniform loads. But it is not
  difficult to find <i>w</i>
            <sub>
               <i>e</i>
            </sub>, approximately enough for
  practical purposes, very simply. Experience shows that (<i>a</i>) a
  parabola having the same ordinate at the centre of the span, or
  (<i>b</i>) a parabola having the same ordinate at one-quarter span as the
  curve of maximum moments, agrees with it closely enough for practical
  designing. A criterion already given shows the position of any set of
  loads which will produce the greatest bending moment at the centre of the
  bridge, or at one-quarter span. Let M<sub>
               <i>c</i>
            </sub> and
  M<sub>
               <i>a</i>
            </sub> be those moments. At a section distant <i>x</i> from
  the centre of a girder of span 2<i>c</i>, the bending moment due to a
  uniform load <i>w</i>
            <sub>
               <i>e</i>
            </sub> per ft run is</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      M = ½<i>w</i>
               <sub>
                  <i>e</i>
               </sub>(<i>c</i>-<i>x</i>)(<i>c</i>+<i>x</i>).

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>Putting x = 0, for the centre section</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      M<sub>
                  <i>c</i>
               </sub> = ½<i>w</i>
               <sub>
                  <i>e</i>
               </sub>
               <i>c</i>
               <sup>2</sup>;

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>and putting x = ½c, for section at quarter span</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      M<sub>
                  <i>a</i>
               </sub> = ⅜<i>w</i>
               <sub>
                  <i>e</i>
               </sub>
               <i>c</i>
               <sup>2</sup>.

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>From these equations a value of <i>w</i>
            <sub>
               <i>e</i>
            </sub> can be
  obtained. Then the bridge is designed, so far as the direct stresses are
  concerned, for bending moments due to a uniform dead load and the uniform
  equivalent load <i>w</i>
            <sub>
               <i>e</i>
            </sub>.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 52.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_52.png">
               <alt>Fig. 52.--Influence Lines.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>27. <i>Influence Lines.</i>—In dealing with the action of
  travelling loads much assistance may be obtained by using a line termed
  an <i>influence line</i>. Such a line has for abscissa the distance of a
  load from one end of a girder, and for ordinate the bending moment or
  shear at any given section, or on any member, due to that load. Generally
  the influence line is drawn for unit load. In fig. 52 let
  A′B′ be a girder supported at the ends and let it be required
  to investigate the bending moment at C′ due to unit load in any
  position on the girder. When the load is at F′, the reaction at
  B′ is <i>m</i>/<i>l</i> and the moment at C′ is
  <i>m</i>(<i>l</i>-<i>x</i>)/<i>l</i>, which will be reckoned positive,
  when it resists a tendency of the right-hand part of the girder to turn
  counter-clockwise. Projecting A′F′C′B′ on to the
  horizontal AB, take F<i>f</i> = <i>m</i>(<i>l</i>-<i>x</i>)/<i>l</i>, the
  moment at C of unit load at F. If this process is repeated for all
  positions of the load, we get the influence line AGB for the bending
  moment at C. The area AGB is termed the influence area. The greatest
  moment CG at C is <i>x</i>(<i>l</i>-<i>x</i>)/<i>l</i>. To use this line
  to investigate the maximum moment at C due to a series of travelling
  loads at fixed distances, let P<sub>1</sub>, P<sub>2</sub>,
  P<sub>3</sub>, ... be the loads which at the moment considered are at
  distances <i>m</i>
            <sub>1</sub>, <i>m</i>
            <sub>2</sub>, ... from the left
  abutment. Set off these distances along AB and let <i>y</i>
            <sub>1</sub>,
  <i>y</i>
            <sub>2</sub>, ... be the corresponding ordinates of the influence
  curve (<i>y</i> = F<i>f</i>) on the verticals under the loads. Then the
  moment at C due to all the loads is</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      M = P<sub>1</sub>
               <i>y</i>
               <sub>1</sub>+P<sub>2</sub>
               <i>y</i>
               <sub>2</sub>+...

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page553">[v.04 p.0553]</ph>
         </p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 53.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_53.png">
               <alt>Fig. 53.--Cross girders.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The position of the loads which gives the greatest moment at C may be
  settled by the criterion given above. For a uniform travelling load
  <i>w</i> per ft. of span, consider a small interval F<i>k</i> =
  ∆<i>m</i> on which the load is <i>w</i>∆m. The moment due
  to this, at C, is <i>wm</i>(<i>l</i>-<i>x</i>)∆<i>m</i>/<i>l</i>.
  But <i>m</i>(<i>l</i>-<i>x</i>)∆<i>m</i>/<i>l</i> is the area of
  the strip F<i>fhk</i>, that is <i>y</i>∆<i>m</i>. Hence the moment
  of the load on ∆<i>m</i> at C is <i>wy</i>∆<i>m</i>, and
  the moment of a uniform load over any portion of the girder is <i>w</i> ×
  the area of the influence curve under that portion. If the scales are so
  chosen that <i>a</i> inch represents 1 in. ton of moment, and <i>b</i>
  inch represents 1 ft. of span, and <i>w</i> is in tons per ft. run, then
  <i>ab</i> is the unit of area in measuring the influence curve.</p>
         <p>If the load is carried by a rail girder (stringer) with cross girders
  at the intersections of bracing and boom, its effect is distributed to
  the bracing intersections D′E′ (fig. 53), and the part of the
  influence line for that bay (panel) is altered. With unit load in the
  position shown, the load at D′ is (<i>p</i>-<i>n</i>)/<i>p</i>, and
  that at E′ is <i>n</i>/<i>p</i>. The moment of the load at C is
  <i>m</i>(<i>l</i>-<i>x</i>)/<i>l</i>-<i>n</i>(<i>p</i>-<i>n</i>)/<i>p</i>.
  This is the equation to the dotted line RS (fig. 52).</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 55
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_55.png">
               <alt>Fig. 55.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 54.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_54.png">
               <alt>Fig. 54.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="br"/>
         </p>
         <p>If the unit load is at F′, the reaction at B′ and the
  shear at C′ is <i>m</i>/<i>l</i>, positive if the shearing stress
  resists a tendency of the part of the girder on the right to move
  upwards; set up F<i>f</i> = <i>m</i>/<i>l</i> (fig. 54) on the vertical
  under the load. Repeating the process for other positions, we get the
  influence line AGHB, for the shear at C due to unit load anywhere on the
  girder. GC = <i>x</i>/<i>l</i> and CH = -(<i>l</i>-<i>x</i>)/<i>l</i>.
  The lines AG, HB are parallel. If the load is in the bay D′E′
  and is carried by a rail girder which distributes it to cross girders at
  D′E′, the part of the influence line under this bay is
  altered. Let <i>n</i> (Fig. 55) be the distance of the load from
  D′, <i>x</i>
            <sub>1</sub> the distance of D′ from the left
  abutment, and <i>p</i> the length of a bay. The loads at D′, E, due
  to unit weight on the rail girder are (<i>p</i>-<i>n</i>)/<i>p</i> and
  <i>n</i>/<i>p</i>. The reaction at B′ is
  {(<i>p</i>-<i>n</i>)<i>x</i>
            <sub>1</sub>+<i>n</i>(<i>x</i>
            <sub>1</sub>+<i>p</i>)}/<i>pl</i>.
  The shear at C′ is the reaction at B′ less the load at
  E′, that is,
  {<i>p</i>(<i>x</i>
            <sub>1</sub>+<i>n</i>)-<i>nl</i>}/<i>pl</i>, which is
  the equation to the line DH (fig. 54). Clearly, the distribution of the
  load by the rail girder considerably alters the distribution of shear due
  to a load in the bay in which the section considered lies. The total
  shear due to a series of loads P<sub>1</sub>, P<sub>2</sub>, ... at
  distances <i>m</i>
            <sub>1</sub>, <i>m</i>
            <sub>2</sub>, ... from the left
  abutment, <i>y</i>
            <sub>1</sub>, <i>y</i>
            <sub>2</sub>, ... being the
  ordinates of the influence curve under the loads, is S =
  P<sub>1</sub>
            <i>y</i>
            <sub>1</sub>+P<sub>2</sub>
            <i>y</i>
            <sub>2</sub>+....
  Generally, the greatest shear S at C will occur when the longer of the
  segments into which C divides the girder is fully loaded and the other is
  unloaded, the leading load being at C. If the loads are very unequal or
  unequally spaced, a trial or two will determine which position gives the
  greatest value of S. The greatest shear at C′ of the opposite sign
  to that due to the loading of the longer segment occurs with the shorter
  segment loaded. For a uniformly distributed load <i>w</i> per ft. run the
  shear at C is <i>w</i> × the area of the influence curve under the
  segment covered by the load, attention being paid to the sign of the area
  of the curve. If the load rests directly on the main girder, the greatest
  + and - shears at C will be <i>w</i> × AGC and -<i>w</i> × CHB. But if
  the load is distributed to the bracing intersections by rail and cross
  girders, then the shear at C′ will be greatest when the load
  extends to N, and will have the values <i>w</i> × ADN and -<i>w</i> ×
  NEB. An interesting paper by F.C. Lea, dealing with the determination of
  stress due to concentrated loads, by the method of influence lines will
  be found in <i>Proc. Inst. C.E.</i> clxi. p.261.</p>
         <p>Influence lines were described by Fränkel, <i>Der Civilingenieur</i>,
  1876. See also <i>Handbuch der Ingenieur-wissenschaften</i>, vol. ii. ch.
  x. (1882), and Levy, <i>La Statique graphique</i> (1886). There is a
  useful paper by Prof. G.F. Swain (<i>Trans. Am. Soc. C.E.</i> xvii.,
  1887), and another by L.M. Hoskins (<i>Proc. Am. Soc. C.E.</i> xxv.,
  1899).</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 56.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_56.png">
               <alt>Fig. 56.--Eddy's Method.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>28. <i>Eddy's Method.</i>—Another method of investigating the
  maximum shear at a section due to any distribution of a travelling load
  has been given by Prof. H.T. Eddy (<i>Trans. Am. Soc. C.E.</i> xxii.,
  1890). Let <i>hk</i> (fig. 56) represent in magnitude and position a load
  W, at <i>x</i> from the left abutment, on a girder AB of span <i>l</i>.
  Lay off <i>kf</i>, <i>hg</i>, horizontal and equal to <i>l</i>. Join
  <i>f</i> and <i>g</i> to <i>h</i> and <i>k</i>. Draw verticals at A, B,
  and join <i>no</i>. Obviously <i>no</i> is horizontal and equal to
  <i>l</i>. Also <i>mn</i>/<i>mf</i> = <i>hk</i>/<i>kf</i> or
  <i>mn</i>-W(<i>l</i>-<i>x</i>)/<i>l</i>, which is the reaction at A due
  to the load at C, and is the shear at any point of AC. Similarly,
  <i>po</i> is the reaction at B and shear at any point of CB. The shaded
  rectangles represent the distribution of shear due to the load at C,
  while <i>no</i> may be termed the datum line of shear. Let the load move
  to D, so that its distance from the left abutment is <i>x</i>+<i>a</i>.
  Draw a vertical at D, intersecting <i>fh</i>, <i>kg</i>, in <i>s</i> and
  <i>q</i>. Then <i>qr</i>/<i>ro</i> = <i>hk</i>/<i>hg</i> or <i>ro</i> =
  W(<i>l</i>-<i>x</i>-<i>a</i>)/<i>l</i>, which is the reaction at A and
  shear at any point of AD, for the new position of the load. Similarly,
  <i>rs</i> = W(<i>x</i>+<i>a</i>)/<i>l</i> is the shear on DB. The
  distribution of shear is given by the partially shaded rectangles. For
  the application of this method to a series of loads Prof. Eddy's paper
  must be referred to.</p>
         <p>29. <i>Economic Span.</i>—In the case of a bridge of many spans,
  there is a length of span which makes the cost of the bridge least. The
  cost of abutments and bridge flooring is practically independent of the
  length of span adopted. Let P be the cost of one pier; C the cost of the
  main girders for one span, erected; <i>n</i> the number of spans;
  <i>l</i> the length of one span, and L the length of the bridge between
  abutments. Then, <i>n</i> = L/<i>l</i> nearly. Cost of piers
  (<i>n</i>-1)P. Cost of main girders <i>n</i>G. The cost of a pier will
  not vary materially with the span adopted. It depends mainly on the
  character of the foundations and height at which the bridge is carried.
  The cost of the main girders for one span will vary nearly as the square
  of the span for any given type of girder and intensity of live load. That
  is, G = <i>al</i>², where <i>a</i> is a constant. Hence the total cost of
  that part of the bridge which varies with the span adopted is—</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      C = (<i>n</i>-<i>i</i>)P+<i>nal</i>²

      = LP/<i>l</i>-P+L<i>al</i>.

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>Differentiating and equating to zero, the cost is least when</p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <i>d</i>C<ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <i>dl</i>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>=</entry>
                     <entry>-LP<ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <i>l</i>²</entry>
                     <entry>+L<i>a</i> = 0,</entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      P = <i>al</i>² = G;

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>that is, when the cost of one pier is equal to the cost erected of the
  main girders of one span. Sir Guilford Molesworth puts this in a
  convenient but less exact form. Let G be the cost of superstructure of a
  100-ft. span erected, and P the cost of one pier with its protection.
  Then the economic span is <i>l</i> = 100√P/√G.</p>
         <p>30. <i>Limiting Span.</i>—If the weight of the main girders of a
  bridge, per ft. run in tons, is—</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>w</i>
               <sub>3</sub> = (<i>w</i>
               <sub>1</sub>+<i>w</i>
               <sub>2</sub>)<i>lr</i>/(K-<i>lr</i>)

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>according to a formula already given, then <i>w</i>
            <sub>3</sub>
  becomes infinite if <i>k</i>-<i>lr</i> = 0, or if</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>l</i> = K/<i>r</i>,

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page554">[v.04 p.0554]</ph>
         </p>
         <p>where <i>l</i> is the span in feet and <i>r</i> is the ratio of span
  to depth of girder at centre. Taking K for steel girders as 7200 to
  9000,</p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:left; width:50%">
    </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center; width:50%">
                        <p>Limiting Span in Ft.</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>
                           <i>r</i> = 12</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>
                           <i>l</i> = 600 to 750</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>
                           <i>r</i> = 10</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>
                           <i>l</i> = 720 to 900</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>
                           <i>r</i> = 8</p>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="text-align:center">
                        <p>
                           <i>l</i> = 900 to 1120</p>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>The practical limit of span would be less than this. Professor Claxton
  Fidier (<i>Treatise on Bridge Construction</i>, 1887) has made a very
  careful theoretical analysis of the weights of bridges of different
  types, and has obtained the following values for the limiting spans. For
  parallel girders when <i>r</i> = 10, the limiting span is 1070 ft. For
  parabolic or bowstring girders, when <i>r</i> = 8, the limiting span is
  1280 ft. For flexible suspension bridges with wrought iron link chains,
  and dip = 1/10th of the span, the limiting span is 2800 ft. For stiffened
  suspension bridges with wire cables, if the dip is 1/10th of the span the
  limiting span is 2700 to 3600 ft., and if the dip is 1/8th of the span,
  3250 to 4250 ft., according to the factor of safety allowed.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 57.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_57.png">
               <alt>Fig. 57.--Braced frame.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>31. <i>Braced Girders.</i>—A frame is a rigid structure composed
  of straight struts and ties. The struts and ties are called bracing bars.
  The frame as a whole may be subject to a bending moment, but each member
  is simply extended or compressed so that the total stress on a given
  member is the same at all its cross sections, while the intensity of
  stress is uniform for all the parts of any one cross section. This result
  must follow in any frame, the members of which are so connected that the
  joints offer little or no resistance to change in the relative angular
  position of the members. Thus if the members are pinned together, the
  joint consisting of a single circular pin, the centre of which lies in
  the axis of the piece, it is clear that the direction of the only stress
  which can be transmitted from pin to pin will coincide with this axis.
  The axis becomes, therefore, a line of resistance, and in reasoning of
  the stresses on frames we may treat the frame as consisting of simple
  straight lines from joint to joint. It is found in practice that the
  stresses on the several members do not differ sensibly whether these
  members are pinned together with a single pin or more rigidly jointed by
  several bolts or rivets. Frames are much used as girders, and they also
  give useful designs for suspension and arched bridges. A frame used to
  support a weight is often called a <i>truss</i>; the stresses on the
  various members of a truss can be computed for any given load with
  greater accuracy than the intensity of stress on the various parts of a
  continuous structure such as a tubular girder, or the rib of an arch.
  Many assumptions are made in treating of the flexure of a continuous
  structure which are not strictly true; no assumption is made in
  determining the stresses on a frame except that the joints are flexible,
  and that the frame shall be so stiff as not sensibly to alter in form
  under the load. Frames used as bridge trusses should never be designed so
  that the elongation or compression of one member can elongate or compress
  any other member. An example will serve to make the meaning of this
  limitation clearer. Let a frame consist of the five members AB, BD, DC,
  CA, CB (fig. 57), jointed at the points A, B, C and D, and all capable of
  resisting tension and compression. This frame will be <i>rigid</i>, i.e.
  it cannot be distorted without causing an alteration in the length of one
  or more of the members; but if from a change of temperature or any other
  cause one or all of the members change their length, this will not
  produce a stress on any member, but will merely cause a change in the
  form of the frame. Such a frame as this cannot be <i>self-strained</i>. A
  workman, for instance, cannot produce a stress on one member by making
  some other member of a wrong length. Any error of this kind will merely
  affect the form of the frame; if, however, another member be introduced
  between A and D, then if BC be shortened AD will be strained so as to
  extend it, and the four other members will be compressed; if CB is
  lengthened AD will thereby be compressed, and the four other members
  extended; if the workman does not make CB and AD of exactly the right
  length they and all the members will be permanently strained. These
  stresses will be unknown quantities, which the designer cannot take into
  account, and such a combination should if possible be avoided. A frame of
  this second type is said to have one <i>redundant member</i>.</p>
         <p>32. <i>Types of Braced Girder Bridges.</i>—Figs. 58, 59 and 60
  show an independent girder, a cantilever, and a cantilever and suspended
  girder bridge.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 59.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_59.png">
               <alt>Fig. 59.--Cantilever girder bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 58.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_58.png">
               <alt>Fig. 58.--Independent girder bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="br"/>
         </p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 60.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_60.png">
               <alt>Fig. 60.--Cantilever and suspended girder bridge.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>In a three-span bridge continuous girders are lighter than
  discontinuous ones by about 45% for the dead load and 15% for the live
  load, if no allowance is made for ambiguity due to uncertainty as to the
  level of the supports. The cantilever and suspended girder types are as
  economical and free from uncertainty as to the stresses. In long-span
  bridges the cantilever system permits erection by building out, which is
  economical and sometimes necessary. It is, however, unstable unless
  rigidly fixed at the piers. In the Forth bridge stability is obtained
  partly by the great excess of dead over live load, partly by the great
  width of the river piers. The majority of bridges not of great span have
  girders with parallel booms. This involves the fewest difficulties of
  workmanship and perhaps permits the closest approximation of actual to
  theoretical dimensions of the parts. In spans over 200 ft. it is
  economical to have one horizontal boom and one polygonal (approximately
  parabolic) boom. The hog-backed girder is a compromise between the two
  types, avoiding some difficulties of construction near the ends of the
  girder.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 61.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_61.png">
               <alt>Fig. 61.--Trusses.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="br"/>
         </p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 62.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_62.png">
               <alt>Fig. 62.--Queen-post trusses in the upright position.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Most braced girders may be considered as built up of two simple forms
  of truss, the king-post truss (fig. 61, <i>a</i>), or the queen-post
  truss (fig. 61, <i>b</i>). These may be used in either the upright or the
  inverted position. A <i>multiple truss</i> consists of a number of simple
  trusses, e.g. Bollman truss. Some timber bridges consist of queen-post
  trusses in the upright position, as shown diagrammatically in fig. 62,
  where the circles indicate points at which the flooring girders transmit
  load to the main girders. <i>Compound</i> trusses consist of simple
  trusses used as primary, secondary and tertiary trusses, the secondary
  supported on the primary, and the tertiary on the secondary. Thus, the
  Fink truss consists of king-post trusses; the Pratt truss (fig. 63) and
  the Whipple truss (fig. 64) of queen-post trusses alternately upright and
  inverted.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 64.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_64.png">
               <alt>Fig. 64.--Whipple truss.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 63.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_63.png">
               <alt>Fig. 63.--Pratt truss.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="br"/>
         </p>
         <p>A combination bridge is built partly of timber, partly of steel, the
  compression members being generally of timber and the tension members of
  steel. On the Pacific coast, where excellent timber is obtainable and
  steel works are distant, combination bridges are still largely used
  (Ottewell, <i>Trans. Am. Soc. C.E.</i> xxvii. p. 467). The combination
  bridge at Roseburgh, Oregon, is a cantilever bridge, <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page555">[v.04 p.0555]</ph>The
  shore arms are 147 ft. span, the river arms 105 ft., and the suspended
  girder 80 ft., the total distance between anchor piers being 584 ft. The
  floor beams, floor and railing are of timber. The compression members are
  of timber, except the struts and bottom chord panels next the river
  piers, which are of steel. The tension members are of iron and the pins
  of steel. The chord blocks and post shoes are of cast-iron.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 65.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_65.png">
               <alt>Fig. 65.--Warren girder.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>33. <i>Graphic Method of finding the Stresses in Braced
  Structures.</i>—Fig. 65 shows a common form of bridge truss known
  as a <i>Warren girder</i>, with lines indicating external forces applied
  to the joints; half the load carried between the two lower joints next
  the piers on either side is directly carried by the abutments. The sum of
  the two upward vertical reactions must clearly be equal to the sum of the
  loads. The lines in the diagram represent the directions of a series of
  forces which must all be in equilibrium; these lines may, for an object
  to be explained in the next paragraph, be conveniently named by the
  letters in the spaces which they separate instead of by the method
  usually employed in geometry. Thus we shall call the first inclined line
  on the left hand the line AG, the line representing the first force on
  the top left-hand joint AB, the first horizontal member at the top left
  hand the line BH, &amp;c; similarly each point requires at least three
  letters to denote it; the top first left-hand joint may be called ABHG,
  being the point where these four spaces meet. In this method of
  lettering, every enclosed space must be designated by a letter; all
  external forces must be represented by lines <i>outside</i> the frame,
  and each space between any two forces must receive a distinctive letter;
  this method of lettering was first proposed by O. Henrici and R. H. Bow
  (<i>Economics of Construction</i>), and is convenient in applying the
  theory of reciprocal figures to the computation of stresses on
  frames.</p>
         <p>34. <i>Reciprocal Figures.</i>—J. Clerk Maxwell gave (<i>Phil.
  Mag. 1864</i>) the following definition of reciprocal figures:—"Two
  plane figures are reciprocal when they consist of an equal number of
  lines so that corresponding lines in the two figures are parallel, and
  corresponding lines which converge to a point in one figure form a closed
  polygon in the other."</p>
         <p>Let a frame (without redundant members), and the external forces which
  keep it in equilibrium, be represented by a diagram constituting one of
  these two plane figures, then the lines in the other plane figure or the
  reciprocal will represent in direction and magnitude the forces between
  the joints of the frame, and, consequently, the stress on each member, as
  will now be explained.</p>
         <p>Reciprocal figures are easily drawn by following definite rules, and
  afford therefore a simple method of computing the stresses on members of
  a frame.</p>
         <p>The external forces on a frame or bridge in equilibrium under those
  forces may, by a well-known proposition in statics, be represented by a
  closed polygon, each side of which is parallel to one force, and
  represents the force in magnitude as well as in direction. The sides of
  the polygon may be arranged in any order, provided care is taken so to
  draw them that in passing round the polygon in one direction this
  direction may for each side correspond to the direction of the force
  which it represents.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 66.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_66.png">
               <alt>Fig. 66.--Frame supported at the two end joints.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>This polygon of forces may, by a slight extension of the above
  definition, be called the <i>reciprocal figure</i> of the external
  forces, if the sides are arranged in the same order as that of the joints
  on which they act, so that if the joints and forces be numbered 1, 2, 3,
  4, &amp;c., passing round the outside of the frame in one direction, and
  returning at last to joint 1, then in the polygon the side representing
  the force 2 will be next the side representing the force 1, and will be
  followed by the side representing the force 3, and so forth. This polygon
  falls under the definition of a reciprocal figure given by Clerk Maxwell,
  if we consider the frame as a point in equilibrium under the external
  forces.</p>
         <p>Fig. 66 shows a frame supported at the two end joints, and loaded at
  each top joint. The loads and the supporting forces are indicated by
  arrows. Fig. 67a shows the reciprocal figure or polygon for the external
  forces on the assumption that the reactions are slightly inclined. The
  lines in fig. 67 <i>a</i>, lettered in the usual manner, correspond to
  the forces indicated by arrows in fig. 66, and lettered according to
  Bow's method. When all the forces are vertical, as will be the case in
  girders, the polygon of external forces will be reduced to two straight
  lines, fig. 67 <i>b</i>, superimposed and divided so that the length AX
  represents the load AX, the length AB the load AB, the length YX the
  reaction YX, and so forth. The line XZ consists of a series of lengths,
  as XA, AB ... DZ, representing the loads taken in their order. In
  subsequent diagrams the two reaction lines will, for the sake of
  clearness, be drawn as if slightly inclined to the vertical.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 67.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_67.png">
               <alt>Fig. 67.--Reciprocal figure or polygon.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>If there are no redundant members in the frame there will be only two
  members abutting at the point of support, for these two members will be
  sufficient to balance the reaction, whatever its direction may be; we can
  therefore draw two triangles, each having as one side the reaction YX,
  and having the two other sides parallel to these two members; each of
  these triangles will represent a polygon of forces in equilibrium at the
  point of support. Of these two triangles, shown in fig. 67 <i>c</i>,
  select that in which the letters X and Y are so placed that (naming the
  apex of the triangle E) the lines XE and YE are the lines parallel to the
  two members of the same name in the frame (fig. 66). Then the triangle
  YXE is the reciprocal figure of the three lines YX, XE, EY in the frame,
  and represents the three forces in equilibrium at the point YXE of the
  frame. The direction of YX, being a thrust upwards, shows the direction
  in which we must go round the triangle YXE to find the direction of the
  two other forces; doing this we find that the force XE must act down
  towards the point YXE, and the force EY away from the same point. Putting
  arrows on the frame diagram to indicate the direction of the forces, we
  see that the member EY must pull and therefore act as a tie, and that the
  member XE must push and act as a strut. Passing to the point XEFA we find
  two known forces, the load XA acting downwards, and a push from the strut
  XE, which, being in compression, must push at both ends, as indicated by
  the arrow, fig. 66. The directions and magnitudes of these two forces are
  already drawn (fig. 67 <i>a</i>) in a fitting position to represent part
  of the polygon of forces at XEFA; beginning with the upward thrust EX,
  continuing down XA, and drawing AF parallel to AF in the frame we
  complete the polygon by drawing EF parallel to EF in the frame. The point
  F is determined by the intersection of the two lines, one beginning at A,
  and the other at E. We then have the polygon of forces EXAF, the
  reciprocal figure of the lines meeting at that point in the frame, and
  representing the forces at the point EXAF; the direction of the forces on
  EH and XA being known determines the direction of the forces due to the
  elastic reaction of the members AF and EF, showing AF to push as a strut,
  while EF is a tie. We have been guided in the selection of the particular
  quadrilateral adopted by the rule of arranging the order of the sides so
  that the same letters indicate corresponding sides in the diagram of the
  frame and its reciprocal. Continuing the construction of the diagram in
  the same way, we arrive at fig. 67 <i>d</i> as the complete reciprocal
  figure of the frame and forces upon it, and we see that each line in the
  reciprocal figure measures the stress on the corresponding member in the
  frame, and that the polygon of forces acting at any point, as IJKY, in
  the frame is represented by a polygon of the same name in the reciprocal
  <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page556">[v.04
  p.0556]</ph>figure. The direction of the force in each member is easily
  ascertained by proceeding in the manner above described. A single known
  force in a polygon determines the direction of all the others, as these
  must all correspond with arrows pointing the same way round the polygon.
  Let the arrows be placed on the frame round each joint, and so as to
  indicate the direction of each force on that joint; then when two arrows
  point to one another on the same piece, that piece is a tie; when they
  point from one another the piece is a strut. It is hardly necessary to
  say that the forces exerted by the two ends of any one member must be
  equal and opposite. This method is universally applicable where there are
  no redundant members. The reciprocal figure for any loaded frame is a
  complete formula for the stress on every member of a frame of that
  particular class with loads on given joints.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 68
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_68.png">
               <alt>Fig. 68.--Warren girder.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 69
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_69.png">
               <alt>Fig. 69.--Reciprocal figures for Warren girder.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Consider a Warren girder (fig. 68), loaded at the top and bottom
  joints. Fig. 69 <i>b</i> is the polygon of external forces, and 69
  <i>c</i> is half the reciprocal figure. The complete reciprocal figure is
  shown in fig. 69 <i>a</i>.</p>
         <p>The method of sections already described is often more convenient than
  the method of reciprocal figures, and the method of influence lines is
  also often the readiest way of dealing with braced girders.</p>
         <p>35. <i>Chain Loaded uniformly along a Horizontal Line.</i>—If
  the lengths of the links be assumed indefinitely short, the chain under
  given simple distributions of load will take the form of comparatively
  simple mathematical curves known as catenaries. The true catenary is that
  assumed by a chain of uniform weight per unit of length, but the form
  generally adopted for suspension bridges is that assumed by a chain under
  a weight uniformly distributed relatively to a horizontal line. This
  curve is a parabola.</p>
         <p>Remembering that in this case the centre bending moment ∑<i>wl</i>
  will be equal to <i>w</i>L²/8, we see that the horizontal tension H at
  the vertex for a span L (the points of support being at equal heights) is
  given by the expression</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      1 . . . H = <i>w</i>L²/8<i>y</i>,

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>or, calling x the distance from the vertex to the point of
  support,</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      H = <i>wx</i>²/2<i>y</i>,

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>The value of H is equal to the maximum tension on the bottom flange,
  or compression on the top flange, of a girder of equal span, equally and
  similarly loaded, and having a depth equal to the dip of the suspension
  bridge.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 70.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_70.png">
               <alt>Fig. 70.--Chain Loaded uniformly along a Horizontal Line.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Consider any other point F of the curve, fig. 70, at a distance
  <i>x</i> from the vertex, the horizontal component of the resultant
  (tangent to the curve) will be unaltered; the vertical component V will
  be simply the sum of the loads between O and F, or <i>wx</i>. In the
  triangle FDC, let FD be tangent to the curve, FC vertical, and DC
  horizontal; these three sides will necessarily be proportional
  respectively to the resultant tension along the chain at F, the vertical
  force V passing through the point D, and the horizontal tension at O;
  hence</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      H : V = DC : FC = <i>wx</i>²/2<i>y</i> : <i>wx</i> = <i>x</i>/2 : <i>y</i>,

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>hence DC is the half of OC, proving the curve to be a parabola.</p>
         <p>The value of R, the tension at any point at a distance x from the
  vertex, is obtained from the equation</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      R² = H²+V² = <i>w</i>²<i>x</i>
               <sup>4</sup>/4<i>y</i>²+<i>w</i>²<i>x</i>²,

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>or,</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      2 . . . R = <i>wx</i>√(1+<i>x</i>²/4<i>y</i>²).

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>Let <i>i</i> be the angle between the tangent at any point having the
  co-ordinates <i>x</i> and <i>y</i> measured from the vertex, then</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      3 . . . tan <i>i</i> = 2<i>y</i>/<i>x</i>.

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>Let the length of half the parabolic chain be called <i>s</i>,
  then</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      4 . . . <i>s</i> = <i>x</i>+2<i>y</i>²/3<i>x</i>.

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>The following is the approximate expression for the relation between a
  change ∆s in the length of the half chain and the corresponding
  change ∆y in the dip:—</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
               <i>s</i>+∆<i>s</i> = <i>x</i>+(2/3<i>x</i>) {<i>y</i>²+2<i>y</i>
               <ph outputclass="grk">Δ</ph>
               <i>y</i>+(∆<i>y</i>)²} = <i>x</i>+2<i>y</i>²/3<i>x</i>+4<i>y</i>
               <ph outputclass="grk">Δ</ph>
               <i>y</i>/3<i>x</i>+2∆<i>y</i>²/3<i>x</i>,

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>or, neglecting the last term,</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      5 . . . ∆<i>s</i> = 4<i>y</i>∆<i>y</i>/3<i>x</i>,

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>and</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      6 . . . ∆<i>y</i> = 3<i>x</i>∆<i>s</i>/4<i>y</i>.

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>From these equations the deflection produced by any given stress on
  the chains or by a change of temperature can be calculated.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 71.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_71.png">
               <alt>Fig. 71.--Beam bent by external loads.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>36. <i>Deflection of Girders.</i>— Let fig. 71 represent a beam
  bent by external loads. Let the origin O be taken at the lowest point of
  the bent beam. Then the deviation y = DE of the neutral axis of the bent
  beam at any point D from the axis OX is given by the relation</p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <i>d²y</i>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <i>dx</i>²</entry>
                     <entry>=</entry>
                     <entry>M<ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>EI</entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>where M is the bending moment and I the amount of inertia of the beam
  at D, and E is the coefficient of elasticity. It is usually accurate
  enough in deflection calculations to take for I the moment of inertia at
  the centre of the beam and to consider it constant for the length of the
  beam. Then</p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <i>dy</i>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <i>dx</i>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>=</entry>
                     <entry>1<ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>EI</entry>
                     <entry>∫M<i>dx</i>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <i>y</i> =</entry>
                     <entry>1<ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>EI</entry>
                     <entry>∫∫M<i>dx</i>².</entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>The integration can be performed when M is expressed in terms of
  <i>x</i>. Thus for a beam supported at the ends and loaded with <i>w</i>
  per inch length M = <i>w</i>(<i>a</i>²-<i>x</i>²), where <i>a</i> is the
  half span. Then the deflection at the centre is the value of <i>y</i> for
  <i>x</i> = <i>a</i>, and is</p>
         <table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
               <colspec colname="col1"/>
               <colspec colname="col2"/>
               <colspec colname="col3"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <ph outputclass="grk">δ</ph> =</entry>
                     <entry>5<ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>24</entry>
                     <entry>
                        <i>wa</i>
                        <sup>4</sup>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>
                        <image href="images/$line.png">
                           <alt>/</alt>
                        </image>
                        <ph outputclass="br"/>EI</entry>
                     <entry>.</entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p>The radius of curvature of the beam at D is given by the relation</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      R = EI/M.

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 72.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/bridges_72.png">
               <alt>Fig. 72.--Graphic Method of finding Deflection</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>37. <i>Graphic Method of finding Deflection.</i>—Divide the span
  L into any convenient number <i>n</i> of equal parts of length <i>l</i>,
  so that <i>nl</i> = L; compute the radii of curvature R<sub>1</sub>,
  R<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>3</sub> for the several sections. Let measurements
  along the beam be represented according to any convenient scale, so that
  calling L<sub>1</sub> and <i>l</i>
            <sub>1</sub> the lengths to be drawn on
  paper, we have L = <i>a</i>L<sub>1</sub>; now let <i>r</i>
            <sub>1</sub>,
  <i>r</i>
            <sub>2</sub>, <i>r</i>
            <sub>3</sub> be a series of radii such that
  <i>r</i>
            <sub>1</sub> = R<sub>1</sub>/<i>ab</i>, <i>r</i>
            <sub>2</sub> =
  R<sub>2</sub>/<i>ab</i>, &amp;c., where <i>b</i> is any convenient
  constant chosen of such magnitude as will allow arcs with the radii,
  <i>r</i>
            <sub>1</sub>, <i>r</i>
            <sub>2</sub>, &amp;c., to be drawn with the
  means at the draughtsman's disposal. Draw a curve <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page557">[v.04 p.0557]</ph>as shown in
  fig. 72 with arcs of the length <i>l</i>
            <sub>1</sub>,
  <i>l</i>
            <sub>2</sub>, <i>l</i>
            <sub>3</sub>, &amp;c., and with the radii
  <i>r</i>
            <sub>1</sub>, <i>r</i>
            <sub>2</sub>, &amp;c. (note, for a length
  ½<i>l</i>
            <sub>1</sub> at each end the radius will be infinite, and the
  curve must end with a straight line tangent to the last arc), then let
  <i>v</i> be the measured deflection of this curve from the straight line,
  and V the actual deflection of the bridge; we have V =
  <i>av</i>/<i>b</i>, approximately. This method distorts the curve, so
  that vertical ordinates of the curve are drawn to a scale <i>b</i> times
  greater than that of the horizontal ordinates. Thus if the horizontal
  scale be one-tenth of an inch to the foot, <i>a</i> = 120, and a beam 100
  ft. in length would be drawn equal to 10 in.; then if the true radius at
  the centre were 10,000 ft., this radius, if the curve were undistorted,
  would be on paper 1000 in., but making <i>b</i> = 50 we can draw the
  curve with a radius of 20 in. The vertical distortion of the curve must
  not be so great that there is a very sensible difference between the
  length of the arc and its chord. This can be regulated by altering the
  value of <i>b</i>. In fig. 72 distortion is carried too far; this figure
  is merely used as an illustration.</p>
         <p>38. <i>Camber.</i>—In order that a girder may become straight
  under its working load it should be constructed with a camber or upward
  convexity equal to the calculated deflection. Owing to the yielding of
  joints when a beam is first loaded a smaller modulus of elasticity should
  be taken than for a solid bar. For riveted girders E is about 17,500,000
  lb per sq. in. for first loading. W.J.M. Rankine gives the approximate
  rule</p>
         <fig outputclass="poem">
            <lines>
      Working deflection = <ph outputclass="grk">δ</ph> = <i>l</i>²/10,000<i>h</i>,

    </lines>
         </fig>
         <p>where <i>l</i> is the span and <i>h</i> the depth of the beam, the
  stresses being those usual in bridgework, due to the total dead and live
  load.</p>
         <p>(W. C. U.)</p>
         <p outputclass="fn-holder">
            <fn id="Footnote_061"> For the ancient
  bridges in Rome see further <ph outputclass="sc">Rome</ph>:
  <i>Archaeology</i>, and such works as R. Lanciani, <i>Ruins and
  Excavations of Ancient Rome</i> (Eng. trans., 1897), pp. 16 foll.</fn>

         </p>
      </section>
   </body>
</topic>