<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e20870">
   <title>BROMINE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROMINE--> (symbol Br, atomic weight 79.96), a chemical element of
  the halogen group, which takes its name from its pungent unpleasant smell
  (<ph outputclass="grk">βρῶμος</ph>, a stench). It was first
  isolated by A.J. Balard in 1826 from the salts in the waters of the
  Mediterranean. He established its elementary character, and his
  researches were amplified by K.J. Löwig (1803-1890) in <i>Das Brom und
  seine chemischen Verhaltnisse</i> (1829). Bromine does not occur in
  nature in the uncombined condition, but in combination with various
  metals is very widely but sparingly distributed. Potassium, sodium and
  magnesium bromides are found in mineral waters, in river and sea-water,
  and occasionally in marine plants and animals. Its chief commercial
  sources are the salt deposits at Stassfurt in Prussian Saxony, in which
  magnesium bromide is found associated with various chlorides, and the
  brines of Michigan, Ohio, Pennsylvania and West Virginia, U.S.A.; small
  quantities are obtained from the mother liquors of Chile saltpetre and
  kelp. In combination with silver it is found as the mineral bromargyrite
  (bromite).</p>
      <p>
         <i>Manufacture.</i>—The chief centres of the bromine industry
  are Stassfurt and the central district of Michigan. It is manufactured
  from the magnesium bromide contained in "bittern" (the mother liquor of
  the salt industry), by two processes, the continuous and the periodic.
  The continuous process depends upon the decomposition of the bromide by
  chlorine, which is generated in special stills. A regular current of
  chlorine mixed with steam is led in at the bottom of a tall tower filled
  with broken bricks, and there meets a descending stream of hot bittern:
  bromine is liberated and is swept out of the tower together with some
  chlorine, by the current of steam, and then condensed in a worm. Any
  uncondensed bromine vapour is absorbed by moist iron borings, and the
  resulting iron bromide is used for the manufacture of potassium bromide.
  The periodic process depends on the interaction between manganese dioxide
  (pyrolusite), sulphuric acid, and a bromide, and the operation is carried
  out in sandstone stills heated to 60° C., the product being condensed as
  in the continuous process. The substitution of potassium chlorate for
  pyrolusite is recommended when calcium chloride is present in the
  bittern. The crude bromine is purified by repeated shaking with
  potassium, sodium or ferrous bromide and subsequent redistillation.
  Commercial bromine is rarely pure, the chief impurities present in it
  being chlorine, hydrobromic acid, and bromoform (M. Hermann,
  <i>Annalen</i>, 1855, 95, p. 211). E. Gessner (<i>Berichte</i>, 1876, 9,
  p. 1507) removes chlorine by repeated shaking with water, followed by
  distillation over sulphuric acid; hydrobromic acid is removed by
  distillation with pure manganese dioxide, or mercuric oxide, and the
  product dried over sulphuric acid. J.S. Stas, in his stoichiometric
  researches, prepared chemically pure bromine from potassium bromide, by
  converting it into the bromate which was purified by repeated
  crystallization. By heating the bromate it was partially converted into
  the bromide, and the resulting mixture was distilled with sulphuric acid.
  The distillate was further purified by digestion with milk of lime,
  precipitation with water, and further digestion with calcium bromide and
  barium oxide, and was finally redistilled.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Characters.</i>—Bromine at ordinary temperatures is a mobile
  liquid of fine red colour, which appears almost black in thick layers. It
  boils at 59° C. According to Sir W. Ramsay and S. Young, bromine, when
  dried over sulphuric acid, boils at 57.65° C., and when dried over
  phosphorus pentoxide, boils at 58.85° C. (under a pressure of 755.8 mm.),
  forming a deep red vapour, which exerts an irritating and directly
  poisonous action on the respiratory organs. It solidifies at -21° C.
  (Quincke) to a dark brown solid. Its specific gravity is 3.18828 (0/4°),
  latent heat of fusion 16.185 calories, latent heat of vaporization 45.6
  calories, specific heat 0.1071. The specific heat of bromine vapour, at
  constant pressure, is 0.05504 and at constant volume is 0.04251 (K.
  Strecker). Bromine is soluble in water, to the extent of 3.226 grammes of
  bromine per 100 grammes of solution at 15° C., the solubility being
  slightly increased by the presence of potassium bromide. The solution is
  of an orange-red colour, and is quite permanent in the dark, but on
  exposure to light, gradually becomes colourless, owing to decomposition
  into hydrobromic acid and oxygen. By cooling the aqueous solution,
  hyacinth-red octahedra of a crystalline hydrate of composition
  Br·4H<sub>2</sub>O or Br<sub>2</sub>·8H<sub>2</sub>O are obtained
  (Bakhuis Roozeboom, <i>Zeits. phys. Chem.</i>, 1888, 2. p. 449). Bromine
  is readily soluble in chloroform, alcohol and ether.</p>
      <p>Its chemical properties are in general intermediate between those of
  chlorine and iodine; thus it requires the presence of a catalytic agent,
  or a fairly high temperature, to bring about its union with hydrogen. It
  does not combine directly with oxygen, nitrogen or carbon. With the other
  elements it unites to form bromides, often with explosive violence;
  phosphorus detonates in liquid bromine and inflames in the vapour; iron
  is occasionally used to absorb bromine vapour, potassium reacts
  energetically, but sodium requires to be heated to 200° C. The chief use
  of bromine in analytical chemistry is based upon the oxidizing action of
  bromine water. Bromine and bromine water both bleach organic colouring
  matters. <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page633">[v.04 p.0633]</ph>The use of bromine in the
  extraction of gold (<i>q.v.</i>) was proposed by R. Wagner (<i>Dingler's
  Journal</i>, 218, p. 253) and others, but its cost has restricted its
  general application. Bromine is used extensively in organic chemistry as
  a substituting and oxidizing agent and also for the preparation of
  addition compounds. Reactions in which it is used in the liquid form, in
  vapour, in solution, and in the presence of the so-called "bromine
  carriers," have been studied. Sunlight affects the action of bromine
  vapour on organic compounds in various ways, sometimes retarding or
  accelerating the reaction, while in some cases the products are different
  (J. Schramm, <i>Monatshefte fur Chemie</i>, 1887, 8, p. 101). Some
  reactions, which are only possible by the aid of nascent bromine, are
  carried out by using solutions of sodium bromide and bromate, with the
  amount of sulphuric acid calculated according to the equation 5NaBr +
  NaBrO<sub>3</sub> + 6H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> = 6NaHSO<sub>4</sub> +
  3H<sub>2</sub>O + 6Br. (German Patent, 26642.) The diluents in which
  bromine is employed are usually ether, chloroform, acetic acid,
  hydrochloric acid, carbon bisulphide and water, and, less commonly,
  alcohol, potassium bromide and hydrobromic acid; the excess of bromine
  being removed by heating, by sulphurous acid or by shaking with mercury.
  The choice of solvent is important, for the velocity of the reaction and
  the nature of the product may vary according to the solvent used, thus A.
  Baeyer and F. Blom found that on brominating orthoacetamido-acetophenone
  in presence of water or acetic acid, the bromine goes into the benzene
  nucleus, whilst in chloroform or sulphuric acid or by use of bromine
  vapour it goes into the side chain as well. The action of bromine is
  sometimes accelerated by the use of compounds which behave catalytically,
  the more important of these substances being iodine, iron, ferric
  chloride, ferric bromide, aluminium bromide and phosphorus. For oxidizing
  purposes bromine is generally employed in aqueous and in alkaline
  solutions, one of its most important applications being by Emil Fischer
  (<i>Berichte</i>, 1889, 22, p. 362) in his researches on the sugars. The
  atomic weight of bromine has been determined by J.S. Stas and C. Marignac
  from the analysis of potassium bromide, and of silver bromide. G.P.
  Baxter (<i>Zeit. anorg. Chem.</i> 1906, 50, p. 389) determined the ratios
  Ag: AgBr, and AgCl: Ag Br.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Hydrobromic Acid.</i>—This acid, HBr, the only compound of
  hydrogen and bromine, is in many respects similar to hydrochloric acid,
  but is rather less stable. It may be prepared by passing hydrogen gas and
  bromine vapour through a tube containing a heated platinum spiral. It
  cannot be prepared with any degree of purity by the action of
  concentrated sulphuric acid on bromides, since secondary reactions take
  place, leading to the liberation of free bromine and formation of sulphur
  dioxide. The usual method employed for the preparation of the gas
  consists in dropping bromine on to a mixture of amorphous phosphorus and
  water, when a violent reaction takes place and the gas is rapidly
  liberated. It can be obtained also, although in a somewhat impure
  condition, by the direct action of bromine on various saturated
  hydrocarbons (e.g. paraffin-wax), while an aqueous solution may be
  obtained by passing sulphuretted hydrogen through bromine water.
  Alexander Scott (<i>Journal of Chem. Soc.</i>, 1900, 77, p. 648) prepares
  pure hydrobromic acid by covering bromine, which is contained in a large
  flask, with a layer of water, and passing sulphur dioxide into the water
  above the surface of the bromine, until the whole is of a pale yellow
  colour; the resulting solution is then distilled in a slow current of air
  and finally purified by distillation over barium bromide. At ordinary
  temperatures hydrobromic acid is a colourless gas which fumes strongly in
  moist air, and has an acid taste and reaction. It can be condensed to a
  liquid, which boils at -64.9° C. (under a pressure of 738.2 mm.), and, by
  still further cooling, gives colourless crystals which melt at -88.5° C.
  It is readily soluble in water, forming the aqueous acid, which when
  saturated at 0° C. has a specific gravity of 1.78. When boiled, the
  aqueous acid loses either acid or water until a solution of constant
  boiling point is obtained, containing 48% of the acid and boiling at 126°
  C. under atmospheric pressure; should the pressure, however, vary, the
  strength of the solution boiling at a constant temperature varies also.
  Hydrobromic acid is one of the "strong" acids, being ionized to a very
  large extent even in concentrated solution, as shown by the molecular
  conductivity increasing by only a small amount over a wide range of
  dilution.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Bromides.</i>—Hydrobromic acid reacts with metallic oxides,
  hydroxides and carbonates to form bromides, which can in many cases be
  obtained also by the direct union of the metals with bromine. As a class,
  the metallic bromides are solids at ordinary temperatures, which fuse
  readily and volatilize on heating. The majority are soluble in water, the
  chief exceptions being silver bromide, mercurous bromide, palladious
  bromide and lead bromide; the last is, however, soluble in hot water.
  They are decomposed by chlorine, with liberation of bromine and formation
  of metallic chlorides; concentrated sulphuric acid also decomposes them,
  with formation of a metallic sulphate and liberation of bromine and
  sulphur dioxide. The non-metallic bromides are usually liquids, which are
  readily decomposed by water. Hydrobromic acid and its salts can be
  readily detected by the addition of chlorine water to their aqueous
  solutions, when bromine is liberated; or by warming with concentrated
  sulphuric acid and manganese dioxide, the same result being obtained.
  Silver nitrate in the presence of nitric acid gives with bromides a pale
  yellow precipitate of silver bromide, AgBr, which is sparingly soluble in
  ammonia. For their quantitative determination they are precipitated in
  nitric acid solution by means of silver nitrate, and the silver bromide
  well washed, dried and weighed.</p>
      <p>No oxides of bromine have as yet been isolated, but three oxy-acids
  are known, namely hypobromous acid, HBrO, bromous acid, HBrO<sub>2</sub>,
  and bromic acid, HBrO<sub>3</sub>. Hypobromous acid is obtained by
  shaking together bromine water and precipitated mercuric oxide, followed
  by distillation of the dilute solution <i>in vacuo</i> at low temperature
  (about 40° C.). It is a very unstable compound, breaking up, on heating,
  into bromine and oxygen. The aqueous solution is light yellow in colour,
  and possesses strong bleaching properties. Bromous acid is formed by
  adding bromine to a saturated solution of silver nitrate (A. H. Richards,
  <i>J. Soc Chem. Ind.</i>, 1906, 25, p. 4). Bromic acid is obtained by the
  addition of the calculated amount of sulphuric acid (previously diluted
  with water) to the barium salt; by the action of bromine on the silver
  salt, in the presence of water, 5AgBrO<sub>3</sub> + 3Br<sub>2</sub> +
  3H<sub>2</sub>O = 5AgBr + 6HBrO<sub>3</sub>, or by passing chlorine
  through a solution of bromine in water. The acid is only known in the
  form of its aqueous solution; this is, however, very unstable,
  decomposing on being heated to 100° C. into water, oxygen and bromine. By
  reducing agents such, for example, as sulphuretted hydrogen and
  sulphur-dioxide, it is rapidly converted into hydrobromic acid.
  Hydrobromic acid decomposes it according to the equation HBrO<sub>3</sub>
  + 5HBr = 3H<sub>2</sub>O + 3Br<sub>2</sub>. Its salts are known as
  bromates, and are as a general rule difficultly soluble in water, and
  decomposed by heat, with evolution of oxygen.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Applications.</i>—The salts of bromine are widely used in
  photography, especially bromide of silver. For antiseptic purposes it has
  been prepared as "bromum solidificatum," which consists of kieselguhr or
  similar substance impregnated with about 75% of its weight of bromine. In
  medicine it is largely employed in the form of bromides of potassium,
  sodium and ammonium, as well as in combination with alkaloids and other
  substances.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Medicinal Use.</i>—Bromide of potassium is the safest and
  most generally applicable sedative of the nervous system. Whilst very
  weak, its action is perfectly balanced throughout all nervous tissue, so
  much so that Sir Thomas Lauder Brunton has suggested its action to be due
  to its replacement of sodium chloride (common salt) in the fluids of the
  nervous system. Hence bromide of potassium—or bromide of sodium,
  which is possibly somewhat safer still though not quite so certain in its
  action—is used as a hypnotic, as the standard anaphrodisiac, as a
  sedative in mania and all forms of morbid mental excitement, and in
  hyperaesthesia of all kinds. Its most striking success is in epilepsy,
  for which it is the specific remedy. It may be given in doses of from ten
  to fifty grains or more, and may be continued without ill effect for long
  periods in grave cases of epilepsy (<i>grand mal</i>). Of the three
  bromides in common use the potassium salt is the most rapid and certain
  in its action, but may depress the heart in morbid states of that organ;
  in such cases the sodium salt—of which the base is inert—may
  be employed. In whooping-cough, when a sedative is required but a
  stimulant is also indicated, ammonium bromide is often invaluable. The
  conditions in which bromides are most frequently used are insomnia,
  epilepsy, whooping-cough, delirium tremens, asthma, migraine, laryngismus
  stridulus, the symptoms often attendant upon the climacteric in women,
  hysteria, neuralgia, certain nervous disorders of the heart, strychnine
  poisoning, nymphomania and spermatorrhoea. Hydrobromic acid is often used
  to relieve or prevent the headache and singing in the ears that may
  follow the administration of quinine and of salicylic acid or
  salicylates.</p>
   </body>
</topic>