<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e118">
   <title>BRESLAU</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRESLAU--> (Polish <i>Wraclaw</i>), a city of Germany, capital of
  the Prussian province of Silesia, and an episcopal see, situated in a
  wide and fertile plain on both banks of the navigable Oder, 350 m. from
  its mouth, at the influx of the Ohle, and 202 m. from Berlin on the
  railway to Vienna. Pop. (1867) 171,926; (1880) 272,912; (1885) 299,640;
  (1890) 335,186; (1905) 470,751, about 60% being Protestants, 35% Roman
  Catholics and nearly 5% Jews. The Oder, which here breaks into several
  arms, divides the city into two unequal halves, crossed by numerous
  bridges. The larger portion, on the left bank, includes the old or inner
  town, surrounded by beautiful promenades, on the site of the ramparts,
  dismantled after 1813, from an eminence within which, the Liebichs Höhe,
  a fine view is obtained of the surrounding country. Outside, as well as
  across the Oder, lies the new town with extensive suburbs, containing,
  especially in the Schweidnitz quarter in the south, and the Oder quarter
  in the north, many handsome streets and spacious squares. The inner town,
  in contrast to the suburbs, still retains with its narrow streets much of
  its ancient characters, and contains several medieval buildings, both
  religious and secular, of great beauty and interest. The cathedral,
  dedicated to St John the Baptist, was begun in 1148 and completed at the
  close of the 15th century, enlarged in the 17th and 18th centuries, and
  restored between 1873 and 1875; it is rich in notable treasures,
  especially the high altar of beaten silver, and in beautiful paintings
  and sculptures. The Kreuzkirche (church of the Holy Cross), dating from
  the 13th and 14th centuries, is an interesting brick building, remarkable
  for its stained glass and its historical monuments, among which is the
  tomb of Henry IV., duke of Silesia. The Sandkirche, so called from its
  dedication to Our Lady on the Sand, dates from the 14th century, and was
  until 1810 the church of the Augustinian canons. The Dorotheenor
  Minoritenkirche, remarkable for its high-pitched roof, was founded by the
  emperor Charles IV. in 1351. These are the most notable of the Roman
  Catholic churches. Of the Evangelical churches the most important is that
  of St Elizabeth, founded about 1250, rebuilt in the 14th and 15th
  centuries, and restored in 1857. Its lofty tower contains the largest
  bell in Silesia, and the church possesses a celebrated organ, fine
  stained glass, a magnificent stone pyx (erected in 1455) over 52 ft.
  high, and portraits of Luther and Melanchthon by Lucas Cranach. The
  church of St Mary Magdalen, built in the 14th century on the model of the
  cathedral, has two lofty Gothic towers connected by a bridge, and is
  interesting as having been the church in which, in 1523, the reformation
  in Silesia was first proclaimed. Other noteworthy ecclesiastical
  buildings are the graceful Gothic church of St Michael built in 1871, the
  bishop's palace and the Jewish synagogue, the finest in Germany after
  that in Berlin.</p>
      <p>The business streets of the city converge upon the Ring, the market
  square, in which is the town-hall, a fine Gothic building, begun in the
  middle of the 14th and completed in the 16th century. Within is the
  Fürstensaal, in which the diets of Silesia were formerly held, while
  beneath is the famous Schweidnitzer Keller, used continuously since 1355
  as a beer and wine house. <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page499">[v.04 p.0499]</ph>The university, a spacious Gothic
  building facing the Oder, is a striking edifice. It was built (1728-1736)
  as a college by the Jesuits, on the site of the former imperial castle
  presented to them by the emperor Leopold I., and contains a magnificent
  hall (Aula Leopoldina), richly ornamented with frescoes and capable of
  holding 1200 persons. Breslau possesses a large number of other important
  public buildings: the Stadthaus (civic hall), the royal palace, the
  government offices (a handsome pile erected in 1887), the provincial
  House of Assembly, the municipal archives, the courts of law, the
  Silesian museum of arts and crafts and antiquities, stored in the former
  assembly hall of the estates (Ständehaus), which was rebuilt for the
  purpose, the museum of fine arts, the exchange, the Stadt and Lobe
  theatres, the post office and central railway station. There are also
  numerous hospitals and schools. Breslau is exceedingly rich in fine
  monuments; the most noteworthy being the equestrian statues of Frederick
  the Great and Frederick William III., both by Kiss; the statue of Blücher
  by Rauch; a marble statue of General Tauentzien by Langhans and Schadow;
  a bronze statue of Karl Gottlieb Svarez (1746-1798), the Prussian jurist,
  a monument to Schleiermacher, born here in 1768, and statues of the
  emperor William I., Bismarck and Moltke. There are also several handsome
  fountains. Foremost among the educational establishments stands the
  university, founded in 1702 by the emperor Leopold I. as a Jesuit
  college, and greatly extended by the incorporation of the university of
  Frankfort-on-Oder in 1811. Its library contains 306,000 volumes and 4000
  MSS., and has in the so-called <i>Bibliotheca Habichtiana</i> a valuable
  collection of oriental literature. Among its auxiliary establishments are
  botanical gardens, an observatory, and anatomical, physiological and
  kindred institutions. There are eight classical and four modern schools,
  two higher girls' schools, a Roman Catholic normal school, a Jewish
  theological seminary, a school of arts and crafts, and numerous literary
  and charitable foundations. It is, however, as a commercial and
  industrial city that Breslau is most widely known. Its situation, close
  to the extensive coal and iron fields of Upper Silesia, in proximity to
  the Austrian and Russian frontiers, at the centre of a network of
  railways directly communicating both with these countries and with the
  chief towns of northern and central Germany, and on a deep waterway
  connecting with the Elbe and the Vistula, facilitates its very
  considerable transit and export trade in the products of the province and
  of the neighbouring countries. These embrace coal, sugar, cereals,
  spirits, petroleum and timber. The local industries comprise machinery
  and tools, railway and tramway carriages, furniture, cast-iron goods,
  gold and silver work, carpets, furs, cloth and cottons, paper, musical
  instruments, glass and china. Breslau is the headquarters of the VI.
  German army corps and contains a large garrison of troops of all
  arms.</p>
      <p>
         <i>History.</i>—Breslau (Lat. <i>Vratislavia</i>) is first
  mentioned by the chronicler Thietmar, bishop of Merseburg, in <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 1000, and was probably founded some years before
  this date. Early in the 11th century it was made the seat of a bishop,
  and after having formed part of Poland, became the capital of an
  independent duchy in 1163. Destroyed by the Mongols in 1241, it soon
  recovered its former prosperity and received a large influx of German
  colonists. The bishop obtained the title of a prince of the Empire in
  1290.<xref href="#d1e118/Footnote_011" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> When
  Henry VI., the last duke of Breslau, died in 1335, the city came by
  purchase to John, king of Bohemia, whose successors retained it until
  about 1460. The Bohemian kings bestowed various privileges on Breslau,
  which soon began to extend its commerce in all directions, while owing to
  increasing wealth the citizens took up a more independent attitude.
  Disliking the Hussites, Breslau placed itself under the protection of
  Pope Pius II. in 1463, and a few years afterwards came under the rule of
  the Hungarian king, Matthias Corvinus. After his death in 1490 it again
  became subject to Bohemia, passing with the rest of Silesia to the
  Habsburgs when in 1526 Ferdinand, afterwards emperor, was chosen king of
  Bohemia. Having passed almost undisturbed through the periods of the
  Reformation and the Thirty Years' War, Breslau was compelled to own the
  authority of Frederick the Great in 1741. It was, however, <ph outputclass="correction">recovered</ph> by the
  Austrians in 1757, but was regained by Frederick after his victory at
  Leuthen in the same year, and has since belonged to Prussia, although it
  was held for a few days by the French in 1807 after the battle of Jena,
  and again in 1813 after the battle of Bautzen. The sites of the
  fortifications, dismantled by the French in 1807, were given to the civic
  authorities by King Frederick William III., and converted into
  promenades. In March 1813 this monarch issued from Breslau his stirring
  appeals to the Prussians, <i>An mein Volk</i> and <i>An mein
  Kriegesheer</i>, and the city was the centre of the Prussian preparations
  for the campaign which ended at Leipzig. After the Prussian victory at
  Sadowa in 1866, William I. made a triumphant and complimentary entry into
  the city, which since the days of Frederick the Great has been only less
  loyal to the royal house than Berlin itself.</p>
      <p>See Bürkner and Stein, <i>Geschichte der Stadt Breslau</i> (Bresl.
  1851-1853); J-Stein, <i>Geschichte der Stadt Breslau im 19ten
  Jahrhundert</i> (1884); O Frenzel, <i>Breslauer Stadtbuch</i> ("Codex
  dipl. Silisiae," vol. ii. 1882); Luchs, <i>Breslau, ein Führer durch die
  Stadt</i> (12th ed., Bresl. 1904).</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_011"> In 1195 Jaroslaw,
  son of Boleslaus I. of Lower Silesia, who became bishop of Breslau in
  1198, inherited the duchy of Neisse, which at his death (1201) he
  bequeathed to his successors in the see. The Austrian part of Neisse
  still belongs to the bishop of Breslau, who also still bears the title of
  prince bishop.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>