<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e29557">
   <title>BUCHAREST</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCHAREST--> (<i>Bucuresci</i>), also written Bucarest, Bukarest,
  Bukharest, Bukorest and Bukhorest, the capital of Rumania, and chief town
  of the department of Ilfov. Although <i>Bucharest</i> is the conventional
  English spelling, the forms <i>Bucarest</i> and <i>Bukarest</i> more
  nearly represent the correct pronunciation. The population in 1900 was
  282,071, including 43,274 Jews, and 53,056 aliens, mostly
  Austro-Hungarian subjects. With its outlying parts, Bucharest covers more
  than 20 sq. m. It lies in a hollow, traversed from north-west to
  south-east by the river Dimbovitza (<i>Dâmbovita</i> or
  <i>Dîmbovita</i>), and is built mainly on the left bank. A range of low
  hills affords shelter on the west and south-west; but on every other side
  there are drained, though still unhealthy, marshes, stretching away to
  meet the central Walachian plains. From a distance, the multitude of its
  gardens, and the turrets and metal-plated or gilded cupolas of its many
  churches give Bucharest a certain picturesqueness. In a few of the older
  districts, too, where land is least valuable, there are antique
  one-storeyed houses, surrounded by poplars and acacias; while the gipsies
  and Rumans, wearing their brightly coloured native costumes, the Russian
  coachmen, or sleigh-drivers, of the banished Lipovan sect, and the
  pedlars, with their doleful street cries, render Bucharest unlike any
  western capital. Nevertheless, the city is modern. Until about 1860,
  indeed, the dimly lit lanes were paved with rough stone blocks, imbedded
  in the clay soil, which often subsided, so as to leave the surface
  undulating like a sea. Drains were rare, epidemics common. Owing to the
  frequency of earthquakes, many houses were built of wood, and in 1847
  fully a quarter of the city was laid waste by fire. The plague visited
  Bucharest in 1718, 1738, 1793, when an earthquake destroyed a number of
  old buildings, and in 1813, when 70,000 of the inhabitants died in six
  weeks. From the accession of Prince Charles, in 1866, a gradual reform
  began. The river was enclosed between stone embankments; sewerage and
  pure water were supplied, gas and electric light installed; and horse or
  electric tramways laid down in the principal thoroughfares, which were
  paved with granite or wood. The older houses are of brick, overlaid with
  white or tinted plaster, and ornamented with figures or foliage in
  terra-cotta; but owing to the great changes of temperature in Rumania,
  the plaster soon cracks and peels off, giving a dilapidated appearance to
  many streets. The chief modern buildings, such as the Athenaeum, with its
  Ionic façade and Byzantine dome, are principally on the quays and
  boulevards, and are constructed of stone.</p>
      <p>Bucharest is often called "The Paris of the East," partly from a
  supposed social resemblance, partly from the number of its boulevards and
  avenues. Three main thoroughfares, the Plevna, Lipscani, and Vacaresci,
  skirt the left bank of the river; the Elizabeth Boulevard, and the Calea
  Victoriei, or "Avenue of Victory," which commemorates the Rumanian
  success at Plevna, in 1877, radiate east and north, respectively, from
  the Lipscani, and meet a broad road which surrounds all sides of
  Bucharest, except the north-west. The Lipscani was originally the street
  of merchants who obtained their wares from the annual fair at Leipzig;
  for almost all crafts or gilds, other than the bakers and tavern-keepers,
  were long confined to separate quarters; and the old names have survived,
  as in the musicians', furriers', and money-changers' quarters. Continuous
  with the Calea Victoriei, on the north, is the Kisilev Park, traversed by
  the Chausée, a favourite drive, leading to the pretty Baneasa
  race-course, where spring and autumn meetings are held. The Cismegiu or
  Cismigiu Park, which has a circumference of about 1 m., is laid out
  between the Plevna road and the Calea Victoriei; and there are botanical
  and zoological gardens.</p>
      <p>The Orthodox Greek churches are generally small, with very narrow
  windows, and are built of brick in a modified Byzantine style. They are
  usually surmounted by two or three towers, but the bells are hung in a
  kind of wooden porch, resembling a <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page718">[v.04 p.0718]</ph>lych-gate, and
  standing about twenty paces from the church. The cathedral, or
  metropolitan church, where the metropolitan primate of Rumania
  officiates, was built between 1656 and 1665. It has the shape of a Greek
  cross, surrounded by a broad cloister, with four main entrances, each
  surmounted by a turret. The whole culminates in three brick towers.
  Standing on high ground, the cathedral overlooks all Bucharest, and
  commands a view of the Carpathians. Other interesting churches are St
  Spiridion the New (1768), the loftiest and most beautiful of all; the
  Doamna Balasa (1751), noteworthy for its rich carved work without, and
  frescoes within; and the ancient Biserica Bucur, said, in local
  traditions, to derive its name from Bucur, a shepherd whom legend makes
  the founder of Bucharest. The real founder and date of this church, and
  of many others, are unknown, thanks to the frequent obliteration of
  Slavonic inscriptions by the Greek clergy. The Protestants, Armenians and
  Lipovans worship in their own churches, and the Jews have several
  synagogues. Bucharest is also the seat of a Roman Catholic archbishop;
  but the Roman Catholics, though numbering nearly 37,000 in 1899, possess
  only three churches, including the cathedral of St Joseph.</p>
      <p>Bucharest is a great educational centre. Besides the ordinary
  ecclesiastical seminaries, lyceums, gymnasia and elementary schools, it
  possesses schools of commerce, science and art institutes, and training
  colleges, for engineers and veterinary surgeons; while the university,
  founded in 1864, has faculties of theology, philosophy, literature, law,
  science, medicine and pharmacy. Students pay no fees except for board.
  The national library, containing many precious Oriental documents, and
  the meeting-hall of the Rumanian senate, are both included in the
  university buildings, which, with the Athenaeum (used for literary
  conferences and for music), and the central girls' school, are regarded
  as the best example of modern Rumanian architecture. Other libraries are
  those of the Nifon seminary, of the Charles University Foundation
  (<i>Fundatiunea universitara Carol</i>), which endows research, and
  rewards literary or scientific merit; the central library, and the
  library of the Academy, which also contains a museum of natural history
  and antiquities. Among philanthropic institutions may be mentioned the
  Coltei, Brancovan, Maternitate, Philantropia and Pantelimon hospitals;
  the Marcutza lunatic asylum; and the Princess Elena refuge (<i>Asilul
  Elena Doamna</i>), founded by Princess Elena Couza in 1862, to provide
  for 230 orphan girls. The summer home of these girls is a convent in the
  Transylvanian Alps. Hotels and restaurants are numerous. There are two
  theatres, the National and the Lyric, which is mainly patronized by
  foreign players; but minor places of amusement abound; as also do
  clubs—political, social and sporting. Socially, indeed, the
  progress of Bucharest is remarkable, its political, literary and
  scientific circles being on a level with those of most European
  capitals.</p>
      <p>Bucharest is the winter residence of the royal family, the
  meeting-place of parliament, and the seat of an appeal court (<i>Curtea
  de Apel</i>), of the supreme court (<i>Curtea de Casatie</i>), of the
  ministries, the national bank, the bank of Rumania, many lesser credit
  establishments, and a chamber of commerce. The railway lines which meet
  on the western limit of the city give access to all parts, and the
  telephone system, besides being internally complete, communicates with
  Braila, Galatz, Jassy and Sinaia. Bucharest has a very large transit
  trade in petroleum, timber and agricultural produce; above all, in wheat
  and maize. Its industries include petroleum-refining, extraction of
  vegetable oils, cabinet-making, brandy-distilling, tanning, and the
  manufacture of machinery, wire, nails, metal-ware, cement, soap, candles,
  paste, starch, paper, cardboard, pearl buttons, textiles, leather goods,
  ropes, glucose, army supplies, preserved meat and vegetables, and
  confectionery. An important fair is held for seven days in each year. The
  mercantile community is largely composed of Austrians, Frenchmen,
  Germans, Greeks and Swiss, who form exclusive colonies. Bucharest is the
  headquarters of the II. army corps, and a fortress of the first rank. The
  fortifications were constructed in 1885-1896 on a project drafted by the
  Belgian engineer, General Brialmont, in 1883. The mean distance of the
  forts from the city is 4 m., and the perimeter of the defences (which are
  technically of special importance as embodying the system of Brialmont)
  is about 48 m., this perimeter being defended by 36 armoured forts and
  batteries. There are barracks for over 30,000 cavalry and infantry, an
  arsenal, a military hospital and three military academies.</p>
      <p>The legend of Bucur is plainly unhistorical, and the meaning of
  <i>Bucharest</i> has been much disputed. One account derives it from an
  Albanian word <i>Bukur</i>, meaning joy, in memory of a victory won by
  Prince Mircea of Walachia (c. 1383-1419) over the Turks. For this reason
  Bucharest is often called "The City of Joy". Like most ancient cities of
  Rumania, its foundation has also been ascribed to the first Walachian
  prince, the half-mythical Radu Negru (c. 1290-1314). More modern
  historians declare that it was originally a fortress, erected on the site
  of the Daco-Roman Thyanus, to command the approaches to Tîrgovishtea,
  formerly the capital of Walachia. It soon became the summer residence of
  the court. In 1595 it was burned by the Turks; but, after its
  restoration, continued to grow in size and prosperity, until, in 1698,
  Prince Constantine Brancovan chose it for his capital. During the 18th
  century the possession of Bucharest was frequently disputed by the Turks,
  Austrians and Russians. In 1812 it gave its name to the treaty by which
  Bessarabia and a third of Moldavia were ceded to Russia. In the war of
  1828 it was occupied by the Russians, who made it over to the prince of
  Walachia in the following year. A rebellion against Prince Bibescu in
  1848 brought both Turkish and Russian interference, and the city was
  again held by Russian troops in 1853-1854. On their departure an Austrian
  garrison took possession and remained till March 1857. In 1858 the
  international congress for the organization of the Danubian
  principalities was held in the city; and when, in 1861, the union of
  Walachia and Moldavia was proclaimed, Bucharest became the Rumanian
  capital. Prince Cuza, the first ruler of the united provinces, was driven
  from his throne by an insurrection in Bucharest in 1866. For the
  subsequent history of the city see <ph outputclass="sc">Rumania</ph>:
  <i>History</i>.</p>
   </body>
</topic>