<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e19707">
   <title>BROCA, PAUL</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROCA, PAUL--> (1824-1880), French surgeon and anthropologist, was
  born at Sainte-Foy la Grande, Gironde, on the 28th of June 1824. He early
  developed a taste for higher mathematics, but circumstances decided him
  in adopting medicine as his profession. Beginning his studies at Paris in
  1841, he made rapid progress, becoming house-surgeon in 1844, assistant
  anatomical lecturer in 1846, and three years later professor of surgical
  anatomy. He had already gained a reputation by his pathological
  researches. In 1853 he was named fellow of the Faculty of Medicine, and
  in 1867 became member of the Academy of Medicine and professor of
  surgical pathology to the Faculty. During the years occupied in winning
  his way to the head of his profession he had published treatises of much
  value on cancer, aneurism and other subjects. It was in 1861 that he
  announced his discovery of the seat of articulate speech in the left side
  of the frontal region of the brain, since known as the convolution of
  Broca. But famous as he was as a surgeon, his name is associated most
  closely with the modern school of anthropology. Establishing the
  Anthropological Society of Paris in 1859, of which he was secretary till
  his death, he was practically the inventor of the modern science of
  craniology. He rendered distinguished service in the Franco-German War,
  and during the Commune by his organization and administration of the
  public hospitals. He founded <i>La Revue d'Anthropologie</i> in 1872, and
  it was in its pages that the larger portion of his writings appeared. In
  his last years Broca turned from his labours in the region of craniology
  to the exclusive study of the brain, in which his greatest triumphs were
  achieved (see <ph outputclass="sc">Aphasia</ph>). He was decorated with the
  Legion of Honour in 1868, and was honorary fellow of the leading
  anatomical, biological and anthropological societies of the world. He
  died on the 9th of July 1880. A statue of him by Choppin was erected in
  1887 in front of the Faculty of Medicine in Paris.</p>
   </body>
</topic>