<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12859">
   <title>BRISTOL</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRISTOL, GEORGE DIGBY,--> <ph outputclass="sc">2nd Earl of</ph>
         <xref href="#d1e12859/Footnote_071" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> (1612-1677),
  eldest son of the 1st earl (see below), was born in October 1612. At the
  age of twelve he appeared at the bar of the House of Commons and pleaded
  for his father, then in the Tower, when his youth, graceful person and
  well-delivered speech made a great impression. He was admitted to
  Magdalen College, Oxford, on the 15th of August 1626, where he was a
  favourite pupil of Peter Heylin, and became M.A. in 1636. He spent the
  following years in study and in travel, from which he returned, according
  to Clarendon, "the most accomplished person of our nation or perhaps any
  other nation," and distinguished by a remarkably handsome person. In 1638
  and 1639 were written the <i>Letters between Lord George Digby and Sir
  Kenelm Digby, Knt. concerning Religion</i> (publ. 1651), in which Digby
  attacked Roman Catholicism. In June 1634 Digby was committed to the Fleet
  till July for striking Crofts, a gentleman of the court, in Spring
  Gardens; and possibly his severe treatment and the disfavour shown to his
  father were the causes of his hostility to the court. He was elected
  member for Dorsetshire in both the Short and Long parliaments in 1640,
  and in conjunction with Pym and Hampden he took an active part in the
  opposition to Charles. He moved on the 9th of November for a committee to
  consider the "deplorable state" of the kingdom, and on the 11th was
  included in the committee for the impeachment of Strafford, against whom
  he at first showed great zeal. He, however, opposed the attainder, made
  an eloquent speech on the 21st of April 1641, accentuating the weakness
  of Vane's evidence against the prisoner, and showing the injustice of
  <i>ex post facto</i> legislation. He was regarded in consequence with
  great hostility by the parliamentary party, and was accused of having
  stolen from Pym's table Vane's notes on which the prosecution mainly
  depended. On the 15th of July his speech was burnt by the hangman by the
  order of the House of Commons. Meanwhile on the 8th of February he had
  made an important speech in the Commons advocating the reformation and
  opposing the abolition of episcopacy. On the 8th of June, during the
  angry discussion on the army plot, he narrowly escaped assault in the
  House; and the following day, in order to save him from further attacks,
  the king called him up to the Lords in his father's barony of Digby.</p>
      <p>He now became the evil genius of Charles, who had the incredible folly
  to follow his advice in preference to such men as Hyde and Falkland. In
  November he is recorded as performing "singular good service," and "doing
  beyond admiration," in speaking in the Lords against the instruction
  concerning evil counsellors. He suggested to Charles the impeachment of
  the five members, and urged upon him the fatal attempt to arrest them on
  the 4th of January 1642; but he failed to play his part in the Lords in
  securing the arrest of Lord Mandeville, to whom on the contrary he
  declared that "the king was very mischievously advised"; and according to
  Clarendon his imprudence was responsible for the betrayal of the king's
  plan. Next day he advised the attempt to seize them in the city by force.
  The same month he was ordered to appear in the Lords to answer a charge
  of high treason for a supposed armed attempt at Kingston, but fled to
  Holland, where he joined the queen, and on the 26th of February was
  impeached. Subsequently he visited Charles at York disguised as a
  Frenchman, but on the return voyage to Holland he was captured and taken
  to Hull, where he for some time escaped detection; and at last he cajoled
  Sir John Hotham, after discovering himself, into permitting his escape.
  Later he ventured on a second visit to Hull to persuade Hotham to
  surrender the place to Charles, but this project failed. He was present
  at Edgehill, and greatly distinguished himself at Lichfield, where he was
  wounded while leading the assault. He soon, however, threw down his
  commission in consequence of a quarrel with Prince Rupert, and returned
  to the king at Oxford, over whom he obtained more influence as the
  prospect became more gloomy. On the 28th of September 1643 he was
  appointed secretary of state and a privy councillor, and on the 31st of
  October high steward of Oxford University. He now supported the queen's
  disastrous policy of foreign alliances and help from Ireland, and engaged
  in a series of imprudent and ill-conducted negotiations which greatly
  injured the king's affairs, while his fierce disputes with Rupert and his
  party further embarrassed them. On the 14th of October 1645 he was made
  lieutenant general of the royal forces north of the Trent, with the
  object of pushing through to join Montrose, but he was defeated on <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page577">[v.04
  p.0577]</ph>the 15th at Sherburn, where his correspondence was
  captured, disclosing the king's expectations from abroad and from Ireland
  and his intrigues with the Scots; and after reaching Dumfries, he found
  his way barred. He escaped on the 24th to the Isle of Man, thence
  crossing to Ireland, where he caused Glamorgan to be arrested. Here, on
  this new stage, he believed he was going to achieve wonders. "Have I not
  carried my body swimmingly," he wrote to Hyde in irrepressible good
  spirits, "who being before so irreconcilably hated by the Puritan party,
  have thus seasonably made myself as odious to the Papists?"<xref href="#d1e12859/Footnote_072" type="fn"><!--[2]--></xref> His project
  now was to bring over Prince Charles to head a royalist movement in the
  island; and having joined Charles at Jersey in April 1646, he intended to
  entrap him on board, but was dissuaded by Hyde. He then travelled to
  Paris to gain the queen's consent to his scheme, but returned to persuade
  Charles to go to Paris, and accompanied him thither, revisiting Ireland
  on the 29th of June once more, and finally escaping to France on the
  surrender of the island to the parliament. At Paris amongst the royalists
  he found himself in a nest of enemies eager to pay off old scores. Prince
  Rupert challenged him, and he fought a duel with Lord Wilmot. He
  continued his adventures by serving in Louis XIV.'s troops in the war of
  the Fronde, in which he greatly distinguished himself. He was appointed
  in 1651 lieutenant-general in the French army, and commander of the
  forces in Flanders. These new honours, however, were soon lost. During
  Mazarin's enforced absence from the court Digby aspired to become his
  successor; and the cardinal, who had from the first penetrated his
  character and regarded him as a mere adventurer,<xref href="#d1e12859/Footnote_073" type="fn"><!--[3]--></xref> on his restoration to power sent
  Digby away on an expedition in Italy; and on his return informed him that
  he was included in the list of those expelled from France, in accordance
  with the new treaty with Cromwell. In August 1656 he joined Charles II.
  at Bruges, and desirous of avenging himself upon the cardinal offered his
  services to Don John of Austria in the Netherlands, being instrumental in
  effecting the surrender of the garrison of St Ghislain to Spain in 1657.
  On the 1st of January 1657 he was appointed by Charles II. secretary of
  state, but shortly afterwards, having become a Roman
  Catholic—probably with the view of adapting himself better to his
  new Spanish friends—he was compelled to resign office. Charles,
  however, on account of his "jollity" and Spanish experience took him with
  him to Spain in 1659, though his presence was especially deprecated by
  the Spanish; but he succeeded in ingratiating himself, and was welcomed
  by the king of Spain subsequently at Madrid.</p>
      <p>By the death of his father Digby had succeeded in January 1659 to the
  peerage as 2nd earl of Bristol, and had been made K.G. the same month. He
  returned to England at the restoration, when he found himself excluded
  from office on account of his religion, and relegated to only secondary
  importance. His desire to make a brilliant figure induced a restless and
  ambitious activity in parliament. He adopted an attitude of violent
  hostility to Clarendon. In foreign affairs he inclined strongly to the
  side of Spain, and opposed the king's marriage with Catherine of
  Portugal. He persuaded Charles to despatch him to Italy to view the
  Medici princesses, but the royal marriage and treaty with Portugal were
  settled in his absence. In June 1663 he made an attempt to upset
  Clarendon's management of the House of Commons, but his intrigue was
  exposed to the parliament by Charles, and Bristol was obliged to attend
  the House to exonerate himself, when he confessed that he had "taken the
  liberty of enlarging," and his "comedian-like speech" excited general
  amusement. Exasperated by these failures, in a violent scene with the
  king early in July, he broke out into fierce and disrespectful
  reproaches, ending with a threat that unless Charles granted his requests
  within twenty-four hours "he would do somewhat that should awaken him out
  of his slumbers, and make him look better to his own business."
  Accordingly on the 10th he impeached Clarendon in the Lords of high
  treason, and on the charge being dismissed renewed his accusation, and
  was expelled from the court, only avoiding the warrant issued for his
  apprehension by a concealment of two years. In January 1664 he caused a
  new sensation by his appearance at his house at Wimbledon, where he
  publicly renounced before witnesses his Roman Catholicism, and declared
  himself a Protestant, his motive being probably to secure immunity from
  the charge of recusancy preferred against him.<xref href="#d1e12859/Footnote_074" type="fn"><!--[4]--></xref> When, however, the fall of
  Clarendon was desired, Bristol was again welcomed at court. He took his
  seat in the Lords on the 29th of July 1667. "The king," wrote Pepys in
  November, "who not long ago did say of Bristoll that he was a man able in
  three years to get himself a fortune in any kingdom in the world and lose
  all again in three months, do now hug him and commend his parts
  everywhere above all the world."<xref href="#d1e12859/Footnote_075" type="fn"><!--[5]--></xref> He pressed eagerly for
  Clarendon's commital, and on the refusal of the Lords accused them of
  mutiny and rebellion, and entered his dissent with "great fury."<xref href="#d1e12859/Footnote_076" type="fn"><!--[6]--></xref> In March 1668
  he attended prayers in the Lords. On the 15th of March 1673 though still
  ostensibly a Roman Catholic, he spoke in favour of the Test Act,
  describing himself as "a Catholic of the church of Rome, not a Catholic
  of the court of Rome," and asserting the unfitness of Romanists for
  public office. His adventurous and erratic career closed by death on the
  20th of March 1677.</p>
      <p>Bristol was one of the most striking and conspicuous figures of his
  time, a man of brilliant abilities, a great orator, one who distinguished
  himself without effort in any sphere of activity he chose to enter, but
  whose natural gifts were marred by a restless ambition and instability of
  character fatal to real greatness. Clarendon describes him as "the only
  man I ever knew of such incomparable parts that was none the wiser for
  any experience or misfortune that befell him," and records his
  extraordinary facility in making friends and making enemies. Horace
  Walpole characterized him in a series of his smartest antitheses as "a
  singular person whose life was one contradiction." "He wrote against
  popery and embraced it; he was a zealous opposer of the court and a
  sacrifice for it; was conscientiously converted in the midst of his
  prosecution of Lord Strafford and was most unconscientiously a persecutor
  of Lord Clarendon. With great parts, he always hurt himself and his
  friends; with romantic bravery, he was always an unsuccessful commander.
  He spoke for the Test Act, though a Roman Catholic; and addicted himself
  to astrology on the birthday of true philosophy." Besides his youthful
  correspondence with Sir K. Digby on the subject of religion already
  mentioned, he was the author of an <i>Apologie</i> (1643, Thomason
  Tracts, E. 34 (32)), justifying his support of the king's cause; of
  <i>Elvira ... a comedy</i> (1667), printed in R. Dodsley's <i>Select
  Collect. of Old English Plays</i> (Hazlitt, 1876), vol. xv., and of
  <i>Worse and Worse</i>, an adaptation from the Spanish, acted but not
  printed. Other writings are also ascribed to him, including the
  authorship with Sir Samuel Tuke of <i>The Adventures of Five Hours</i>
  (1663). His eloquent and pointed speeches, many of which were printed,
  are included in the article in the <i>Biog. Brit.</i> and among the
  <i>Thomason Tracts</i>; see also the general catalogue in the British
  Museum. The catalogue of his library was published in 1680. He married
  Lady Anne Russell, daughter of Francis, 4th earl of Bedford, by whom,
  besides two daughters, he had two sons, Francis, who predeceased him
  unmarried, and John, who succeeded him as 3rd earl of Bristol, at whose
  death without issue the peerage became extinct.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Authorities</ph>.—See the article in <i>Dict.
  Nat. Biog.</i>; Wood's <i>Ath. Oxon.</i> (Bliss), iii. 1100-1105;
  <i>Biographia Brit.</i> (Kippis), v. 210-238; H. Walpole's <i>Royal and
  Noble Authors</i> (Park, 1806), iii. 191; <i>Roscius Anglicanus</i>, by
  J. Downes, pp. 31, 36 (1789); Cunningham's <i>Lives of Eminent
  Englishmen</i> (1837), iii. 29; <i>Somers Tracts</i> (1750), iii. (1809),
  iv.; <i>Harleian Miscellany</i> (1808), v., vi.; <i>Life</i> by T. H.
  Lister (1838); <i>State Papers</i>.</p>
      <p>(P. C. Y.)</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_071"> 
            <i>I.e.</i> in the
  Digby line; for the Herveys see above.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_072"> 
            <i>Clarendon State
  Papers</i>, ii. 201.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_073"> 
            <i>Mémoires du
  Cardinal de Retz</i> (1859), app. iii. 437, 442.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_074"> Pepys's
  <i>Diary</i>, iv. 51.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_075"> 
            <i>Ib.</i> vii.
  199.</fn>

         <fn id="Footnote_076"> 
            <i>Ib.</i> 207;
  <i>Protests of the Lords</i>, by J.E.T. Rogers, i. 36.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>