<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e21735">
   <title>BROOCH</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROOCH,--> or <ph outputclass="sc">Broach</ph> (from the Fr.
  <i>broche</i>, originally an awl or bodkin; a spit is sometimes called a
  broach, and hence the phrase "to broach a barrel"; see <ph outputclass="sc">Broker</ph>), a term now used to denote a clasp or fastener
  for the dress, provided with a pin, having a hinge or spring at one end,
  and a catch or loop at the other.</p>
      <p>Brooches of the safety-pin type (<i>fibulae</i>) were extensively used
  in antiquity, but only within definite limits of time and place. They
  seem to have been unknown to the Egyptians, and to the oriental nations
  untouched by Greek influence. In lands adjacent to Greece, they do not
  occur in Crete or at Hissarlik. The place of origin cannot as yet be
  exactly determined, but it would seem to have been in central Europe,
  towards the close of the Bronze Age, somewhat before 1000 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph> The earliest form is little more than a pin,
  bent round for security, with the point caught against the head. One such
  actual pin has been found. In its next simplest form, very similar to
  that of the modern safety-pin (in which the coiled spring forces the
  point against the catch), it occurs in the lower city of Mycenae, and in
  late deposits of the Mycenaean Age, such as at Enkomi in Cyprus. It
  occurs also (though rarely) in the "terramare" deposits of the Po valley,
  in the Swiss lake-dwellings of the later Bronze Age, in central Italy, in
  Hungary and in Bosnia. (fig. 1).<xref href="#d1e21735/Footnote_151" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref>
      </p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
            <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 1.—Early type from Peschiera.
  </title>
         <desc/>
         <image href="images/brooch_1.png">
            <alt>Fig. 1.--Early type from Peschiera.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>From the comparatively simple initial form, the fibula developed in
  different lines of descent, into different shapes, varying according to
  the structural feature which was emphasized. On account of the number of
  local variations, the subject is extremely complex, but the main lines of
  development were approximately as follows.</p>
      <p>Towards the end of the Bronze Age the safety-pin was arched into a
  bow, so as to include a greater amount of stuff in its compass.</p>
      <p>In the older Iron Age or "Hallstatt period" the bow and its
  accessories are thickened and modified in various directions, so as to
  give greater rigidity, and prominences or surfaces for decoration. The
  chief types have been conveniently classed by <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page642">[v.04 p.0642]</ph>Montelius in
  four main groups, according to the characteristic forms:—</p>
      <p>I. The wire of the catch-plate is hammered into a flat disk, on which
  the pin rests (fig. 2)</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 2.—Type I. with disk
    for catch-plate.</p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/brooch_2.png">
            <alt>Fig. 2.--Type I. with disk for catch-plate.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>II. The bow is thickened towards the middle, so as to assume the
  "leech" shape, or it is hollowed out underneath, into the "boat" form.
  The catch-plate is only slightly turned up, but it becomes elongated, in
  order to mask the end of a long pin (fig. 3).</p>
      <p>III. The catch-plate is flattened out as in group I., but additional
  convolutions are added to the bow (fig. 4).</p>
      <p>IV. The bow is convoluted (but the convolutions are sometimes
  represented by knobs); the catch-plate develops as in group II. (fig. 5).
  For further examples of the four types, see <i>Antiquities of Early Iron
  Age in British Museum</i>, p. 32.</p>
      <p>Among the special variations of the early form, mention should be made
  of the fibulae of the geometric age of Greece, with an exaggerated
  development of the vertical portion of the catch-plate (fig. 6).</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 3.—Type II. with
    turned-up and elongated catch-plate. <i>a</i>, "Leech" fibula;
    <i>b</i>, "Boat" fibula; <i>c.</i> variation of "Boat" fibula.</p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/brooch_3.png">
            <alt>Fig. 3.--Type II. with turned-up and elongated catch-plate.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>The example shown in fig. 7 is an ornate development of type II.
  above.</p>
      <p>In the later Iron Age (or early La Tène period) the prolongation of
  the catch-plate described in the second and fourth groups above has a
  terminal knob ornament, which is reflexed upwards, at first slightly
  (fig. 8), and then to a marked extent, turning back towards the bow.</p>
      <p>A far-reaching change in the design was at the same time brought about
  by a simple improvement in principle, apparently introduced within the
  area of the La Tène culture. Instead of a unilateral spring—that
  is, of one coiled on one side only of the bow as commonly in the modern
  safety-pin—the brooch became bilateral. The spring was coiled on
  one side of the axis of the bow, and thence the wire was taken to the
  other side of the axis, and again coiled in a corresponding manner before
  starting in a straight line to form the pin. Once invented, the bilateral
  spring became almost universal, and its introduction serves to divide the
  whole mass of ancient fibulae into an older and a younger group.</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 4.—Type III with
    disk for catch-plate, and convoluted bow.</p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/brooch_4.png">
            <alt>Fig. 4.--Type III with disk for catch-plate, and convoluted bow.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>With the progress of the La Tène period (300-1 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>) the reflection of the catch-plate terminal
  became yet more marked, until it became practically merged in the bow
  (fig. 9). Meanwhile, the bilateral spring described above was developing
  into two marked projections on each side of the axis. In order to give
  the double spring strength and protection it was given a metal core, and
  a containing tube. When the core had been provided the pin was no longer
  necessarily a continuation of the bow, and it became in fact a separate
  member, as in a modern brooch of a non-safety-pin type, and was no longer
  actuated by its own spring.</p>
      <p>The T-shaped or "cross-bow" fibula was thus developed. During the
  first centuries of the Empire it attained great size and importance
  (figs. 10-12). The form is conveniently dated at its highest development
  by its occurrence on the ivory diptych of Stilicho at Monza (c. <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 400).</p>
      <p>In the tombs of the Frankish and kindred Teutonic tribes between the
  5th and 9th centuries the crossbar of the T becomes a yet more
  elaborately decorated semicircle, often surrounded by radial knobs and a
  chased surface. The base of the shaft is flattened out, and is no less
  ornate (fig. 13). At the beginning of this period the fibula of King
  Childeric (<ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 481) has a singularly
  complicated pin-fastening.</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 7.—Gold fibula from
    Naples.</p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/brooch_7.png">
            <alt>Fig. 7.--Gold fibula from Naples.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 6.—Greek geometric
    fibula.</p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/brooch_6.png">
            <alt>Fig. 6.--Greek geometric fibula.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 5.—Type IV. with
    turned-up catch-plate and convoluted bow.</p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/brooch_5.png">
            <alt>Fig. 5.--Type IV. with turned-up catch-plate and convoluted bow.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 8.—Early La Tène
    period. Reflexed terminal ornament.</p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/brooch_8.png">
            <alt>Fig. 8.--Early La Tène period. Reflexed terminal ornament.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>So far we have traced the history of the safety-pin form of brooch.
  Concurrently with it, other forms of brooch were developed in which the
  safety-pin principle is either absent or effectually disguised. One such
  form is that of the circular medallion brooch. It is found in Etruscan
  deposits of a fully developed style, and is commonly represented in Greek
  and Roman sculptures as a stud to fasten the cloak on the shoulder. In
  the Roman provinces the circular brooches are very numerous, and are
  frequently decorated with inlaid stone, paste or enamel. Another kind of
  brooch, also known from early times, is in the form of an animal. In the
  early types the animal is a decorative appendage, but in later examples
  it forms the body of the brooch, to which a pin like the modern
  brooch-pin is attached underneath. Both of these shapes, namely the
  medallion and the animal form, are found in Frankish cemeteries, together
  with the later variations of the T-shaped brooch described above. Such
  brooches were made in gold, silver or bronze, adorned with precious
  stones, filigree work, or enamel; but whatever the richness of the
  material, the pin was nearly always of iron. The Scandinavian or northern
  group of T-shaped brooches are in their early forms indistinguishable
  from those of the Frankish tombs, but as time went on they became more
  massive, and richly decorated with intricate devices (perhaps brought in
  by Irish missionary influence), into which animal forms were introduced.
  The period covered is from the 5th to the 8th centuries.</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 9, a-d.—Fibula of
    the La Tène period, showing the development of the reflexed terminal,
    and the bilateral spring.</p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/brooch_9.png">
            <alt>Fig. 9.--Fibula of the La Tène period.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="br"/>
      </p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 11.—Fibula with
    niello work. 3rd century <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph>
            </p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/brooch_11.png">
            <alt>Fig. 11.--Fibula with niello work.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 10.—Military Fibula.
    3rd century <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph>
            </p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/brooch_10.png">
            <alt>Fig. 10.--Military Fibula.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>The T-form, the medallion-form, and (occasionally) the animal forms
  occur in Anglo-Saxon graves in England. In Kent the medallion-form
  predominates. The Anglo-Saxon brooches <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page643">[v.04 p.0643]</ph>were exquisite
  works of art, ingeniously and tastefully constructed. They are often of
  gold, with a central boss, exquisitely decorated, the flat part of the
  brooch being a mosaic of turquoises, garnets on gold foil, mother of
  pearl, &amp;c. arranged in geometric patterns, and the gold work enriched
  with filigree or decorated with dragonesque engravings.</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
            <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 12.—Gold Fibula. 4th century <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph>
         </title>
         <desc/>
         <image href="images/brooch_12.png">
            <alt>Fig. 12.--Gold Fibula.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>The Scandinavian brooches of the Viking period (<ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 800-1050) were oval and convex, somewhat in the
  form of a tortoise. In their earliest form they occur in the form of a
  frog-like animal, itself developed from the previous Teutonic T-shaped
  type. With the introduction of the intricate system of ornament described
  above, the frog-like animal is gradually superseded by purely decorative
  lines. The convex bowls are then worked <i>à jour</i> with a perforated
  upper shell of chased work over an under shell of impure bronze, gilt on
  the convex side. These outer cases are at last decorated with open
  crown-like ornament and massive projecting bosses. The geographical
  distribution of these peculiar brooches indicates the extent of the
  conquests of the Northmen. They occur in northern Scotland, England,
  Ireland, Iceland, Normandy and Livonia.</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
            <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 13.—Fibula of the Frankish period.
  </title>
         <desc/>
         <image href="images/brooch_13.png">
            <alt>Fig. 13.--Fibula of the Frankish period.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <p>The Celtic group is characterized by the penannular form of the ring
  of the brooch and the greater length of the pin. The penannular ring,
  inserted through a hole at the head of the long pin, could be partially
  turned when the pin had been thrust through the material in such a way
  that the brooch became in effect a buckle. These brooches are usually of
  bronze or silver, chased or engraved with intricate designs of interlaced
  or dragonesque work in the style of the illuminated Celtic manuscripts of
  the 7th, 8th and 9th centuries. The Hunterston brooch, which was found at
  Hawking Craig in Ayrshire, is a well-known example of this style. Silver
  brooches of immense size, some having pins 15 in. in length, and the
  penannular ring of the brooch terminating in large knobs resembling
  thistle heads, are occasionally found in Viking hoards of this period,
  consisting of bullion, brooches and Cufic and Anglo-Saxon coins buried on
  Scottish soil. In medieval times the form of the brooch was usually a
  simple, flat circular disk, with open centre, the pin being equal in
  length to the diameter of the brooch. They were often inscribed with
  religious and talismanic <i>formulae</i>. The Highland brooches were
  commonly of this form, but the disk was broader, and the central opening
  smaller in proportion to the size of the brooch. They were ornamented in
  the style so common on Highland powder-horns, with engraved patterns of
  interlacing work and foliage, arranged in geometrical spaces, and
  sometimes mingled with figures of animals.</p>
      <p>(<ph outputclass="sc">A. H. Sm.</ph>)</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_151"> The illustrations
  of this article are from Dr Robert Forrer's <i>Reallexikon</i>, by
  permission of W. Spemann, Berlin and Stuttgart.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>