<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12501">
   <title>BRINDISI</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRINDISI--> (anc. <i>Brundisium</i>, <i>q.v.</i>), a seaport town
  and archiepiscopal see of Apulia, Italy, in the province of Lecce, 24 m.
  N.W. by rail from the town of Lecce, and 346 m. from Ancona. Pop.(1861)
  8000; (1871) 13,755; (1901) 25,317. The chief importance of Brindisi is
  due to its position as a starting-point for the East. The inner harbour,
  admirably sheltered and 27 to 30 ft. in depth, allows ocean steamers to
  lie at the quays. Brindisi has, however, been abandoned by the large
  steamers of the Peninsular &amp; Oriental Steam Navigation Company, which
  had called there since 1870, but since 1898 call at Marseilles instead;
  small express boats, carrying the mails, still leave every week,
  connecting with the larger steamers at Port Said; but the number of
  passengers leaving the port, which for the years 1893-1897 averaged
  14,728, was only 7608 in 1905, and only 943 of these were carried by the
  P. &amp; O. boats. The harbour railway station was not completed until
  1905 (<i>Consular <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page572">[v.04 p.0572]</ph>Report</i>, No. 3672, 1906, pp. 13
  sqq.). The port was cleared in 1905 by 1492 vessels of 1,486,269 tons.
  The imports represented a value of £629,892 and the exports a value of
  £663,201—an increase of £84,077 and £57,807 respectively on the
  figures of the previous year, while in 1899 the amounts, which were below
  the average, were only £298,400 and £253,000. The main imports are coal,
  flour, sulphur, timber and metals; and the main exports, wine and
  spirits, oil and dried fruits.</p>
      <p>Frederick II. erected a castle, with huge round towers, to guard the
  inner harbour; it is now a convict prison. The cathedral, ruined by
  earthquakes, was restored in 1743-1749, but has some remains of its
  mosaic pavement (1178). The baptismal church of S. Giovanni al Sepolcro
  (11th century) is now a museum. The town was captured in 836 by the
  Saracens, and destroyed by them; but was rebuilt in the 11th century by
  Lupus the protospatharius, Byzantine governor. In 1071 it fell into the
  hands of the Normans, and frequently appears in the history of the
  Crusades. Early in the 14th century the inner port was blocked by
  Giovanni Orsini, prince of Taranto; the town was devastated by pestilence
  in 1348, and was plundered in 1352 and 1383; but even greater damage was
  done by the earthquake of 1456.</p>
      <p>(<ph outputclass="sc">T. As.</ph>)</p>
   </body>
</topic>