<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e19441">
   <title>BRITTON, JOHN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRITTON, JOHN--> (1771-1857), English antiquary, was born on the
  7th of July 1771 at Kington-St-Michael, near Chippenham. His parents were
  in humble circumstances, and he was left an orphan at an early age. At
  sixteen he went to London and was apprenticed to a wine merchant.
  Prevented by ill-health from serving his full term, he found himself
  adrift in the world, without money or friends. In his fight with poverty
  he was put to strange shifts, becoming cellarman at a tavern and clerk to
  a lawyer, reciting and singing at a small theatre, and compiling a
  collection of common songs. After some slight successes as a writer, a
  Salisbury publisher commissioned him to compile an account of Wiltshire
  and, in conjunction with his friend Edward Wedlake Brayley, Britton
  produced <i>The Beauties of Wiltshire</i> (1801; 2 vols., a third added
  in 1825), the first of the series <i>The Beauties of England and
  Wales</i>, nine volumes of which Britton and his friend wrote. Britton
  was the originator of a new class of literary works. "Before his time,"
  says Digby Wyatt, "popular topography was unknown." In 1805 Britton
  published the first part of his <i>Architectural Antiquities of Great
  Britain</i> (9 vols., 1805-1814); and this was followed by <i>Cathedral
  Antiquities of England</i> (14 vols., 1814-1835). In 1845 a Britton Club
  was formed, and a sum of £1000 was subscribed and given to Britton, who
  was subsequently granted a civil list pension by Disraeli, then
  chancellor of the exchequer. Britton was an earnest advocate of the
  preservation of national monuments, proposing in 1837 the formation of a
  society such as the modern Society for the Preservation of Ancient
  Monuments. Britton himself supervised the reparation of Waltham Cross and
  Stratford-on-Avon church. He died in London on the 1st of January
  1857.</p>
      <p>Among other works with which Britton was associated either as author
  or editor are <i>Historical Account of Redcliffe Church, Bristol</i>
  (1813); <i>Illustrations of Fonthill Abbey</i> (1823); <i>Architectural
  Antiquities of Normandy</i>, with illustrations by Pugin (1825-1827);
  <i>Picturesque Antiquities of English Cities</i> (1830); and <i>History
  of the Palace and Houses of Parliament at Westminster</i> (1834-1836),
  the joint work of Britton and Brayley. He contributed much to the
  <i>Gentleman's Magazine</i> and other periodicals.</p>
      <p>His <i>Autobiography</i> was published in 1850. A <i>Descriptive
  Account of his Literary Works</i> was published by his assistant T.E.
  Jones.</p>
   </body>
</topic>