<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e33243">
   <title>BUFFET</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUFFET,--> a piece of furniture which may be open or closed, or
  partly open and partly closed, for the reception of dishes, china, glass
  and plate. The word may also signify a long counter at which one stands
  to eat and drink, as at a restaurant, or—which would appear to be
  the original meaning—the room in which the counter stands. The
  word, like the thing it represents, is French. The buffet is the
  descendant of the credence, and the ancestor of the sideboard, and
  consequently has a close affinity to the dresser. Few articles of
  furniture, while preserving their original purpose, have varied more
  widely in form. In the beginning the buffet was a tiny apartment, or
  recess, little larger than a cupboard, separated from the room which it
  served either by a breast-high balustrade or by pillars. It developed
  into a definite piece of furniture, varying from simplicity to splendour,
  but always provided with one or more flat spaces, or broad shelves, for
  the reception of such necessaries of the dining-room as were not placed
  upon the table. The early buffets were sometimes carved with the utmost
  elaboration; the Renaissance did much to vary their form and refine their
  ornament. Often the lower part contained receptacles as in the
  characteristic English court-cupboard. The rage for collecting china in
  the middle of the 18th century was responsible for a new form—the
  high glazed back, fitted with shelves, for the display of fine pieces of
  crockery-ware. This, however, was hardly a true buffet, and was the very
  antithesis of the primary arrangement, in which the huge goblets and
  beakers and fantastic pieces of plate, of which so extremely few examples
  are left, were displayed upon the open "gradines." The tiers of shelves,
  with or without a glass front, which are still often found in Georgian
  houses, were sometimes called buffets—in short, any dining-room
  receptacle for articles that were not immediately wanted came at last to
  bear the name. In France the variations of type were even more numerous
  than in England, and it is sometimes difficult to distinguish a commode
  from a buffet. In the latter part of the 18th century the buffet
  occasionally took the form of a console table.</p>
   </body>
</topic>