<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e4348">
   <title>BRIDGES, ROBERT</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIDGES, ROBERT--> (1844- ), English poet, born on the 23rd of
  October 1844, was educated at Eton and at Corpus Christi College, Oxford,
  and studied medicine in London at St Bartholomew's hospital. He was
  afterwards assistant physician at the Children's hospital, Great Ormond
  Street, and physician at the Great Northern hospital, retiring in 1882.
  Two years later he married Mary, daughter of Alfred Waterhouse, R.A. As a
  poet Robert Bridges stands rather apart from the current of modern
  English verse, but his work has had great influence in a select circle,
  by its restraint, purity, precision, and delicacy yet strength of
  expression; and it embodies a distinct theory of prosody. His chief
  critical works are <i>Milton's Prosody</i> (1893), a volume made up of
  two earlier essays (1887 and 1889), and <i>John Keats, a Critical
  Essay</i> (1895). He maintained that English prosody depended on the
  number of "stresses" in a line, not on the number of syllables, and that
  poetry should follow the rules of natural speech. His poetry was
  privately printed in the first instance, and was slow in making its way
  beyond a comparatively small circle of his admirers. His best work is to
  be found in his <i>Shorter Poems</i> (1890), and a complete edition of
  his <i>Poetical Works</i> (6 vols.) was published in 1898-1905. His chief
  volumes are <i>Prometheus</i> (Oxford, 1883, privately printed), a "mask
  in the Greek Manner"; <i>Eros and Psyche</i> (1885), a version of
  Apuleius; <i>The Growth of Love</i>, a series of sixty-nine sonnets
  printed for private circulation in 1876 and 1889; <i>Shorter Poems</i>
  (1890); <i>Nero</i> (1885), a historical tragedy, the second part of
  which appeared in 1894; <i>Achilles in Scyros</i> (1890), a drama;
  <i>Palicio</i> (1890), a romantic drama in the Elizabethan manner; <i>The
  Return of Ulysses</i> (1890), a drama in five acts; <i>The Christian
  Captives</i> (1890), a tragedy on the same subject as Calderon's <i>El
  Principe Constante</i>; <i>The Humours of the Court</i> (1893), a comedy
  founded on the same dramatist's <i>El secreto รก voces</i> and on Lope de
  Vega's <i>El Perro del hortelano</i>; <i>The Feast of Bacchus</i> (1889),
  partly translated from the <i>Heauton-Timoroumenos</i> of Terence;
  <i>Hymns from the Yattendon Hymnal</i> (Oxford, 1899); and <i>Demeter, a
  Mask</i> (Oxford, 1905).</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page533">[v.04 p.0533]</ph>
      </p>
   </body>
</topic>