<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e2982">
   <title>BRIAND, ARISTIDE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIAND, ARISTIDE--> (1862- ), French statesman, was born at
  Nantes, of a bourgeois family. He studied law, and while still young took
  to politics, associating himself with the most advanced movements,
  writing articles for the anarchist journal <i>Le Peuple</i>, and
  directing the <i>Lanterne</i> for some time. From this he passed to the
  <i>Petite République</i>, leaving it to found, with Jean Jaurès,
  <i>L'Humanité</i>. At the same time he was prominent in the movement for
  the formation of labour unions, and at the congress of working men at
  Nantes in 1894 he secured the adoption of the labour union idea against
  the adherents of Jules Guesde. From that time, Briand became one of the
  leaders of the French Socialist party. In 1902, after several
  unsuccessful attempts, he was elected deputy. He declared himself a
  strong partisan of the union of the Left in what is known as the
  <i>Bloc</i>, in order to check the reactionary deputies of the Right.
  From the beginning of his career in the chamber of deputies, Briand was
  occupied with the question of the separation of church and state. He was
  appointed reporter of the commission charged with the preparation of the
  law, and his masterly report at once marked him out as one of the coming
  leaders. He succeeded in carrying his project through with but slight
  modifications, and without dividing the parties upon whose support he
  relied. He was the principal author of the law of separation, but, not
  content with preparing it, he wished to apply it as well, especially as
  the existing Rouvier <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page516">[v.04 p.0516]</ph>ministry allowed disturbances to
  occur during the taking of inventories of church property, a clause of
  the law for which Briand was not responsible. Consequently he accepted
  the portfolio of public instruction and worship in the Sarrien ministry
  (1906). So far as the chamber was concerned his success was complete. But
  the acceptance of a portfolio in a bourgeois ministry led to his
  exclusion from the Unified Socialist party (March 1906). As opposed to
  Jaurès, he contended that the Socialists should co-operate actively with
  the Radicals in all matters of reform, and not stand aloof to await the
  complete fulfilment of their ideals.</p>
   </body>
</topic>