<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e24072">
   <title>BROWNE, SIR THOMAS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWNE, SIR THOMAS--> (1605-1682), English author and physician,
  was born in London, on the 19th of October 1605. He was admitted as a
  scholar of Winchester school in 1616, and matriculated at Broadgates Hall
  (Pembroke College), Oxford, in 1623, where he graduated B.A. in January
  1626. He took the further degree of M.A. in 1629, studied medicine, and
  practised for some time in Oxfordshire. Between 1630 and 1633 he left
  England, travelled in Ireland, France and Italy, and on his way home
  received the degree of M.D. at the university of Leiden. He returned to
  London in 1634, and, after a short residence at Shipden Hall, near
  Halifax, settled in practice at Norwich in 1637. He married in 1641
  Dorothy Mileham. Their eldest son, Edward, became president of the Royal
  College of Physicians, and glimpses of their happy family life are
  obtainable in the fragmentary correspondence contained in Simon Wilkin's
  edition. In 1642 a copy of his <i>Religio Medici</i>, which he describes
  as "a private exercise directed to myself," was printed from one of his
  MSS. without his knowledge, and reviewed by Sir Kenelm Digby in
  <i>Observations ...</i> (1643). The interest aroused by this edition
  compelled Browne to put forth a correct version (1643) of the work, in
  which letters between Digby and Browne were included. The book was
  probably written as early as 1635, for he describes himself as still
  under thirty. In 1646 he published <i>Pseudodoxia Epidemica; Enquiries
  into very many commonly received Tenents and commonly presumed Truths</i>
  (1646), and in 1658 <i>Hydriotaphia, Urne-Buriall; or, a discourse of the
  sepulchrall urnes lately found in Norfolk. Together with the Garden of
  Cyrus, or the quincunciall, lozenge, or net-work plantations of the
  ancients, artificially, naturally, and mystically considered. With Sundry
  observations</i> (1658). These four works were all that he published,
  though several tracts, notably the <i>Christian Morals</i>
         <xref href="#d1e24072/Footnote_191" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> intended as a
  continuation of <i>Religio Medici</i>, were prepared for publication, and
  appeared posthumously. In 1671 he received the honour of knighthood from
  Charles II. on his visit to Norwich. He began a correspondence with John
  Evelyn in 1658. Very few of the letters are extant, but the diarist has
  left an account of a visit to Browne (<i>Diary</i>, 17th of October
  1671). He died in 1682 on his seventy-seventh birthday, and was buried at
  St Peter's, Mancroft, Norwich. His coffin was accidentally broken in
  1840, and his skull is preserved in the museum of the Norwich
  hospital.</p>
      <p>Browne's writings are among the few specimens of purely literary work
  produced during a period of great political excitement and discord. He
  remained to all appearance placidly indifferent to the struggle going on
  around him. His first book appeared in the year of the outbreak of the
  Civil War; <i>Pseudodoxia Epidemica</i> in the critical year of 1646; and
  <i>Hydriotaphia</i>, the reflections on the shortness of human life
  inspired by the unearthing of some funeral urns, on the eve of the
  Restoration. A mind as aloof as his is a psychological curiosity, and its
  peculiarities are faithfully reflected in the form and matter of his
  works. His display of erudition, his copious citations from authorities,
  his constant use of metaphor and analogy, and his elaborate diction, are
  common qualities of the writers of the 17th century, but Browne stands
  apart from his contemporaries by reason of the peculiar cast of his mind.
  Imbued with the Platonic mysticism which taught him to look on this world
  as only the image, the shadow of an invisible system, he regarded the
  whole of experience as only food for contemplation. Nothing is too great
  or too small for him; all finds a place in the universe of being, which
  he seems to regard almost from the position of an outsider. He did not
  speculate systematically on the problems of existence, but he meditates
  repeatedly on the outward and visible signs of mortality, and on what
  lies beyond death. Of Browne, as of the greatest writers, it is true that
  the style is the man. The form of his thought is as peculiar and
  remarkable as the matter; the two, indeed, react on one another. Much of
  the quaintness of his style, no doubt, depends on the excessive
  employment of latinized words, many of which have failed to justify their
  existence; but the peculiarities of his vocabulary do not explain the
  unique character of his writing, which is appreciated to-day as much as
  ever.</p>
      <p>The <i>Religio Medici</i> was a puzzle to his contemporaries, and it
  is still hard to reconcile its contradictions. A Latin translation
  appeared at Leiden in 1644, and it was widely read on the continent,
  being translated subsequently into Dutch, French and German. In Paris it
  was issued in the belief that Browne was really a Roman Catholic, but in
  Rome the authorities thought otherwise, and the book was placed on the
  <i>Index Expurgatorius</i>. It is the confession of a mind keen and
  sceptical in some aspects, and credulous in others. Browne professes to
  be absolutely free from heretical opinions, but asserts the right to be
  guided by his own reason in cases where no precise guidance is given
  either by Scripture or by Church teaching. "I love," he says, "to lose
  myself in a mystery, to pursue my reason to an O, Altitudo!" The
  <i>Pseudodoxia Epidemica</i>, written in a more direct and simple style
  than is usual with Browne, is a wonderful storehouse of out-of-the-way
  facts and scraps of erudition, <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page667">[v.04 p.0667]</ph>exhibiting a singular mixture of
  credulity and shrewdness. Sir Thomas evidently takes delight in
  discussing the wildest fables. That he himself was by no means free from
  superstition is proved by the fact that the condemnation of two
  unfortunate women, Amy Duny and Rose Cullender, for witchcraft at Norwich
  in 1664 was aided by his professional evidence. The <i>Garden of
  Cyrus</i> is a continued illustration of one quaint conceit. The whole
  universe is ransacked for examples of the <i>Quincunx</i>, and he
  discovers, as Coleridge says, "quincunxes in heaven above, quincunxes in
  earth below, quincunxes in the mind of man, quincunxes in tones, in optic
  nerves, in roots of trees, in leaves, in everything!" But the whole
  strength of his genius and the wonderful charm of his style are to be
  sought in the <i>Urnburial</i>, the concluding chapter of which, for
  richness of imagery and majestic pomp of diction, can hardly be
  paralleled in the English language. For anything at all resembling it we
  must turn to the finest passages of Jeremy Taylor or of Milton's prose
  writings.</p>
      <p>In 1684 appeared a collection of <i>Certain Miscellany Tracts</i> (ed.
  Tenison), and in 1712 <i>Posthumous Works of the learned Sir Thomas
  Browne</i>. The first collected edition of Browne's works appeared in
  1686. It is said to have been edited by Dr, afterwards Archbishop
  Tenison. Sir Thomas Browne's <i>Works, including his Life and
  Correspondence</i>, were carefully edited by Simon Wilkin in 1835-1836.
  Among modern reprints may be mentioned Dr W.A. Greenhill's editions in
  the "Golden Treasury" series of the <i>Religio Medici, Letter to a
  friend</i> and <i>Christian Morals</i> (1881), with an admirable
  bibliographical note on the complicated subject of the numerous editions
  of the <i>Religio Medici</i>; of the <i>Hydriotaphia</i> and the
  <i>Garden of Cyrus</i> (1896), completed by Mr E.H. Marshall; a complete
  edition for the English Library, edited by Mr Charles Sayle (1904,
  &amp;c.). Browne's interest in bird-lore is noted by Evelyn, and some
  <i>Notes and Letters on the Natural History of Norfolk</i> were collected
  from his MSS. in the Sloane Collection, and edited by Thomas Southwell in
  1902.</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_191"> Ed. John Jeffery,
  archdeacon of Norwich, 1716. The dignified "Letter to a Friend, upon the
  occasion of the Death of his Intimate Friend" (written about 1672, pr.
  1690) has been generally supposed to be a preliminary sketch for
  <i>Christian Morals</i>, but Dr W.A. Greenhill thinks it was written
  later.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>