<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e3988">
   <title>BRIDE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIDE--> (a common Teutonic word, e.g. Goth. <i>bruths</i>, O.Eng.
  <i>bryd</i>, O.H.Ger. <i>prût</i>, Mod. Ger. <i>Braut</i>, Dut.
  <i>bruid</i>, possibly derived from the root <i>bru-</i>, cook, brew;
  from the med. latinized form <i>bruta</i>, in the sense of
  daughter-in-law, is derived the Fr. <i>bru</i>), the term used of a woman
  on her wedding-day, and applicable during the first year of wifehood. It
  appears in combination with many words, some of them obsolete. Thus
  "bridegroom" is the newly married man, and "bride-bell," "bride-banquet"
  are old equivalents of wedding-bells, wedding-breakfast. "Bridal" (from
  <i>Bride-ale</i>), originally the wedding-feast itself, has grown into a
  general descriptive adjective, e.g. the <i>bridal</i> party, the
  <i>bridal</i> ceremony. The <i>bride-cake</i> had its origin in the Roman
  <i>confarreatio</i>, a form of marriage, the essential features of which
  were the eating by the couple of a cake made of salt, water and flour,
  and the holding by the bride of three wheat-ears, symbolical of plenty.
  Under Tiberius the cake-eating fell into disuse, but the wheat ears
  survived. In the middle ages they were either worn or carried by the
  bride. Eventually it became the custom for the young girls to assemble
  outside the church porch and throw grains of wheat over the bride, and
  afterwards a scramble for the grains took place. In time the wheat-grains
  came to be cooked into thin dry biscuits, which were broken over the
  bride's head, as is the custom in Scotland to-day, an oatmeal cake being
  used. In Elizabeth's reign these biscuits began to take the form of small
  rectangular cakes made of eggs, milk, sugar, currants and spices. Every
  wedding guest had one at least, and the whole collection were thrown at
  the bride the instant she crossed the threshold. Those which lighted on
  her head or shoulders were most prized by the scramblers. At last these
  cakes became amalgamated into a large one which took on its full glories
  of almond paste and ornaments during Charles II.'s time. But even to-day
  in rural parishes, e.g. north Notts, wheat is thrown over the bridal
  couple with the cry "Bread for life and pudding for ever," expressive of
  a wish that the newly wed may be always affluent. The throwing of rice, a
  very ancient custom but one later than the wheat, is symbolical of the
  wish that the bridal may be fruitful. The <i>bride-cup</i> was the bowl
  or loving-cup in which the bridegroom pledged the bride, and she him. The
  custom of breaking this wine-cup, after the bridal couple had drained its
  contents, is common to both the Jews and the members of the Greek Church.
  The former dash it against the wall or on the ground, the latter tread it
  under foot. The phrase "bride-cup" was also sometimes used of the bowl of
  spiced wine prepared at night for the bridal couple.
  <i>Bride-favours</i>, anciently called bride-lace, were at first pieces
  of gold, silk or other lace, used to bind up the sprigs of rosemary
  formerly worn at weddings. These took later the form of bunches of
  ribbons, which were at last metamorphosed into rosettes.
  <i>Bridegroom-men</i> and <i>bridesmaids</i> had formerly important
  duties. The men were called bride-knights, and represented a survival of
  the primitive days of marriage by capture, when a man called his friends
  in to assist to "lift" the bride. Bridesmaids were usual in Saxon
  England. The senior of them had personally to attend the bride for some
  days before the wedding. The making of the bridal wreath, the decoration
  of the tables for the wedding feast, the dressing of the bride, were
  among her special tasks. In the same way the senior groomsman (the
  <i>best man</i>) was the personal attendant of the husband. The
  <i>bride-wain</i>, the wagon in which the bride was driven to her new
  home, gave its name to the weddings of any poor deserving couple, who
  drove a "wain" round the village, collecting small sums of money or
  articles of furniture towards their housekeeping. These were called
  bidding-weddings, or bid-ales, which were in the nature of "benefit"
  feasts. So general is still the custom of "bidding-weddings" in Wales,
  that printers usually keep the form of invitation in type. Sometimes as
  many as six hundred couples will walk in the bridal procession. The
  <i>bride's wreath</i> is a Christian substitute for the gilt coronet all
  Jewish brides wore. The crowning of the bride is still observed by the
  Russians, and the Calvinists of Holland and Switzerland. The wearing of
  orange blossoms is said to have started with the Saracens, who regarded
  them as emblems of fecundity. It was introduced into Europe by the
  Crusaders. The <i>bride's veil</i> is the modern form of the
  <i>flammeum</i> or large yellow veil which completely enveloped the Greek
  and Roman brides during the ceremony. Such a covering is still in use
  among the Jews and the Persians.</p>
      <p>See Brand, <i>Antiquities of Great Britain</i> (Hazlitt's ed., 1905);
  Rev J. Edward Vaux, <i>Church Folklore</i> (1894).</p>
   </body>
</topic>