<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e29397">
   <title>BUCHANAN, JAMES</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCHANAN, JAMES--> (1791-1868), fifteenth president of the United
  States, was born near Foltz, Franklin county, Pennsylvania, on the 23rd
  of April 1791. Both parents were of Scottish-Irish Presbyterian descent.
  He graduated at Dickinson College, Carlisle, Pennsylvania, in 1809,
  studied law at Lancaster in 1809-1812, and was admitted to the bar in
  1812. He served in the lower house of the state legislature in 1814-1816,
  and as a representative in Congress from 1821 to 1831. As chairman of the
  judiciary committee he conducted the impeachment trial (1830) of Judge
  James H. Peck, led an unsuccessful movement to increase the number of
  Supreme Court judges and to relieve them of their circuit duties, and
  succeeded in defeating an attempt to repeal the twenty-fifth section of
  the Judiciary Act of 1789, which gave the Supreme Court appellate
  jurisdiction by writ of error to the state courts in cases where federal
  laws and treaties are in question. After the dissolution of the
  Federalist party, of which he had been a member, he supported the
  Jackson-Van Buren faction, and soon came to be definitely associated with
  the Democrats. He represented the United States at the court of St
  Petersburg in 1832-1833, and there negotiated an important commercial
  treaty. He was a Democratic member of the United States Senate from
  December 1834 until March 1845, ardently supporting President Jackson,
  and was secretary of state in the cabinet of President Polk from 1845 to
  1849—a period marked by the annexation of Texas, the Mexican War,
  and negotiations with Great Britain relative to the Oregon question.
  After four years of retirement spent in the practice of his profession,
  he was appointed by President Pierce minister to Great Britain in
  1853.</p>
      <p>Up to this time Buchanan's attitude on the slavery question had been
  that held by the conservative element among Northern Democrats. He felt
  that the institution was morally wrong, but held that Congress could not
  interfere with it in the states in which it existed, and ought not to
  hinder the natural tendency toward territorial expansion through a fear
  that the evil would spread. He voted for the bill to exclude anti-slavery
  literature from the mails, approved of the annexation of Texas, the war
  with Mexico, and the Compromise of 1850, and disapproved of the Wilmot
  Proviso. Fortunately for his career he was abroad during the
  Kansas-Nebraska debates, and hence did not share in the unpopularity
  which attached to Stephen A. Douglas as the author of the bill, and to
  President Pierce as the executive who was called upon to enforce it. At
  the same time, by joining with J.Y. Mason and Pierre Soule in issuing the
  Ostend Manifesto in 1854, he retained the good-will of the South.<xref href="#d1e29397/Footnote_241" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> Accordingly
  on his return from England in 1856 he was nominated by the Democrats as a
  compromise candidate for president, and was elected, receiving 174
  electoral votes to 114 for John C. Frémont, Republican, and 8 for Millard
  Fillmore, American or "Know-Nothing."</p>
      <p>His high moral character, the breadth of his legal knowledge, and his
  experience as congressman, cabinet member and diplomat, would have made
  Buchanan an excellent president in ordinary times; but he lacked the
  soundness of judgment, the self-reliance and the moral courage needed to
  face a crisis. At the beginning of his administration he appointed Robert
  J. Walker of Mississippi, territorial governor of Kansas, and Frederick
  P. Stanton of Tennessee, secretary, and assured them of his determination
  to adhere to the popular sovereignty principle. He soon began to use his
  influence, however, to force the admission of Kansas into the Union under
  the pro-slavery Lecompton Constitution, contrary to the wishes of the
  majority of the settlers. Stanton was removed from office for opposing
  the scheme, and Walker resigned in disgust. This change of policy was
  doubtless the result of timidity rather than of a desire to secure
  re-election by gaining the favour of the Southern Democracy. Under the
  influence of Howell Cobb of Georgia, secretary of the treasury, and Jacob
  Thompson of Mississippi, secretary of the interior, the president was
  convinced that it was the only way to avoid civil war. Federal patronage
  was freely used to advance the Lecompton measure and the compromise
  English Bill, and to prevent Douglas's election to the Senate in 1858.
  Some of these facts were brought out in the famous Covode Investigation
  conducted by a committee of the House of Representatives in 1860. The
  investigations, however, were very partisan in character, and there is
  reason to doubt the constitutional power of the House to make it, except
  as the basis for an impeachment trial.</p>
      <p>The call issued by the South Carolina legislature just after the
  election of Lincoln for a state convention to decide upon the
  advisability of secession brought forward the most serious question of
  Buchanan's administration. The part of his annual message of the 4th of
  December 1860 dealing with it is based upon a report prepared by
  Attorney-General Jeremiah S. Black of Pennsylvania. He argued that a
  state had no legal right to secede, but denied that the federal
  government had any power forcibly to prevent it. At the same time it was
  the duty of the president to call out the army and navy of the United
  States to protect federal property or to enforce federal laws. Soon after
  the secession movement began the Southern members of the cabinet
  resigned, and the president gradually came under the influence of Black,
  Stanton, Dix, and other Northern leaders. He continued, however, to work
  for a peaceful settlement, supporting the Crittenden Compromise and the
  work of the Peace Congress. He disapproved of Major Anderson's removal of
  his troops from Fort Moultrie to Fort Sumter in December 1860; but there
  is probably no basis for the charge made by Southern writers that the
  removal itself was in violation of a pledge given by the president to
  preserve the <i>status quo</i> in Charleston harbour until the arrival of
  the South Carolina commissioners in Washington. Equally unfounded is the
  assertion first made by Thurlow Weed in the London <i>Observer</i> (9th
  of February 1862) that the president was prevented from ordering Anderson
  back to Fort Moultrie only by the threat of four members of the cabinet
  to resign.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page717">[v.04 p.0717]</ph>
      </p>
      <p>On the expiration of his term of office (March 4, 1861) Buchanan
  retired to his home at Wheatland, near Lancaster, Pennsylvania, where he
  died on the 1st of June 1868. His mistakes as president have been so
  emphasized as to obscure the fact that he was a man of unimpeachable
  honesty, of the highest patriotism, and of considerable ability. He never
  married.</p>
      <p>See George Ticknor Curtis, <i>The Life of James Buchanan</i> (2 vols.,
  New York, 1883), the standard biography; Curtis, however, was a close
  personal and political friend, and his work is too eulogistic. More
  trustworthy, but at times unduly severe, is the account given by James
  Ford Rhodes in the first two volumes of his <i>History of the United
  States since the Compromise of 1850</i> (New York, new edition,
  1902-1907). John Bassett Moore has edited <i>The Works of James Buchanan,
  comprising his Speeches, State Papers, and Private Correspondence</i>
  (Philadelphia, 1908-1910).</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_241"> This "manifesto,"
  which was bitterly attacked in the North, was agreed upon (October 18,
  1854) by the three ministers after several meetings at Ostend and at
  Aix-la-Chapelle, arranged in pursuance of instructions to them from
  President Pierce to "compare opinions, and to adopt measures for perfect
  concert of action in aid of the negotiations at Madrid" on the subject of
  reparations demanded from Spain by the United States for alleged injuries
  to American commerce with Cuba. In the manifesto the three ministers
  asserted that "from the peculiarity of its geographical position, and the
  considerations attendant upon it, Cuba is as necessary to the North
  American republic as any of its present members"; spoke of the danger to
  the United States of an insurrection in Cuba; asserted that "we should be
  recreant to our duty, be unworthy of our gallant forefathers, and commit
  base treason against our posterity, should we permit Cuba to be
  Africanized and become a second Santo Domingo, with all its attendant
  horrors to the white race, and suffer the flames to extend to our own
  neighboring shores, seriously to endanger or actually destroy the fair
  fabric of our Union"; and recommended that "the United States ought, if
  practicable, to purchase Cuba as soon as possible." To Spain, they
  argued, the sale of the island would be a great advantage. The most
  startling declaration of the manifesto was that if Spain should refuse to
  sell "after we shall have offered a price for Cuba far beyond its present
  value," and if Cuba, in the possession of Spain, should seriously
  endanger "our internal peace and the existence of our cherished Union,"
  then "by every law, human and divine, we shall be justified in wresting
  it from Spain if we have the power."</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>