<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e34358">
   <title>BUILTH</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUILTH,--> or <ph outputclass="sc">Builth Wells</ph>, a market town
  of Brecknockshire, Wales. Pop. of urban district (1901), 1805. It has a
  station on the Cambrian line between Moat Lane and Brecon, and two others
  (high and low levels) at Builth Road about 1¾ m. distant where the London
  &amp; North-Western and the Cambrian cross one another. It is pleasantly
  situated in the upper valley of the Wye, in a bend of the river on its
  right bank below the confluence of its tributary the Irfon. During the
  summer it is a place of considerable resort for the sake of its
  waters—saline, chalybeate and sulphur—and it possesses the
  usual accessories of pump-rooms, baths and a recreation ground. The
  scenery of the Wye valley, including a succession of rapids just above
  the town, also attracts many tourists. The town is an important
  agricultural centre, its fairs for sheep and ponies in particular being
  well attended.</p>
      <p>The town, called in Welsh Llanfair (yn) Muallt, i.e. St Mary's in
  Builth, took its name from the ancient territorial division of Buallt in
  which it is situated, which was, according to Nennius, an independent
  principality in the beginning of the 9th century, and later a cantrev,
  corresponding to the modern hundred of Builth. Towards the end of the
  11th century, when the tide of Norman invasion swept upwards along the
  Wye valley, the district became a lordship marcher annexed to that of
  Brecknock, but was again severed from it on the death of William de
  Breos, when his daughter Matilda brought it to her husband, Roger
  Mortimer of Wigmore. Its castle, built probably in Newmarch's time, or
  shortly after, was the most advanced outpost of the invaders in a wild
  part of Wales where the tendency to revolt was always strong. It was
  destroyed in 1260 by Llewellyn ab Gruffydd, prince of Wales, with the
  supposed connivance of Mortimer, but its site was reoccupied by the earl
  of Lincoln in 1277, and a new castle at once erected. It was with the
  expectation that he might, with local aid, seize the castle, that
  Llewellyn invaded this district in December 1282, when he was surprised
  and killed by Stephen de Frankton in a ravine called Cwm Llewellyn on the
  left bank of the Irfon, 2½ m. from the town. According to local tradition
  he was buried at Cefn-y-bedd ("the ridge of the grave") close by, but it
  is more likely that his headless trunk was taken to Abbey Cwmhir. No
  other important event was associated with the castle, of which not a
  stone is now standing. The lordship remained in the marches till the Act
  of Union 1536, when it was grouped with a number of others so as to form
  the shire of Brecknock. The town was governed by a local board from 1866
  until the establishment of an urban district council in 1894; the urban
  district was then made conterminous with the civil parish, and in 1898 it
  was re-named Builth Wells.</p>
   </body>
</topic>