<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e24884">
   <title>BROWN-SÉQUARD, CHARLES EDWARD</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWN-SÉQUARD, CHARLES EDWARD--> (1817-1894), British physiologist
  and neurologist, was born at Port Louis, Mauritius, on the 8th of April
  1817. His father was an American and his mother a Frenchwoman, but he
  himself always desired to be looked upon as a British subject, though in
  the restlessness of his life and the enthusiasm of his disposition,
  characteristics of his mother's nation were plainly visible. After
  graduating in medicine at Paris in 1846 he returned to Mauritius with the
  intention of practising there, but in 1852 he went to America.
  Subsequently he returned to Paris, and in 1859 he migrated to London,
  becoming physician to the national hospital for the paralysed and
  epileptic. There he stayed for about five years, expounding his views on
  the pathology of the nervous system in numerous lectures which attracted
  considerable attention. In 1864 he again crossed the Atlantic, and was
  appointed professor of physiology and neuro-pathology at Harvard. This
  position he relinquished in 1867, and in 1869 became professor at the
  École de Médecine in Paris, but in 1873 he again returned to America and
  began to practise in New York. Finally, he went back to Paris to succeed
  Claude Bernard in 1878 as professor of experimental medicine in the
  Collège de France, and he remained there till his death, which occurred
  on the 2nd of April 1894 at Sceaux. Brown-Séquard was a keen observer and
  experimentalist. He contributed largely to our knowledge of the blood and
  animal heat, as well as many facts of the highest importance on the
  nervous system. He was the first scientist to work out the physiology of
  the spinal cord, demonstrating that the decussation of the sensory fibres
  is in the cord itself. He also did valuable work on the internal
  secretion of organs, the results of which have been applied with the most
  satisfactory results in the treatment of myxoedema. Unfortunately in his
  extreme old age, he advocated the hypodermic injection of a fluid
  prepared from the testicles of sheep, as a means of prolonging human
  life. It was known, among scientists, derisively, as the Brown-Séquard
  Elixir. His researches, published in about 500 essays and papers,
  especially in the <i>Archives de Physiologie</i>, which he helped to
  found in 1868, cover a very wide range of physiological and pathological
  subjects.</p>
   </body>
</topic>