<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e597">
   <title>BRETWALDA</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRETWALDA,--> a word used in the <i>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</i>
  under the date 827, and also in a charter of Æthelstan, king of the
  English. It appears in several variant forms (<i>brytenwalda</i>,
  <i>bretenanwealda</i>, &amp;c.), and means most probably "lord of the
  Britons" or "lord of Britain"; for although the derivation of the word is
  uncertain, its earlier syllable seems to be cognate with the words Briton
  and Britannia. In the <i>Chronicle</i> the title is given to Ecgbert,
  king of the English, "the eighth king that was Bretwalda," and
  retrospectively to seven kings who ruled over one or other of the English
  kingdoms. The seven names are copied from Bede's <i>Historia
  Ecclesiastica</i>, and it is interesting to note that the last king
  named, Oswiu of Northumbria, lived 150 years before Ecgbert. It has been
  assumed that these seven kings exercised a certain superiority over a
  large part of England, but if such superiority existed it is certain that
  it was extremely vague and was unaccompanied by any unity of
  organization. Another theory is that Bretwalda refers to a
  war-leadership, or <i>imperium</i>, over the English south of the Humber,
  and has nothing to do with Britons or Britannia. In support of this
  explanation it is urged that the title is given in the <i>Chronicle</i>
  to Ecgbert in the year in which he "conquered the kingdom of the Mercians
  and all that was south of the Humber." Less likely is the theory of
  Palgrave that the Bretwaldas were the successors of the pseudo-emperors,
  Maximus and Carausius, and claimed to share the imperial dignity of Rome;
  or that of Kemble, who derives Bretwalda from the British word
  <i>breotan</i>, to distribute, and translates it "widely ruling." With
  regard to Ecgbert the word is doubtless given as a title in imitation of
  its earlier use, and the same remark applies to its use in Æthelstan's
  charter.</p>
      <p>See E.A. Freeman, <i>History of the Norman Conquest</i>, vol. i.
  (Oxford, 1877); W. Stubbs, <i>Constitutional History</i>, vol. i.
  (Oxford, 1897); J.R. Green, <i>The Making of England</i>, vol. ii.
  (London, 1897); F. Palgrave, <i>The Rise and Progress of the English
  Commonwealth</i> (London, 1832); J. M. Kemble, <i>The Saxons in
  England</i> (London, 1876); J. Rhys, <i>Celtic Britain</i> (London,
  1884).</p>
   </body>
</topic>