<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e13312">
   <title>BRISTOW, BENJAMIN HELM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRISTOW, BENJAMIN HELM--> (1832-1896), American lawyer and
  politician, was born in Elkton, Kentucky, on the 20th of June 1832, the
  son of Francis Marion Bristow (1804-1864), a Whig member of Congress in
  1854-1855 and 1859-1861. He graduated at Jefferson College, Canonsburg,
  Pennsylvania, in 1851, studied law under his father, and was admitted to
  the Kentucky bar in 1853. At the beginning of the Civil War he became
  lieutenant-colonel of the 25th Kentucky Infantry; was severely wounded at
  Shiloh; helped to recruit the 8th Kentucky Cavalry, of which he was
  lieutenant-colonel and later colonel; and assisted at the capture of John
  H. Morgan in July 1863. In 1863-1865 he was state senator; in 1865-1866
  assistant United States district-attorney, and in 1866-1870
  district-attorney for the Louisville district; and in 1870-1872, after a
  few months' practice of law with John M. Harlan, was the (first
  appointed) solicitor-general of the United States. In 1873 President
  Grant nominated him attorney-general of the United States in case George
  H. Williams were confirmed as chief justice of the United States,—a
  contingency which did not arise. As secretary of the treasury (1874-1876)
  he prosecuted with vigour the so-called "Whisky Ring," the headquarters
  of which was at St Louis, and which, beginning in 1870 or 1871, had
  defrauded the Federal government out of a large part of its rightful
  revenue from the distillation of whisky. Distillers and revenue officers
  in St Louis, Milwaukee, Cincinnati and other cities were implicated, and
  the illicit gains—which in St Louis alone probably amounted to more
  than $2,500,000 in the six years 1870-1876—were divided between the
  distillers and the revenue officers, who levied assessments on distillers
  ostensibly for a Republican campaign fund to be used in furthering
  Grant's re-election. Prominent among the ring's alleged accomplices at
  Washington was Orville E. Babcock, private secretary to President Grant,
  whose personal friendship for Babcock led him to indiscreet interference
  in the prosecution. Through Bristow's efforts more than 200 men were
  indicted, a number of whom were convicted, but after some months'
  imprisonment were pardoned. Largely owing to friction between himself and
  the president, Bristow resigned his portfolio in June 1876; as secretary
  of the treasury he advocated the resumption of specie payments and at
  least a partial retirement of "greenbacks"; and he was also an advocate
  of civil service reform. He was a prominent candidate for the Republican
  presidential nomination in 1876. After 1878 he practised law in New York
  City, where he died on the 22nd of June 1896.</p>
      <p>See <i>Memorial of Benjamin Helm Bristow</i>, largely prepared by
  David Willcox (Cambridge, Mass., privately printed, 1897); <i>Whiskey
  Frauds</i>, 44th Cong., 1st Sess., Mis. Doc. No. 186; <i>Secrets of the
  Great Whiskey Ring</i> (Chicago, 1880), by John McDonald, who for nearly
  six years had been supervisor of internal revenue at St Louis,—a
  book by one concerned and to be considered in that light.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page583">[v.04 p.0583]</ph>
      </p>
   </body>
</topic>