<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e32946">
   <title>BUENOS AIRES</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUENOS AIRES,--> a maritime province of Argentina, South America,
  bounded N. by the province of Santa Fé and Entre Rios, E. by the latter,
  the La Plata estuary, and the Atlantic, S. by the Atlantic, and W. by the
  territories (<i>gobernaciones</i>) of Rio Negro and Las Pampas, and the
  provinces of Córdoba and Santa Fé. Its area is 117,812 sq. m., making it
  the largest province of the republic. It is also the most populous, even
  excluding the federal district, an official estimate of 1903 giving it a
  population of 1,251,000. Although it has a frontage of over 900 m. on the
  La Plata and the Atlantic, the province has but few good natural ports,
  the best being Bahia Blanca, where the Argentine government has
  constructed a naval port, and Ensenada (La Plata), where extensive
  artificial basins have been constructed for the reception of ocean-going
  steamers. San Nicolas in the extreme north has a fairly good river port,
  while at Buenos Aires a costly artificial port has been constructed.</p>
      <p>In its general aspect the province forms a part of the great treeless
  plain extending from the Atlantic and La Plata estuary westward to the
  Andes. A fringe of small tangled wood covers the low river banks and
  delta region of the Paraná between San Nicolas and Buenos Aires; thence
  southward to Bahia Blanca the sea-shore is low and sandy, with a zone of
  lagoons and partially submerged lands immediately behind. The
  south-eastern and central parts of the province are low and marshy, and
  their effective drainage has long been an urgent problem. Two ranges of
  low mountains extend partly across the southern part of the
  province—the first from Mar del Plata, on the coast, in a
  north-east direction, known at different points as the Sierra del Volcan
  (885 ft.), Sierra de Tandil (1476 ft.), and Sierra Baya, and the second
  and shorter range nearer Bahia Blanca, having the same general direction,
  known at different points as the Sierra Pillahuinco and Sierra de la
  Ventana (3543 ft.). The country is well watered with numerous lakes and
  small rivers, the largest river being the Rio Salado del Sud, which rises
  near the north-western boundary and flows entirely across the province in
  a south-easterly direction with a course of about 360 m. The Rio Colorado
  crosses the extreme southern extension of the province, a distance of
  about 80 m., but its mouth is obstructed, and its lower course is subject
  to occasional disastrous inundations.</p>
      <p>Cattle-raising naturally became the principal industry of this region
  soon after its settlement by the Spaniards, and sheep-raising on a
  profitable basis was developed about the middle of the 19th century.
  Toward the end of that century the exports of wool, live-stock and
  dressed meats reached enormous proportions. There is a large export of
  jerked beef (<i>tasajo</i>) to Brazil and Cuba, and of live-stock to
  Europe, South Africa and neighbouring South American republics. Much
  attention also has been given to raising horses, asses, mules, swine and
  goats, all of which thrive on these grassy plains. Butter and
  cheese-making have gained considerable prominence in the province since
  1890, and butter has become an article of export. Little attention had
  been given to cereals up to 1875, but subsequently energetic efforts were
  made to increase the production of wheat, Indian corn, linseed, barley,
  oats and alfalfa, so that by the end of the century the exports of wheat
  and flour had reached a considerable value. In 1895 there were 3,400,000
  acres under cultivation in the province, and in 1900 the area devoted to
  wheat alone aggregated 1,960,000 acres. Fruit-growing also has made good
  progress, especially on the islands of the Paraná delta, and Argentine
  peaches, pears, strawberries, grapes and figs are highly appreciated.</p>
      <p>The navigation of the Paraná is at all times difficult, and is
  impossible for the larger ocean-going steamers. The greater part of the
  trade of the northern and western provinces, therefore, must pass through
  the ports of Buenos Aires and Ensenada, at which an immense volume of
  business is concentrated. All the great trunk railways of the republic
  pass through the province and converge at these ports, and from them a
  number of transatlantic steamship lines carry away the products of its
  fertile soil. The province is also liberally supplied with branch
  railways. In the far south the new port of Bahia Blanca has become
  prominent in the export of wool and wheat.</p>
      <p>The principal cities and towns of the province (apart from Buenos
  Aires and its suburbs of Belgrano and Flores) are its capital La Plata;
  Bahia Blanca, San Nicolas, a river port on the Paraná 150 m. by rail
  north-west of Buenos Aires, with a population (1901) of 13,000; Campana
  (pop. 5419 in 1895), the former river port of Buenos Aires on one of the
  channels of the Paraná, 51 m. by rail north-west of that city, and the
  site of the first factory in Argentina (1883) for freezing mutton for
  export; Chivilcoy, an important interior town, with a population (1901)
  of 15,000; Pergamino (9540 in 1895), a northern inland railway centre;
  Mar del Plata, a popular seaside resort 250 m. by rail south of Buenos
  Aires; Azul (9494), Tandil (7088), Chascomús (5667), Mercedes (9269), and
  Barracas al Sud (10,185), once the centre of the jerked beef
  industries.</p>
      <p>The early history of the province of Buenos Aires was a struggle for
  supremacy over the other provinces for a period of two generations. Its
  large extent of territory was secured through successive additions by
  conquest of adjoining Indian territories south and west, the last
  additions being as late as 1879. Buenos Aires became a province of the
  Confederation in 1820, and adopted a constitution in 1854, which provides
  for its administration by a governor and legislature of two chambers,
  both chosen by popular vote. An unsuccessful revolt in 1880 against the
  national government led to the federalization of the city of Buenos
  Aires, and the selection of La Plata as the provincial capital, the
  republic assuming the public indebtedness of the provinces at that time
  as an indemnification. Before the new capital was finished, however, the
  province had incurred further liabilities of ten millions sterling, and
  has since then been greatly handicapped in its development in
  consequence.</p>
      <p>(A. J. L.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>