<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23760">
   <title>BROWN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWN, SIR WILLIAM,--> <ph outputclass="sc">Bart.</ph> (1784-1864),
  British merchant and banker, founder of the banking-house of Brown,
  Shipley &amp; Co., was born at Ballymena, Ireland, on the 30th of May
  1784, the son of an Irish linen-merchant. At the age of sixteen he
  accompanied his father and brothers to Baltimore, Maryland, U.S.A.,
  whither it had been decided to transfer the family business, but in 1809
  left America for Liverpool. Here he established a branch of the firm,
  which had now begun to deal largely in raw cotton as well as linen and
  soon afterwards developed into one of general merchants and finally
  bankers. Brown became one of the leaders in Liverpool commerce, and in
  1832 took a principal share in the reform of the system of
  dock-management then in vogue at that port. The great financial crisis of
  1837 seriously threatened the ruin of the firm, but on Brown's urgent
  representations as to the multiplicity of interests involved the Bank of
  England agreed to advance him £2,000,000 to tide matters over. Actually
  Brown only found it necessary to apply for £1,000,000, which he repaid
  within six months. His business, both mercantile and banking, continued
  to increase, and in 1844 he was in possession of a sixth of the trade
  between Great Britain and the United States. "There is hardly," declared
  Richard Cobden at this period, "a wind that blows, or a tide that flows
  in the Mersey, that does not bring a ship freighted with cotton or some
  other costly commodity for Mr Brown's house." In 1856 the friction
  between the British and American governments due to the enlistment by
  British consuls of recruits for the Crimean War was largely allayed by
  the action of Brown, who in an interview with Lord Palmerston, then
  prime-minister, explained the objections taken in America. From 1846 to
  1859 he was Liberal M.P. for South Lancashire. In 1860 he presented
  Liverpool with a public library and museum, and in 1863 was made a
  baronet. He died at Liverpool in 1864.</p>
   </body>
</topic>