<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e29784">
   <title>BUCHON, JEAN ALEXANDRE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCHON, JEAN ALEXANDRE--> (1791-1849), French scholar, was born on
  the 21st of May 1791 at Menetou-Salon (Cher), and died on the 29th of
  August 1849. An ardent Liberal, he took an active part in party struggles
  under the Restoration, while <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page720">[v.04 p.0720]</ph>throwing himself with equal vigour
  into the great work of historical regeneration which was going on at that
  period. During 1822 and the succeeding years he travelled about Europe on
  the search for materials for his <i>Collection des chroniques nationales
  françaises écrites en langue vulgaire du XIII<sup>e</sup> au
  XVI<sup>e</sup> siècle</i> (47 vols., 1824-1829). After the revolution of
  1830 he founded the <i>Panthéon litteraire</i>, in which he published a
  <i>Choix d'ouvrages mystiques</i> (1843), a <i>Choix de monuments
  primitifs de l'église chrétienne</i> (1837), a <i>Choix des historiens
  grecs</i> (1837), a collection of <i>Chroniques étrangères relatives aux
  expéditions françaises pendant le XIII<sup>e</sup> siècle</i> (1840),
  and, most important of all, a <i>Choix de chroniques et mémoires sur
  l'histoire de France</i> (1836-1841). His travels in southern Italy and
  in the East had put him upon the track of the medieval French settlements
  in those regions, and to this subject he devoted several important works:
  <i>Recherches et matériaux pour servir a une histoire de la domination
  française dans les provinces démembrées de l'empire grec</i> (1840);
  <i>Nouvelles recherches historiques sur la principauté française de Morée
  et ses hautes baronnies</i> (2 vols., 1843-1844); <i>Histoire des
  conquêtes et de l'établissement des Français dans les états de l'ancienne
  Grèce sous es Villehardouin</i> (1846, unfinished). None of the numerous
  publications which we owe to Buchon can be described as thoroughly
  scholarly; but they have been of great service to history, and those
  concerning the East have in especial the value of original research.</p>
   </body>
</topic>