<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e24892">
   <title>BROWNSON, ORESTES AUGUSTUS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWNSON, ORESTES AUGUSTUS--> (1803-1876), American theological,
  philosophical and sociological writer, was born in Stockbridge, Vermont,
  on the 16th of September 1803. Having spent some time in active
  religious, reformatory and political (Democratic) work in the interior of
  New York state, and at Walpole, New Hampshire, and Canton, Massachusetts,
  Brownson removed in 1839 to Chelsea, Mass. He at once began to take an
  independent part in the movements then agitating New England, which
  between 1830 and 1850 was stirred by discussions pertaining to
  Unitarianism, transcendentalism, spiritualism, abolitionism and various
  schemes for communistic living. He was one of the founders, in New York,
  of the short-lived Workingman's party in 1828, and established the
  <i>Boston Quarterly Review</i>, mainly written by himself, in 1838. This
  periodical was merged in the <i>U.S. Democratic Review</i> of New York in
  1842. <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page675">[v.04
  p.0675]</ph>In religion he first became a Presbyterian (1822); was a
  Universalist minister from 1826 to 1831, editing for some time the chief
  journal of this church, the <i>Gospel Advocate</i>; was an independent
  preacher at Ithaca, N.Y., in 1831; became a Unitarian minister in 1832,
  and in 1836 organized in Boston the Society for Christian Union and
  Progress, of which he was the pastor for seven years. In 1844 he became a
  Roman Catholic and so remained, though the question of the orthodoxy of
  his writings was at one time submitted by the pope to Cardinal Franzelin,
  who recommended Brownson, to little purpose, to express his views with
  more moderation. In his philosophy Brownson was a more or less
  independent follower of Comte for a short time, and of Victor Cousin,
  who, in his <i>Fragmens philosophiques</i>, praised him; he may be said
  to have taught a modified intuitionalism. In his schemes for social
  reform he was at first a student of Robert Owen, until his later views
  led him to accept Roman Catholicism. His first quarterly was followed, in
  1844, by <i>Brownson's Quarterly Review</i> (first published in Boston
  and after 1855 in New York), in which he expressed his opinions on many
  themes until its suspension in 1864, and after its revival for a brief
  period in 1873-1875. Of his numerous publications in book form, the chief
  during his lifetime were <i>Charles Elwood, or the Infidel Converted</i>
  (1840, autobiographical), in which he strongly favoured the Roman
  Catholic Church; and <i>The American Republic: its Constitution,
  Tendencies and Destiny</i> (1865), in which he based government on
  ethics, declaring the national existence to be a moral and even a
  theocratic entity, not depending for validity upon the sovereignty of the
  people. Brownson died in Detroit, Michigan, on the 17th of April
  1876.</p>
      <p>After his death, his son, Henry F. Brownson, collected and published
  his various political, religious, philosophical, scientific and literary
  writings, in twenty octavo volumes (Detroit, 1883-1887), of which a
  condensed summary appeared in a single volume, also prepared by his son,
  entitled <i>Literary and Political Views</i> (New York, 1893). The son
  also published a biography in three volumes (Detroit, 1898-1900).</p>
      <p>His daughter, Sarah M. Brownson (1839-1876), who married in 1873
  William J. Tenney, was the author of several novels, and wrote a <i>Life
  of Demetrius Augustine Gallitzin, Prince and Priest</i> (1873).</p>
   </body>
</topic>