<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25283">
   <title>BRUCKNER, ANTON</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUCKNER, ANTON--> (1824-1896), Austrian musical composer, was
  born on the 4th of September 1824 at Ansfelden in upper Austria. He
  successfully competed for the organistship for Linz Cathedral in 1855. In
  1867 he succeeded his former master of counterpoint, Sechter, as organist
  of the <i>Hofkapelle</i> in Vienna, and also became professor in the
  conservatorium. In 1875 he was appointed to a lectureship in the
  university. His most striking talent was shown in his extemporizations on
  the organ. His success in an organ competition at Nancy in 1869 led to
  his playing in Paris and London (six recitals at the Albert Hall, 1871).
  His permanent reputation, however, rests on his compositions, especially
  his nine symphonies. In these gigantic efforts the influence of Wagner is
  paramount in almost every feature of harmony and orchestration; and if
  sustained seriousness of purpose and style were all that was necessary to
  give coherence to works in which these influences are stultified by the
  rhythmic uniformities of an experienced <i>improvisatore</i> and the
  impressions of classical form as taught in schools, then Bruckner would
  certainly have been what the extreme Wagnerian party called him, the
  symphonic successor of Beethoven, or the Wagner of the symphony. But
  their lack of organization and proportion, to say nothing of humour, will
  always make their revival a somewhat severe task. No composer has ever
  been more consistent to lofty ideals, though few who have ever had an
  ideal have shown less adroitness in their methods of embodying it. The
  most poetic and admired feature of his style is a slow growth to a
  gigantic climax, slow enough and gigantic enough for any situation in
  Wagner's <i>Nibelungen</i> tetralogy. The symphonies in which these
  climaxes occur are in obviously unskilful classical form, with only an
  outward appearance of freedom; and the Great Pyramid would hardly be more
  out of place in an Oxford quadrangle than Bruckner's climaxes in his
  four-movement symphonies with their "second subjects" and
  recapitulations. Nor is it likely that Bruckner would have been much more
  successful in handling these gigantic things in their legitimate
  Wagnerian dramatic environment, for even in his last three symphonies he
  hardly ever frees himself from the trammels of square rhythm; and, as he
  accepts the classical sonata-forms without inquiry into their meaning or
  relevance, so he accepts the Wagnerian stage orchestra in its minutest
  details, without inquiry as to its relevance for the purposes and
  acoustics of the concert-room, and with the same lack of sense of relief
  that ruins the balance of his rhythmic periods. So unsophisticated a
  temperament may be not unpoetical, but it is eminently undramatic, as
  well as unsymphonic. Of Bruckner's choral works, which include three
  masses and several psalms and motets, the most famous is the <i>Te
  Deum</i> (1885?),<xref href="#d1e25283/Footnote_211" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> which shows his characteristic
  power in massive effect. Bruckner wished this to be appended to the three
  complete movements of his 9th symphony, which his last illness (ending in
  his death at Vienna on the 11th of October 1896) prevented him from
  finishing. This 9th symphony is designed, with characteristic
  tactlessness and simplicity, to follow Beethoven's 9th symphony in every
  possible point which could challenge comparison; in key (D minor),
  opening (mysterious tremolo leading to tremendous unison <i>tutti</i>),
  contrasts (return in first movement) and choral finale. The three
  complete movements were first performed in Vienna in 1903, and have done
  more for Bruckner's fame than anything since the production in 1884 of
  his 7th symphony (of which the slow movement is an elegy on the death of
  Wagner). It is probable that the impression produced by this 9th symphony
  is the deeper as owing little or nothing to the musical politics which
  had gone far to prevent the 7th symphony from standing on its own
  unmistakable merits. It does not, however, seem likely that Bruckner's
  work will have much influence on musical progress; for the modern
  characteristics in which its strength lies are obviously better realized
  in other forms which have often been handled successfully by composers
  greatly Bruckner's inferiors both in invention and sincerity.</p>
      <p>(D. F. T.)</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_211"> This date is given
  in Grove (new ed.), but the style of the work is far earlier than that of
  the 7th symphony (1884) which quotes it in the slow movement.</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>