<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e21565">
   <title>BRONZE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRONZE,--> an alloy formed wholly or chiefly of copper and tin in
  variable proportions. The word has been etymologically connected with the
  same root as appears in "brown," but according to M.P.E. Berthelot (<i>La
  Chimie au moyen âge</i>) it is a place-name derived from <i>aes
  Brundusianum</i> (cf. Pliny, <i>Nat. Hist.</i> xxxiii. ch. ix. §45,
  "specula optima apud majores fuerunt Brundusiana, stanno et aere
  mixtis"). A Greek MS. of about the 11th century in the library of St
  Mark's, Venice, contains <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page640">[v.04 p.0640]</ph>the form <ph outputclass="grk">βροντήσιον</ph>,
  and gives the composition of the alloy as 1 lb of copper with 2 oz. of
  tin. The product obtained by adding tin to copper is more fusible than
  copper and thus better suited for casting; it is also harder and less
  malleable. A soft bronze or <i>gun-metal</i> is formed with 16 parts of
  copper to 1 of tin, and a harder gun-metal, such as was used for bronze
  ordnance, when the proportion of tin is about doubled. The <i>steel
  bronze</i> of Colonel Franz Uchatius (1811-1881) consisted of copper
  alloyed with 8% of tin, the tenacity and hardness being increased by
  cold-rolling. Bronze containing about 7 parts of copper to 1 of tin is
  hard, brittle and sonorous, and can be tempered to take a fine edge.
  <i>Bell-metal</i> varies considerably in composition, from about 3 to 5
  parts of copper to 1 of tin. In <i>speculum metal</i> there are 2 to 2½
  parts of copper to 1 of tin. Statuary bronze may contain from 80 to 90%
  of copper, the residue being tin, or tin with zinc and lead in various
  proportions. The bronze used for the British and French copper coinage
  consists of 95% copper, 4% tin and 1% zinc. Many copper-tin alloys
  employed for machinery-bearings contain a small proportion of zinc, which
  gives increased hardness. "Anti-friction metals," also used in bearings,
  are copper-tin alloys in which the amount of copper is small and there is
  antimony in addition. Of this class an example is "Babbitt's metal,"
  invented by Isaac Babbitt (1799-1862); it originally consisted of 24
  parts of tin, 8 parts of antimony and 4 parts of copper, but in later
  compositions for the same purpose the proportion of tin is often
  considerably higher. Bronze is improved in quality and strength when
  fluxed with phosphorus. Alloys prepared in this way, and known as
  <i>phosphor bronze</i>, may contain only about 1% of phosphorus in the
  ingot, reduced to a mere trace after casting, but their value is
  nevertheless enhanced for purposes in which a hard strong metal is
  required, as for pump plungers, valves, the bushes of bearings, &amp;c.
  Bronze again is improved by the presence of manganese in small quantity,
  and various grades of <i>manganese bronze</i>, in some of which there is
  little or no tin but a considerable percentage of zinc, are extensively
  used in mechanical engineering. Alloys of copper with aluminium, though
  often nearly or completely destitute of tin, are known as <i>aluminium
  bronze</i>, and are valuable for their strength and the resistance they
  offer to corrosion. By the addition of a small quantity of silicon the
  tensile strength of copper is much increased; a sample of such <i>silicon
  bronze</i>, used for telegraph wires, on analysis was found to consist of
  99.94% of copper, 0.03% of tin, and traces of iron and silicon.</p>
      <p>The bronze (Gr. <ph outputclass="grk">χαλκός</ph>, Lat. <i>aes</i>) of
  classical antiquity consisted chiefly of copper, alloyed with one or more
  of the metals, zinc, tin, lead and silver, in proportions that varied as
  times changed, or according to the purposes for which the alloy was
  required. Among bronze remains the copper is found to vary from 67 to
  95%. From the analysis of coins it appears that for their bronze coins
  the Greeks adhered to an alloy of copper and tin till 400 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>, after which time they used also lead with
  increasing frequency. Silver is rare in their bronze coins. The Romans
  also used lead as an alloy in their bronze coins, but gradually reduced
  the quantity, and under Caligula, Nero, Vespasian and Domitian, coined
  pure copper coins; afterwards they reverted to the mixture of lead. So
  far the words <ph outputclass="grk">χαλκός</ph> and <i>aes</i> may be
  translated as bronze. Originally, no doubt, <ph outputclass="grk">χαλκός</ph> was the name for pure
  copper. It is so employed by Homer, who calls it <ph outputclass="grk">ἐρυθρός</ph> (red), <ph outputclass="grk">αἴθυψ</ph>
  (glittering), <ph outputclass="grk">φαεννός</ph> (shining), terms
  which apply only to copper. But instead of its following from this that
  the process of alloying copper with other metals was not practised in the
  time of the poet, or was unknown to him, the contrary would seem to be
  the case from the passage (<i>Iliad</i> xviii. 474) where he describes
  Hephaestus as throwing into his furnace copper, tin, silver and gold to
  make the shield of Achilles, so that it is not always possible to know
  whether when he uses the word <ph outputclass="grk">χαλκός</ph> he means copper pure
  or alloyed. Still more difficult is it to make this distinction when we
  read of the mythical Dactyls of Ida in Crete or the Telchines or Cyclopes
  being acquainted with the smelting of <ph outputclass="grk">χαλκός</ph>. It is not, however,
  likely that later Greek writers, who knew bronze in its true sense, and
  called it <ph outputclass="grk">χαλκός</ph>, would have employed
  this word without qualification for objects which they had seen unless
  they had meant it to be taken as bronze. When Pausanias (iii. 17. 6)
  speaks of a statue, one of the oldest figures he had seen of this
  material, made of separate pieces fastened together with nails, we
  understand him to mean literally bronze, the more readily since there
  exist very early figures and utensils of bronze so made.</p>
      <p>For the use of bronze in art, see <ph outputclass="sc">Metal-work</ph>.</p>
   </body>
</topic>