<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e26655">
   <title>BRUTTII</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUTTII,--> an ancient tribe of lower Italy. This tribe, called
  Bruttii and Brittii in Latin inscriptions, and <ph outputclass="grk">Βρέττιοι</ph> on Greek coins
  and by Greek authors, occupied the south-western peninsula of Italy in
  historical times, the <i>ager Bruttius</i> (wrongly called
  <i>Bruttium</i>) corresponding almost exactly to the modern Calabria. It
  was separated from Lucania on the north by a line drawn from the mouth of
  the river Lāus on the west to a point a little south of the river
  Crathis on the east. To part or the whole of this peninsula the name
  <i>Italia</i> was first applied. In alliance with the Lucanians the
  Bruttii made war on the Greek colonies of the coast and seized on Vibo in
  356 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>, and, though for a time overcome by
  the Greeks who were aided by Alexander of Epirus and Agathocles of
  Syracuse, they reasserted their mastery of the town from about the
  beginning of the 3rd century <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>, and held it
  until it became a Latin colony at the end of the same century (see
  <i>Corp. Inscr. Lat.</i> x. p. 7, and the references there given). At
  this time they were speaking Oscan as well as Greek, and two of three
  Oscan inscriptions in Greek alphabet still testify to the language spoken
  in the town in the 3rd century <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph> We know,
  however, that the Bruttians, though at this date speaking the same
  language (Oscan) as the Samnite tribe of the Lucani, were not actually
  akin to them. The name <i>Bruttii</i> was used by the Lucanians to mean
  "runaway slaves," but it is considerably more likely that this
  signification was attached to the tribal name of the Bruttii from the
  historical fact that they had been conquered and expelled by the Samnite
  invaders (cf. the use of <ph outputclass="grk">Σκύθαι</ph> to mean "policemen" at
  Athens, and still more closely the German, French and English word
  "slave" derived from "Slav"), than that the tribe when living in
  territory it could call its own should have adopted an opprobrious name
  taken from the language of hostile neighbours (see Strabo vi. I, 4; Diod.
  Sic. xvi. 15). Mommsen pointed out (<i>Unterital. Dialekte</i>, p. 97)
  the evidence of tradition (especially Aristotle, <i>Pol</i>. 4 [7] 10)
  showing that the customs of the Bruttii had a certain affinity with those
  of the pre-Hellenic inhabitants of Greece, and it has been argued
  (Ridgeway <i>apud</i> Conway, <i>Ital. Dialects</i>, p. 16) that a
  tradition (preserved in Stephanus of Byzantium, <i>s.v.</i> 
         <ph outputclass="grk">Χῖοι</ph>) made it
  probable that they were called <ph outputclass="grk">Πέλασγοι</ph>. This
  evidence points to the conjecture that they were part of what is now
  generally called the Mediterranean race (see, <i>e.g.</i> G. Sergi,
  <i>The Mediterranean Race</i>, Eng. trans., 1901; W.Z. Ripley, <i>Races
  of Europe</i>, p. 128). Many Indo-European elements appear in their
  place-names (<i>e.g.</i> 
         <i>Sila</i>=Latin <i>silva</i>, Greek <ph outputclass="grk">ὕλη</ph>; <i>Temesa</i>, cf.
  Gr. <ph outputclass="grk">τέμενος</ph> or Sanskrit
  <i>tamas</i>, darkness, shadow), and none that suggest a
  non-Indo-European origin. <i>A priori</i> considerations suggest that
  they may have been akin to the Siceli, but of this at present no positive
  evidence can be given.</p>
      <p>As we have seen, the Bruttii were at the height of their power during
  the 3rd century <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph> Their chief towns were
  Consentia (Cosenza), Petelia (near Strongoli), and Clampetia (Amantea).
  To this period (about the time of the Roman War against Pyrrhus) is to be
  assigned the series of their coins, and they appear to have retained the
  right of coinage even after their final subjugation by the Romans (see
  B.V. Head, <i>Historia Numorum</i>, p. 77). The influence of Hellenism
  over them is shown by finds in the tombs and the fact that they spoke the
  Greek language as well as their own (<i>bilingues</i> in Ennius). The
  mountainous country, ill-suited for agricultural purposes, was well
  adapted for these hardy warriors, whose training was Spartan in its
  simplicity and severity.</p>
      <p>The Bruttii first came into collision with the Romans during the war
  with Pyrrhus, to whom they sent auxiliaries; after his defeat, they
  submitted, and were deprived of half their territory in the Sila forest,
  which was declared state property. In the war with Hannibal, they were
  among the first to declare in his favour after the battle of Cannae, and
  it was in their country that Hannibal held his ground during the last
  stage of the war (at Castrum Hannibalis on the gulf of Scylacium).</p>
      <p>(R. S. C.)</p>
      <p>The Bruttii entirely lost their freedom at the end of the Hannibalic
  war; in 194 colonies of Roman citizens were founded at Tempsa and Croton,
  and a colony with Latin rights at Hipponium called henceforward Vibo
  Valentia. In 132 the consul P. Popillius built the great inland road from
  Capua through Vibo and Consentia to Rhegium, while the date of the
  construction of the east and west coast roads is uncertain. Neither in
  the Social War, nor in the rising of Spartacus, who held out a long time
  in the Sila (71 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>), do the Bruttii play a
  part as a people. Vibo was the naval base of Octavian in the conflict
  with Sextus Pompeius (42-36 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>).</p>
      <p>The most important product of the district was the wood from the
  forests of the Sila, and the pitch produced from it. The Sila also
  contained minerals, which were worked out in very early times. The coast
  plains were in parts very fertile, especially the (now malarious) lower
  valley of the Crathis. Under the empire, however, the whole district
  remained backward and was remarkable for the absence of important towns,
  as the scarcity of ancient inscriptions, both Greek and Latin, shows: the
  Sila was state domain, and most of the rest in the hands of large
  proprietors. Augustus joined it with Lucania (from which it was divided
  by the rivers Laus and Crathis) to form the third region of Italy. In the
  2nd and 3rd centuries, for administrative and juridical purposes, it was
  sometimes (with Lucania) joined to Apulia and Calabria. Diocletian placed
  Lucania and Brittii (as the name was then spelt) under a
  <i>corrector</i>, whose residence was at Rhegium. The boundaries of the
  original third Augustan region had by that time become somewhat altered,
  Metapontum belonging to Calabria, and Salernum and the territory of the
  Picentini to the third region instead of the first (Campania). From the
  6th century, after the fall of <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page696">[v.04 p.0696]</ph>the Ostrogothic power, and the
  establishment of that of Byzantium in its place in south Italy, the name
  Calabria was applied to the whole of the south Italian possessions of the
  Eastern empire, and the name of the Brittii entirely disappeared; and
  after the eastern peninsula (the ancient Calabria) had been taken by the
  Lombards about <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 668, the western retained
  the name, and has kept it till the present day.</p>
      <p>(<ph outputclass="sc">T. As.</ph>)</p>
      <p>See Strabo vi. p. 253-265; Dion. Halic. xx. I, 4, 15; Pliny, <i>Nat.
  Hist.</i> iii. 71-74; Justin xii. 2, xxiii. 1; F. Lenormant, <i>La
  Grande-Grèce</i>, i. (1881-1884); H. Nissen, <i>Italische Landeskunde</i>
  (1883-1902); C. Hulsen in Pauly-Wissowa's <i>Realencyclopädie</i>, iii.
  pt. i. (1897); E.H. Bunbury in Smith's <i>Dictionary of Greek and Roman
  Geography</i>; R.S. Conway, <i>The Italic Dialects</i> (1897), for
  Bruttian inscriptions and local and personal names; P. Orsi in <i>Atti
  del congresso storico</i> (Rome, 1904), v. 193 seq.; M. Schipa, <i>La
  Migrazione del nome Calabria</i> (1895), whose conclusions are summarized
  in J.B. Bury's edition of Gibbon's <i>Decline and Fall</i>, v. p. 24,
  note; other authorities in J. Jung, "Geographie von Italien" (1897) in I.
  Müller's <i>Handbuch der klassischen Altertumswissenschaft</i>, iii.
  Abteilung 3.</p>
   </body>
</topic>