<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e11810">
   <title>BRIENNE-LE-CHÂTEAU</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIENNE-LE-CHÂTEAU,--> a town of north-eastern France, in the
  department of Aube, 1 m. from the right bank of the Aube and 26 m. N.E.
  of Troyes on the Eastern railway. Pop. (1906) 1761. The château, which
  overlooks the town, is an imposing building of the latter half of the
  18th century, built by the cardinal de Brienne (see below). It possesses
  an important collection of pictures, many of them historical portraits of
  the 17th and 18th centuries. The church dates from the 16th century and
  contains good stained glass. A statue of Napoleon commemorates his
  sojourn at Brienne from 1779 to 1784, when he was studying at the
  military school suppressed in 1790. In 1814 Brienne was the scene of
  fighting between Napoleon and the Allies (see <ph outputclass="sc">Napoleonic
  Campaigns</ph>). Brewing is carried on in the town. Brienne-la-Vieille,
  a village 1½ m. south of Brienne-le-Château, has a church of the 12th and
  16th centuries with fine stained windows. The portal once belonged to the
  ancient abbey of Bassefontaine, the ruins of which are situated near the
  village.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Counts of Brienne.</i>—Under the Carolingian dynasty
  Brienne-le-Château was the capital town of a French countship. In the
  10th century it was captured by two adventurers named Engelbert and
  Gobert, and from the first of these sprang the noble house of Brienne. In
  1210 John of Brienne (1148-1237) became king of Jerusalem, through his
  marriage with Mary of Montsserrat, heiress of the kingdom of Jerusalem.
  He led a crusade in Egypt which had no lasting success; and when in 1229
  he was elected emperor of the East, for the period of Baldwin II.'s
  minority, he fought and conquered the Greek emperor John III. (Batatzes
  or Vatatzes). Walter V., count of Brienne and of Lecce (Apulia) and duke
  of Athens, fought against the Greeks and at first drove them from
  Thessaly, but was eventually defeated and killed near Lake Copais in
  1311. His son, Walter VI., after having vainly attempted to reconquer
  Athens in 1331, served under Philip of Valois against the English. Having
  defended Florence against the Pisans he succeeded in obtaining
  dictatorial powers for himself in the republic; but his tyrannical
  conduct brought about his expulsion. He was appointed constable of France
  by John the Good, and was killed at the battle of Poitiers in 1356. His
  sister and heiress Isabelle married Walter of Enghien, and so brought
  Brienne to the house of Enghien, and, by his marriage with Margaret of
  Enghien, John of Luxemburg-St Pol (d. about 1397) became count of
  Brienne. The house of Luxemburg retained the countship until Margaret
  Charlotte of Luxemburg sold it to a certain Marpon, who ceded it to Henri
  Auguste de Loménie (whose wife, Louise de Béon, descended from the house
  of Luxemburg-Brienne) in 1640. The Limousin house of Loménie (the
  genealogies which trace this family to the 15th century are
  untrustworthy) produced many well-known statesmen, among others the
  celebrated cardinal Étienne Charles de Loménie de Brienne (1727-1794),
  minister of Louis XV.; and the last lords of Brienne were members of this
  family.</p>
      <p>(M. P.*)</p>
   </body>
</topic>