<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25813">
   <title>BRUNHILDA</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNHILDA--> (Brunechildis), queen of Austrasia (d. 613), was a
  daughter of Athanagild, king of the Visigoths. In 567 she was asked in
  marriage by Sigebert, who was reigning at Metz. She now abjured Arianism
  and was converted to the orthodox faith, and the union was celebrated at
  Metz; on which occasion Fortunatus, an Italian poet, who was then at the
  Frankish court, composed the epithalamium. Chilperic, brother of
  Sigebert, and king of the west Frankish kingdom, jealous of the renown
  which this marriage brought to his elder brother, hastened to ask the
  hand of Galswintha, sister of Brunhilda; but at the instigation of his
  mistress Fredegond, he assassinated his wife. Sigebert was anxious to
  avenge his sister-in-law, but on the intervention of Guntram, he accepted
  the compensation offered by Chilperic, namely the cities of Bordeaux,
  Cahors and Limoges, with Béarn and Bigorre.</p>
      <p>This treaty did not prevent war soon again breaking out between
  Sigebert and Chilperic. So long as her husband lived, Brunhilda played a
  secondary part, but having been made captive by Chilperic after her
  husband's assassination (575), she succeeded in escaping from her prison
  at Rouen, after a series of extraordinary adventures, by means of a
  marriage with Merovech, the son of her conqueror. From this time on, she
  took the lead; in Austrasia she engaged in a desperate struggle against
  the nobles, who wished to govern in the name of her son Childebert II.;
  but she was worsted in the conflict and for some time had to seek refuge
  in Burgundy. After the death of Childebert II. (597) she aspired to
  govern Austrasia and Burgundy in the name of her grandsons Theudebert and
  Theuderich II. She was expelled from Austrasia, and then stirred up
  Theuderich II. against his brother, whom he defeated at Toul and Tolbiac,
  and put to death. Theuderich II. died shortly after this victory, and
  Brunhilda caused one of her great-grandchildren to be proclaimed king.
  The nobles of Austrasia and Burgundy, however, now summoned Clotaire II.,
  son of Fredegond, and king of Neustria, to help them against the queen.
  Brunhilda was given up to him, and died a terrible death, being dragged
  at the heels of a wild horse (613).</p>
      <p>Brunhilda seems to have had political ideas, and to have wished to
  attain to the royal power. She was a protectress of the Church, and Pope
  Gregory I. (590-604) addressed a series of letters to her, in which he
  showered praises upon her. She took it upon herself, however, to
  supervise the bishoprics and monasteries, and came into conflict with
  Columban (Columbanus), abbot of Luxeuil. As Brunhilda was a great queen,
  tradition ascribes to her the construction of many old castles, and a
  number of old Roman roads are also known by the name of <i>Chaussées de
  Brunehaut</i>.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Authorities</ph>.—Gregory of Tours,
  <i>Historia Francorum</i>, bks. iv.-x.; the so-called <i>Chronicle of
  Fredegarius</i>; Aug. Thierry, <i>Récits des temps mérovingiens</i> (2
  vols., Paris, 8th ed., 1864); G. Kurth, "La Reine Brunehaut," in the
  <i>Revue des questions historiques</i>, vol. xxvi. (1891).</p>
      <p>(<ph outputclass="sc">C. Pf.</ph>)</p>
   </body>
</topic>