<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12624">
   <title>BRIQUEMAULT</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIQUEMAULT--> (or <ph outputclass="sc">Briquemaut</ph>),
  <b>FRANÇOIS DE BEAUVAIS,</b> 
         <ph outputclass="sc">Seigneur de</ph>
  (<i>c.</i> 1502-1572), leader of the Huguenots during the first religious
  wars, was the son of Adrien de Briquemault and Alexane de Sainte Ville,
  and was born about 1502. His first campaign was under the count of
  Brissac in the Piedmontese wars. On his return to France in 1554 he
  joined Admiral Coligny. Charged with the defence of Rouen, in 1562, he
  resigned in favour of Montgomery, to whom the prince of Condé had
  entrusted the task, and went over to England, where he concluded the
  treaty of Hampton Court on the 20th of September. He then returned to
  France, and took Dieppe from the Catholics before the conclusion of
  peace. If his share in the second religious war was less important, he
  played a very active part in the third. He fought at Jarnac,
  Roche-Abeille and Montcontour, assisted in the siege of Poitiers, was
  nearly captured by the Catholics at Bourg-Dieu, re-victualled Vézelay,
  and almost surprised Bourges. In 1570, being charged by Coligny to stop
  the army of the princes in its ascent of the Rhone valley, he crossed
  Burgundy and effected his junction with the admiral at St. Étienne in
  May. On the 21st of the following June he assisted in achieving the
  victory of Arnay-le-Duc, and was then employed to negotiate a marriage
  between the prince of Navarre and Elizabeth of England. Being in Paris on
  the night of St Bartholomew he took refuge in the house of the English
  ambassador, but was arrested there. With his friend Arnaud da Cavagnes he
  was delivered over to the parlement, and failed in courage when
  confronted with his judges, seeking to escape death by unworthy means. He
  was condemned, nevertheless, on the 27th of October 1572, to the last
  penalty and to the confiscation of his property, and on the 29th of
  October he and Cavagnes were executed.</p>
      <p>See <i>Histoire ecclésiastique des Églises réformées au royaume de
  France</i> (new edition, 1884), vol. ii.; <i>La France protestante</i>
  (2nd edition), vol. ii., article "Beauvais."</p>
   </body>
</topic>