<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e20222">
   <title>BROGLIE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROGLIE, DE,--> the name of a noble French family which,
  originally Piedmontese, emigrated to France in the year 1643. The head of
  the family, <ph outputclass="sc">François Marie</ph> (1611-1656), then took
  the title of comte de Broglie. He had already distinguished himself as a
  soldier, and died, as a lieutenant-general, at the siege of Valenza on
  the 2nd of July 1656. His son, <ph outputclass="sc">Victor Maurice, Comte de
  Broglie</ph> (1647-1727), served under Condé, Turenne and other great
  commanders of the age of Louis XIV., becoming <i>maréchal de camp</i> in
  1676, lieutenant-general in 1688, and finally marshal of France in
  1724.</p>
      <p>The eldest son of Victor Marie, <ph outputclass="sc">François
  Marie</ph>, afterwards <ph outputclass="sc">Duc de Broglie</ph>
  (1671-1745), entered the army at an early age, and had a varied career of
  active service before he was made, at the age of twenty-three,
  lieutenant-colonel of the king's regiment of cavalry. He served
  continuously in the War of the Spanish Succession and was present at
  Malplaquet. He was made lieutenant-general in 1710, and served with
  Villars in the last campaign of the war and at the battle of Denain.
  During the peace he continued in military employment, and in 1719 he was
  made director-general of cavalry and dragoons. He was also employed in
  diplomatic missions, and was ambassador in England in 1724. The war in
  Italy called him into the field again in 1733, and in the following year
  he was made marshal of France. In the campaign of 1734 he was one of the
  chief commanders on the French side, and he fought the battles of Parma
  and Guastalla. A famous episode was his narrow personal escape when his
  quarters on the Secchia were raided by the enemy on the night of the 14th
  of September 1734. In 1735 he directed a war of positions with credit,
  but he was soon replaced by Marshal de Noailles. He was governor-general
  of Alsace when Frederick the Great paid a secret visit to Strassburg
  (1740). In 1742 de Broglie was appointed to command the French army in
  Germany, but such powers as he had possessed were failing him, and he had
  always been the "man of small means," safe and cautious, but lacking in
  elasticity and daring. The only success obtained was in the action of
  Sahay (25th May 1742), for which he was made a duke. He returned to
  France in 1743, and died two years later.</p>
      <p>His son, <ph outputclass="sc">Victor François, Duc de Broglie</ph>
  (1718-1804), served with his father at Parma and Guastalla, and in 1734
  obtained a colonelcy. In the German War he took part in the storming of
  Prague in 1742, and was made a brigadier. In 1744 and 1745 he saw further
  service on the Rhine, and in 1756 he was made <i>maréchal de camp</i>. He
  subsequently served with Marshal Saxe in the low countries, and was
  present at Roucoux, Val and Maastricht. At the end of the war he was made
  a lieutenant-general. During the Seven Years' War he served successively
  under d'Estrées, Soubise and Contades, being present at all the battles
  from Hastenbeck onwards. His victory over Prince Ferdinand at Bergen
  (1759) won him the rank of marshal of France from his own sovereign and
  that of prince of the empire from the emperor Francis I. In 1760 he won
  an action at Corbach, but was defeated at Vellinghausen in 1761. After
  the war he fell into disgrace and was not recalled to active employment
  until 1778, when he was given command of the troops designed to operate
  against England. He played a prominent part in the Revolution, which he
  opposed with determination. After his emigration, de Broglie commanded
  the "army of the princes" for a short time (1792). He died at Münster in
  1804.</p>
      <p>Another son of the first duke, <ph outputclass="sc">Charles François,
  Comte de Broglie</ph> (1719-1781), served for some years in the army,
  and afterwards became one of the foremost diplomatists in the service of
  Louis XV. He is chiefly remembered in connexion with the <i>Secret du
  Roi</i>, the private, as distinct from the official, diplomatic service
  of Louis, of which he was the ablest and most important member. The son
  of Victor François, <ph outputclass="sc">Victor Claude, Prince de
  Broglie</ph> (1757-1794), served in the army, attaining the rank of
  <i>maréchal de camp</i>. He adopted revolutionary opinions, served with
  Lafayette and Rochambeau in America, was a member of the Jacobin Club,
  and sat in the Constituent Assembly, constantly voting on the Liberal
  side. He served as chief of the staff to the Republican army on the
  Rhine; but in the Terror he was denounced, arrested and executed at Paris
  on the 27th of June 1794. His dying admonition to his little son was to
  remain <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page627">[v.04
  p.0627]</ph>faithful to the principles of the Revolution, however
  unjust and ungrateful.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Achille Charles Léonce Victor, Duc de Broglie</ph>
  (1785-1870), statesman and diplomatist, son of the last-named, was born
  at Paris on the 28th of November 1785. His mother had shared her
  husband's imprisonment, but managed to escape to Switzerland, where she
  remained till the fall of Robespierre. She now returned to Paris with her
  children and lived there quietly until 1796, when she married a M.
  d'Argenson, grandson of Louis XV.'s minister of war. Under the care of
  his step-father young de Broglie received a careful and liberal education
  and made his entrée into the aristocratic and literary society of Paris
  under the Empire. In 1809, he was appointed a member of the council of
  state, over which Napoleon presided in person; and was sent by the
  emperor on diplomatic missions, as attaché, to various countries. Though
  he had never been in sympathy with the principles of the Empire, de
  Broglie was not one of those who rejoiced at its downfall. In common with
  all men of experience and sense he realized the danger to France of the
  rise to power of the forces of violent reaction. With Decazes and
  Richelieu he saw that the only hope for a calm future lay in "the
  reconciliation of the Restoration with the Revolution." By the influence
  of his uncle, Prince Amédée de Broglie, his right to a peerage had been
  recognized; and to his own great surprise he received, in June 1814, a
  summons from Louis XVIII. to the Chamber of Peers. There, after the
  Hundred Days, he distinguished himself by his courageous defence of
  Marshal Ney, for whose acquittal he, alone of all the peers, both spoke
  and voted. After this defiant act of opposition it was perhaps fortunate
  that his impending marriage gave him an excuse for leaving the country.
  On the 15th of February 1816, he was married at Leghorn to the daughter
  of Madame de Staël. He returned to Paris at the end of the year, but took
  no part in politics until the elections of September 1817 broke the power
  of the "ultra-royalists" and substituted for the <i>Chambre
  introuvable</i> a moderate assembly. De Broglie's political attitude
  during the years that followed is best summed up in his own words: "From
  1812 to 1822 all the efforts of men of sense and character were directed
  to reconciling the Restoration and the Revolution, the old régime and the
  new France. From 1822 to 1827 all their efforts were directed to
  resisting the growing power of the counter-revolution. From 1827 to 1830
  all their efforts aimed at moderating and regulating the reaction in a
  contrary sense." During the last critical years of Charles X.'s reign, de
  Broglie identified himself with the <i>doctrinaires</i>, among whom
  Royer-Collard and Guizot were the most prominent. The July revolution
  placed him in a difficult position; he knew nothing of the intrigues
  which placed Louis Philippe on the throne; but, the revolution once
  accomplished, he was ready to uphold the <i>fait accompli</i> with
  characteristic loyalty, and on the 9th of August took office in the new
  government as minister of public worship and education. As he had
  foreseen, the ministry was short-lived, and on the 2nd of November he was
  once more out of office. During the critical time that followed he
  consistently supported the principles which triumphed with the fall of
  Laffitte and the accession to power of Casimir Périer in March 1832.
  After the death of the latter and the insurrection of June 1832, de
  Broglie took office once more as minister for foreign affairs (October
  11th). His tenure of the foreign office was coincident with a very
  critical period in international relations. But for the sympathy of Great
  Britain under Palmerston, the July monarchy would have been completely
  isolated in Europe; and this sympathy the aggressive policy of France in
  Belgium and on the Mediterranean coast of Africa had been in danger of
  alienating. The Belgian crisis had been settled, so far as the two powers
  were concerned, before de Broglie took office; but the concerted military
  and naval action for the coercion of the Dutch, which led to the French
  occupation of Antwerp, was carried out under his auspices. The good
  understanding of which this was the symbol characterized also the
  relations of de Broglie and Palmerston during the crisis of the first war
  of Mehemet Ali (<i>q.v.</i>) with the Porte, and in the affairs of the
  Spanish peninsula their common sympathy with constitutional liberty led
  to an agreement for common action, which took shape in the treaty of
  alliance between Great Britain, France, Spain and Portugal, signed at
  London on the 22nd of April 1834. De Broglie had retired from office in
  the March preceding, and did not return to power till March of the
  following year, when he became head of the cabinet. In 1836, the
  government having been defeated on a proposal to reduce the five per
  cents, he once more resigned, and never returned to official life. He had
  remained in power long enough to prove what honesty of purpose,
  experience of affairs, and common sense can accomplish when allied with
  authority. The debt that France and Europe owed him may be measured by
  comparing the results of his policy with that of his successors under not
  dissimilar circumstances. He had found France isolated and Europe full of
  the rumours of war; he left her strong in the English alliance and the
  respect of Liberal Europe, and Europe freed from the restless
  apprehensions which were to be stirred into life again by the attitude of
  Thiers in the Eastern Question and of Guizot in the affair of the
  "Spanish marriages." From 1836 to 1848 de Broglie held almost completely
  aloof from politics, to which his scholarly temperament little inclined
  him, a disinclination strengthened by the death of his wife on the 22nd
  of September 1838. His friendship for Guizot, however, induced him to
  accept a temporary mission in 1845, and in 1847 to go as French
  ambassador to London. The revolution of 1848 was a great blow to him, for
  he realized that it meant the final ruin of the Liberal monarchy—in
  his view the political system best suited to France. He took his seat,
  however, in the republican National Assembly and in the Convention of
  1848, and, as a member of the section known as the "Burgraves," did his
  best to stem the tide of socialism and to avert the reaction in favour of
  autocracy which he foresaw. He shared with his colleagues the indignity
  of the <i>coup d'état</i> of the 2nd of December 1851, and remained for
  the remainder of his life one of the bitterest enemies of the imperial
  regime, though he was heard to remark, with that caustic wit for which he
  was famous, that the empire was "the government which the poorer classes
  in France desired and the rich deserved." The last twenty years of his
  life were devoted chiefly to philosophical and literary pursuits. Having
  been brought up by his step-father in the sceptical opinions of the time,
  he gradually arrived at a sincere belief in the Christian religion. "I
  shall die," said he, "a penitent Christian and an impenitent Liberal."
  His literary works, though few of them have been published, were rewarded
  in 1856 by a seat in the French Academy, and he was also a member of
  another branch of the French Institute, the Academy of Moral and
  Political Science. In the labours of those learned bodies he took an
  active and assiduous part. He died on the 25th of January 1870.</p>
      <p>Besides his <i>Souvenirs</i>, in 4 vols. (Paris, 1885-1888), the duc
  de Broglie left numerous works, of which only some have been published.
  Of these may be mentioned <i>Écrits et discours</i> (3 vols., Paris,
  1863); <i>Le Libre Échange et l'impôt</i> (Paris, 1879); <i>Vues sur le
  gouvernement de la France</i> (Paris, 1861). This last was confiscated
  before publication by the imperial government. See Guizot, <i>Le Duc de
  Broglie</i> (Paris, 1870), and <i>Mémoires</i> (Paris, 1858-1867); and
  the histories of Thureau-Dangin and Duvergier de Hauranne.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Jacques Victor Albert, Duc de Broglie</ph>
  (1821-1901), his eldest son, was born at Paris on the 13th of June 1821.
  After a brief diplomatic career at Madrid and Rome, the revolution of
  1848 caused him to withdraw from public life and devote himself to
  literature. He had already published a translation of the religious
  system of Leibnitz (1846). He now at once made his mark by his
  contributions to the <i>Revue des deux Mondes</i> and the Orleanist and
  clerical organ <i>Le Correspondant</i>, which were afterwards collected
  under the titles of <i>Études morales et littéraires</i> (1853) and
  <i>Questions de religion et d'histoire</i> (1860). These were
  supplemented in 1869 by a volume of <i>Nouvelles études de littérature et
  de morale</i>. His <i>L'Église et l'empire romain au IVe siècle</i>
  (1856-1866) brought him the succession to Lacordaire's seat in the
  Academy in 1862. In 1870 he succeeded his father in the dukedom, having
  previously been known as the prince de Broglie. In the following year he
  was elected to the National <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page628">[v.04 p.0628]</ph>Assembly for the department of the
  Eure, and a few days later (on the 19th of February) was appointed
  ambassador in London; but in March 1872, in consequence of criticisms
  upon his negotiations concerning the commercial treaties between England
  and France, he resigned his post and took his seat in the National
  Assembly, where he became the leading spirit of the monarchical campaign
  against Thiers. On the replacement of the latter by Marshal MacMahon, the
  duc de Broglie became president of the council and minister for foreign
  affairs (May 1873), but in the reconstruction of the ministry on the 26th
  of November, after the passing of the septennate, transferred himself to
  the ministry of the interior. His tenure of office was marked by an
  extreme conservatism, which roused the bitter hatred of the Republicans,
  while he alienated the Legitimist party by his friendly relations with
  the Bonapartists, and the Bonapartists by an attempt to effect a
  compromise between the rival claimants to the monarchy. The result was
  the fall of the cabinet on the 16th of May 1874. Three years later (on
  the 16th of May 1877) he was entrusted with the formation of a new
  cabinet, with the object of appealing to the country and securing a new
  chamber more favourable to the reactionaries than its predecessor had
  been. The result, however, was a decisive Republican majority. The duc de
  Broglie was defeated in his own district, and resigned office on the 20th
  of November. Not being re-elected in 1885, he abandoned politics and
  reverted to his historical work, publishing a series of historical
  studies and biographies written in a most pleasing style, and especially
  valuable for their extensive documentation. He died in Paris on the 19th
  of January 1901.</p>
      <p>Besides editing the <i>Souvenirs</i> of his father (1886, &amp;c.),
  the <i>Mémoires</i> of Talleyrand (1891, &amp;c.), and the <i>Letters</i>
  of the Duchess Albertine de Broglie (1896), he published <i>Le Secret du
  roi, Correspondance secrète de Louis XV avec ses agents diplomatiques,
  1752-1774</i> (1878); <i>Frédéric II et Marie Thérèse</i> (1883);
  <i>Frédéric II et Louis XV</i> (1885); <i>Marie Thérèse Impératrice</i>
  (1888); <i>Le Père Lacordaire</i> (1889); <i>Maurice de Saxe et le
  marquis d'Argenson</i> (1891); <i>La Paix d'Aix-la-Chapelle</i> (1892);
  <i>L'Alliance autrichienne</i> (1895); <i>La Mission de M. de
  Gontaut-Biron à Berlin</i> (1896); <i>Voltaire avant et pendant la Guerre
  de Sept Ans</i> (1898); <i>Saint Ambroise</i>, translated by Margaret
  Maitland in the series of "The Saints" (1899).</p>
   </body>
</topic>