<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e24955">
   <title>BRUCE, ALEXANDER BALMAIN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUCE, ALEXANDER BALMAIN--> (1831-1899), Scottish divine, was born
  at Aberargie near Perth on the 31st of January 1831. His father suffered
  for his adherence to the Free Church at the Disruption in 1843, and
  removed to Edinburgh, where the son was educated, showing exceptional
  ability from the first. His early religious doubts, awakened especially
  by Strauss's <i>Life of Jesus</i>, made him throughout life sympathetic
  with those who underwent a similar stress. After serving as assistant
  first at Ancrum, then at Lochwinnoch, he was called to Cardross in
  Dumbartonshire in 1859, and to Broughty Ferry in 1868. There he published
  his first considerable exegetical work, the <i>Training of the
  Twelve</i>. In 1874 he delivered his Cunningham Lectures, afterwards
  published as <i>The Humiliation of Christ</i>, and in the following year
  was appointed to the chair of Apologetics and New Testament exegesis at
  the Free Church College, Glasgow. This post he held for twenty-four
  years. He was one of the first British New Testament students whose work
  was received with consideration by German scholars of repute. The
  character and work of Christ were, he held, the ultimate proof and the
  best defence of Christianity; and his tendency was to concentrate
  attention somewhat narrowly on the historic Jesus. In <i>The Kingdom of
  God</i> (1889), which first encountered serious hostile criticism in his
  own communion, he accounted for some of the differences between the first
  and third evangelists on the principle of accommodation—maintaining
  that Luke had altered both the text and the spirit of his sources to suit
  the needs of those for whom he wrote. It was held that these admissions
  were not consistent with the views of inspiration professed by the Free
  Church. When the case was tried, the assembly held that the charge of
  heresy was based on a misunderstanding, but that "by want of due care in
  his mode of statement he had given some ground for the painful
  impressions which had existed."</p>
      <p>Bruce rendered signal service to his own communion in connexion with
  its service of praise. He was convener of the committee which issued the
  Free Church hymn book, and he threw into this work the same energy and
  catholicity of mind which marked the rest of his activities. He died on
  the 7th of August 1899, and was buried at Broughty Ferry. His chief
  works, beside the above, are: <i>The Chief End of Revelation</i> (Lond.,
  1881); <i>The Parabolic Teaching of Christ</i> (Lond., 1882); <i>F.C.
  Baur and his Theory of the Origin of Christianity and of the <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page676">[v.04
  p.0676]</ph>New Testament Writings</i> in "Present Day Tracts" (Lond.,
  1885); <i>Apologetics, or Christianity Defensively Stated</i> (Edin.,
  1892); <i>St Paul's Conception of Christianity</i> (Lond., 1894);
  <i>Expos. Gk. Test.</i> (the Synoptic Gospels, Lond., 1897). <i>With Open
  Face</i> (Lond., 1896); <i>The Epistle to the Hebrews</i> (Edin., 1899);
  <i>The Providential Order of the World</i>, and the <i>Moral Order of the
  World in Ancient and Modern Thought</i> (Gifford Lectures, 1896-1897;
  Lond., 1897, 1899).</p>
      <p>(<ph outputclass="sc">D. Mn.</ph>)</p>
   </body>
</topic>