<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e21369">
   <title>BRONSART VON SCHELLENDORF, PAUL</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRONSART VON SCHELLENDORF, PAUL--> (1832-1891), Prussian general,
  was born at Danzig in 1832. He entered the Prussian Guards in 1849, and
  was appointed to the general staff in 1861 as a captain; after three
  years of staff service he returned to regimental duty, but was soon
  reappointed to the staff, and lectured at the war academy, becoming major
  in 1865 and lieut.-colonel in 1869. During the war of 1870 he was chief
  of a section on the Great General Staff, and conducted the preliminary
  negotiations for the surrender of the French at Sedan. After the war
  Bronsart was made a colonel and chief of staff of the Guard army corps,
  becoming major-general in 1876 and lieut.-general (with a division
  command) in 1881. Two years later he became war minister, and during his
  tenure of the post (1883-1889) many important reforms were carried out in
  the Prussian army, in particular the introduction of the magazine rifle.
  He was appointed in 1889 to command the I. army corps at Königsberg. He
  died on the 23rd of June 1891 at his estate near Braunsberg. Bronsart's
  military writings include two works of great importance—<i>Ein
  Rückblick auf die taktischen Ruckblicke</i> (2nd ed., Berlin, 1870), a
  pamphlet written in reply to Captain May's <i>Tactical Retrospect of
  1866</i>; and <i>Der Dienst des Generalstabes</i> (1st ed., Berlin, 1876;
  3rd ed. revised by General Meckel, 1893; new ed. by the author's son,
  Major Bronsart von Schellendorf, Berlin, 1904), a comprehensive treatise
  on the duties of the general staff. The third edition of this work was
  soon after its publication translated into English and issued officially
  to the British army as <i>The Duties of the General Staff</i>. Major
  Bronsart's new edition of 1904 was reissued in English by the General
  Staff, under the same title, in 1905.</p>
   </body>
</topic>