<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22693">
   <title>BROSSES, CHARLES DE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROSSES, CHARLES DE--> (1709-1777), French magistrate and scholar,
  was born at Dijon and studied law with a view to the magistracy. The bent
  of his mind, however, was towards literature and science, and, after a
  visit to Italy in 1739 in company with his friend Jean Baptiste de
  Lacurne de Sainte-Palaye, he published his <i>Lettres sur l'état actuel
  de la mile souterraine d'Herculée</i> (Dijon, 1750), the first work upon
  the ruins of Herculaneum. It was during this Italian tour that he wrote
  his famous letters on Italy, which remained in MS. till long after his
  death. In 1760 he published a dissertation, <i>Du culte des dieux
  fétiches</i>, which was afterwards inserted in the <i>Encyclopédie
  méthodique</i>. At the solicitation of his friend Buffon, he undertook
  his <i>Histoire des navigations aux terres australes</i>, which was
  published in 1756, in two vols. 4to, with maps. It was in this work that
  de Brosses first laid down the geographical divisions of Australasia and
  Polynesia, which were afterwards adopted by John Pinkerton and succeeding
  geographers. He also contributed to the <i>Encyclopédie</i> the articles
  "Langues," "Musique," "Étymologic." In 1765 appeared his work on the
  origin of language, <i>Traite de la formation mécanique des langues</i>,
  the merits of which are recognized by E. B. Tylor in <i>Primitive
  Culture</i>. De Brosses had been occupied, during a great part of his
  life, on a translation of Sallust, and in attempting to supply the lost
  chapters in that celebrated historian. At length in 1777 he published
  <i>L'Histoire du septième siècle de la république romaine</i>, 3 vols.
  4to, to which is prefixed a learned life of Sallust, reprinted at the
  commencement of the translation of that historian by Jean Baptiste Dureau
  de La Malle. These literary occupations did not prevent the author from
  discharging with ability his official duties as first president of the
  parliament of Burgundy, nor from carrying on a constant and extensive
  correspondence with the most distinguished literary characters of his
  time. In 1758 he succeeded the marquis de Caumont in the Académie des
  Belles-lettres; but when in 1770 he presented himself at the French
  Academy, his candidature was rejected owing to Voltaire's opposition on
  personal grounds. Besides the works already mentioned, he wrote several
  memoirs and dissertations in the collections of the Academy of
  Inscriptions, and in those of the Academy of Dijon, and he left behind
  him several MSS., which were unfortunately lost during the Revolution.
  His letters on Italy were, however, found in MS. in the confiscated
  library by his son, the <i>émigré</i> officer René de Brosses, and were
  first published in 1799, in the uncritical edition of Antoine Serieys,
  under the title of <i>Lettres historiques et critiques</i>. A fresh
  edition, freed from errors and interpolations, by R. Colomb, with the
  title <i>L'Italie il y a cent ans</i>, was issued in 1836; and two
  subsequent reprints appeared, one edited by Poulet-Malassis, under the
  title <i>Lettres familières</i> (1858); the other, a re-impression of
  Colomb's edition, under that of <i>Le Président de Brosses en Italic</i>
  (1858).</p>
      <p>See H. Mamet, <i>Le President de Brosses, sa vie et ses ouvrages</i>
  (Lille, 1874); also Cunisset-Carnot, "La Querelle de Voltaire et du
  président de Brosses," in the <i>Revue des Deux Mondes</i> (February 15,
  1888).</p>
   </body>
</topic>