<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23098">
   <title>BROUGHTON, HUGH</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROUGHTON, HUGH--> (1549-1612), English scholar and divine, was
  born at Owlbury, Bishop's Castle, Shropshire, in 1549. He was educated by
  Bernard Gilpin at Houghton-le-Spring and at Cambridge, where he became
  fellow of St John's and then of Christ's, and took orders. Here he laid
  the foundation of the Hebrew scholarship for which he was afterwards so
  distinguished. From Cambridge he went to London, where his eloquence
  gained him many and powerful friends. In 1588 he published his first
  work, "a little book of great pains," entitled <i>A Concent of
  Scripture</i>. This work, dealing with biblical chronology and textual
  criticism, was attacked at both universities, and the author was obliged
  to defend it in a series of lectures. In 1589 he went to Germany, where
  he frequently engaged in discussions both with Romanists and with the
  learned Jews whom he met at Frankfort and elsewhere. In 1591 he returned
  to England, but his Puritan leanings incurred the hostility of Whitgift.
  Accordingly in 1592 he once more went abroad, and cultivated the
  acquaintance of the principal scholars of Europe, including Scaligeri and
  Rabbi Elias. Such was the esteem in which he was held, even by his
  opponents, that he might have had a cardinal's hat if he had been willing
  to change his faith. In 1599 he published his "Explication" of the
  article "He descended into hell," in which he maintained that Hades means
  simply the abode of departed spirits, not the place of torment. On the
  accession of James he returned to England; but not being engaged to
  co-operate in the new translation of the Bible (though he had for some
  years planned a similar work), he retired to Middleburg in Holland, where
  he preached to the English congregation. In 1611 he returned to England,
  where he died on the 4th of August 1612.</p>
      <p>Some of his works were collected and published in a large folio volume
  in 1662, with a sketch of his life by John Lightfoot, but many of his
  theological MSS. remain still unedited in the British Museum.</p>
   </body>
</topic>