<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25140">
   <title>BRUCH, MAX</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUCH, MAX--> (1838- ), German musical composer, son of a city
  official and grandson of the famous Evangelical cleric, Dr Christian
  Bruch, was born at Cologne on the 6th of January 1838. From his mother
  (<i>née</i> Almenräder), a well-known musician of her time, he learnt the
  elements of music, but under Breidenstein he made his first serious
  effort at composition at the age of fourteen, by the production of a
  symphony. In 1853 Bruch gained the Mozart Stipendium of 400 gulden per
  annum for four years at Frankfort-on-Main, and for the following few
  years studied under Hiller, Reinecke and Breunung. Subsequently he lived
  from 1858 to 1861 as pianoforte teacher at Cologne, in which city his
  first opera (in one act), <i>Scherz, List und Roche</i>, was produced in
  1858. On his father's death in 1861, Bruch began a tour of study at
  Berlin, Leipzig, Vienna, Munich, Dresden and Mannheim, where his opera
  <i>Lorelei</i> was brought out in 1863. At Mannheim he lived till 1864,
  and there he wrote some of his best-known works, including the beautiful
  <i>Frithjof</i>. After a further period of travel he became
  musical-director at Coblenz (1865-1867), Hofkapellmeister at
  Sondershausen (1867-1870), and lived in Berlin (1871-1873), where he
  wrote his <i>Odysseus</i>, his first violin concerto and two symphonies
  being composed at Sondershausen. After five years at Bonn (1873-1878),
  during which he made two visits to England, Bruch, in 1878, became
  conductor of the Stern Choral Union; and in 1880 of the Liverpool
  Philharmonic. In 1892 he was appointed director of the Berlin Hochschule.
  In 1893 he was given the honorary degree of Mus. Doc. by Cambridge
  University. Max Bruch has written in almost every conceivable musical
  form, invariably with straight-forward honest simplicity of design. He
  has a gift of refined melody beyond the common, his melodies being broad
  and suave and often exceptionally beautiful.</p>
   </body>
</topic>