<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12129">
   <title>BRIGGS, CHARLES AUGUSTUS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIGGS, CHARLES AUGUSTUS--> (1841- ), American Hebrew scholar and
  theologian, was born in New York City on the 15th of January 1841. He was
  educated at the university of Virginia (1857-1860), graduated at the
  Union Theological Seminary in 1863, and studied further at the university
  of Berlin. He was pastor of the Presbyterian church of Roselle, New
  Jersey, 1869-1874, and professor of Hebrew and cognate languages in Union
  Theological Seminary 1874-1891, and of Biblical theology there from 1891
  to 1904, when he became professor of theological encyclopaedia and
  symbolics. From 1880 to 1890 he was an editor of the <i>Presbyterian
  Review</i>. In 1892 he was tried for heresy by the presbytery of New York
  and acquitted. The charges were based upon his inaugural address of the
  preceding year. In brief they were as follows: that he had taught that
  reason and the Church are each a "fountain of divine authority which
  apart from Holy Scripture may and does savingly enlighten men"; that
  "errors may have existed in the original text of the Holy Scripture";
  that "many of the Old Testament predictions have been reversed by
  history" and that "the great body of Messianic prediction has not and
  cannot be fulfilled"; that "Moses is not the author of the Pentateuch,"
  and that "Isaiah is not the author of half of the book which bears his
  name"; that "the processes of redemption extend to the world to
  come"—he had considered it a fault of Protestant theology that it
  limits redemption to this world—and that "sanctification is not
  complete at death." The general assembly, to which the case was appealed,
  suspended Dr Briggs in 1893, being influenced, it would seem, in part, by
  the manner and tone of his expressions—by what his own colleagues
  in the Union Theological Seminary called the "dogmatic and irritating"
  nature of his inaugural address. He was ordained a priest of the
  Protestant Episcopal Church in 1899. His scholarship procured for him the
  honorary degree of D.D. from Edinburgh (1884) and from Glasgow (1901),
  and that of Litt.D. from Oxford (1901). With S.R. Driver and Francis
  Brown he prepared a revised <i>Hebrew and English Lexicon</i>
  (1891-1905), and with Driver edited the "International Commentary
  Series." His publications include <i>Biblical Study: Its Principles,
  Methods and History</i> (1883); <i>Hebrew Poems of the Creation</i>
  (1884); <i>American Presbyterianism: Its Origin and Early History</i>
  (1885); <i>Messianic Prophecy</i> (1886); <i>Whither? A Theological
  Question for the Times</i> (1889); <i>The Authority of the Holy
  Scripture</i> (1891); <i>The Bible, the Church and the Reason</i> (1892);
  <i>The Higher Criticism of the Hexateuch</i> (1893); <i>The Messiah of
  the Gospels</i> (1804), <i>The Messiah of the Apostles</i> (1894); <i>New
  Light on the Life of Jesus</i> (1904); <i>The Ethical Teaching of
  Jesus</i> (1904); <i>A Critical and Exegetical Commentary on the Book of
  Psalms</i> (2 vols., 1906-1907), in which he was assisted by his
  daughter; and <i>The Virgin Birth of Our Lord</i> (1909).</p>
   </body>
</topic>