<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25862">
   <title>BRÜNN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRÜNN--> (Czech <i>Brno</i>), the capital of the Austrian
  margraviate and crownland of Moravia, 89 m. N. of Vienna by rail. Pop.
  (1900) 108,944, of whom 70% are Germans and 30% are Czechs. Brünn is
  situated for the most part between two hills at the confluence of the
  Schwarzawa and the Zwittawa, and consists of <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page685">[v.04 p.0685]</ph>the old town
  and extensive suburbs. On one of the hills, known as the Spielberg (945
  ft.), stands a castle which has long been used as a prison, famous for
  its connexion with Silvio Pellico, who was confined within its walls from
  1822 to 1830. The fortifications of the old town have now been entirely
  removed, giving place to handsome gardens and well-built streets, which
  put it in communication with its adjoining suburbs. The old town,
  although comparatively small, with narrow and crooked but well-paved
  streets, contains the most important buildings in the city. The Rathaus,
  which dates from 1511, has a fine Gothic portal, and contains several
  interesting antiquities. The ecclesiastical buildings comprise the
  cathedral of St Peter, situated on the lower hill; the fine Gothic church
  of St Jacob, built in the 15th century, with its iron tower added in
  1845, and a remarkable collection of early prints; the church of the
  Augustinian friars, dating from the 14th century; and that of the
  Minorites, with its frescoes, its holy stair and its Loretto-house.
  Amongst the new buildings are the hall of the provincial diet, opened in
  1881; a handsome new synagogue; the national museum of Moravia and
  Silesia and several high educational establishments, including a
  technical academy and a theological seminary, which are the remnants of
  the former university of Brünn. It is the seat of a Roman Catholic bishop
  and of a Protestant consistory. Brünn, which is sometimes styled "the
  Austrian Manchester," is one of the most industrial towns of Austria and
  the chief seat of the cloth industry in the whole empire. Other important
  branches of industry are: the manufacture of various woollen, cotton and
  silk goods, leather, the machinery required in the textile factories,
  brewing, distilling and milling, and the production of sugar, oil, gloves
  and hardware. It is also an important railway junction and carries on a
  very active trade.</p>
      <p>Brünn probably dates from the 9th century. In the 11th century it was
  bestowed by Duke Wratislas II. on his son Otto. A place of great
  strength, it held out successfully against sieges—in 1428 by the
  Hussites, in 1467 by King George of Bohemia, in 1645 by the Swedish
  general Torstenson, and in 1742 by the Prussians. In 1805 it was the
  headquarters of Napoleon before the battle of Austerlitz.</p>
      <p>See Trautenberger, <i>Die Chronik der Landeshauptstadt Brünn</i>
  (Brünn, 1893-1897, 5 vols.).</p>
   </body>
</topic>