<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e26831">
   <title>BRUTUS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUTUS--> (originally an adjective meaning "heavy," "stupid,"
  kindred with Gr. <ph outputclass="grk">βαρύς</ph>, cf. Eng. "brute," "brutal"),
  the surname of several distinguished Romans belonging to the Junian
  gens.</p>
      <p>I. <ph outputclass="sc">Lucius Junius Brutus</ph>, one of the first two
  consuls, 509 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph> According to the legends, his
  mother was the sister of Tarquinius Superbus, the last of the Roman
  kings, and his father and his elder brother had been put to death by the
  reigning family in order to get possession of his wealth. Junius, the
  younger, owed his safety to his reputed dullness of intellect (whence his
  surname), which character, however, he had only assumed for prudential
  reasons (Dion. Halic. iv. 67, 77). The story is probably an invention to
  account for his name; in any case his dullness did not prevent his
  appointment as master of the horse. When Lucretia, wife of Collatinus,
  was outraged by Sextus Tarquinius (the incident which inspired
  Shakespeare's <i>Rape of Lucrece</i>), Brutus, together with her husband
  and father, took a leading part in expelling the Tarquinii from Rome. He
  and Collatinus were therefore elected consuls—or rather praetors,
  which was the original title (Livy i. 59). In a conspiracy formed for the
  restoration of the dynasty, the two sons of Brutus were deeply
  implicated, and were executed by sentence of their father, and in his
  sight (Livy ii. 3). The Etruscans of Veii and Tarquinii making an attempt
  to restore Tarquinius, a battle took place between them and the Romans,
  in which Junius Brutus engaged Aruns, son of the deposed king, in single
  combat on horseback, and each fell by the other's hand (Livy ii. 6; Dion.
  Halic. v. 14). The Roman matrons mourned a year for him, as "the avenger
  of woman's honour," and a statue was erected to him on the Capitol. The
  conspiracy of his sons is the subject of a tragedy by Voltaire.</p>
      <p>The patrician branch of the family appears to have become extinct with
  L. Junius Brutus; the chief representatives of the plebeian branch in
  later times are dealt with below.</p>
      <p>II. <ph outputclass="sc">Decimus Junius Brutus</ph>, consul 138,
  surnamed Gallaecus from his victory over the Gallaeci (136) in the
  north-west of Spain (Plutarch, <i>Tib. Gracchus</i>, 21). He was a highly
  educated man, a patron of literature, and a friend of the poet Accius
  (Livy, <i>Epit.</i> 55; Appian, <i>Hisp.</i> 71-73; Vell. Pat. ii. 5;
  Cicero, <i>Brutus</i>, 28).</p>
      <p>III. <ph outputclass="sc">Marcus Junius Brutus</ph>, a jurist of high
  authority, was considered as one of the founders of Roman civil law
  (Cicero, <i>De Oratore</i>, ii. 33, 55).</p>
      <p>IV. His son, of the same name, made a great reputation at the bar, and
  from the vehemence and bitterness of his speeches became known as "the
  Accuser" (Cicero, <i>De Officiis</i>, ii. 15).</p>
      <p>V. <ph outputclass="sc">Decimus Junius Brutus</ph> (Albinus), born about
  84 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>, first served under Caesar in Gaul, and
  afterwards commanded his fleet. Caesar, who esteemed him very highly,
  made him his master of the horse and governor of Gaul, and, in case of
  Octavian's death, nominated him as one of his heirs. Nevertheless he
  joined in the conspiracy against his patron, and, like his relative
  Marcus Junius Brutus (see below), was one of his assassins. He afterwards
  resisted the attempt of Antony to obtain absolute power; and after
  heading the republican armies against him for some time with success, was
  deserted by his soldiers in Gaul, betrayed by one of the native chiefs,
  and put to death by order of Antony (43), while attempting to escape to
  Brutus and Cassius in Macedonia. He figures in Cicero's correspondence.
  (See Appian, <i>B.C.</i> iii. 97; Dio Cassius xlvi. 53; Caesar,
  <i>B.G.</i> iii. 11, <i>B.C.</i> i. 36, 45.)</p>
      <p>VI. <ph outputclass="sc">Marcus Junius Brutus</ph> (85, according to
  some, 79 or 78-42 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>), son of a father of the
  same name and of Servilia, half-sister of Cato of Utica, is the most
  famous of the name, and is the real hero of Shakespeare's <i>Julius
  Caesar.</i> His father had been treacherously put to death by order of
  Pompey during the civil wars. At that time young Marcus was only eight
  years old, and was educated with great care by his mother and uncles. He
  at first practised as an advocate. In spite of his father's fate, he
  supported the cause of Pompey against Caesar, but was pardoned by the
  latter after the victory of Pharsalus, and subsequently appointed by him
  to the government of Cisalpine Gaul (46). His justice and moderation won
  him great honour from the provincials under his rule. In 44 he was city
  praetor, and Caesar promised him the governorship of Macedonia at the
  expiration of his term of office. Influenced probably by his friend Gaius
  Cassius, he afterwards joined in the conspiracy against the great
  dictator, and was one of the foremost in his assassination. He maintained
  the cause of the republic by seizing and holding against Antony's forces
  the province of Macedonia, where he was joined by Cassius. But at
  Philippi (42) they were defeated by Antony and Octavian, and, rather than
  be taken prisoner, he fell on his sword. His wife Porcia, daughter of
  Cato of Utica, afterwards committed suicide, it is said, by swallowing
  red-hot coals (Dio Cassius xlvii. 20-49; Plutarch, <i>Brutus</i>; Appian,
  <i>B.C.</i> iv.; Vell. Paterculus ii. 72).</p>
      <p>Brutus was an earnest student through all his active life, and is said
  to have been working on an abridgment of Pausanias the night before
  Pharsalus. He was generally friendly with Cicero, who dedicated several
  of his works to him (amongst them his <i>Orator</i>), and gave the name
  of <i>Brutus</i> to his dialogue on famous orators; but there were
  frequent disagreements between them, and Cicero frequently speaks of his
  coldness and lack of enthusiasm. It is difficult to understand his great
  influence over the Romans (he was only forty-three when he died);
  probably they admired him for his respectability, the old-fashioned
  <i>gravitas</i>. He was slow in decision, amazingly obstinate, lacking in
  sympathy save towards his womenkind—who unduly influenced
  him—and in his financial dealings with the provincials both
  extortionate and cruel (Cic. <i>ad Att.</i> vi. 1. 7). Shakespeare's
  portrait of him is far too flattering. It has been held that he was
  really an illegitimate son of Julius Caesar. If so we may find an
  explanation of his joining the conspirators by the fact that in 45 Caesar
  had appointed Octavian as his heir. He wrote several philosophical
  treatises (<i>de Virtute</i>, <i>de Officiis</i>, <i>de Patientia</i>)
  and some poetry, but nothing has survived. On the other hand, we possess
  part of his correspondence with Cicero (two books out of an original
  nine), the authenticity of which, though formerly disputed, is now
  regarded as firmly established, with the possible exception of two of the
  letters. The letters of Brutus written in Greek are probably the
  composition of some rhetorician.</p>
      <p>See E.T. Bynum, <i>Das Leben des M.J. Brutus</i> (Halle a/S., 1898);
  Tyrrell and Purser's edition of Cicero's <i>Letters</i> (refs. in index
  vol. <i>s.v.</i>, "Iunius Brutus," especially introductions to vols. iii.
  and v.); G. Boissier, <i>Cicero and his Friends</i> (Eng. trans. 1897);
  J.L. Strachan-Davidson, <i>Cicero</i> (1894); other authorities under
  <ph outputclass="sc">Caesar; Cicero</ph>.</p>
   </body>
</topic>