<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e28987">
   <title>BUCENTAUR</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCENTAUR--> (Ital. <i>bucintoro</i>), the state gallery of the
  doges of Venice, on which, every year on Ascension day up to 1789, they
  put into the Adriatic in order to perform the ceremony of "wedding the
  sea." The name <i>bucintoro</i> is derived from the Ital. <i>buzino d'
  oro</i>, "golden bark," latinized in the middle ages as
  <i>bucentaurus</i> on the analogy of a supposed Gr. <ph outputclass="grk">βουκένταυρος</ph>,
  ox-centaur (from <ph outputclass="grk">βοῦς</ph> and <ph outputclass="grk">Κένταυρος</ph>).
  This led to the explanation of the name as derived from the head of an ox
  having served as the galley's figurehead. This derivation is, however,
  fanciful; the name <i>bucentaurus</i> is unknown in ancient mythology,
  and the figurehead of the bucentaurs, of which representations have come
  down to us, is the lion of St Mark. <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page713">[v.04 p.0713]</ph>The name
  bucentaur seems, indeed, to have been given to any great and sumptuous
  Venetian galley. Du Cange (<i>Gloss.</i>, <i>s.v.</i> "Bucentaurus")
  quotes from the chronicle of the doge Andrea Dandolo (d. 1354): <i>cum
  uno artificioso et solemni Bucentauro, super quo venit usque ad S.
  Clementem, quo jam pervenerat principalior et solemnior Bucentaurus cum
  consiliariis</i>, &amp;c. The last and most magnificent of the
  bucentaurs, built in 1729, was destroyed by the French in 1798 for the
  sake of its golden decorations. Remains of it are preserved at Venice in
  the Museo Civico Correr and in the Arsenal; in the latter there is also a
  fine model of it.</p>
      <p>The "Marriage of the Adriatic," or more correctly "of the sea"
  (<i>Sposalizio del Mar</i>) was a ceremony symbolizing the maritime
  dominion of Venice. The ceremony, established about <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 1000 to commemorate the doge Orseolo II.'s
  conquest of Dalmatia, was originally one of supplication and placation,
  Ascension day being chosen as that on which the doge had set out on his
  expedition. The form it took was a solemn procession of boats, headed by
  the doge's <i>maesta nave</i>, afterwards the Bucentaur (from 1311) out
  to sea by the Lido port. A prayer was offered that "for us and all who
  sail thereon the sea may be calm and quiet," whereupon the doge and the
  others were solemnly aspersed with holy water, the rest of which was
  thrown into the sea while the priests chanted "Purge me with hyssop and I
  shall be clean." To this ancient ceremony a sacramental character was
  given by Pope Alexander III in 1177, in return for the services rendered
  by Venice in the struggle against the emperor Frederick I. The pope drew
  a ring from his finger and, giving it to the doge, bade him cast such a
  one into the sea each year on Ascension day, and so wed the sea.
  Henceforth the ceremonial, instead of placatory and expiatory, became
  nuptial. Every year the doge dropped a consecrated ring into the sea, and
  with the words <i>Desponsamus te, mare</i> (We wed thee, sea) declared
  Venice and the sea to be indissolubly one (see H. F. Brown,
  <i>Venice</i>, London, 1893, pp. 69, 110).</p>
   </body>
</topic>