<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25018">
   <title>BRUCE, JAMES</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUCE, JAMES--> (1730-1794), Scottish explorer in Africa, was born
  at Kinnaird House, Stirlingshire, on the 14th of December 1730. He was
  educated at Harrow and Edinburgh University, and began to study for the
  bar; but his marriage to the daughter of a wine merchant resulted in his
  entering that business. His wife died in October 1754, within nine months
  of marriage, and Bruce thereafter travelled in Portugal and Spain. The
  examination of oriental MSS. at the Escurial led him to the study of
  Arabic and Geez and determined his future career. In 1758 his father's
  death placed him in possession of the estate of Kinnaird. On the outbreak
  of war with Spain in 1762 he submitted to the British government a plan
  for an attack on Ferrol. His suggestion was not adopted, but it led to
  his selection by the 2nd earl of Halifax for the post of British consul
  at Algiers, with a commission to study the ancient ruins in that country,
  in which interest had been excited by the descriptions sent home by
  Thomas Shaw<xref href="#d1e25018/Footnote_201" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref>
  (1694-1751), consular chaplain at Algiers, 1719-1731. Having spent six
  months in Italy studying antiquities, Bruce reached Algiers in March
  1763. The whole of his time was taken up with his consular duties at the
  piratical court of the dey, and he was kept without the assistance
  promised. But in August 1765, a successor in the consulate having
  arrived, Bruce began his exploration of the Roman ruins in Barbary.
  Having examined many ruins in eastern Algeria, he travelled by land from
  Tunis to Tripoli, and at Ptolemeta took passage for Candia; but was
  shipwrecked near Bengazi and had to swim ashore. He eventually reached
  Crete, and sailing thence to Sidon, travelled through Syria, visiting
  Palmyra and Baalbek. Throughout his journeyings in Barbary and the
  Levant, Bruce made careful drawings of the many ruins he examined. He
  also acquired a sufficient knowledge of medicine to enable him to pass in
  the East as a physician.</p>
      <p>In June 1768 he arrived at Alexandria, having resolved to endeavour to
  discover the source of the Nile, which he believed to rise in Abyssinia.
  At Cairo he gained the support of the Mameluke ruler, Ali Bey; after
  visiting Thebes he crossed the desert to Kosseir, where he embarked in
  the dress of a Turkish sailor. He reached Jidda in May 1769, and after
  some stay in Arabia he recrossed the Red Sea and landed at Massawa, then
  in possession of the Turks, on the 19th of September. He reached Gondar,
  then the capital of Abyssinia, on the 14th of February 1770, where he was
  well received by the negus Tekla Haimanot II., by Ras Michael, the real
  ruler of the country, by the ras's wife, Ozoro Esther, and by the
  Abyssinians generally. His fine presence (he was 6 ft. 4 in. high), his
  knowledge of Geez, his excellence in sports, his courage, resource and
  self-esteem, all told in his favour among a people who were in general
  distrustful of all foreigners. He stayed in Abyssinia for two years,
  gaining knowledge which enabled him subsequently to present a perfect
  picture of Abyssinian life. On the 14th of November 1770 he reached the
  long-sought source of the Blue Nile. Though admitting that the White Nile
  was the larger stream, Bruce claimed that the Blue Nile was the Nile of
  the ancients and that he was thus the discoverer of its source. The
  claim, however, was not well founded (see <ph outputclass="sc">Nile</ph>:
  <i>Story of Exploration</i>). Setting out from Gondar in December 1771,
  Bruce made his way, in spite of enormous difficulties, by Sennar to
  Nubia, being the first to trace the Blue Nile to its confluence with the
  White Nile. On the 29th of November 1772 he reached Assuan, presently
  returning to the desert to recover his journals and his baggage, which
  had been abandoned in consequence of the death of all his camels. Cairo
  was reached in January 1773, and in March Bruce arrived in France, where
  he was welcomed by Buffon and other <i>savants</i>. He came to London in
  1774, but, offended by the incredulity with which his story was received,
  retired to his home at Kinnaird. It was not until 1790 that, urged by his
  friend Daines Barrington, he published his <i>Travels to Discover the
  Source of the Nile in the Years 1768-73</i>, in five octavo volumes,
  lavishly illustrated. The work was very popular, but was assailed by
  other travellers as being unworthy of credence. The manner in which the
  book was written—twelve years after Bruce's return from Africa and
  without reference to his journals—gave some handle to his critics,
  but the substantial accuracy of every statement concerning his Abyssinian
  travels has since been amply demonstrated. He died on the 27th of April
  1794.</p>
      <p>Bruce wrote an autobiography, part of which is printed in editions of
  his <i>Travels</i>, published in 1805 and 1813, accompanied by a
  biographical notice by the editor, Alexander Murray. The best edition of
  the <i>Travels</i> is the third (Edinburgh, 1813, 8 vols.). Of the
  abridgments the best is that of Major (afterwards Sir Francis) Head, the
  author of a well-informed <i>Life of Bruce</i> (London, 1830). The best
  account of Bruce's travels in Barbary is contained in Sir R. Lambert
  Playfair's <i>Travels in the Footsteps of Bruce</i> (London, 1877), in
  which a selection of his drawings was published for the first time.
  Several of Bruce's drawings were presented to George III. and are in the
  royal collection at Windsor.</p>
      <p outputclass="fn-holder">
         <fn id="Footnote_201"> Dr Shaw's
  <i>Travels relating to Several Parts of Barbary ...</i> was first printed
  at Oxford (1738).</fn>

      </p>
   </body>
</topic>