<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e33389">
   <title>BUGENHAGEN, JOHANN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUGENHAGEN, JOHANN--> (1485-1558), surnamed <ph outputclass="sc">Pomeranus</ph>, German Protestant reformer, was born at
  Wollin near Stettin on the 24th of June 1485. At the university of
  Greifswald he gained much distinction as a humanist, and in 1504 was
  appointed by the abbot of the Praemonstratensian monastery at Belbuck
  rector of the town school at Treptow. In 1509 he was ordained priest and
  became a vicar in the collegiate <i>Marienkirche</i> at Treptow; in 1517
  he was appointed lecturer on the Bible and Church Fathers at the abbey
  school at Belbuck. In 1520 Luther's <i>De Captivitate Babylonica</i>
  converted him into a zealous supporter of the Reformer's views, to which
  he won over the abbot among others. In 1521 he went to Wittenberg, where
  he formed a close friendship with Luther and Melanchthon, and in 1522 he
  married. He preached and lectured in the university, but his zeal and
  organizing skill soon spread his reforming influence far beyond its
  limits. In 1528 he arranged the church affairs of Brunswick and Hamburg;
  in 1530 those of Lübeck and Pomerania. In 1537 he was invited to Denmark
  by Christian III., and remained five years in that country, organizing
  the church (though only a presbyter, he consecrated the new Danish
  bishops) and schools. He passed the remainder of his life at Wittenberg,
  braving the perils of war and persecution rather than desert the place
  dear to him as the home of the Reformation. He died on the 20th of April
  1558. Among his numerous works is a history of Pomerania, which remained
  unpublished till 1728. Perhaps his best book is the <i>Interpretatio in
  Librum Psalmorum</i> (1523), and he is also remembered as having helped
  Luther in his translation of the Bible.</p>
      <p>See Life by H. Hering (Halle, 1888); Emil Görigk, <i>Bugenhagen und
  die Protestantisierung Pommerns</i> (1895). O. Vogt published a
  collection of Bugenhagen's correspondence in 1888, and a supplement in
  1890.</p>
   </body>
</topic>