<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e13350">
   <title>BRITAIN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRITAIN--> (Gr. <ph outputclass="grk">Πρετανικαὶ
  νῆσοι,
  Βρεττανία</ph>; Lat.
  <i>Britannia</i>, rarely <i>Brittania</i>), the anglicized form of the
  classical name of England, Wales and Scotland, sometimes extended to the
  British Isles as a whole (<i>Britannicae Insulae</i>). The Greek and
  Roman forms are doubtless attempts to reproduce a Celtic original, the
  exact form of which is still matter of dispute. Brittany (Fr.
  <i>Bretagne</i>) in western France derived its name from Britain owing to
  migrations in the 5th and 6th century <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> The
  personification of Britannia as a female figure may be traced back as far
  as the coins of Hadrian and Antoninus Pius (early 2nd century <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph>); its first appearance on modern coins is on the
  copper of Charles II. (see <ph outputclass="sc">Numismatics</ph>).</p>
      <p>In what follows, the archaeological interest of early Britain is dealt
  with, in connexion with the history of Britain in Pre-Roman, Roman, and
  Anglo-Saxon days; this account being supplementary to the articles <ph outputclass="sc">England; English History; Scotland</ph>, &amp;c.</p>
      <section>
         <title>Pre-Roman Britain</title>
         <p>Geologists are not yet agreed when and by whom Britain was first
  peopled. Probably the island was invaded by a succession of races. The
  first, the Paleolithic men, may have died out or retired before
  successors arrived. During the Neolithic and Bronze Ages we can dimly
  trace further immigrations. Real knowledge begins with two Celtic
  invasions, that of the Goidels in the later part of the Bronze Age, and
  that of the Brythons and Belgae in the Iron Age. These invaders brought
  Celtic civilization and dialects. It is uncertain how far they were
  themselves Celtic in blood and how far they were numerous enough to
  absorb or obliterate the races which they found in Britain. But it is not
  unreasonable to think that they were no mere conquering caste, and that
  they were of the same race as the Celtic-speaking peoples of the western
  continent. By the age of Julius Caesar all the inhabitants of Britain,
  except perhaps some tribes of the far north, were Celts in speech and
  customs. Politically they were divided into separate and generally
  warring tribes, each under its own princes. They dwelt in hill forts with
  walls of earth or rude stone, or in villages of round huts sunk into the
  ground and resembling those found in parts of northern Gaul, or in
  subterranean chambered houses, or in hamlets of pile-dwellings
  constructed among the marshes. But, at least in the south, market centres
  had sprung up, town life was beginning, houses of a better type were
  perhaps coming into use, and the southern tribes employed a gold coinage
  and also a currency of iron bars or ingots, attested by Caesar and by
  surviving examples, which weigh roughly, some two-thirds of a pound, some
  2⅔ lb, but mostly 1⅓ lb. In religion, the chief feature was
  the priesthood of Druids, who here, as in Gaul, practised magical arts
  and barbarous rites of human sacrifice, taught a secret lore, wielded
  great influence, but, at least as Druids, took ordinarily no part in
  politics. In art, these tribes possessed a native Late Celtic fashion,
  descended from far-off Mediterranean antecedents and more directly
  connected with the La-Tène culture of the continental Celts. Its
  characteristics were a flamboyant and fantastic treatment of plant and
  animal (though not of human) forms, a free use of the geometrical device
  called the "returning spiral," and much skill in enamelling. Its finest
  products were in bronze, but the artistic impulse spread to humbler work
  in wood and pottery. The late Celtic age was one which genuinely
  delighted in beauty of form and detail. In this it resembled the middle
  ages rather than the Roman empire or the present day, and it resembled
  them all the more in that its love of beauty, like theirs, was mixed with
  a feeling for the fantastic and the grotesque. The Roman conquest of
  northern Gaul (57-50 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>) brought Britain into
  definite relation with the Mediterranean. It was already closely
  connected with Gaul, and when Roman civilization and its products invaded
  Gallia Belgica, they passed on easily to Britain. The British coinage now
  begins to bear Roman legends, and after Caesar's two raids (55, 54 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>) the southern tribes were regarded at Rome,
  though they do not seem to have regarded themselves, as vassals. Actual
  conquest was, however, delayed. Augustus planned it. But both he and his
  successor Tiberius realized that the greater need was to consolidate the
  existing empire, and absorb the vast additions recently made to it by
  Pompey, Caesar and Augustus.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Roman Britain</title>
         <p>I. <i>The Roman Conquest.</i>—The conquest of Britain was
  undertaken by Claudius in <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 43. Two causes
  coincided to produce the step. On the one hand a forward policy then
  ruled at Rome, leading to annexations in various lands. On the other
  hand, a probably philo-Roman prince, Cunobelin (known to literature as
  Cymbeline), had just been succeeded by two sons, Caractacus (<i>q.v.</i>)
  and Togodumnus, who were hostile to Rome. Caligula, the half-insane
  predecessor of Claudius, had made in respect to this event some blunder
  which we know only through a sensational exaggeration, but which
  doubtless had to be made good. An immediate reason for action was the
  appeal of a fugitive British prince, presumably a Roman partisan and
  victim of Cunobelin's sons. So Aulus Plautius with a singularly well
  equipped army of some 40,000 men landed in Kent and advanced on London.
  Here Claudius himself appeared—the one reigning emperor of the 1st
  century who crossed the waves of ocean,—and the army, crossing the
  Thames, moved forward through Essex and captured the native capital,
  Camulodūnum, now Colchester. From the base of London and Colchester
  three corps continued the conquest. The left wing, the Second Legion
  (under Vespasian, afterwards emperor), subdued the south; the centre, the
  Fourteenth and Twentieth Legions, subdued the midlands, while the right
  wing, the Ninth Legion, advanced through the eastern part of the island.
  This strategy was at first triumphant. The lowlands of Britain, with
  their partly Romanized and partly scanty population and their easy
  physical features, presented no obstacle. Within three or four years
  everything south of the Humber and east of the Severn had been either
  directly annexed or entrusted, as protectorates, to native
  client-princes.</p>
         <p>A more difficult task remained. The wild hills and wilder tribes of
  Wales and Yorkshire offered far fiercer resistance. There followed thirty
  years of intermittent hill fighting (<ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph>
  47-79). The precise steps of the conquest are not known. Legionary
  fortresses were established at Wroxeter (for a time only), Chester and
  Caerleon, facing the Welsh hills, and at Lincoln in the northeast.
  Monmouthshire, and Flintshire with its lead mines, were early overrun; in
  60 Suetonius Paulinus reached Anglesea. The method of conquest was the
  establishment of small detached forts in strategic positions, each
  garrisoned by 500 or 1000 men, and it was accompanied by a full share of
  those disasters which vigorous barbarians always inflict on civilized
  invaders. Progress was delayed too by the great revolt of Boadicea
  (<i>q.v.</i>) and a large part of the nominally conquered Lowlands. Her
  rising was soon crushed, but the government was obviously afraid for a
  while to move its garrisons forward. Indeed, other needs of the empire
  caused the withdrawal of the Fourteenth Legion about 67. But the decade
  <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 70-80 was decisive. A series of three able
  generals commanded an army restored to its proper strength by the
  addition of Legio II. Adiutrix, and achieved the final subjugation of
  Wales and the first conquest of Yorkshire, where a legionary fortress at
  York was substituted for that at Lincoln.</p>
         <p>The third and best-known, if not the ablest, of these generals, Julius
  Agricola, moved on in <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 80 to the conquest
  of the farther north. He established between the Clyde and Forth a
  frontier meant to be permanent, guarded by a line of forts, <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page584">[v.04 p.0584]</ph>two of
  which are still traceable at Camelon near Falkirk, and at Bar Hill. He
  then advanced into Caledonia and won a "famous victory" at Mons Graupius
  (sometimes, but incorrectly, spelt Grampius), probably near the
  confluence of the Tay and the Isla, where a Roman encampment of his date,
  Inchtuthill, has been partly examined (see <ph outputclass="sc">Galgacus</ph>). He dreamt even of invading Ireland, and
  thought it an easy task. The home government judged otherwise. Jealous
  possibly of a too brilliant general, certainly averse from costly and
  fruitless campaigns and needing the Legio II. Adiutrix for work
  elsewhere, it recalled both governor and legion, and gave up the more
  northerly of his nominal conquests. The most solid result of his
  campaigns is that his battlefield, misspelt Grampius, has provided to
  antiquaries, and through them to the world, the modern name of the
  Grampian Hills.</p>
         <p>What frontier was adopted after Agricola's departure, whether Tweed or
  Cheviot or other, is unknown. For thirty years (<ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 85-115) the military history of Britain is a
  blank. When we recover knowledge we are in an altered world. About 115 or
  120 the northern Britons rose in revolt and destroyed the Ninth Legion,
  posted at York, which would bear the brunt of any northern trouble. In
  122 the second reigning emperor who crossed the ocean, Hadrian, came
  himself to Britain, brought the Sixth Legion to replace the Ninth, and
  introduced the frontier policy of his age. For over 70 m. from Tyne to
  Solway, more exactly from Wallsend to Bowness, he built a continuous
  rampart, more probably of turf than of stone, with a ditch in front of
  it, a number of small forts along it, one or two outposts a few miles to
  the north of it, and some detached forts (the best-known is on the hill
  above Maryport) guarding the Cumberland coast beyond its western end. The
  details of his work are imperfectly known, for though many remains
  survive, it is hard to separate those of Hadrian's date from others that
  are later. But that Hadrian built a wall here is proved alike by
  literature and by inscriptions. The meaning of the scheme is equally
  certain. It was to be, as it were, a Chinese wall, marking the definite
  limit of the Roman world. It was now declared, not by the secret
  resolutions of cabinets, but by the work of the spade marking the solid
  earth for ever, that the era of conquest was ended.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/britain_roman.png">
               <alt>Roman Britain.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>But empires move, though rulers bid them stand still. Whether the land
  beyond Hadrian's wall became temptingly peaceful or remained in vexing
  disorder, our authorities do not say. We know only that about 142
  Hadrian's successor, Antoninus Pius, acting through his general Lollius
  Urbicus, advanced from the Tyne and Solway frontier to the narrower
  isthmus between Forth and Clyde, 36 m. across, which Agricola had
  fortified before him. Here he reared a continuous rampart with a ditch in
  front of it, fair-sized forts, probably a dozen in number, built either
  close behind it or actually abutting on it, and a connecting road running
  from end to end. An ancient writer states that the rampart was built of
  regularly laid sods (the same method which had probably been employed by
  Hadrian), and excavations in 1891-1893 have verified the statement. The
  work still survives visibly, though in varying preservation, except in
  the agricultural districts near its two ends. Occasionally, as on
  Croyhill (near Kilsyth), at Westerwood, and in the covers of Bonnyside (3
  m. west of Falkirk), wall and ditch and even road can be distinctly
  traced, and the sites of many of the forts are plain to practised eyes.
  Three of these forts have been excavated. All three show the ordinary
  features of Roman <i>castella</i>, though they differ more than one would
  expect in forts built at one time by one general. Bar Hill, the most
  completely explored, covers three acres—nearly five times as much
  as the earlier fort of Agricola on the same site. It had ramparts of
  turf, barrack-rooms of wood, and a headquarters building, storehouse and
  bath in stone: it stands a few yards back from the wall. Castle Cary
  covers nearly four acres: its ramparts contain massive and well-dressed
  masonry; its interior buildings, though they agree in material, do not
  altogether agree in plan with those of Bar Hill, and its north face falls
  in line with the frontier wall. Rough Castle, near Falkirk, is very much
  smaller; it is remarkable for the astonishing strength of its turf-built
  and earthen ramparts and ravelins, and for a remarkable series of
  defensive pits, reminiscent of Caesar's <i>lilia</i> at Alesia, plainly
  intended to break an enemy's charge, and either provided with stakes to
  impale the assailant or covered over with hurdles or the like to deceive
  him. Besides the dozen forts on the wall, one or two outposts may have
  been held at Ardoch and Abernethy along the natural route which runs by
  Stirling and Perth to the lowlands of the east coast. This frontier was
  reached from the south by two roads. One, known in medieval times as Dere
  Street and misnamed Watling Street by modern antiquaries, ran from
  Corbridge on the Tyne past Otterburn, crossed Cheviot near Makendon
  Camps, and passed by an important fort at Newstead near Melrose, and
  another at Inveresk (outside of Edinburgh), to the eastern end of the
  wall. The other, starting from Carlisle, ran to Birrens, a Roman fort
  near Ecclefechan, and thence, by a line not yet explored and indeed not
  at all certain, to Carstairs and the west end of the wall. This wall was
  in addition to, and not instead of, the wall of Hadrian. Both barriers
  were held together, and the district between them was regarded as a
  military area, outside the range of civilization.</p>
         <p>The work of Pius brought no long peace. Sixteen years later disorder
  broke out in north Britain, apparently in the district between the
  Cheviots and the Derbyshire hills, and was repressed with difficulty
  after four or five years' fighting. Eighteen or twenty years later
  (180-185) a new war broke out with a different issue. The Romans lost
  everything beyond Cheviot, and perhaps even more. The government of
  Commodus, feeble in itself and vexed by many troubles, could not repair
  the loss, and the civil wars which soon raged in Europe (193-197) gave
  the Caledonians further chance. It was not till 208 that Septimius
  Severus, the ablest emperor of his age, could turn his attention to the
  island. He came thither in person, invaded Caledonia, commenced the
  reconstruction of the wall of Hadrian, rebuilding it from end to end in
  stone, and then in the fourth year of his operations died at York. Amid
  much that is uncertain and even legendary about his work in Britain, this
  is plain, that he fixed on the line of Hadrian's wall as his substantive
  frontier. His successors, Caracalla and Severus Alexander (211-235),
  accepted the position, and many inscriptions refer to building or
  rebuilding executed by them for the greater efficiency of the frontier
  defences. The conquest of Britain was at last over. The wall of Hadrian
  remained for nearly two hundred years more the northern limit of Roman
  power in the extreme west.</p>
         <p>II. <i>The Province of Britain and its Military
  System.</i>—Geographically, Britain consists of two parts: (1) the
  comparatively flat lowlands of the south, east and midlands, suitable to
  agriculture and open to easy intercourse with the continent, i.e. with
  the rest of the Roman empire; (2) the district consisting of the hills of
  Devon and Cornwall, of Wales and of northern England, regions lying more,
  and often very much more, than 600 ft. above the sea, scarred with gorges
  and deep valleys, mountainous in character, difficult for armies to
  traverse, ill fitted to the peaceful pursuits in agriculture. These two
  parts of the province differ also in their history. The lowlands, as we
  have seen, were conquered easily and quickly. The uplands were hardly
  subdued completely till the end of the 2nd century. They differ, thirdly,
  in the character of their Roman occupation. The lowlands were the scene
  of civil life. Towns, villages and country houses were their prominent
  features; troops were hardly seen in them save in some fortresses on the
  edge of the hills and in a chain of forts built in the 4th century to
  defend the south-east coast, the so-called Saxon Shore. The uplands of
  Wales and the north presented another spectacle. Here civil life was
  almost wholly absent. No country town or country house has been found
  more than 20 m. north of York or west of Monmouthshire. The hills were
  one extensive military frontier, covered with forts and strategic roads
  connecting them, and devoid of town life, country houses, farms or
  peaceful civilized industry. This geographical division was not
  reproduced by Rome in any administrative partitions of the province. At
  first the whole was governed by one <i>legatus Augusti</i> of consular
  standing. <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page585">[v.04 p.0585]</ph>Septimius Severus made it two
  provinces, Superior and Inferior, with a boundary which probably ran from
  Humber to Mersey, but we do not know how long this arrangement lasted. In
  the 5th century there were five provinces, Britannia Prima and Secunda,
  Flavia and Maxima Caesariensis and (for a while) Valentia, ruled by
  <i>praesides</i> and <i>consulares</i> under a <i>vicartus</i>, but the
  only thing known of them is that Britannia Prima included
  Cirencester.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 1.—Plan of Housesteads (Borcovicium)
    on Hadrian's Wall.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/britain_1.png">
               <alt>Fig 1.--Plan of Housesteads.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The army which guarded or coerced the province consisted, from the
  time of Hadrian onwards, of (1) three legions, the Second at Isca Silurum
  (Caerleon-on-Usk, <i>q.v.</i>), the Ninth at Eburācum (<i>q.v.</i>;
  now York), the Twentieth at Deva (<i>q.v.</i>; now Chester), a total of
  some 15,000 heavy infantry; and (2) a large but uncertain number of
  auxiliaries, troops of the second grade, organized in infantry cohorts or
  cavalry <i>alae</i>, each 500 or 1000 strong, and posted in
  <i>castella</i> nearer the frontiers than the legions. The legionary
  fortresses were large rectangular enclosures of 50 or 60 acres,
  surrounded by strong walls of which traces can still be seen in the lower
  courses of the north and east town-walls of Chester, in the abbey gardens
  at York, and on the south side of Caerleon. The auxiliary <i>castella</i>
  were hardly a tenth of the size, varying generally from three to six
  acres according to the size of the regiment and the need for stabling. Of
  these upwards of 70 are known in England and some 20 more in Scotland. Of
  the English examples a few have been carefully excavated, notably
  Gellygaer between Cardiff and Brecon, one of the most perfect specimens
  to be found anywhere in the Roman empire of a Roman fort dating from the
  end of the 1st century <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph>; Hardknott, on a
  Cumberland moor overhanging Upper Eskdale; and Housesteads on Hadrian's
  wall. In Scotland excavation has been more active, in particular at the
  forts of Birrens, Newstead near Melrose, Lyne near Peebles, Ardoch
  between Stirling and Perth, and Castle Cary, Rough Castle and Bar Hill on
  the wall of Pius. The internal arrangements of all these forts follow one
  general plan. But in some of them the internal buildings are all of
  stone, while in others, principally (it seems) forts built before 150,
  wood is used freely and only the few principal buildings seem to have
  been constructed throughout of stone.</p>
         <p>We may illustrate their character from Housesteads, which, in the form
  in which we know it, perhaps dates from Septimius Severus. This fort
  measures about 360 by 600 ft. and covers a trifle less than 5 acres. Its
  ramparts are of stone, and its north rampart coincides with the great
  wall of Hadrian. Its interior is filled with stone buildings. Chief among
  these (see fig. 1), and in the centre of the whole fort, is the
  Headquarters, in Lat. <i>Principia</i> or, as it is often (though perhaps
  less correctly) styled by moderns, <i>Praetorium</i>. This is a
  rectangular structure with only one entrance which gives access, first,
  to a small cloistered court (x. 4), then to a second open court (x. 7),
  and finally to a row of five rooms (x. 8-12) containing the shrine for
  official worship, the treasury and other offices. Close by were officers'
  quarters, generally built round a tiny cloistered court (ix., xi., xii.),
  and substantially built storehouses with buttresses and dry basements
  (viii.). These filled the middle third of the fort. At the two ends were
  barracks for the soldiers (i.-vi., xiii.-xviii.). No space was allotted
  to private religion or domestic life. The shrines which voluntary
  worshippers might visit, the public bath-house, and the cottages of the
  soldiers' wives, camp followers, &amp;c., lay outside the walls. Such
  were nearly all the Roman forts in Britain. They differ somewhat from
  Roman forts in Germany or other provinces, though most of the differences
  arise from the different usage of wood and of stone in various
  places.</p>
         <p>Forts of this kind were dotted all along the military roads of the
  Welsh and northern hill-districts. In Wales a road ran from Chester past
  a fort at Caer-hyn (near Conway) to a fort at Carnarvon (Segontium). A
  similar road ran along the south coast from Caerleon-on-Usk past a fort
  at Cardiff and perhaps others, to Carmarthen. A third, roughly parallel
  to the shore of Cardigan Bay, with forts at Llanio and Tommen-y-mur (near
  Festiniog), connected the northern and southern roads, while <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page586">[v.04
  p.0586]</ph>the interior was held by a system of roads and forts not
  yet well understood but discernible at such points as Caer-gai on Bala
  Lake, Castle Collen near Llandrindod Wells, the Gaer near Brecon, Merthyr
  and Gellygaer. In the north of Britain we find three principal roads. One
  led due north from York past forts at Catterick Bridge, Piers Bridge,
  Binchester, Lanchester, Ebchester to the wall and to Scotland, while
  branches through Chester-le-Street reached the Tyne Bridge (Pons Aelius)
  at Newcastle and the Tyne mouth at South Shields. A second road, turning
  north-west from Catterick Bridge, mounted the Pennine Chain by way of
  forts at Rokeby, Bowes and Brough-under-Stainmoor, descended into the
  Eden valley, reached Hadrian's wall near Carlisle (Luguvallium), and
  passed on to Birrens. The third route, starting from Chester and passing
  up the western coast, is more complex, and exists in duplicate, the
  result perhaps of two different schemes of road-making. Forts in plenty
  can be detected along it, notably Manchester (Mancunium or Mamucium),
  Ribchester (Bremetennacum), Brougham Castle (Brocavum), Old Penrith
  (Voreda), and on a western branch, Watercrook near Kendal, Waterhead near
  the hotel of that name on Ambleside, Hardknott above Eskdale, Maryport
  (Uxellodūnum), and Old Carlisle (possibly Petriana). In addition,
  two or three cross roads, not yet sufficiently explored, maintained
  communication between the troops in Yorkshire and those in Cheshire and
  Lancashire. This road system bears plain marks of having been made at
  different times, and with different objectives, but we have no evidence
  that any one part was abandoned when any other was built. There are
  signs, however, that various forts were dismantled as the country grew
  quieter. Thus, Gellygaer in South Wales and Hardknott in Cumberland have
  yielded nothing later than the opening of the 2nd century.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 2.—Hadrian's Wall.

    
  </title>
            <desc>
               <p>From <i>Social England</i>, by permission of Cassell
    &amp; Co., Ltd.</p>
            </desc>
            <image href="images/britain_2.png">
               <alt>Fig 2.--Hadrian's Wall.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>Besides these detached forts and their connecting roads, the north of
  Britain was defended by Hadrian's wall (figs. 2 and 3). The history of
  this wall has been given above. The actual works are threefold. First,
  there is that which to-day forms the most striking feature in the whole,
  the wall of stone 6-8 ft. thick, and originally perhaps 14 ft. high, with
  a deep ditch in front, and forts and "mile castles" and turrets and a
  connecting road behind it. On the high moors between Chollerford and
  Gilsland its traces are still plain, as it climbs from hill to hill and
  winds along perilous precipices. Secondly, there is the so-called
  "Vallum," in reality no <i>vallum</i> at all, but a broad flat-bottomed
  ditch out of which the earth has been cast up on either side into regular
  and continuous mounds that resemble ramparts. Thirdly, nowhere very clear
  on the surface and as yet detected only at a few points, there are the
  remains of the "turf wall," constructed of sods laid in regular courses,
  with a ditch in front. This turf wall is certainly older than the stone
  wall, and, as our ancient writers mention two wall-builders, Hadrian and
  Septimius Severus, the natural inference is that Hadrian built his wall
  of turf and Severus reconstructed it in stone. The reconstruction
  probably followed in general the line of Hadrian's wall in order to
  utilize the existing ditch, and this explains why the turf wall itself
  survives only at special points. In general it was destroyed to make way
  for the new wall in stone. Occasionally (as at Birdoswald) there was a
  deviation, and the older work survived. This conversion of earthwork into
  stone in the age of Severus can be paralleled from other parts of the
  Roman empire.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 3.—Section of Hadrian's Wall.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/britain_3.png">
               <alt>Fig 3.--Section of Hadrian's Wall.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The meaning of the <i>vallum</i> is much more doubtful. John Hodgson
  and Bruce, the local authorities of the 19th century, supposed that it
  was erected to defend the wall from southern insurgents. Others have
  ascribed it to Agricola, or have thought it to be the wall of Hadrian, or
  even assigned it to pre-Roman natives. The two facts that are clear about
  it are, that it is a Roman work, no older than Hadrian (if so old), and
  that it was not intended, like the wall, for military defence. Probably
  it is contemporaneous with either the turf wall or the stone wall, and
  marked some limit of the civil province of Britain. Beyond this we cannot
  at present go.</p>
         <p>III. <i>The Civilization of Roman Britain.</i>—Behind these
  formidable garrisons, sheltered from barbarians and in easy contact with
  the Roman empire, stretched the lowlands of southern and eastern Britain.
  Here a civilized life grew up, and Roman culture spread. This part of
  Britain became Romanized. In the lands looking on to the Thames estuary
  (Kent, Essex, Middlesex) the process had perhaps begun before the Roman
  conquest. It was continued after that event, and in two ways. To some
  extent it was definitely encouraged by the Roman government, which here,
  as elsewhere, founded towns peopled with Roman citizens—generally
  discharged legionaries—and endowed them with franchise and
  constitution like those of the Italian municipalities. It developed still
  more by its own automatic growth. The coherent civilization of the Romans
  was accepted by the Britons, as it was by the Gauls, with something like
  enthusiasm. Encouraged perhaps by sympathetic Romans, spurred on still
  more by their own instincts, and led no doubt by their nobles, they began
  to speak Latin, to use the material resources of Roman civilized life,
  and in time to consider themselves not the unwilling subjects of a
  foreign empire, but the British members of the Roman state. The steps by
  which these results were reached can to some extent be dated. Within a
  few years of the Claudian invasion a <i>colonia</i>, or municipality of
  time-expired soldiers, had been planted in the old native capital of
  Colchester (Camulodūnum), and though it served at first mainly as a
  fortress and thus provoked British hatred, it came soon to exercise a
  civilizing influence. At the same time the British town of Verulamium (St
  Albans) was thought sufficiently Romanized to deserve the municipal
  status of a <i>municipium</i>, which at this period differed little from
  that of a <i>colonia</i>. Romanized Britons must now have begun to be
  numerous. In the great revolt of Boadicea (60) the nationalist party seem
  to have massacred many thousands of them along with actual Romans.
  Fifteen or twenty years later, the movement increases. Towns spring up,
  such as Silchester, laid out in Roman fashion, furnished with public
  buildings of Roman type, and filled with houses which are Roman in
  fittings if not in plan. The baths of Bath (Aquae Sulis) are exploited.
  Another <i>colonia</i> is planted at Lincoln (Lindum), and a third at
  Gloucester (Glevum) in 96. A new "chief judge" is appointed for
  increasing civil business. The tax-gatherer and recruiting officer begin
  to make their way into the hills. During the 2nd century progress was
  perhaps slower, hindered doubtless by the repeated risings in the north.
  It was not till the 3rd century that country houses and farms became
  common in most parts of the civilized area. In the beginning of the <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page587">[v.04
  p.0587]</ph>4th century the skilled artisans and builders, and the
  cloth and corn of Britain were equally famous on the continent. This
  probably was the age when the prosperity and Romanization of the province
  reached its height. By this time the town populations and the educated
  among the country-folk spoke Latin, and Britain regarded itself as a
  Roman land, inhabited by Romans and distinct from outer barbarians.</p>
         <p>The civilization which had thus spread over half the island was
  genuinely Roman, identical in kind with that of the other western
  provinces of the empire, and in particular with that of northern Gaul.
  But it was defective in quantity. The elements which compose it are
  marked by smaller size, less wealth and less splendour than the same
  elements elsewhere. It was also uneven in its distribution. Large tracts,
  in particular Warwickshire and the adjoining midlands, were very thinly
  inhabited. Even densely peopled areas like north Kent, the Sussex coast,
  west Gloucestershire and east Somerset, immediately adjoin areas like the
  Weald of Kent and Sussex where Romano-British remains hardly occur.</p>
         <p>The administration of the civilized part of the province, while
  subject to the governor of all Britain, was practically entrusted to
  local authorities. Each Roman municipality ruled itself and a territory
  perhaps as large as a small county which belonged to it. Some districts
  belonged to the Imperial Domains, and were administered by agents of the
  emperor. The rest, by far the larger part of the country, was divided up
  among the old native tribes or cantons, some ten or twelve in number,
  each grouped round some country town where its council (<i>ordo</i>) met
  for cantonal business. This cantonal system closely resembles that which
  we find in Gaul. It is an old native element recast in Roman form, and
  well illustrates the Roman principle of local government by
  devolution.</p>
         <p>In the general framework of Romano-British life the two chief features
  were the town, and the <i>villa</i>. The towns of the province, as we
  have already implied, fall into two classes. Five modern cities,
  Colchester, Lincoln, York, Gloucester and St Albans, stand on the sites,
  and in some fragmentary fashion bear the names of five Roman
  municipalities, founded by the Roman government with special charters and
  constitutions. All of these reached a considerable measure of prosperity.
  None of them rivals the greater municipalities of other provinces.
  Besides them we trace a larger number of country towns, varying much in
  size, but all possessing in some degree the characteristics of a town.
  The chief of these seem to be cantonal capitals, probably developed out
  of the market centres or capitals of the Celtic tribes before the Roman
  conquest. Such are Isurium Brigantum, capital of the Brigantes, 12 m.
  north-west of York and the most northerly Romano-British town; Ratae, now
  Leicester, capital of the Coritani; Viroconium, now Wroxeter, near
  Shrewsbury, capital of the Cornovii; Venta Silurum, now Caerwent, near
  Chepstow; Corinium, now Cirencester, capital of the Dobuni; Isca
  Dumnoniorum, now Exeter, the most westerly of these towns; Durnovaria,
  now Dorchester, in Dorset, capital of the Durotriges; Venta Belgarum, now
  Winchester; Calleva Atrebatum, now Silchester, 10 m. south of Reading;
  Durovernum Cantiacorum, now Canterbury; and Venta Icenorum, now
  Caistor-by-Norwich. Besides these country towns, Londinium (London) was a
  rich and important trading town, centre of the road system, and the seat
  of the finance officials of the province, as the remarkable objects
  discovered in it abundantly prove, while Aquae Sulis (Bath) was a spa
  provided with splendid baths, and a richly adorned temple of the native
  patron deity, Sul or Sulis, whom the Romans called Minerva. Many smaller
  places, too, for example, Magna or Kenchester near Hereford, Durobrivae
  or Rochester in Kent, another Durobrivae near Peterborough, a site of
  uncertain name near Cambridge, another of uncertain name near
  Chesterford, exhibited some measure of town life.</p>
         <p>As a specimen we may take Silchester, remarkable as the one town in
  the whole Roman empire which has been completely and systematically
  uncovered. As we see it to-day, it is an open space of 100 acres, set on
  a hill with a wide prospect east and south and west, in shape an
  irregular hexagon, enclosed in a circuit of a mile and a half by the
  massive ruins of a city wall which still stands here and there some 20
  ft. high (fig. 4). Outside, on the north-east, is the grassy hollow of a
  tiny amphitheatre; on the west a line of earthworks runs in wider circuit
  than the walls. The area within the walls is a vast expanse of cultivated
  land, unbroken by any vestige of antiquity; yet the soil is thick with
  tile and potsherd, and in hot summers the unevenly growing corn reveals
  the remains of streets beneath the surface. Casual excavations were made
  here in 1744 and 1833; more systematic ones intermittently between 1864
  and 1884 by the Rev. J.G. Joyce and others; finally, in May 1890, the
  complete uncovering of the whole site was begun by Mr G.E. Fox and
  others. The work was carried on with splendid perseverance, and the
  uncovering of the interior was completed in 1908.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 4.—General Plan of Silchester
    (Calleva Atrebatum).
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/britain_4.png">
               <alt>Fig. 4.--General Plan of Silchester.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>The chief results concern the buildings. Though these have vanished
  wholly from the surface, the foundations and lowest courses of their
  walls survive fairly perfect below ground: thus the plan of the town can
  be minutely recovered, and both the character of the buildings which make
  up a place like Calleva, and the character of Romano-British buildings
  generally, become plainer. Of the buildings the chief are:—</p>
         <p>1. <i>Forum.</i>—Near the middle of the town was a rectangular
  block covering two acres. It comprised a central open court, 132 ft. by
  140 ft. in size, surrounded on three sides by a corridor or cloister,
  with rooms opening on the cloister (fig. 5). On the fourth side was a
  great hall, with rooms opening into it from behind. This hall was 270 ft.
  long and 58 ft. wide; two rows of Corinthian columns ran down the middle,
  and the clerestory roof may have stood 50 ft. above the floor; the walls
  were frescoed or lined with marble, and for ornament there were probably
  statues. Finally, a corridor ran round outside the whole block. Here the
  local authorities had their offices, justice was administered, traders
  trafficked, citizens and idlers gathered. Though we cannot apportion the
  rooms to their precise uses, the great hall was plainly the basilica, for
  meetings and business; the rooms behind it were perhaps law courts, and
  some of the rooms on the other three sides of the quadrangle may have
  been shops. Similar municipal buildings existed in most towns of the
  western Empire, whether they were full municipalities or (as probably
  Calleva was) of lower rank. The Callevan Forum seems in general simpler
  than others, but its basilica is remarkably large. Probably the British
  climate compelled more indoor life than the sunnier south.</p>
         <p>2. <i>Temples.</i>—Two small square temples, of a common
  western-provincial type, were in the east of the town; the <i>cella</i>
  of the larger measured 42 ft. sq., and was lined with Purbeck marble. A
  third, circular temple stood between the forum and the south gate. A
  fourth, a smaller square shrine found in 1907 a little east of the <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page588">[v.04
  p.0588]</ph>forum, yielded some interesting inscriptions which relate
  to a gild (<i>collegium</i>) and incidentally confirm the name
  Calleva.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 5.—Plan of Forum, Basilica and
    surroundings, Silchester.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/britain_5.png">
               <alt>Fig. 5.--Plan of Forum, Basilica and surroundings, Silchester.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>3. <i>Christian Church.</i>—Close outside the south-east angle
  of the forum was a small edifice, 42 ft. by 27 ft., consisting of a nave
  and two aisles which ended at the east in a porch as wide as the
  building, and at the west in an apse and two flanking chambers. The nave
  and porch were floored with plain red tesserae: in the apse was a simple
  mosaic panel in red, black and white. Round the building was a yard,
  fenced with wooden palings; in it were a well near the apse, and a small
  structure of tile with a pit near the east end. No direct proof of date
  or use was discovered. But the ground plan is that of an early Christian
  church of the "basilican" type. This type comprised nave and aisles,
  ending at one end in an apse and two chambers resembling rudimentary
  transepts, and at the other end in a porch (<i>narthex</i>). Previous to
  about <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 420 the porch was often at the east
  end and the apse at the west, and the altar, often movable, stood in the
  apse—as at Silchester, perhaps, on the mosaic panel. A court
  enclosed the whole; near the porch was a laver for the ablutions of
  intending worshippers. Many such churches have been found in other
  countries, especially in Roman Africa; no other satisfactory instance is
  known in Britain.</p>
         <p>4. <i>Town Baths.</i>—A suite of public baths stood a little
  east of the forum. At the entrance were a peristyle court for loungers
  and a latrine: hence the bather passed into the Apodyterium
  (dressing-room), the Frigidarium (cold room) fitted with a cold bath for
  use at the end of the bathing ceremony, and a series of hot
  rooms—the whole resembling many modern Turkish baths. In their
  first form the baths of Silchester were about 160 ft. by 80 ft., but they
  were later considerably extended.</p>
         <p>5. <i>Private Houses.</i>—The private houses of Silchester are
  of two types. They consist either of a row of rooms, with a corridor
  along them, and perhaps one or two additional rooms at one or both ends,
  or of three such corridors and rows of rooms, forming three sides of a
  large square open yard. They are detached houses, standing each in its
  own garden, and not forming terraces or rows. The country houses of Roman
  Britain have long been recognized as embodying these (or allied) types;
  now it becomes plain that they were the normal types throughout Britain.
  They differ widely from the town houses of Rome and Pompeii: they are
  less unlike some of the country houses of Italy and Roman Africa; but
  their real parallels occur in Gaul, and they may be Celtic types modified
  to Roman use—like Indian bungalows. Their internal
  fittings—hypocausts, frescoes, mosaics—are everywhere Roman;
  those at Silchester are average specimens, and, except for one mosaic,
  not individually striking. The largest Silchester house, with a special
  annexe for baths, is usually taken to be a guest-house or inn for
  travellers between London and the west (fig. 6). Altogether, the town
  probably did not contain more than seventy or eighty houses of any size,
  and large spaces were not built over at all. This fact and the peculiar
  character of the houses must have given to Silchester rather the
  appearance of a village with scattered cottages, each in its own plot
  facing its own way, than a town with regular and continuous streets.</p>
         <p>6. <i>Industries.</i>—Shops are conjectured in the forum and
  elsewhere, but were not numerous. Many dyers' furnaces, a little silver
  refinery, and perhaps a bakery have also been noticed.</p>
         <fig>
            <title>
      
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 6.—Plan of supposed Inn and Baths at
    Silchester.
  </title>
            <desc/>
            <image href="images/britain_6.png">
               <alt>Fig. 6.--Plan of supposed Inn and Baths at Silchester.</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>7. <i>Streets, Roads, &amp;c.</i>—The streets were paved with
  gravel: they varied in width up to 28½ ft. They intersect regularly at
  right angles, dividing the town into square blocks, like modern Mannheim
  or Turin, according to a Roman system usual in both Italy and the
  provinces: plainly they were laid out all at once, possibly by Agricola
  (Tac. <i>Agr.</i> 21) and most probably about his time. There were four
  chief gates, not quite symmetrically placed. The town-walls are built of
  flint and concrete bonded with ironstone, and are backed with earth. In
  the plans, though not in the reports, of the excavations, they are shown
  as built later than the streets. No traces of meat-market, theatre or
  aqueduct have come to light: water was got from wells lined with wooden
  tubs, and must have been scanty in dry summers. Smaller objects
  abound—coins, pottery, window and bottle and cup glass, bronze
  ornaments, iron tools, &amp;c.—and many belong to the beginnings of
  Calleva, but few pieces are individually notable. Traces of late Celtic
  art are singularly absent; Roman fashions rule supreme, and inscriptions
  show that even the lower classes here spoke and wrote Latin. Outside the
  walls were the cemeteries, not yet explored. Of suburbs we have as yet no
  hint. Nor indeed is the neighbourhood of Calleva at all rich in Roman
  remains. In fact, as well as in Celtic etymology, it was "the town in the
  forest." A similar absence of remains may be noticed outside other
  Romano-British towns, and is significant of their economic position. Such
  doubtless were most of the towns of Roman Britain—thoroughly
  Romanized, peopled with Roman-speaking citizens, furnished with Roman
  appurtenances, living in Roman ways, but not very large, not very rich, a
  humble witness to the assimilating power of the Roman civilization in
  Britain.</p>
         <p>The country, as opposed to the towns, of Roman Britain seems to have
  been divided into estates, commonly (though perhaps incorrectly) known as
  "villas." Many examples survive, some of them large and luxurious
  country-houses, some mere farms, constructed usually on one of the two
  patterns described in the account of Silchester above. The inhabitants
  were plainly as various—a few of them great nobles and wealthy
  landowners, others small farmers or possibly bailiffs. Some of these
  estates were worked on the true "villa" system, by which the lord
  occupied the "great house," and cultivated the land close round it by
  slaves, while he let the rest to half-free <i>coloni</i>. But other
  systems may have prevailed as well. Among the most important
  country-houses are those of Bignor in west Sussex, and Woodchester and
  Chedworth in Gloucestershire.</p>
         <p>The wealth of the country was principally agrarian. Wheat and wool
  were exported in the 4th century, when, as we have said, Britain was
  especially prosperous. But the details of the trade are unrecorded. More
  is known of the lead and iron mines which, at least in the first two
  centuries, were worked in many districts—lead in Somerset,
  Shropshire, Flintshire and Derbyshire; iron in the west Sussex Weald, the
  Forest of Dean, and (to a slight extent) elsewhere. Other minerals were
  less notable. The gold mentioned by Tacitus proved scanty. The Cornish
  tin, according to present evidence, was worked comparatively little, and
  perhaps most in the later Empire.</p>
         <p>Lastly, the roads. Here we must put aside all idea of "Four Great
  Roads." That category is probably the invention of <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page589">[v.04 p.0589]</ph>antiquaries,
  and certainly unconnected with Roman Britain (see <ph outputclass="sc">Ermine
  Street</ph>). Instead, we may distinguish four main groups of roads
  radiating from London, and a fifth which runs obliquely. One road ran
  south-east to Canterbury and the Kentish ports, of which Richborough
  (Rutupiae) was the most frequented. A second ran west to Silchester, and
  thence by various branches to Winchester, Exeter, Bath, Gloucester and
  South Wales. A third, known afterwards to the English as Watling Street,
  ran by St Albans Wall near Lichfield (Letocetum), to Wroxeter and
  Chester. It also gave access by a branch to Leicester and Lincoln. A
  fourth served Colchester, the eastern counties, Lincoln and York. The
  fifth is that known to the English as the Fosse, which joins Lincoln and
  Leicester with Cirencester, Bath and Exeter. Besides these five groups,
  an obscure road, called by the Saxons Akeman Street, gave alternative
  access from London through Alchester (outside of Bicester) to Bath, while
  another obscure road winds south from near Sheffield, past Derby and
  Birmingham, and connects the lower Severn with the Humber. By these roads
  and their various branches the Romans provided adequate communications
  throughout the lowlands of Britain.</p>
         <p>IV. <i>The End of Roman Britain.</i>—Early in the 4th century it
  was necessary to establish a special coast defence, reaching from the
  Wash to Spithead, against Saxon pirates: there were forts at Brancaster,
  Borough Castle (near Yarmouth), Bradwell (at the mouth of the Colne and
  Blackwater), Reculver, Richborough, Dover and Lymme (all in Kent),
  Pevensey in Sussex, Porchester near Portsmouth, and perhaps also at
  Felixstowe in Suffolk. After about 350, barbarian assaults, not only of
  Saxons but also of Irish (Scoti) and Picts, became commoner and more
  terrible. At the end of the century Magnus Maximus, claiming to be
  emperor, withdrew many troops from Britain and a later pretender did the
  same. Early in the 5th century the Teutonic conquest of Gaul cut the
  island off from Rome. This does not mean that there was any great
  "departure of Romans." The central government simply ceased to send the
  usual governors and high officers. The Romano-British were left to
  themselves. Their position was weak. Their fortresses lay in the north
  and west, while the Saxons attacked the east and south. Their trained
  troops, and even their own numbers, must have been few. It is
  intelligible that they followed a precedent set by Rome in that age, and
  hired Saxons to repel Saxons. But they could not command the fidelity of
  their mercenaries, and the Saxon peril only grew greater. It would seem
  as if the Romano-Britons were speedily driven from the east of the
  island. Even Wroxeter on the Welsh border may have been finally destroyed
  before the end of the 5th century. It seems that the Saxons though
  apparently unable to maintain their hold so far to the west, were able to
  prevent the natives from recovering the lowlands. Thus driven from the
  centres of Romanized life, from the region of walled cities and civilized
  houses, into the hills of Wales and the north-west, the provincials
  underwent an intelligible change. The Celtic element, never quite extinct
  in those hills and, like most forms of barbarism, reasserting itself in
  this wild age—not without reinforcement from
  Ireland—challenged the remnants of Roman civilization and in the
  end absorbed them. The Celtic language reappeared; the Celtic art emerged
  from its shelters in the west to develop in new and medieval
  fashions.</p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="sc">Authorities</ph>.—The principal references to
  early Britain in classical writers occur in Strabo, Diodorus, Julius
  Caesar, the elder Pliny, Tacitus, Ptolemy and Cassius Dio, and in the
  lists of the Antonine Itinerary (probably about <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 210-230; ed. Parthey, 1848), the <i>Notitia
  Dignitatum</i> (about <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 400; ed. Seeck,
  1876), and the Ravennas (7th-century <i>rechauffé</i>; ed. Parthey 1860).
  The chief passages are collected in Petrie's <i>Monumenta Hist.
  Britann.</i> (1848), and (alphabetically) in Holder's <i>Altkeltische
  Sprachschatz</i> (1896-1908). The Roman inscriptions have been collected
  by Hübner, <i>Corpus Inscriptionum Latin.</i> vii. (1873), and in
  supplements by Hübner and Haverfield in the periodical <i>Ephemeris
  epigraphica</i>; see also Hübner, <i>Inscript. Britann. Christianae</i>
  (1876, now out of date), and J. Rhys on Pictish, &amp;c., inscriptions,
  <i>Proceedings Soc. Antiq. Scotland</i>, xxvi., xxxii.</p>
         <p>Of modern works the best summary for Roman Britain and for Caesar's
  invasions is T.R. Holmes, <i>Ancient Britain</i> (1907), who cites
  numerous authorities. See also Sir John Evans, <i>Stone Implements,
  Bronze Implements</i>, and <i>Ancient British Coins</i> (with suppl.);
  Boyd Dawkins, <i>Early Man in Britain</i> (1880); J. Rhys, <i>Celtic
  Britain</i> (3rd ed., 1904). For late Celtic art see J.M. Kemble and A.W.
  Franks' <i>Horae Ferales</i> (1863), and Arthur J. Evans in
  <i>Archaeologia</i>, vols. lii.-lv. Celtic ethnology and philology (see
  <ph outputclass="sc">Celt</ph>) are still in the "age of discussion." For
  ancient earthworks see A. Hadrian Allcroft, <i>Earthwork of England</i>
  (1909).</p>
         <p>For Roman Britain see, in general, Prof. F. Haverfield, <i>The
  Romanization of Roman Britain</i> (Oxford, 1906), and his articles in the
  <i>Victoria County History</i>; also the chapter in Mommsen's <i>Roman
  Provinces</i>; and an article in the <i>Edinburgh Review</i>, 1899. For
  the wall of Hadrian see John Hodgson, <i>History of Northumberland</i>
  (1840); J.C. Bruce, <i>Roman Wall</i> (3rd ed., 1867); reports of
  excavations by Haverfield in the <i>Cumberland Archaeological Society
  Transactions</i> (1894-1904); and R.C. Bosanquet, <i>Roman Camp at
  Housesteads</i> (Newcastle, 1904). For the Scottish Excavations see
  <i>Proceedings of the Society of Antiquaries of Scotland</i>, xx.-xl.,
  and especially J. Macdonald, <i>Bar Hill</i> (reprint, Glasgow, 1906).
  For other forts see R.S. Ferguson, <i>Cumberland Arch. Soc. Trans.</i>
  xii., on Hardknott; and J. Ward, <i>Roman Fort of Gellygaer</i> (London,
  1903). For the Roman occupation of Scotland see Haverfield in <i>Antonine
  Wall Report</i> (1899); J. Macdonald, <i>Roman Stones in Hunterian
  Mus.</i> (1897); and, though an older work, Stuart's <i>Caledonia
  Romana</i> (1852). For Silchester, <i>Archaeologia</i> (1890-1908); for
  Caerwent (ib. 1901-1908); for London, Charles Roach Smith, <i>Roman
  London</i> (1859); for Christianity in Roman Britain, <i>Engl. Hist.
  Rev.</i> (1896); for the villages, Gen. Pitt-Rivers' <i>Excavations in
  Cranborne Chase, &amp;c.</i> (4 vols., 1887-1908), and <i>Proc. Soc. of
  Ant.</i> xviii. For the end of Roman Britain see <i>Engl. Hist. Rev.</i>
  (1904); Prof. Bury's <i>Life of St Patrick</i> (1905); Haverfield's
  <i>Romanization</i> (cited above); and P. Vinogradoff, <i>Growth of the
  Manor</i> (1905), bk. i.</p>
         <p>(F. J. H.)</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Anglo-Saxon Britain</title>
         <p>1. <i>History.</i>—The history of Britain after the withdrawal
  of the Roman troops is extremely obscure, but there can be little doubt
  that for many years the inhabitants of the provinces were exposed to
  devastating raids by the Picts and Scots. According to Gildas it was for
  protection against these incursions that the Britons decided to call in
  the Saxons. Their allies soon obtained a decisive victory; but
  subsequently they turned their arms against the Britons themselves,
  alleging that they had not received sufficient payment for their
  services. A somewhat different account, probably of English origin, may
  be traced in the <i>Historia Brittonum</i>, according to which the first
  leaders of the Saxons, Hengest and Horsa, came as exiles, seeking the
  protection of the British king, Vortigern. Having embraced his service
  they quickly succeeded in expelling the northern invaders. Eventually,
  however, they overcame the Britons through treachery, by inducing the
  king to allow them to send for large bodies of their own countrymen. It
  was to these adventurers, according to tradition, that the kingdom of
  Kent owed its origin. The story is in itself by no means improbable,
  while the dates assigned to the first invasion by various Welsh, Gaulish
  and English authorities, with one exception all fall within about a
  quarter of a century, viz. between the year 428 and the joint reign of
  Martian and Valentinian III. (450-455).</p>
         <p>For the subsequent course of the invasion our information is of the
  most meagre and unsatisfactory character. According to the Anglo-Saxon
  Chronicle the kingdom of Sussex was founded by a certain Ella or Ælle,
  who landed in 477, while Wessex owed its origin to Cerdic, who arrived
  some eighteen years later. No value, however, can be attached to these
  dates; indeed, in the latter case the story itself is open to suspicion
  on several grounds (see <ph outputclass="sc">Wessex</ph>). For the
  movements which led to the foundation of the more northern kingdoms we
  have no evidence worth consideration, nor do we know even approximately
  when they took place. But the view that the invasion was effected
  throughout by small bodies of adventurers acting independently of one
  another, and that each of the various kingdoms owes its origin to a
  separate enterprise, has little probability in its favour. Bede states
  that the invaders belonged to three different nations, Kent and southern
  Hampshire being occupied by Jutes (<i>q.v.</i>), while Essex, Sussex and
  Wessex were founded by the Saxons, and the remaining kingdoms by the
  Angli (<i>q.v.</i>). The peculiarities of social organization in Kent
  certainly tend to show that this kingdom had a different origin from the
  rest; but the evidence for the distinction between the Saxons and the
  Angli is of a much less satisfactory character (see <ph outputclass="sc">Anglo-Saxons</ph>). <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page590">[v.04 p.0590]</ph>The royal
  family of Essex may really have been of Saxon origin (see <ph outputclass="sc">Essex</ph>), but on the other hand the West Saxon royal
  family claimed to be of the same stock as that of Bernicia, and their
  connexions in the past seem to have lain with the Angli.</p>
         <p>We need not doubt that the first invasion was followed by a long
  period of warfare between the natives and the invaders, in which the
  latter gradually strengthened their hold on the conquered territories. It
  is very probable that by the end of the 5th century all the eastern part
  of Britain, at least as far as the Humber, was in their hands. The first
  important check was received at the siege of "Mons Badonicus" in the year
  517 (<i>Ann. Cambr.</i>), or perhaps rather some fifteen or twenty years
  earlier. According to Gildas this event was followed by a period of peace
  for at least forty-four years. In the latter part of the 6th century,
  however, the territories occupied by the invaders seem to have been
  greatly extended. In the south the West Saxons are said to have conquered
  first Wiltshire and then all the upper part of the Thames valley,
  together with the country beyond as far as the Severn. The northern
  frontier also seems to have been pushed considerably farther forward,
  perhaps into what is now Scotland, and it is very probable that the basin
  of the Trent, together with the central districts between the Trent and
  the Thames, was conquered about the same time, though of this we have no
  record. Again, the destruction of Chester about 615 was soon followed by
  the overthrow of the British kingdom of Elmet in south-west Yorkshire,
  and the occupation of Shropshire and the Lothians took place perhaps
  about the same period, that of Herefordshire probably somewhat later. In
  the south, Somerset is said to have been conquered by the West Saxons
  shortly after the middle of the 7th century. Dorset had probably been
  acquired by them before this time, while part of Devon seems to have come
  into their hands soon afterwards.</p>
         <p>The area thus conquered was occupied by a number of separate kingdoms,
  each with a royal family of its own. The districts north of the Humber
  contained two kingdoms, Bernicia (<i>q.v.</i>) and Deira (<i>q.v.</i>),
  which were eventually united in Northumbria. South of the Humber, Lindsey
  seems to have had a dynasty of its own, though in historical times it was
  apparently always subject to the kings of Northumbria or Mercia. The
  upper basin of the Trent formed the nucleus of the kingdom of Mercia
  (<i>q.v.</i>), while farther down the east coast was the kingdom of East
  Anglia (<i>q.v.</i>). Between these two lay a territory called Middle
  Anglia, which is sometimes described as a kingdom, though we do not know
  whether it ever had a separate dynasty. Essex, Kent and Sussex (see
  articles on these kingdoms) preserve the names of ancient kingdoms, while
  the old diocese of Worcester grew out of the kingdom of the Hwicce
  (<i>q.v.</i>), with which it probably coincided in area. The south of
  England, between Sussex and "West Wales" (eventually reduced to
  Cornwall), was occupied by Wessex, which originally also possessed some
  territory to the north of the Thames. Lastly, even the Isle of Wight
  appears to have had a dynasty of its own. But it must not be supposed
  that all these kingdoms were always, or even normally, independent. When
  history begins, Æthelberht, king of Kent, was supreme over all the kings
  south of the Humber. He was followed by the East Anglian king Raedwald,
  and the latter again by a series of Northumbrian kings with an even wider
  supremacy. Before Æthelberht a similar position had been held by the West
  Saxon king Ceawlin, and at a much earlier period, according to tradition,
  by Ella or Ælle, the first king of Sussex. The nature of this supremacy
  has been much discussed, but the true explanation seems to be furnished
  by that principle of personal allegiance which formed such an important
  element in Anglo-Saxon society.</p>
         <p>2. <i>Government.</i>—Internally the various states seem to have
  been organized on very similar lines. In every case we find kingly
  government from the time of our earliest records, and there is no doubt
  that the institution goes back to a date anterior to the invasion of
  Britain (see <ph outputclass="sc">Offa</ph>; <ph outputclass="sc">Wermund</ph>). The royal title, however, was frequently
  borne by more than one person. Sometimes we find one supreme king
  together with a number of under-kings (<i>subreguli</i>); sometimes
  again, especially in the smaller kingdoms, Essex, Sussex and Hwicce, we
  meet with two or more kings, generally brothers, reigning together
  apparently on equal terms. During the greater part of the 8th century
  Kent seems to have been divided into two kingdoms; but as a rule such
  divisions did not last beyond the lifetime of the kings between whom the
  arrangement had been made. The kings were, with very rare exceptions,
  chosen from one particular family in each state, the ancestry of which
  was traced back not only to the founder of the kingdom but also, in a
  remoter degree, to a god. The members of such families were entitled to
  special wergilds, apparently six times as great as those of the higher
  class of nobles (see below).</p>
         <p>The only other central authority in the state was the king's council
  or court (<i>þeod</i>, <i>witan</i>, <i>plebs</i>, <i>concilium</i>).
  This body consisted partly of young warriors in constant attendance on
  the king, and partly of senior officials whom he called together from
  time to time. The terms used for the two classes by Bede are
  <i>milites</i> (<i>ministri</i>) and <i>comites</i>, for which the
  Anglo-Saxon version has <i>þegnas</i> and <i>gesiðas</i> respectively.
  Both classes alike consisted in part of members of the royal family. But
  they were by no means confined to such persons or even to born subjects
  of the king. Indeed, we are told that popular kings like Oswine attracted
  young nobles to their service from all quarters. The functions of the
  council have been much discussed, and it has been claimed that they had
  the right of electing and deposing kings. This view, however, seems to
  involve the existence of a greater feeling for constitutionalism than is
  warranted by the information at our disposal. The incidents which have
  been brought forward as evidence to this effect may with at least equal
  probability be interpreted as cases of profession or transference of
  personal allegiance. In other respects the functions of the council seem
  to have been of a deliberative character. It was certainly customary for
  the king to seek their advice and moral support on important questions,
  but there is nothing to show that he had to abide by the opinion of the
  majority.</p>
         <p>For administrative purposes each of the various kingdoms was divided
  into a number of districts under the charge of royal reeves (<i>cyninges
  gerefa</i>, <i>praefectus</i>, <i>praepositus</i>). These officials seem
  to have been located in royal villages (<i>cyninges tun</i>, <i>villa
  regalis</i>) or fortresses (<i>cyninges burg</i>, <i>urbs regis</i>),
  which served as centres and meeting-places (markets, &amp;c.) for the
  inhabitants of the district, and to which their dues, both in payments
  and services had to be rendered. The usual size of such districts in
  early times seems to have been 300, 600 or 1200 hides.<xref href="#d1e13350/Footnote_091" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref> In addition
  to these districts we find mention also of much larger divisions
  containing 2000, 3000, 5000 or 7000 hides. To this category belong the
  shires of Wessex (Hampshire, Wiltshire, Berkshire, &amp;c.), each of
  which had an earl (<i>aldormon</i>, <i>princeps</i>, <i>dux</i>) of its
  own, at all events from the 8th century onwards. Many, if not all, of
  these persons were members of the royal family, and it is not unlikely
  that they originally bore the kingly title. At all events they are
  sometimes described as <i>subreguli</i>.</p>
         <p>3. <i>Social Organization.</i>—The officials mentioned above,
  whether of royal birth or not, were probably drawn from the king's
  personal retinue. In Anglo-Saxon society, as in that of all Teutonic
  nations in early times, the two most important principles were those of
  kinship and personal allegiance. If a man suffered injury it was to his
  relatives and his lord, rather than to any public official, that he
  applied first for protection and redress. If he was slain, a fixed sum
  (<i>wergild</i>), varying according to his station, had to be paid to his
  relatives, while a further but smaller sum (<i>manbot</i>) was due to his
  lord. These principles applied to all classes of society alike, and
  though strife within the family was by no means unknown, at all events in
  royal families, the actual slaying of a kinsman was regarded as the most
  heinous of all offences. Much the same feeling applied to the slaying of
  a lord—an offence for which no compensation could be rendered. How
  far the armed followers of a lord were entitled to compensation when the
  latter was slain <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page591">[v.04 p.0591]</ph>is uncertain, but in the case of a
  king they received an amount equal to the wergild. Another important
  development of the principle of allegiance is to be found in the custom
  of heriots. In later times this custom amounted practically to a system
  of death-duties, payable in horses and arms or in money to the lord of
  the deceased. There can be little doubt, however, that originally it was
  a restoration to the lord of the military outfit with which he had
  presented his man when he entered his service. The institution of
  thegnhood, <i>i.e.</i> membership of the <i>comitatus</i> or retinue of a
  prince, offered the only opening by which public life could be entered.
  Hence it was probably adopted almost universally by young men of the
  highest classes. The thegn was expected to fight for his lord, and
  generally to place his services at his disposal in both war and peace.
  The lord, on the other hand, had to keep his thegns and reward them from
  time to time with arms and treasure. When they were of an age to marry he
  was expected to provide them with the means of doing so. If the lord was
  a king this provision took the form of a grant, perhaps normally ten
  hides, from the royal lands. Such estates were not strictly hereditary,
  though as a mark of favour they were not unfrequently re-granted to the
  sons of deceased holders.</p>
         <p>The structure of society in England was of a somewhat peculiar type.
  In addition to slaves, who in early times seem to have been numerous, we
  find in Wessex and apparently also in Mercia three classes, described as
  <i>twelfhynde</i>, <i>sixhynde</i> and <i>twihynde</i> from the amount of
  their wergilds, viz. 1200, 600 and 200 shillings respectively. It is
  probable that similar classes existed also in Northumbria, though not
  under the same names. Besides these terms there were others which were
  probably in use everywhere, viz. <i>gesiðcund</i> for the two higher
  classes and <i>ceorlisc</i> for the lowest. Indeed, we find these terms
  even in Kent, though the social system of that kingdom seems to have been
  of an essentially different character. Here the wergild of the
  <i>ceorlisc</i> class amounted to 100 shillings, each containing twenty
  silver coins (<i>sceattas</i>), as against 200 shillings of four (in
  Wessex five) silver coins, and was thus very much greater than the
  latter. Again, there was apparently but one <i>gestiðcund</i> class in
  Kent, with a wergild of 300 shillings, while, on the other hand, below
  the <i>ceorlisc</i> class we find three classes of persons described as
  <i>laetas</i>, who corresponded in all probability to the <i>liti</i> or
  freedmen of the continental laws, and who possessed wergilds of 80, 60
  and 40 shillings respectively. To these we find nothing analogous in the
  other kingdoms, though the poorer classes of Welsh freemen had wergilds
  varying from 120 to 60 shillings. It should be added that the
  differential treatment of the various classes was by no means confined to
  the case of wergilds. We find it also in the compensations to which they
  were entitled for various injuries, in the fines to which they were
  liable, and in the value attached to their oaths. Generally, though not
  always, the proportions observed were the same as in the wergilds.</p>
         <p>The nature of the distinction between the <i>gesiðcund</i> and
  <i>ceorlisc</i> classes is nowhere clearly explained; but it was
  certainly hereditary and probably of considerable antiquity. In general
  we may perhaps define them as nobles and commons, though in view of the
  numbers of the higher classes it would probably be more correct to speak
  of gentry and peasants. The distinction between the <i>twelfhynde</i> and
  <i>sixhynde</i> classes was also in part at least hereditary, but there
  is good reason for believing that it arose out of the possession of land.
  The former consisted of persons who possessed, whether as individuals or
  families, at least five hides of land—which practically means a
  village—while the latter were landless, <i>i.e.</i> probably
  without this amount of land. Within the <i>ceorlisc</i> class we find
  similar subdivisions, though they were not marked by a difference in
  wergild. The <i>gafolgelda</i> or <i>tributarius</i> (tribute-payer)
  seems to have been a ceorl who possessed at least a hide, while the
  <i>gebur</i> was without land of his own, and received his outfit as a
  loan from his lord.</p>
         <p>4. <i>Payments and Services.</i>—We have already had occasion to
  refer to the dues which were rendered by different classes of the
  population, and which the reeves in royal villages had to collect and
  superintend. The payments seem to have varied greatly according to the
  class from which they were due. Those rendered by landowners seem to have
  been known as <i>feorm</i> or <i>fostor</i>, and consisted of a fixed
  quantity of articles paid in kind. In Ine's Laws (cap. 70) we find a list
  of payments specified for a unit of ten hides, perhaps the normal holding
  of a <i>twelfhynde</i> man—though on the other hand it may be
  nothing more than a mere fiscal unit in an aggregate of estates. The list
  consists of oxen, sheep, geese, hens, honey, ale, loaves, cheese, butter,
  fodder, salmon and eels. Very similar specifications are found elsewhere.
  The payments rendered by the <i>gafolgelda</i> (<i>tributarius</i>) were
  known as <i>gafol</i> (<i>tributuni</i>), as his name implies. In Ine's
  Laws we hear only of the <i>hwitel</i> or white cloak, which was to be of
  the value of six pence per household (hide), and of barley, which was to
  be six pounds in weight for each worker. In later times we meet with many
  other payments both in money and in kind, some of which were doubtless in
  accordance with ancient custom. On the other hand the <i>gebur</i> seems
  not to have been liable to payments of this kind, presumably because the
  land which he cultivated formed part of the demesne (<i>inland</i>) of
  his lord. The term <i>gafol</i>, however, may have been applied to the
  payments which he rendered to the latter.</p>
         <p>The services required of landowners were very manifold in character.
  Probably the most important were military service (<i>fird</i>,
  <i>expeditio</i>) and the repairing of fortifications and
  bridges—the <i>trinoda necessitas</i> of later times. Besides these
  we find reference in charters of the 9th century to the keeping of the
  king's hunters, horses, dogs and hawks, and the entertaining of
  messengers and other persons in the king's service. The duties of men of
  the <i>sixhynde</i> class, if they are to be identified with the
  <i>radcnihtas</i> (<i>radmanni</i>) of later times, probably consisted
  chiefly in riding on the king's (or their lord's) business. The services
  of the peasantry can only be conjectured from what we find in later
  times. Presumably their chief duty was to undertake a share in the
  cultivation of the demesne land. We need scarcely doubt also that the
  labour of repairing fortifications and bridges, though it is charged
  against the landowners, was in reality delegated by them to their
  dependents.</p>
         <p>5. <i>Warfare.</i>—All classes are said to have been liable to
  the duty of military service. Hence, since the ceorls doubtless formed
  the bulk of the population, it has been thought that the Anglo-Saxon
  armies of early times were essentially peasant forces. The evidence at
  our disposal, however, gives little justification for such a view. The
  regulation that every five or six hides should supply a warrior was not a
  product of the Danish invasions, as is sometimes stated, but goes back at
  least to the beginning of the 9th century. Had the fighting material been
  drawn from the <i>ceorlisc</i> class a warrior would surely have been
  required from each hide, but for military service no such regulation is
  found. Again, the fird (<i>fyrd</i>) was composed of mounted warriors
  during the 9th century, though apparently they fought on foot, and there
  are indications that such was the case also in the 7th century. No doubt
  ceorls took part in military expeditions, but they may have gone as
  attendants and camp-followers rather than as warriors, their chief
  business being to make stockades and bridges, and especially to carry
  provisions. The serious fighting, however, was probably left to the
  <i>gesiðcund</i> classes, who possessed horses and more or less effective
  weapons. Indeed, there is good reason for regarding these classes as
  essentially military.</p>
         <p>The chief weapons were the sword and spear. The former were two-edged
  and on the average about 3 ft. long. The hilts were often elaborately
  ornamented and sometimes these weapons were of considerable value. No
  definite line can be drawn between the spear proper and the javelin. The
  spear-heads which have been found in graves vary considerably in both
  form and size. They were fitted on to the shaft, by a socket which was
  open on one side. Other weapons appear to have been quite rare. Bows and
  arrows were certainly in use for sporting purposes, but there is no
  reason for believing that they were much used in warfare before the
  Danish invasions. They are very seldom met with in graves. The most
  common article of defensive armour was the shield, which was small and
  circular and apparently of quite thin lime-wood, the edge being formed
  <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page592">[v.04
  p.0592]</ph>probably by a thin band of iron. In the centre of the
  shield, in order to protect the hand which held it, was a strong iron
  boss, some 7 in. in diameter and projecting about 3 in. It is clear from
  literary evidence that the helmet (<i>helm</i>) and coat of chain mail
  (<i>byrne</i>) were also in common use. They are seldom found in graves,
  however, whether owing to the custom of heriots or to the fact that, on
  account of their relatively high value, they were frequently handed on
  from generation to generation as heirlooms. Greaves are not often
  mentioned. It is worth noting that in later times the heriot of an
  "ordinary thegn" (<i>medema þegn</i>)—by which is meant apparently
  not a king's thegn but a man of the <i>twelfhynde</i>
  class—consisted of his horse with its saddle, &amp;c. and his arms,
  or two pounds of silver as an equivalent of the whole. The arms required
  were probably a sword, helmet, coat of mail and one or two spears and
  shields. There are distinct indications that a similar outfit was fairly
  common in Ine's time, and that its value was much the same. One would
  scarcely be justified, however, in supposing that it was anything like
  universal; for the purchasing power of such a sum was at that time
  considerable, representing as it did about 16-20 oxen or 100-120 sheep.
  It would hardly be safe to credit men of the <i>sixhynde</i> class in
  general with more than a horse, spear and shield.</p>
         <p>6. <i>Agriculture and Village Life.</i>—There is no doubt that a
  fairly advanced system of agriculture must have been known to the
  Anglo-Saxons before they settled in Britain. This is made clear above all
  by the representation of a plough drawn by two oxen in one of the very
  ancient rock-carvings at Tegneby in Bohuslän. In Domesday Book the heavy
  plough with eight oxen seems to be universal, and it can be traced back
  in Kent to the beginning of the 9th century. In this kingdom the system
  of agricultural terminology was based on it. The unit was the
  <i>sulung</i> (<i>aratrum</i>) or ploughland (from <i>sulh</i>,
  "plough"), the fourth part of which was the <i>geocled</i> or <i>geoc</i>
  (<i>jugum</i>), originally a yoke of oxen. An analogy is supplied by the
  <i>carucata</i> of the Danelagh, the eighth part of which was the
  <i>bouata</i> or "ox-land." In the 10th century the <i>sulung</i> seems
  to have been identified with the hide, but in earlier times it contained
  apparently two hides. The hide itself, which was the regular unit in the
  other kingdoms, usually contained 120 acres in later times and was
  divided into four <i>girda</i> (<i>virgatae</i>) or yardlands. But
  originally it seems to have meant simply the land pertaining to a
  household, and its area in early times is quite uncertain, though
  probably far less. For the acre also there was in later times a standard
  length and breadth, the former being called <i>furhlang</i>
  (<i>furlong</i>) and reckoned at one-eighth of a mile, while the
  <i>aecerbraedu</i> or "acre-breadth" (chain) was also a definite measure.
  We need not doubt, however, that in practice the form of the acre was
  largely conditioned by the nature of the ground. Originally it is thought
  to have been the measure of a day's ploughing, in which case the
  dimensions given above would scarcely be reached. Account must also be
  taken of the possibility that in early times lighter teams were in
  general use. If so the normal dimensions of the acre may very well have
  been quite different.</p>
         <p>The husbandry was of a co-operative character. In the 11th century it
  was distinctly unusual for a peasant to possess a whole team of his own,
  and there is no reason for supposing the case to have been otherwise in
  early times; for though the peasant might then hold a hide, the hide
  itself was doubtless smaller and not commensurate in any way with the
  ploughland. The holdings were probably not compact but consisted of
  scattered strips in common fields, changed perhaps from year to year, the
  choice being determined by lot or otherwise. As for the method of
  cultivation itself there is little or no evidence. Both the "two-course
  system" and the "three-course system" may have been in use; but on the
  other hand it is quite possible that in many cases the same ground was
  not sown more than once in three years. The prevalence of the
  co-operative principle, it may be observed, was doubtless due in large
  measure to the fact that the greater part of England, especially towards
  the east, was settled not in scattered farms or hamlets but in compact
  villages with the cultivated lands lying round them.</p>
         <p>The mill was another element which tended to promote the same
  principle. There can be little doubt that before the Anglo-Saxons came to
  Britain they possessed no instrument for grinding corn except the quern
  (<i>cweorn</i>), and in remote districts this continued in use until
  quite late times. The grinding seems to have been performed chiefly by
  female slaves, but occasionally we hear also of a donkey-mill
  (<i>esolcweorn</i>). The mill proper, however, which was derived from the
  Romans, as its name (<i>mylen</i>, from Lat. <i>molina</i>) indicates,
  must have come into use fairly early. In the 11th century every village
  of any size seems to have possessed one, while the earliest references go
  back to the 8th century. It is not unlikely that they were in use during
  the Roman occupation of Britain, and consequently that they became known
  to the invaders almost from the first. The mills were presumably driven
  for the most part by water, though we have a reference to a windmill as
  early as the year 833.</p>
         <p>All the ordinary domestic animals were known. Cattle and sheep were
  pastured on the common lands appertaining to the village, while pigs,
  which (especially in Kent) seem to have been very numerous, were kept in
  the woods. Bee-keeping was also practised. In all these matters the
  invasion of Britain had brought about no change. The cultivation of fruit
  and vegetables on the other hand was probably almost entirely new. The
  names are almost all derived from Latin, though most of them seem to have
  been known soon after the invasion, at all events by the 7th century.</p>
         <p>From the considerations pointed out above we can hardly doubt that the
  village possessed a certain amount of corporate life, centred perhaps in
  an ale-house where its affairs were discussed by the inhabitants. There
  is no evidence, however, which would justify us in crediting such
  gatherings with any substantial degree of local authority. So far as the
  limited information at our disposal enables us to form an opinion, the
  responsibility both for the internal peace of the village, and for its
  obligations to the outside world, seems to have lain with the lord or his
  steward (<i>gerefa</i>, <i>villicus</i>) from the beginning. A quite
  opposite view has, it is true, found favour with many scholars, viz. that
  the villages were orginally settlements of free kindreds, and that the
  lord's authority was superimposed on them at a later date. This view is
  based mainly on the numerous place-names ending in <i>-ing</i>,
  <i>-ingham</i>, <i>-ington</i>, &amp;c., in which the syllable
  <i>-ing</i> is thought to refer to kindreds of cultivators. It is more
  probable, however, that these names are derived from persons of the
  <i>twelfhynde</i> class to whom the land had been granted. In many cases
  indeed there is good reason for doubting whether the name is a patronymic
  at all.</p>
         <p>The question how far the villages were really new settlements is
  difficult to answer, for the terminations <i>-ham</i>, <i>-ton</i>,
  &amp;c. cannot be regarded as conclusive evidence. Thus according to the
  Anglo-Saxon Chronicle (ann. 571) Bensington and Eynsham were formerly
  British villages. Even if the first part of Egonesham is
  English—which is by no means certain—it is hardly sufficient
  reason for discrediting this statement, for Canterbury
  (<i>Cantwaraburg</i>) and Rochester (<i>Hrofes ceaster</i>) were without
  doubt Roman places in spite of their English names. On the whole it seems
  likely that the cultivation of the land was not generally interrupted for
  more than a very few years; hence the convenience of utilizing existing
  sites of villages would be obvious, even if the buildings themselves had
  been burnt.</p>
         <p>7. <i>Towns.</i>—Gildas states that in the time of the Romans
  Britain contained twenty-eight cities (<i>civitates</i>), besides a
  number of fortresses (<i>castetta</i>). Most of these were situated
  within the territories eventually occupied by the invaders, and reappear
  as towns in later times. Their history in the intervening period,
  however, is wrapped in obscurity. Chester appears to have been deserted
  for three centuries after its destruction early in the 7th century, and
  in most of the other cases there are features observable in the situation
  and plan of the medieval town which suggest that its occupation had not
  been continuous. Yet London and Canterbury must have recovered a certain
  amount of importance quite early, at all events within two centuries
  after the invasion, and the same is probably true of York, <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page593">[v.04
  p.0593]</ph>Lincoln and a few other places. The term applied to both
  the cities and the fortresses of the Romans was <i>ceaster</i> (Lat.
  <i>castra</i>), less frequently the English word <i>burg</i>. There is
  little or no evidence for the existence of towns other than Roman in
  early times, for the word <i>urbs</i> is merely a translation of
  <i>burg</i>, which was used for any fortified dwelling-place, and it is
  improbable that anything which could properly be called a town was known
  to the invaders before their arrival in Britain. The Danish settlements
  at the end of the 9th century and the defensive system initiated by King
  Alfred gave birth to a new series of fortified towns, from which the
  boroughs of the middle ages are mainly descended.</p>
         <p>8. <i>Houses.</i>—Owing to the fact that houses were built
  entirely of perishable materials, wood and wattle, we are necessarily
  dependent almost wholly upon literary evidence for knowledge of this
  subject. Stone seems to have been used first for churches, but this was
  not before the 7th century, and we are told that at first masons were
  imported from Gaul. Indeed wood was used for many churches, as well as
  for most secular buildings, until a much later period. The walls were
  formed either of stout planks laid together vertically or horizontally,
  or else of posts at a short distance from one another, the interstices
  being filled up with wattlework daubed with clay. It is not unlikely that
  the houses of wealthy persons were distinguished by a good deal of
  ornamentation in carving and painting. The roof was high-pitched and
  covered with straw, hay, reeds or tiles. The regular form of the
  buildings was rectangular, the gable sides probably being shorter than
  the others. There is little evidence for partitions inside, and in
  wealthy establishments the place of rooms seems to have been supplied by
  separate buildings within the same enclosure. The windows must have been
  mere openings in the walls or roof, for glass was not used for this
  purpose before the latter part of the 7th century. Stoves were known, but
  most commonly heat was obtained from an open fire in the centre of the
  building. Of the various buildings in a wealthy establishment the chief
  were the hall (<i>heall</i>), which was both a dining and reception room,
  and the "lady's bower" (<i>brydbur</i>), which served also as a bedroom
  for the master and mistress. To these we have to add buildings for the
  attendants, kitchen, bakehouse, &amp;c., and farm buildings. There is
  little or no evidence for the use of two-storeyed houses in early times,
  though in the 10th and 11th centuries they were common. The whole group
  of buildings stood in an enclosure (<i>tun</i>) surrounded by a stockade
  (<i>burg</i>), which perhaps rested on an earthwork, though this is
  disputed. Similarly the homestead of the peasant was surrounded by a
  fence (<i>edor</i>).</p>
         <p>9. <i>Clothes.</i>—The chief material for clothing was at first
  no doubt wool, though linen must also have been used and later became
  fairly common. The chief garments were the coat (<i>roc</i>), the
  trousers (<i>brec</i>), and the cloak, for which there seem to have been
  a number of names (<i>loða</i>, <i>hacele</i>, <i>sciccing</i>,
  <i>pad</i>, <i>hwitel</i>). To these we may add the hat (<i>haet</i>),
  belt (<i>gyrdel</i>), stockings (<i>hosa</i>), shoes (<i>scoh</i>,
  <i>gescy</i>, <i>rifeling</i>) and gloves (<i>glof</i>). The
  <i>crusene</i> was a fur coat, while the <i>serc</i> or <i>smoc</i> seems
  to have been an undergarment and probably sleeveless. The whole attire
  was of national origin and had probably been in use long before the
  invasion of Britain. In the great bog-deposit at Thorsbjaerg in Angel,
  which dates from about the 4th century, there were found a coat with long
  sleeves, in a fair state of preservation, a pair of long trousers with
  remains of socks attached, several shoes and portions of square cloaks,
  one of which had obviously been dyed green. The dress of the upper
  classes must have been of a somewhat gorgeous character, especially when
  account is taken of the brooches and other ornaments which they wore. It
  is worth noting that according to Jordanes the Swedes in the 6th century
  were splendidly dressed.</p>
         <p>10. <i>Trade.</i>—The few notices of this subject which occur in
  the early laws seem to refer primarily to cattle-dealing. But there can
  be no doubt that a considerable import and export trade with the
  continent had sprung up quite early. In Bede's time, if not before,
  London was resorted to by many merchants both by land and by sea. At
  first the chief export trade was probably in slaves. English slaves were
  to be obtained in Rome even before the end of the 6th century, as appears
  from the well-known story of Gregory the Great. Since the standard price
  of slaves on the continent was in general three or four times as great as
  it was in England, the trade must have been very profitable. After the
  adoption of Christianity it was gradually prohibited by the laws. The
  nature of the imports during the heathen period may be learned chiefly
  from the graves, which contain many brooches and other ornaments of
  continental origin, and also a certain number of silver, bronze and glass
  vessels. With the introduction of Christianity the ecclesiastical
  connexion between England and the continent without doubt brought about a
  large increase in the imports of secular as well as religious objects,
  and the frequency of pilgrimages by persons of high rank must have had
  the same effect. The use of silk (<i>seoluc</i>) and the adoption of the
  mancus (see below) point to communication, direct or indirect, with more
  distant countries. In the 8th century we hear frequently of tolls on
  merchant ships at various ports, especially London.</p>
         <p>11. <i>Coinage.</i>—The earliest coins which can be identified
  with certainty are some silver pieces which bear in Runic letters the
  name of the Mercian king Æthelred (675-704). There are others, however,
  of the same type and standard (about 21 grains) which may be attributed
  with probability to his father Penda (d. 655). But it is clear from the
  laws of Æthelberht that a regular silver coinage was in use at least half
  a century before this time, and it is not unlikely that many unidentified
  coins may go back to the 6th century. These are fairly numerous, and are
  either without inscriptions or, if they do bear letters at all, they seem
  to be mere corruptions of Roman legends. Their designs are derived from
  Roman or Frankish coins, especially the former, and their weight varies
  from about 10 to 21 grains, though the very light coins are rare.
  Anonymous gold coins, resembling Frankish trientes in type and standard
  (21 grains), are also fairly common, though they must have passed out of
  use very early, as the laws give no hint of their existence. Larger gold
  coins (<i>solidi</i>) are very rare. In the early laws the money actually
  in use appears to have been entirely silver. In Offa's time a new gold
  coin, the <i>mancus</i>, resembling in standard the Roman solidus (about
  70 grains), was introduced from Mahommedan countries. The oldest extant
  specimen bears a faithfully copied Arabic inscription. In the same reign
  the silver coins underwent a considerable change in type, being made
  larger and thinner, while from this time onwards they always bore the
  name of the king (or queen or archbishop) for whom they were issued. The
  design and execution also became remarkably good. Their weight was at
  first unaffected, but probably towards the close of Offa's reign it was
  raised to about 23 grains, at which standard it seems to have remained,
  nominally at least, until the time of Alfred. It is to be observed that
  with the exception of Burgred's coins and a few anonymous pieces the
  silver was never adulterated. No bronze coins were current except in
  Northumbria, where they were extremely common in the 9th century.</p>
         <p>Originally <i>scilling</i> ("shilling") and <i>sceatt</i> seem to have
  been the terms for gold and silver coins respectively. By the time of
  Ine, however, <i>pending</i>, <i>pen(n)ing</i> ("penny"), had already
  come into use for the latter, while, owing to the temporary disappearance
  of a gold coinage, <i>scilling</i> had come to denote a mere unit of
  account. It was, however, a variable unit, for the Kentish shilling
  contained twenty <i>sceattas</i> (pence), while the Mercian contained
  only four. The West Saxon shilling seems originally to have been
  identical with the Mercian, but later it contained five pence. Large
  payments were generally made by weight, 240-250 pence being reckoned to
  the pound, perhaps from the 7th century onwards. The mancus was equated
  with thirty pence, probably from the time of its introduction. This means
  that the value of gold relatively to silver was 10:1 from the end of
  Offa's reign. There is reason, however, for thinking that in earlier
  times it was as low as 6:1, or even 5:1. In Northumbria a totally
  different monetary system prevailed, the unit being the <i>tryms</i>,
  which contained three <i>sceattas</i> or pence. As to the value of the
  bronze coins we are without information.</p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page594">[v.04 p.0594]</ph>
         </p>
         <p>The purchasing power of money was very great. The sheep was valued at
  a shilling in both Wessex and Mercia, from early times till the 11th
  century. One pound was the normal price of a slave and half a pound that
  of a horse. The price of a pig was twice, and that of an ox six times as
  great as that of a sheep. Regarding the prices of commodities other than
  live-stock we have little definite information, though an approximate
  estimate may be made of the value of arms. It is worth noticing that we
  often hear of payments in gold and silver vessels in place of money. In
  the former case the mancus was the usual unit of calculation.</p>
         <p>12. <i>Ornaments.</i>—Of these the most interesting are the
  brooches which were worn by both sexes and of which large numbers have
  been found in heathen cemeteries. They may be classed under eight leading
  types: (1) circular or ring-shaped, (2) cruciform, (3) square-headed, (4)
  radiated, (5) S-shaped, (6) bird-shaped, (7) disk-shaped, (8) cupelliform
  or saucer-shaped. Of these Nos. 5 and 6 appear to be of continental
  origin, and this is probably the case also with No. 4 and in part with
  No. 7. But the last-mentioned type varies greatly, from rude and almost
  plain disks of bronze to magnificent gold specimens studded with gems.
  No. 8 is believed to be peculiar to England, and occurs chiefly in the
  southern Midlands, specimens being usually found in pairs. The interiors
  are gilt, often furnished with detachable plates and sometimes set with
  brilliants. The remaining types were probably brought over by the
  Anglo-Saxons at the time of the invasion. Nos. 1 and 3 are widespread
  outside England, but No. 2, though common in Scandinavian countries, is
  hardly to be met with south of the Elbe. It is worth noting that a number
  of specimens were found in the cremation cemetery at Borgstedterfeld near
  Rendsburg. In England it occurs chiefly in the more northern counties.
  Nos. 2 and 3 vary greatly in size, from 2½ to 7 in. or more. The smaller
  specimens are quite plain, but the larger ones are gilt and generally of
  a highly ornamental character. In later times we hear of brooches worth
  as much as six mancusas, <i>i.e.</i> equivalent to six oxen.</p>
         <p>Among other ornaments we may mention hairpins, rings and ear-rings,
  and especially buckles which are often of elaborate workmanship.
  Bracelets and necklets are not very common, a fact which is rather
  surprising, as in early times, before the issuing of a coinage, these
  articles (<i>beagas</i>) took the place of money to a large extent. The
  glass vessels are finely made and of somewhat striking appearance, though
  they closely resemble contemporary continental types. Since the art of
  glass-working was unknown, according to Bede, until nearly the end of the
  7th century, it is probable that these were all of continental or
  Roman-British origin.</p>
         <p>13. <i>Amusements</i>.—It is clear from the frequent references
  to dogs and hawks in the charters that hunting and falconry were keenly
  pursued by the kings and their retinues. Games, whether indoor or
  outdoor, are much less frequently mentioned, but there is no doubt that
  the use of dice (<i>taefl</i>) was widespread. At court much time was
  given to poetic recitation, often accompanied by music, and accomplished
  poets received liberal rewards. The chief musical instrument was the harp
  (<i>hearpe</i>), which is often mentioned. Less frequently we hear of the
  flute (<i>pipe</i>) and later also of the fiddle (<i>fiðele</i>).
  Trumpets (<i>horn</i>, <i>swegelhorn</i>, <i>byme</i>) appear to have
  been used chiefly as signals.</p>
         <p>14. <i>Writing.</i>—The Runic alphabet seems to have been the
  only form of writing known to the Anglo-Saxons before the invasion of
  Britain, and indeed until the adoption of Christianity. In its earliest
  form, as it appears in inscriptions on various articles found in
  Schleswig and in Scandinavian countries, it consisted of twenty-four
  letters, all of which occur in abecedaria in England. In actual use,
  however, two letters soon became obsolete, but a number of others were
  added from time to time, some of which are found also on the continent,
  while others are peculiar to certain parts of England. Originally the
  Runic alphabet seems to have been used for writing on wooden boards,
  though none of these have survived. The inscriptions which have come down
  to us are engraved partly on memorial stones, which are not uncommon in
  the north of England, and partly on various metal objects, ranging from
  swords to brooches. The adoption of Christianity brought about the
  introduction of the Roman alphabet; but the older form of writing did not
  immediately pass out of use, for almost all the inscriptions which we
  possess date from the 7th or following centuries. Coins with Runic
  legends were issued at least until the middle of the 8th century, and
  some of the memorial stones date probably even from the 9th. The most
  important of the latter are the column at Bewcastle, Cumberland, believed
  to commemorate Alhfrith, the son of Oswio, who died about 670, and the
  cross at Ruthwell, Dumfriesshire, which is probably about a century
  later. The Roman alphabet was very soon applied to the purpose of writing
  the native language, <i>e.g.</i> in the publication of the laws of
  Æthelberht. Yet the type of character in which even the earliest
  surviving MSS. are written is believed to be of Celtic origin. Most
  probably it was introduced by the Irish missionaries who evangelized the
  north of England, though Welsh influence is scarcely impossible.
  Eventually this alphabet was enlarged (probably before the end of the 7th
  century) by the inclusion of two Runic letters for <i>th</i> and
  <i>w</i>.</p>
         <p>15. <i>Marriage.</i>—This is perhaps the subject on which our
  information is most inadequate. It is evident that the relationships
  which prohibited marriage were different from those recognized by the
  Church; but the only fact which we know definitely is that it was
  customary, at least in Kent, for a man to marry his stepmother. In the
  Kentish laws marriage is represented as hardly more than a matter of
  purchase; but whether this was the case in the other kingdoms also the
  evidence at our disposal is insufficient to decide. We know, however,
  that in addition to the sum paid to the bride's guardian, it was
  customary for the bridegroom to make a present (<i>morgengifu</i>) to the
  bride herself, which, in the case of queens, often consisted of a
  residence and considerable estates. Such persons also had retinues and
  fortified residences of their own. In the Kentish laws provision is made
  for widows to receive a proportionate share in their husbands'
  property.</p>
         <p>16. <i>Funeral Rites.</i>—Both inhumation and cremation were
  practised in heathen times. The former seems to have prevailed
  everywhere; the latter, however, was much more common in the more
  northern counties than in the south, though cases are fairly numerous
  throughout the valley of the Thames. In <i>Beowulf</i> cremation is
  represented as the prevailing custom. There is no evidence that it was
  still practised when the Roman and Celtic missionaries arrived, but it is
  worth noting that according to the tradition given in the Anglo-Saxon
  Chronicle, Oxfordshire, where the custom seems to have been fairly
  common, was not conquered before the latter part of the 6th century. The
  burnt remains were generally, if not always, enclosed in urns and then
  buried. The urns themselves are of clay, somewhat badly baked, and bear
  geometrical patterns applied with a punch. They vary considerably in size
  (from 4 to 12 in. or more in diameter) and closely resemble those found
  in northern Germany. Inhumation graves are sometimes richly furnished.
  The skeleton is laid out at full length, generally with the head towards
  the west or north, a spear at one side and a sword and shield obliquely
  across the middle. Valuable brooches and other ornaments are often found.
  In many other cases, however, the grave contained nothing except a small
  knife and a simple brooch or a few beads. Usually both classes of graves
  lie below the natural surface of the ground without any perceptible trace
  of a barrow.</p>
         <p>17. <i>Religion.</i>—Here again the information at our disposal
  is very limited. There can be little doubt that the heathen Angli
  worshipped certain gods, among them Ti (Tig), Woden, Thunor and a goddess
  Frigg, from whom the names Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday and Friday are
  derived. Ti was probably the same god of whom early Roman writers speak
  under the name Mars (see <ph outputclass="sc">Týr</ph>), while Thunor was
  doubtless the thunder-god (see <ph outputclass="sc">Thor</ph>). From Woden
  (<i>q.v.</i>) most of the royal families traced their descent. Seaxneat,
  the ancestor of the East Saxon dynasty, was also in all probability a god
  (see <ph outputclass="sc">Essex, Kingdom of</ph>).</p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page595">[v.04 p.0595]</ph>
         </p>
         <p>Of anthropomorphic representations of the gods we have no clear
  evidence, though we do hear of shrines in sacred enclosures, at which
  sacrifices were offered. It is clear also that there were persons
  specially set apart for the priesthood, who were not allowed to bear arms
  or to ride except on mares. Notices of sacred trees and groves, springs,
  stones, &amp;c., are much more frequent than those referring to the gods.
  We hear also a good deal of witches and valkyries, and of charms and
  magic; as an instance we may cite the fact that certain (Runic) letters
  were credited, as in the North, with the power of loosening bonds. It is
  probable also that the belief in the spirit world and in a future life
  was of a somewhat similar kind to what we find in Scandinavian religion.
  (See <ph outputclass="sc">Teutonic Peoples</ph>, §6.)</p>
         <p>The chief primary authorities are Gildas, <i>De Excidio
  Britanniae</i>, and Nennius, <i>Historia Britonum</i> (ed. San-Marte,
  Berlin, 1844); Th. Mommsen in <i>Mon. Germ. Hist., Auct. Antiquiss.</i>,
  tom. xiii. (Berlin, 1898); Bede, <i>Hist. Eccl.</i> (ed. C. Plummer,
  Oxford, 1896); the <i>Saxon Chronicle</i> (ed. C. Plummer, Oxford,
  1892-1899); and the <i>Anglo-Saxon Laws</i> (ed. F. Liebermann, Halle,
  1903), and Charters (W. de G. Birch, <i>Cartularium Saxonicum</i>,
  London, 1885-1893). Modern authorities: Sh. Turner, <i>History of the
  Anglo-Saxons</i> (London, 1799-1805; 7th ed., 1852); Sir F. Palgrave,
  <i>Rise and Progress of the English Commonwealth</i> (London, 1831-1832);
  J.M. Kemble, <i>The Saxons in England</i> (London, 1849; 2nd ed., 1876);
  K. Maurer, <i>Kritische Überschau d. deutschen Gesetzgebung u.
  Rechtswissenschaft</i>, vols. i.-iii. (Munich, 1853-1855); J.M.
  Lappenberg, <i>Geschichte von England</i> (Hamburg, 1834); <i>History of
  England under the Anglo-Saxon Kings</i> (London, 1845; 2nd ed., 1881);
  J.R. Green, <i>The Making of England</i> (London, 1881); T. Hodgkin,
  <i>History of England from the Earliest Times to the Norman Conquest</i>
  (vol. i. of <i>The Political History of England</i>) (London, 1906); F.
  Seebohm, <i>The English Village Community</i> (London, 1883); A. Meitzen,
  <i>Siedelung und Agrarwesen d. Westgermanen, u. Ostgermanen, &amp;c.</i>
  (Berlin, 1895); Sir F. Pollock and F.W. Maitland, <i>History of English
  Law</i> (Cambridge, 1895; 2nd ed., 1898); F.W. Maitland, <i>Domesday Book
  and Beyond</i> (Cambridge, 1897); F. Seebohm, <i>Tribal Custom in
  Anglo-Saxon Law</i> (London, 1903); P. Vinogradoff, <i>The Growth of the
  Manor</i> (London, 1905); H.M. Chadwick, <i>Studies on Anglo-Saxon
  Institutions</i> (Cambridge, 1905); <i>The Origin of the English
  Nation</i> (<i>ib.</i>, 1907); M. Heyne, <i>Über die Lage und
  Construction der Halle Heorot</i> (Paderborn, 1864); R. Henning, <i>Das
  deutsche Haus</i> (<i>Quellen u. Forschungen</i>, 47) (Strassburg, 1882);
  M. Heyne, <i>Deutsche Hausaltertümer</i>, i., ii., iii. (Leipzig,
  1900-1903); G. Baldwin Brown, <i>The Arts in Early England</i> (London,
  1903); C.F. Keary, <i>Catalogue of Anglo-Saxon Coins in the British
  Museum</i>, vol. i. (London, 1887); C. Roach Smith, <i>Collectanea
  Antiqua</i> (London, 1848-1868); R.C. Neville, <i>Saxon Obsequies</i>
  (London, 1852); J.Y. Akerman, <i>Remains of Pagan Saxondom</i> (London,
  1855); Baron J. de Baye, <i>Industrie anglo-saxonne</i> (Paris, 1889);
  <i>The Industrial Arts of the Anglo-Saxons</i> (London, 1893); G.
  Stephens, <i>The Old Northern Runic Monuments</i> (London and Copenhagen,
  1866-1901); W. Vietor, <i>Die northumbrischen Runensteine</i> (Marburg,
  1895). Reference must also be made to the articles on Anglo-Saxon
  antiquities in the <i>Victoria County Histories</i>, and to various
  papers in <i>Archaeologia</i>, the <i>Archaeological Journal</i>, the
  <i>Journal of the British Archaeological Society</i>, the <i>Proceedings
  of the Society of Antiquaries</i>, the <i>Associated Architectural
  Societies' Reports</i>, and other antiquarian journals.</p>
         <p>(H. M. C.)</p>
         <p outputclass="fn-holder">
            <fn id="Footnote_091"> The hide
  (<i>hid</i>, <i>hiwisc</i>, <i>familia</i>, <i>tributarius</i>,
  <i>cassatus</i>, <i>manens</i>, &amp;c.) was in later times a measure of
  land, usually 120 acres. In early times, however, it seems to have meant
  (1) household, (2) normal amount of land appertaining to a household.</fn>

         </p>
      </section>
   </body>
</topic>