<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e23217">
   <title>BROWN, CHARLES BROCKDEN</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWN, CHARLES BROCKDEN--> (1771-1810), American novelist, was
  born of Quaker parents in Philadelphia, on the 17th of January 1771. Of
  delicate constitution and retiring habits, he early devoted himself to
  study; his principal amusement was the invention of ideal architectural
  designs, devised on the most extensive and elaborate scale. This
  characteristic talent for construction subsequently assumed the shape of
  Utopian projects for perfect commonwealths, and at a later period of a
  series of novels distinguished by the ingenuity and consistent evolution
  of the plot. The transition between these intellectual phases is marked
  by a juvenile romance entitled <i>Carsol</i>, not published until after
  the author's death, which professes to depict an imaginary community, and
  shows how thoroughly the young American was inspired by Godwin and Mary
  Wollstonecraft, whose principal writings had recently made their
  appearance. From the latter he derived the idea of his next work, <i>The
  Dialogue of Alcuin</i> (1797), an enthusiastic but inexperienced essay on
  the question of woman's rights and liberties. From Godwin he learned his
  terse style, condensed to a fault, but too laconic for eloquence or
  modulation, and the art of developing a plot from a single psychological
  problem or mysterious circumstance. The novels which he now rapidly
  produced offer the strongest affinity to <i>Caleb Williams</i>, and if
  inferior to that remarkable work in subtlety of mental analysis, greatly
  surpass it in affluence of invention and intensity of poetical feeling.
  All are wild and weird in conception, with incidents bordering on the
  preternatural, yet the limit of possibility is never transgressed. In
  <i>Wieland; or the Transformation</i> (1798), the first and most
  striking, a seemingly inexplicable mystery is resolved into a case of
  ventriloquism. <i>Arthur Mervyn; or Memoirs of the Year 1793</i>
  (1798-1800), is remarkable for the description of the epidemic of yellow
  fever in Philadelphia. <i>Edgar Huntly</i> (Philadelphia, 1801), a
  romance rich in local colouring, is remarkable for the effective use made
  of somnambulism, and anticipates Cooper's introduction of the American
  Indian into fiction. <i>Ormond</i> (1799) is less powerful, but contains
  one character, Constantia Dudley, which excited the enthusiastic
  admiration of Shelley. Two subsequent novels, <i>Clara Howard</i> (1801)
  and <i>Jane Talbot</i> (1804), dealing with ordinary life, proved
  failures, and Brown betook himself to compiling a general system of
  geography, editing a periodical, and an annual register, and writing
  political pamphlets. He died of consumption on the 22nd of February 1810.
  He is depicted by his biographer as the purest and most amiable of men,
  and in spite of a certain formality, due perhaps to his Quaker education,
  the statement is borne out by his correspondence.</p>
      <p>The life of Charles Brockden Brown was written by his friend William
  Dunlap (Philadelphia, 1815). See also William H. Prescott,
  <i>Biographical and Critical Miscellanies</i> (New York, 1845). His works
  in 6 vols. were published at Philadelphia in 1857 with a "life," and in a
  limited and more elaborate edition (1887).</p>
   </body>
</topic>