<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25459">
   <title>BRUNDISIUM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNDISIUM--> (Gr. <ph outputclass="grk">Βρεντέσιον</ph>,
  mod. <i>Brindisi</i>), an important harbour town of Calabria (in the
  ancient sense), Italy, on the E.S.E. coast. The name is said to mean
  "stag's head" in the Messapian dialect, in allusion to the shape of the
  harbour. Tradition varies as to its founders; but we find it hostile to
  Tarentum, and in friendly relations with Thurii. With a fertile territory
  round it, it became the most important city of the Messapians, but it was
  developed by the Romans, into whose hands it only came after the conquest
  of the Sallentini in 266 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph> They founded a
  colony there in 245 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>, and the Via Appia was
  perhaps extended through Tarentum as far as Brundisium at this period.
  Pacuvius was born here about 220 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph> After the
  Punic Wars it became the chief point of embarkation for Greece and the
  East, via Dyrrachium or Corcyra. In the Social War it received Roman
  citizenship, and was made a free port by Sulla. It suffered, however,
  from a siege conducted by Caesar in 49 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph>
  (<i>Bell. Civ.</i> i.) and was again attacked in 42 and 40 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph> Virgil died here in 19 <ph outputclass="scac">B.C.</ph> on his return from Greece. Trajan constructed
  the Via Trajana, a more direct route from Beneventum to Brundisium. The
  remains of ancient buildings are unimportant, though a considerable
  number of antiquities, especially inscriptions, have been discovered
  here: one column 62 ft. in height, with an ornate capital, still stands,
  and near it is the base of another, the column itself having been removed
  to Lecce. They are said to have marked the termination of the Via
  Appia.</p>
      <p>See Ch. Hülsen in Pauly-Wissowa, <i>Realencyclopädie</i>, iii. (1899),
  902; <i>Notizie degli Scavi</i>, passim. Also <ph outputclass="sc">Brindisi</ph>.</p>
      <p>(<ph outputclass="sc">T. As.</ph>)</p>
   </body>
</topic>