<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e11476">
   <title>BRIDGEWATER, FRANCIS EGERTON</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIDGEWATER, FRANCIS EGERTON-->, <ph outputclass="sc">3rd Duke
  of</ph> (1736-1803), the originator of British inland navigation,
  younger son of the 1st duke, was born on the 21st of May 1736. Scroop,
  1st duke of Bridgewater (1681-1745), was the son of the 3rd earl of
  Bridgewater, and was created a duke in 1720; he was the great-grandson of
  John Egerton, 1st earl of Bridgewater (d. 1649; cr. 1617), whose name is
  associated with the production of Milton's <i>Comus</i>; and the latter
  was the son of Sir Thomas Egerton (1540-1617), Queen Elizabeth's lord
  keeper and James I.'s lord chancellor, who was created baron of Ellesmere
  in 1603, and in 1616 Viscount Brackley (<i>q.v.</i>).</p>
      <p>Francis Egerton succeeded to the dukedom at the age of twelve on the
  death of his brother, the 2nd duke. As a child he was sickly and of such
  unpromising intellectual capacity that at one time the idea of cutting
  the entail was seriously entertained. Shortly after attaining his
  majority he became engaged to the beautiful duchess of Hamilton, but her
  refusal to give up the acquaintance of her sister, Lady Coventry, led to
  the breaking off of the match. Thereupon the duke broke up his London
  establishment, and retiring to his estate at Worsley, devoted himself to
  the making of canals. The navigable canal from Worsley to Manchester
  which he projected for the transport of the coal obtained on his estates
  was (with the exception of the Sankey canal) the first great undertaking
  of the kind executed in Great Britain in modern times. The construction
  of this remarkable work, with its famous aqueduct across the Irwell, was
  carried out by James Brindley, the celebrated engineer. The completion of
  this canal led the duke to undertake a still more ambitious work. In 1762
  he obtained parliamentary powers to provide an improved waterway between
  Liverpool and Manchester by means of a canal. The difficulties
  encountered in the execution of the latter work were still more
  formidable than those of the Worsley canal, involving, as they did, the
  carrying of the canal over Sale Moor Moss. But the genius of Brindley,
  his engineer, proved superior to all obstacles, and though at one period
  of the undertaking the financial resources of the duke were almost
  exhausted, the work was carried to a triumphant conclusion. The untiring
  perseverance displayed by the duke in surmounting the various
  difficulties that retarded the accomplishment of his projects, together
  with the pecuniary restrictions he imposed on himself in order to supply
  the necessary capital (at one time he reduced his personal expenses to
  £400 a year), affords an instructive example of that energy and
  self-denial on which the success of great undertakings so much depends.
  Both these canals were completed when the duke was only thirty-six years
  of age, and the remainder of his life was spent in extending them and in
  improving his estates; and during the latter years of his life he derived
  a princely income from the success of his enterprise. Though a steady
  supporter of Pitt's administration, he never took any prominent part in
  politics.</p>
      <p>He died unmarried on the 8th of March 1803, when the ducal title
  became extinct, but the earldom of Bridgewater passed to a cousin, John
  William Egerton, who became 7th earl. By his will he devised his canals
  and estates on trust, under which his nephew, the marquess of Stafford
  (afterwards first duke of Sutherland), became the first beneficiary, and
  next his son Francis Leveson Gower (afterwards first earl of Ellesmere)
  and his issue. In order that the trust should last as long as possible,
  an extraordinary use was made of the legal rule that property may be
  settled for the duration of lives in being and twenty-one years after, by
  choosing a great number of persons connected with the duke and their
  living issue and adding to them the peers who had taken their seats in
  the House of Lords on or before the duke's decease. Though the last of
  the peers died in 1857, one of the commoners survived till the 19th of
  October 1883, and consequently the trust did not expire till the 19th of
  October 1903, when the whole property passed under the undivided control
  of the earl of Ellesmere. The canals, however, had in 1872 been
  transferred to the Bridgewater Navigation Company, by whom they were sold
  in 1887 to the Manchester Ship Canal Company.</p>
   </body>
</topic>