<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e25623">
   <title>BRUNEL, SIR MARC ISAMBARD</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNEL, SIR MARC ISAMBARD--> (1769-1849), British inventor and
  engineer, was born at Hacqueville in Normandy on the 25th of April 1769.
  His father, a small landowner and farmer, intended him for the church,
  but his taste for mathematics and mechanics inclined him to another
  career, and he obtained a nomination for the navy, in which he served for
  six years. When his ship was paid off in 1792 and he returned to France,
  he found the Revolution at its height, and owing to his pronounced
  royalist opinions he was obliged to leave the country. Reaching New York
  in September 1793 he began to practise as an architect and civil
  engineer. His first employment was in land-surveying and
  canal-engineering. Later he submitted a highly ornamental design for the
  National Capitol at Washington, which, however, was not accepted, and was
  engaged to design and superintend the construction of the Bowery theatre,
  New York, burnt down in 1821. He fitted novel and ingenious machinery in
  the arsenal and cannon factory which he was commissioned to erect in New
  York, and he was asked to supply plans for the defences of the Narrows
  between the upper and lower bays of that port. Early in 1799 he sailed
  for England in order to submit to the British government his plans for
  the mechanical production of ships' blocks, in substitution for the
  manual processes then employed. After the usual difficulties and delays
  his proposals were adopted, largely through the recommendation of Sir
  Samuel Bentham, and about 1803 the erection of his machines was begun at
  Portsmouth dockyard. They were constructed by Henry Maudslay, and formed
  one of the earliest examples of a complete range of machine tools, each
  <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page683">[v.04
  p.0683]</ph>performing its part in a long series of operations. Not
  only was the quality of the product much improved but the cost was
  greatly diminished, and the saving effected in the first year in which
  the machines were in full work was estimated at £24,000, of which about
  two-thirds was awarded to Brunel. A little later he was occupied in
  devising improved machines for sawing and bending timber, and in 1811 and
  1812 he was employed by the government in erecting saw-mills at Woolwich
  and Chatham, carrying out at the latter dockyard a complete
  reorganization of the system for handling timber. About 1812 he devised
  machinery for making boots which was adopted for the purposes of the
  army, but abandoned a few years later when, owing to the cessation of
  war, the demand became less and the supply of manual labour cheaper. At
  the same time he interested himself in the establishment of steam
  navigation on the Thames between London and Ramsgate. In 1814 he
  succeeded in persuading the admiralty to try steam-tugs for towing
  warships out to sea. The experiments were made at his own expense, for a
  few months after undertaking to contribute to the cost the admiralty
  revoked its promise on the ground that the attempt was "too chimerical to
  be seriously entertained." Another vain enterprise on which he wasted
  much time and money was an attempt to use liquefied gases as a source of
  motive power. His round stocking-frame or <i>tricoteur</i> was patented
  in 1816, and among his other inventions were machines for winding
  cotton-thread into balls, for copying drawings, for making small wooden
  boxes such as are used by druggists, and for the manufacture of nails,
  together with processes of preparing tinfoil for decorative purposes and
  improvements in stereotype plates for printing.</p>
      <p>In 1821, partly as the result of the damage done by fire in 1814 to
  the saw-mills he owned at Battersea, and partly because his commercial
  abilities were far from equal to his mechanical genius, he got into
  financial difficulties and was thrown into prison for debt, only
  regaining his freedom through a grant of £5000 which his friends obtained
  for him from the government. Subsequently his attention was mainly
  devoted to projects of civil engineering, the most noteworthy being the
  Thames Tunnel. In 1820 he had prepared plans of bridges for erection in
  Rouen and St Petersburg and in the island of Bourbon. In 1823 he designed
  swing-bridges, and in 1826 floating landing-stages, for the port of
  Liverpool. A company, which was supported by the duke of Wellington, was
  formed in 1824 to carry out his scheme for boring a tunnel under the
  Thames between Wapping and Rotherhithe. The work was begun at the
  beginning of 1825, the excavation being accomplished by the aid of a
  "shield," which he had patented in 1818. Many difficulties were
  encountered. The river broke through the roof of the tunnel in 1827, and
  after a second irruption in 1828 work was discontinued for lack of funds.
  Seven years later it was resumed with the aid of money advanced by the
  government, and after three more irruptions the tunnel was completed and
  opened in 1843. Aided by his son, Brunel displayed extraordinary skill
  and resource in the various emergencies with which he had to deal, but
  the anxiety broke down his health. He recovered sufficiently from one
  paralytic stroke to attend the opening ceremony, but he was able to
  undertake little more professional work. A second stroke followed in
  1845, and four years later he died in London on the 12th of December
  1849. He received the order of the Legion of Honour in 1829 and was
  knighted in 1841.</p>
      <p>See Richard Beamish, <i>Memoirs of Sir Marc Isambard Brunel</i>
  (1862).</p>
   </body>
</topic>