<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e2866">
   <title>BRÉZÉ</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRÉZÉ--> the name of a noble Angevin family, the most famous
  member of which was <ph outputclass="sc">Pierre de Brézé</ph> (<i>c.</i>
  1410-1465), one of the trusted soldiers and statesmen of Charles VII. He
  had made his name as a soldier in the English wars when in 1433 he joined
  with Yolande, queen of Sicily, the constable Richmond and others, in
  chasing from power Charles VII.'s minister La Trémoille. He was knighted
  by Charles of Anjou in 1434, and presently entered the royal council. In
  1437 he became seneschal of Anjou, and in 1440 of Poitou. During the
  Praguerie he rendered great service to the royal cause against the
  dauphin Louis and the revolted nobles, a service which was remembered
  against him after Louis's accession to the throne. He fought against the
  English in Normandy in 1440-1441, and in Guienne in 1442. In the next
  year he became chamberlain to Charles VII., and gained the chief power in
  the state through the influence of Agnes Sorel, superseding his early
  allies Richmond and Charles of Anjou. The six years (1444-1450) of his
  ascendancy were the most prosperous period of the reign of Charles VII.
  His most dangerous opponent was the dauphin Louis, who in 1448 brought
  against him accusations which led to a formal trial resulting in a
  complete exoneration of Brézé and his restoration to favour. He fought in
  Normandy in 1450-1451, and became seneschal of the province after the
  death of Agnes Sorel and the consequent decline of his influence at
  court. He made an ineffective descent on the English coast at Sandwich in
  1457, and was preparing an expedition in favour of Margaret of Anjou when
  the accession of Louis XI. brought him disgrace and a short imprisonment.
  In 1462, however, his son Jacques married Louis's half-sister, Charlotte
  de Valois, daughter of Agnes Sorel. In 1462 he accompanied Margaret to
  Scotland with a force of 2000 men, and after the battle of Hexham he
  brought her back to Flanders. On his return he was reappointed seneschal
  of Normandy, and fell in the battle of Montlhéry on the 16th of July
  1465. He was succeeded as seneschal of Normandy by his eldest son Jacques
  de Brézé (<i>c.</i> 1440-1490), count of Maulevrier; and by his grandson,
  husband of the famous Diane de Poitiers, Louis de Brézé (d. 1531), whose
  tomb in Rouen cathedral, attributed to Jean Goujon and Jean Cousin, is a
  splendid example of French Renaissance work.</p>
      <p>The lordship of Brézé passed eventually to Claire Clémence de Maillé,
  princess of Condé, by whom it was sold to Thomas Dreux, who took the name
  of Dreux Brézé, when it was erected into a marquisate. <ph outputclass="sc">Henri Evrard</ph>, marquis de Dreux-Brézé (1762-1829),
  succeeded his father as master of the ceremonies to Louis XVI. in 1781.
  On the meeting of the states-general in 1789 it fell to him to regulate
  the questions of etiquette and precedence between the three estates. That
  as the immediate representative of the crown he should wound the
  susceptibilities of the deputies was perhaps inevitable, but little
  attempt was made to adapt traditional etiquette to changed circumstances.
  Brézé did not formally intimate to President Bailly the proclamation of
  the royal séance until the 20th of June, when the carpenters were about
  to enter the hall to prepare for the event, thus provoking the session in
  the tennis court. After the royal séance Brézé was sent to reiterate
  Louis's orders that the estates should meet separately, when Mirabeau
  replied that the hall could not be cleared except by force. After the
  fall of the Tuileries Brézé emigrated for a short time, but though he
  returned to France he was spared during the Terror. At the Restoration he
  was made a peer of France, and resumed his functions as guardian of an
  antiquated ceremonial. He died on the 27th of January 1829, when he was
  succeeded in the peerage and at court by his son Scipion (1793-1845).</p>
      <p>The best contemporary account of Pierre de Brézé is given in the
  <i>Chroniques</i> of the Burgundian chronicler, Georges Chastellain, who
  had been his secretary. Chastellain addressed a <i>Déprécation</i> to
  Louis XI. on his behalf at the time of his disgrace.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page515">[v.04 p.0515]</ph>
      </p>
   </body>
</topic>