<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e27012">
   <title>BRYAN, WILLIAM JENNINGS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRYAN, WILLIAM JENNINGS--> (1860- ), American political leader,
  son of Silas Lillard Bryan, a native of Culpeper county, Virginia, who
  was a lawyer and from 1860 to 1897 a state circuit judge, was born at
  Salem, Marion county, Illinois, on the 19th of March 1860. He graduated
  from Illinois College as valedictorian in 1881, and from the Union
  College of Law, Chicago, in 1883; during his course he studied in the law
  office of Lyman Trumbull. He practised law at Jacksonville from 1883 to
  1887, when he removed to Lincoln, Nebraska. There he soon became
  conspicuous both as a lawyer and as a politician, attracting particular
  attention by his speeches during the presidential campaign of 1888 on
  behalf of the candidates of the Democratic party. From 1891 to 1895 he
  represented the First Congressional District of Nebraska, normally
  Republican, in the national House of Representatives, and received the
  unusual honour of being placed on the important Committee on Ways and
  Means during his first term. He was a hard and conscientious worker and
  became widely known for his ability in debate. Two of his speeches in
  particular attracted attention, one against the policy of protection
  (16th of March 1892), and the other against the repeal of the silver
  purchase clause of the Sherman Act (16th of August 1893). In the latter
  he advocated the unlimited coinage of silver, irrespective of
  international agreement, at a ratio of 16 to 1, a policy with which his
  name was afterwards most prominently associated. In a campaign largely
  restricted to the question of free-silver coinage he was defeated for
  re-election in 1894, and subsequently was also defeated as the Democratic
  candidate for the United States Senate. As editor of the <i>Omaha
  World-Herald</i> he then championed the cause of bimetallism in the press
  as vigorously as he had in Congress and on the platform, his articles
  being widely quoted and discussed.</p>
      <p>The Democratic party was even more radically divided on the question
  of monetary policy than the Republican; and President Cleveland, by
  securing the repeal of the silver purchase clause in the Sherman Act by
  Republican votes, had alienated a great majority of his party. In the
  Democratic national convention at Chicago in 1896, during a long and
  heated debate with regard to the party platform, Bryan, in advocating the
  "plank" declaring for the free coinage of silver, of which he was the
  author, delivered a celebrated speech containing the passage, "You shall
  not press down upon the brow of labour this crown of thorns; you shall
  not crucify mankind upon a cross of gold." This speech made him the idol
  of the "silver" majority of the convention and brought him the Democratic
  nomination for the presidency on the following day. Subsequently he
  received the nominations of the People's and National Silver parties. In
  the ensuing presidential campaign he travelled over 18,000 m. and made
  altogether 600 speeches in 27 different states—an unprecedented
  number. In the election, however, he was defeated by William McKinley,
  the Republican candidate, receiving 176 electoral votes to 271. But
  though defeated, he remained the leader of his party. Between 1896 and
  1900, except during the Spanish-American War when he was colonel of the
  3rd Nebraska Volunteers, though he saw no active service, he devoted his
  time to the interest of his party. His ability, sincerity of character,
  and wide information, and his attitude towards the new issues arising
  from the war, in which he took the side opposed to "imperialism,"
  increased his following. Although he had advised the ratification of the
  Peace Treaty, he opposed the permanent acquisition of the Philippine
  Islands. In 1900 he was nominated for the presidency by the Democratic,
  Silver Republican, and Populist party conventions; but although
  "imperialism" was declared to be the paramount issue, he had insisted
  that the "platforms" should contain explicit advocacy of free-coinage,
  and this declaration, combined with the popularity of President McKinley,
  the Republican candidate for re-election, again turned the scales against
  him. In the November election after a canvass that almost equalled in
  activity that of 1896 he was again defeated, receiving only 155 electoral
  votes to 292.</p>
      <p>After the 1900 election he established and edited at Lincoln a weekly
  political journal, <i>The Commoner</i>, which attained a wide
  circulation. In 1904 although not actively a candidate for the Democratic
  nomination (which eventually went to Judge Parker), he was to the very
  last considered a possible nominee; and he strenuously opposed in the
  convention the repudiation by the conservative element of the stand taken
  in the two previous campaigns. The decisive defeat of Parker by President
  Roosevelt did much to bring back the Democrats to Mr Bryan's banner. In
  1905-1906 he made a trip round the world, and in London was cordially
  received as a great American orator. He was again nominated for the
  presidency by the Democratic party in 1908. The free-silver theory was
  now dead, and while the main question was that of the attitude to be
  taken towards the Trusts it was much confused by personal issues, Mr
  Roosevelt himself intervening strongly in favour of the Republican
  nominee, Mr Taft. After a heated contest Mr Bryan again suffered a
  decisive defeat, President Taft securing 321 electoral votes to Mr
  Bryan's 162.</p>
   </body>
</topic>