<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e31720">
   <title>BUDDHAGHOSA</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUDDHAGHOSA,--> a celebrated Buddhist writer. He was a Brahmin by
  birth and was born near the great Bodhi tree at Budh Gayā; in north
  India about <ph outputclass="scac">A.D.</ph> 390, his father's name being
  Kesī. His teacher, Revata, induced him to go to Ceylon, where the
  commentaries on the scriptures had been preserved in the Sinhalese
  language, with the object of translating them into Pāli. He went
  accordingly to Anuradhapura, studied there under Sanghapāla, and
  asked leave of the fraternity there to translate the commentaries. With
  their consent he then did so, having first shown his ability by writing
  the work <i>Visuddhi Magga</i> (the Path of Purity, a kind of summary of
  Buddhist doctrine). When he had completed his many years' labours he
  returned to the neighbourhood of the Bodhi tree in north India. Before he
  came to Ceylon he had already written a book entitled
  <i>Nānodaya</i> (the Rise of Knowledge), and had commenced a
  commentary on the principal psychological manual contained in the
  <i>Pitakas</i>. This latter work he afterwards rewrote in Ceylon, as the
  present text (now published by the Pāli Text Society) shows. One
  volume of the <i>Sumangala Vilāsinī</i> (a portion of the
  commentaries mentioned above) has been edited, and extracts from his
  comment on the Buddhist canon law. This last work has been discovered in
  a nearly <ph outputclass="correction">contemporaneous</ph> Chinese translation (an edition in Pāli is
  based on a comparison with that translation). The works here mentioned
  form, however, only a small portion of what Buddhaghosa wrote. His
  industry must have been prodigious. He is known to have written books
  that would fill about 20 octavo volumes of about 400 pages each; and
  there are other writings ascribed to him which may or may not be really
  his work. It is too early therefore to attempt a criticism of it. But it
  is already clear that, when made acceptable, it will be of the greatest
  value for the history of Indian literature and of Indian ideas. So much
  is uncertain at present in that history for want of definite dates that
  the voluminous writings of an author whose date is approximately certain
  will afford a standard by which the age of other writings can be tested.
  And as the original commentaries in Sinhalese are now lost his works are
  the only evidence we have of the traditions then handed down in the
  Buddhist community. The main source of our information about Buddhaghosa
  is the <i>Mahāvamsa</i>, written in Anurādhapura about fifty
  years after he was working there. But there are numerous references to
  him in Pāli books on Pāli literature; and a Burmese author of
  unknown date, but possibly of the 15th century, has compiled a biography
  of him, the <i>Buddhaghos' Uppatti</i>, of little value and no critical
  judgment.</p>
      <p>See <i>Mahāvamsa</i>, ch. xxxvii. (ed. Turnour, Colombo, 1837);
  "Gandhavaramsa," p. 59, in <i>Journal of the Pāli Text Society</i>
  (1886); <i>Buddhghosuppatti</i> (text and translation, ed. by E. Gray,
  London, 1893); <i>Sumangala Vilāsinī</i>, edited by T. W.
  Rhys Davids and J. E. Carpenter, vol. i. (London, Pāli Text
  Society, 1886). (T. W. R. D.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>