<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e29452">
   <title>BUCHANAN, ROBERT WILLIAMS</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUCHANAN, ROBERT WILLIAMS--> (1841-1901), British poet, novelist
  and dramatist, son of Robert Buchanan (1813-1866), Owenite lecturer and
  journalist, was born at Caverswall, Staffordshire, on the 18th of August
  1841. His father, a native of Ayr, after living for some years in
  Manchester, removed to Glasgow, where Buchanan was educated, at the high
  school and the university, one of his fellow-students being the poet
  David Gray. His essay on Gray, originally contributed to the <i>Cornhill
  Magazine</i>, tells the story of their close friendship, and of their
  journey to London in 1860 in search of fame. After a period of struggle
  and disappointment Buchanan published <i>Undertones</i> in 1863. This
  "tentative" volume was followed by <i>Idyls and Legends of Inverburn</i>
  (1865), <i>London Poems</i> (1866), and <i>North Coast and other
  Poems</i> (1868), wherein he displayed a faculty for poetic narrative,
  and a sympathetic insight into the humbler conditions of life. On the
  whole, Buchanan is at his best in these narrative poems, though he
  essayed a more ambitious flight in <i>The Book of Orm: A Prelude to the
  Epic</i>, a study in mysticism, which appeared in 1870. He was a frequent
  contributor to periodical literature, and obtained notoriety by an
  article which, under the <i>nom de plume</i> of Thomas Maitland, he
  contributed to the <i>Contemporary Review</i> for October 1871, entitled
  "The Fleshly School of Poetry." This article was expanded into a pamphlet
  (1872), but he subsequently withdrew from the criticisms it contained,
  and it is chiefly remembered by the replies it evoked from D.G. Rossetti
  in a letter to the <i>Athenaeum</i> (16th December 1871), entitled "The
  Stealthy School of Criticism," and from Mr Swinburne in <i>Under the
  Microscope</i> (1872). Buchanan himself afterwards regretted the violence
  of his attack, and the "old enemy" to whom <i>God and the Man</i> is
  dedicated was Rossetti. In 1876 appeared <i>The Shadow of the Sword</i>,
  the first and one of the best of a long series of novels. Buchanan was
  also the author of many successful plays, among which may be mentioned
  <i>Lady Clare</i>, produced in 1883; <i>Sophia</i> (1886), an adaptation
  of <i>Tom Jones; A Man's Shadow</i> (1890); and <i>The Charlatan</i>
  (1894). He also wrote, in collaboration with Harriett Jay, the melodrama
  <i>Alone in London</i>. In 1896 he became, so far as some of his work was
  concerned, his own publisher. In the autumn of 1900 he had a paralytic
  seizure, from which he never recovered. He died at Streatham on the 10th
  of June 1901.</p>
      <p>Buchanan's poems were collected into three volumes in 1874, into one
  volume in 1884; and as <i>Complete Poetical Works</i> (2 vols., 1901).
  Among his poems should also be mentioned: "The Drama of Kings" (1871);
  "St Abe and his Seven Wives," a lively tale of Salt Lake City, published
  anonymously in 1872; and "Balder the Beautiful" (1877); "The City of
  Dream" (1888); "The Outcast: a Rhyme for the Time" (1891); and "The
  Wandering Jew" (1893). His earlier novels, <i>The Shadow of the
  Sword</i>, and <i>God and the Man</i> (1881), a striking tale of a family
  feud, are distinguished by a certain breadth and simplicity of treatment
  which is not so noticeable in their successors, among which may be
  mentioned <i>The Martyrdom of Madeline</i> (1882); <i>Foxglove Manor</i>
  (1885); <i>Effie Hetherington</i> (1896); and <i>Father Anthony</i>
  (1898). <i>David Gray and other Essays, chiefly on Poetry</i> (1868);
  <i>Master Spirits</i> (1873); <i>A Poet's Sketch Book</i> (1883), in
  which the interesting essay on Gray is reprinted; and <i>A Look round
  Literature</i> (1887), contain Buchanan's chief contributions to
  periodical literature. More valuable is <i>The Land of Lorne</i> (2
  vols., 1871), a vivid record of yachting experiences on the west coast of
  Scotland.</p>
      <p>See also Harriett Jay, <i>Robert Buchanan; some Account of his
  Life</i> (1903).</p>
   </body>
</topic>