<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e24181">
   <title>BROWNE, WILLIAM</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROWNE, WILLIAM--> (1591-1643), English pastoral poet, was born at
  Tavistock, Devonshire, in 1591, of a branch of the family of Browne of
  Betchworth Castle, Surrey. He received his early education at the grammar
  school of his native town, and is said to have proceeded to Oxford about
  1603. After a short residence at Clifford's Inn he entered the Inner
  Temple in 1611. His elegy on the death of Henry, prince of Wales, and the
  first book of <i>Britannia's Pastorals</i> appeared in 1613; the
  <i>Shepherd's Pipe</i>, which contained some eclogues by other poets, in
  1614. The second book of the pastorals (1616) is dedicated to William
  Herbert, earl of Pembroke, whose seat at Wilton was Browne's home for
  some time. In 1624 he returned to Oxford as tutor to Robert Dormer,
  afterwards earl of Carnarvon, matriculating at Exeter College in April
  and receiving his M.A. degree in November of the same year. Nearly all
  Browne's poetic work dates from his early manhood, before his marriage in
  1628 with Timothy, daughter of Sir Thomas Eversham of Horsham, Essex. In
  the fourth eclogue of George Wither's <i>Shepherd's Hunting</i>, written
  as early as 1613-1614, Philarete (Wither) asks Willy (Browne) why he is
  silent, and the reply is that some "my music do contemne." The times were
  unfavourable to his tranquil talent, and the second half of his life was
  spent in retirement. He died some time before 1645, when letters of
  administration were granted to his widow, and he may have been the
  William Browne whose burial is recorded in the Tavistock registers under
  the date of the 27th of March 1643.</p>
      <p>Browne was the pupil and friend of Michael Drayton, who associates "my
  Browne" in the "Epistle to Henry Reynolds" with the two Beaumonts as "my
  dear companions whom I freely chose, My bosom friends." But directly
  indebted as Browne is for the form of his poems, for the slight story and
  the rather wearisome allegory, to Spenser, Sidney, Drayton and especially
  to Fletcher's <i>Faithful Shepherdess</i>, his poetry is no mere copy of
  any of these models. His Arcadia is localized in his native Devonshire.
  He was untiring in his praises of "Tavy's voiceful stream (to whom I owe
  more strains than from my pipe can ever flow)." He knew local history and
  traditions, and he celebrates the gallant sailors who "by their power
  made the Devonian shore Mock the proud Tagus." (<i>Brit. Past.</i> bk.
  ii., song 3). It is for his truthful, affectionate pictures of his
  country life and its surroundings that the stories of Marina and
  Celandine, Doridon and the rest are still read. A copy of Browne's
  pastorals with annotations in Milton's handwriting is preserved in the
  Huth library, and there are many points of likeness between Lycidas and
  the elegy on Philarete (Thomas Manwood) in the fourth eclogue of the
  <i>Shepherd's Pipe</i>. Keats was a student of Browne, and Herrick's
  fairy fantasies are thought to owe something to the third book of the
  pastorals.</p>
      <p>The first two books of <i>Britannia's Pastorals</i> were re-issued in
  1625. The third, though it had no doubt circulated in the author's
  lifetime, remained unknown until Beriah Botfield discovered a copy of it
  in the library of Salisbury cathedral, bound up with the 1613 and 1616
  editions of the first and second books. This MS. was edited for the Percy
  Society by T.C. Croker in 1852. A collected edition of Browne's works was
  published in 1772 by John Davies. It is not known whether <i>The Inner
  Temple Masque</i> on the story of Ulysses and Circe, which was written
  for performance on the 13th of January 1615, was ever actually
  represented. A series of sonnets to Caelia, some epistles, elegies and
  epitaphs, with some other miscellaneous poems, complete the list of
  Browne's works. These have been collected from various sources, the most
  important being Lansdowne MS. 777 (British Museum), and they were printed
  for the first time by Sir S.E. Brydges in 1815. Excellent modern complete
  editions of Browne and Mr W.C. Hazlitt's (1868-1869) for the Roxburghe
  library, and a more compact one (1894) by Mr Gordon Goodwin, with an
  introduction by Mr A.H. Bullen, for the "Muse's Library." For an
  elaborate analysis of Browne's obligations to earlier pastoral writers
  see F.W. Moorman, "William Browne" (<i>Quellen und Forschungen zur
  Sprach- und Culturgeschichte der Germanischen Völker</i> Strassburg,
  1897). A translation of Marin le Roy de Gomberville's <i>Polexandre</i>,
  by William Browne (1647), may be a posthumous work of the poet's.</p>
   </body>
</topic>