<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12535">
   <title>BRINTON, DANIEL GARRISON</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRINTON, DANIEL GARRISON--> (1837-1899), American archaeologist
  and ethnologist, was born at Thornbury, Pennsylvania, on the 13th of May
  1837. He graduated at Yale in 1858, studied for two years in the
  Jefferson Medical College, and then for one year travelled in Europe and
  continued his studies at Paris and Heidelberg. From 1862 to 1865, during
  the Civil War in America, he was a surgeon in the Union army, acting for
  one year, 1864-1865, as surgeon in charge of the U.S. Army general
  hospital at Quincy, Illinois. After the war he practised medicine at
  Westchester, Pennsylvania, for several years; was the editor of a weekly
  periodical, the <i>Medical and Surgical Reporter</i>, in Philadelphia,
  from 1874 to 1887; became professor of ethnology and archaeology in the
  Academy of Natural Sciences in Philadelphia in 1884, and was professor of
  American linguistics and archaeology in the university of Pennsylvania
  from 1886 until his death at Philadelphia on the 31st of July 1899. He
  was a member of numerous learned societies in the United States and in
  Europe, and was president at different times of the Numismatic and
  Antiquarian Society of Philadelphia, of the American Folk-Lore Society
  and of the American Association for the Advancement of Science. During
  the period from 1859 (when he published his first book) to 1899, he wrote
  a score of books, several of them of great value, and a large number of
  pamphlets, brochures, addresses and magazine articles. His principal
  works are:—<i>The Myths of the New World</i> (1868), the first
  attempt to analyse and correlate, according to true scientific
  principles, the mythology of the American Indians; <i>The Religious
  Sentiment: Its Sources and Aim: A Contribution to the Science and
  Philosophy of Religion</i> (1876); <i>American Hero Myths</i> (1882);
  <i>Essays of an Americanist</i> (1890); <i>Races and Peoples</i> (1890);
  <i>The American Race</i> (1891); <i>The Pursuit of Happiness</i> (1893);
  and <i>Religions of Primitive People</i> (1897). In addition, he edited
  and published a <i>Library of American Aboriginal Literature</i> (8 vols.
  1882-1890), a valuable contribution to the science of anthropology in
  America. Of the eight volumes, six were edited by Brinton himself, one by
  Horatio Hale and one by A.S. Gatschet.</p>
   </body>
</topic>