<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e26019">
   <title>BRUNO, GIORDANO</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRUNO, GIORDANO--> (c. 1548-1600), Italian philosopher of the
  Renaissance, was born near Nola in the village of Cicala. Little is known
  of his life. He was christened Filippo, and took the name Giordano only
  on entering a religious order. In his fifteenth year he entered the order
  of the Dominicans at Naples, and is said to have composed a treatise on
  the ark of Noah. Why he submitted to a discipline palpably unsuited to
  his fiery spirit we cannot tell. In consequence of his views on
  transubstantiation and the immaculate conception he was accused of
  impiety, and after enduring persecution for some years, he fled from Rome
  about 1576, and wandered through various cities, reaching Geneva in 1579.
  The home of Calvinism was no resting-place for him (T. Dufour,
  <i>Giordano Bruno à Genève</i>, Geneva, 1884), and he travelled on
  through Lyons, Toulouse and Montpellier, arriving at Paris in 1581.
  Everywhere he bent his energies to the exposition of the new thoughts
  which were beginning to effect a revolution in the thinking world. He had
  drunk deeply of the spirit of the Renaissance, the determination to see
  for himself the noble universe, unclouded by the mists of authoritative
  philosophy and church tradition. The discoveries of Copernicus were
  eagerly accepted by him, and he used them as the lever by which to push
  aside the antiquated system that had come down from Aristotle, for whom,
  indeed, he had a perfect hatred. Like Bacon and Telesio he preferred the
  older Greek philosophers, who had looked at nature for themselves, and
  whose speculations had more of reality in them. He had read widely and
  deeply, and in his own writings we come across many expressions familiar
  to us in earlier systems. Yet his philosophy is no eclecticism. He owed
  something to Lucretius, something to the Stoic nature-pantheism,
  something to Anaxagoras, to Heraclitus, to the Pythagoreans, and to the
  Neoplatonists, who were partially known to him; above all, he was a
  profound student of Nicolas of Cusa, who was indeed a speculative
  Copernicus. But his own system has a distinct unity and originality; it
  breathes throughout the fiery spirit of Bruno himself.</p>
      <p>Bruno had been well received at Toulouse, where he had lectured on
  astronomy; even better fortune awaited him at Paris, especially at the
  hands of Henry III. He was offered a chair of philosophy, provided he
  would receive the Mass. He at once refused, but was permitted to deliver
  lectures. These seem to have been altogether devoted to expositions of a
  certain logical system which Bruno had taken up with great eagerness, the
  <i>Ars Magna</i> of Raimon Lull. With the exception of a satiric comedy,
  <i>Il Candelajo</i>, all the works of this period are devoted to this
  logic—<i>De Umbris Idearum, Ars Memoriae, De compendiosa
  architectura et complemento artis Lullii</i>, and <i>Cantus Circaeus</i>.
  To many it has seemed a curious freak of Bruno's that he should have so
  eagerly adopted a view of thought like that of Lull, but in reality it is
  in strict accordance with the principles of his philosophy. Like the
  Arabian logicians, and some of the scholastics, who held that ideas
  existed in a threefold form—<i>ante res</i>, <i>in rebus</i> and
  <i>post res</i>—he laid down the principle that the archetypal
  ideas existed metaphysically in the ultimate unity or intelligence,
  physically in the world of things, and logically in signs, symbols or
  notions. These notions were shadows of the ideas, and the <i>Ars
  Magna</i> furnished him with a general scheme, according to which their
  relations and correspondences should be exhibited. It supplied not only a
  <i>memoria technica</i>, but an <i>organon</i>, or method by which the
  genesis of all ideas from unity might be represented intelligibly and
  easily. It provided also a substitute for either the Aristotelian or the
  Ramist logic, which was an additional element in its favour.</p>
      <p>Under the protection of the French ambassador, Michel de Castelnau,
  sieur de Mauvissière, Bruno passed over in 1583 to England, where he
  resided for about two years. He was disgusted with the brutality of
  English manners, which he paints in no flattering colours, and he found
  pedantry and superstition as rampant in Oxford as in Geneva. Indeed,
  there still existed on the statute a provision that "Masters and
  Bachelors who did not follow Aristotle faithfully were liable to a fine
  of five shillings for every point of divergence, and for every fault
  committed against the logic of the Organon." But he indulges in
  extravagant eulogies of Elizabeth. He is generally said to have formed
  the acquaintance of Sir Philip Sidney, Fulke Greville and other eminent
  Englishmen, but there has been much controversy as to the facts of his
  life in London. It seems probable that he lived in the French embassy in
  some secretarial or tutorial position. He may conceivably have met Bacon,
  but it is quite incredible that he met Shakespeare in the printing shop
  of Thomas Vautrollier. In Oxford he was allowed to hold a disputation
  with some learned doctors on the rival merits of the Copernican and
  so-called Aristotelian systems of the universe, and, according to his own
  report, had an easy victory. The best of his works were written in the
  freedom of English social life. The <i>Cena de le Ceneri</i>, or Ash
  Wednesday conversation, devoted to an exposition of the Copernican
  theory, was printed in 1584. In the same year appeared his two great
  metaphysical works, <i>De la Causa, Principio, ed Uno</i>, and <i>De
  l'Infinito, Universo, e Mondi</i>; in the year following the <i>Eroici
  Furori</i> and <i>Cabala del Cavallo Pegaseo</i>. In 1584 also appeared
  the strange dialogue, <i>Spaccio della Bestia Trionfante</i>
  (<i>Expulsion of the Triumphant Beast</i>), an allegory treating chiefly
  of moral philosophy, but giving the essence of Bruno's philosophy. The
  gods are represented as resolving to banish from the heavens the
  constellations, which served to remind them of their evil deeds. In their
  places are put the moral virtues. The first of the three dialogues
  contains the substance of the allegory, which, under the disguise of an
  assault on heathen mythology, is a direct attack on all forms of
  anthropomorphic religion. But in a philosophical point of view the first
  part of the second dialogue is the most important. Among the moral
  virtues which take the place of the beasts are Truth, Prudence, Wisdom,
  Law and Universal Judgment, and in the explanation of what these mean
  Bruno unfolds the inner essence of his system. Truth is the unity and
  substance which underlies all things; Prudence or Providence is the
  regulating power of truth, and comprehends both liberty and necessity;
  Wisdom is providence itself in its supersensible aspect—in man it
  is reason which grasps the truth of things; Law results from wisdom, for
  no good law is irrational, and its sole end and aim is the good of
  mankind; Universal Judgment is the principle whereby men are judged
  according to their deeds, and not according to their belief in this or
  that catechism. Mingled with his allegorical philosophy are the most
  vehement attacks upon the established religion. The monks are stigmatized
  as pedants who would destroy the joy of life on earth, who are
  avaricious, dissolute and the breeders of eternal dissensions and
  squabbles. The mysteries of faith are scoffed at. The Jewish records are
  put on a level with the Greek myths, and miracles are laughed at as
  magical tricks. Through all this runs the train of thought resulting
  naturally from Bruno's fundamental principles, and familiar in modern
  philosophy as Spinozism, the denial of particular providence, the
  doctrine of the uselessness of prayer, the identification in a sense of
  liberty and necessity, and the peculiar definition of good and evil.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page687">[v.04 p.0687]</ph>
      </p>
      <p>In 1585-1586 he returned with Castelnau to Paris, where his
  anti-Aristotelian views were taken up by the college of Cambrai, but was
  soon driven from his refuge, and we next find him at Marburg and
  Wittenberg, the headquarters of Lutheranism. There is a tradition that
  here or in England he embraced the Protestant faith; nothing in his
  writings would lead one to suppose so. Several works, chiefly logical,
  appeared during his stay at Wittenberg (<i>De Lampade combinatoria
  Lulliana</i>, 1587, and <i>De Progressu et Lampade venatoria
  logicorum</i>, 1587). In 1588 he went to Prague, then to Helmstadt. In
  1591 he was at Frankfort, and published three important metaphysical
  works, <i>De Triplici Minimo et Mensura</i>; <i>De Monade, Numero, et
  Figura</i>; <i>De Immenso et Innumerabilibus</i>. He did not stay long at
  Prague, and we find him next at Zürich, whence he accepted an invitation
  to Venice from a young patrician, Giovanni Mocenigo. It was a rash step.
  The emissaries of the Inquisition were on his track; he was thrown into
  prison, and in 1593 was brought to Rome. Seven years were spent in
  confinement. On the 9th of February 1600 he was excommunicated, and on
  the 17th was burned at the stake.</p>
      <p>For more than two centuries Bruno received scarcely the consideration
  he deserved. On the 9th of June 1889, however, as a result of a strong
  popular movement, a statue to him was unveiled in Rome in the Campo dei
  Fiori, the place of his execution.</p>
      <p>To Bruno, as to all great thinkers, philosophy is the search for
  unity. Amid all the varying and contradictory phenomena of the universe
  there is something which gives coherence and intelligibility to them. Nor
  can this unity be something apart from the things; it must contain in
  itself the universe, which develops from it; it must be at once all and
  one. This unity is God, the universal substance,—the one and only
  principle, or <i>causa immanens</i>,—that which is in things and
  yet is distinct from them as the universal is distinct from the
  particular. He is the efficient and final cause of all, the beginning,
  middle, and end, eternal and infinite. By his action the world is
  produced, and his action is the law of his nature, his necessity is true
  freedom. He is living, active intelligence, the principle of motion and
  creation, realizing himself in the infinitely various forms of activity
  that constitute individual things. To the infinitely actual there is
  necessary the possible; that which determines involves somewhat in which
  its determinations can have existence. This other of God, which is in
  truth one with him, is matter. The universe, then, is a living cosmos, an
  infinitely animated system, whose end is the perfect realization of the
  variously graduated forms. The unity which sunders itself into the
  multiplicity of things may be called the <i>monas monadum</i>, each thing
  being a <i>monas</i> or self-existent, living being, a universe in
  itself. Of these monads the number is infinite. The soul of man is a
  thinking monad, and stands mid-way between the divine intelligence and
  the world of external things. As a portion of the divine life, the soul
  is immortal. Its highest function is the contemplation of the divine
  unity, discoverable under the manifold of objects.</p>
      <p>Such is a brief summary of the principal positions of Bruno's
  philosophy. It seems quite clear that in the earlier works, particularly
  the two Italian dialogues, he approached more nearly to the pantheistic
  view of things than in his later Latin treatises. The unity expounded at
  first is simply an <i>anima mundi</i>, a living universe, but not
  intelligent. There is a distinct development traceable towards the later
  and final form of his doctrine, in which the universe appears as the
  realization of the divine mind.</p>
      <p>Bruno's writings had been much neglected when Jacobi brought them into
  notice in his <i>Briefe über die Lehre Spinozas</i> (2nd ed., 1879).
  Since then many have held that Descartes, Spinoza and Leibnitz were
  indebted to him for their main principles. So far as Descartes is
  concerned, it is highly improbable that he had seen any of Bruno's works.
  Schelling, however, called one of his works after him, <i>Bruno</i>.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Bibliography</ph>.—The chief edition of the
  Latin works is that published at the public expense by F. Fiorentino, F.
  Tocco and H. Vitelli (Naples, 1879-1891), which superseded that of A.F.
  Gfrörer (Stuttgart, 1834, incomplete). The Italian works were collected
  by A. Wagner (Leipzig, 1830), and a new edition was published by P. de
  Lagarde (Göttingen, 1888-1889); also <i>Opere Italiane</i>, ed. Croce and
  G. Gentile (1907 foll.), with notes by the latter. In Germany,
  <i>Gesammelte Werke</i>, trans. L. Kuhlenbeck (1904 foll.). English
  translations:—The <i>Spaccio</i>, by Morehead, not as has been
  supposed by J. Toland (dated 1713, but probably printed earlier and very
  rare); of the preface to <i>De l' Infinito</i> (J. Toland in posthumous
  works); <i>Eroici Furores</i>, L. Williams (1888). There are also French
  and German translations.</p>
      <p>The chief English work on Giordano Bruno is that of J. Lewis
  M<sup>c</sup>Intyre (London, 1903), containing life, commentary and
  bibliography. See also C. Bartholmess, <i>J. Bruno</i> (Paris,
  1846-1847); Domenico Berti, <i>Giordano Bruno da Nola</i> (2nd ed.,
  1889); H. Brunnhofer, <i>Giordano Brunos Weltanschauung</i> (Leipzig,
  1883); M. Carrière, <i>Philosophische Weltanschauung der
  Reformationszeit</i>, pp. 411-494 (2nd ed., 1887); F.J. Clemens,
  <i>Giordano Bruno und Nicolaus von Cusa</i> (Bonn, 1847); Miss I. Frith,
  <i>Life of Giordano Bruno the Nolan</i> (London, 1887); C.E. Plumptre,
  <i>Life and Works of Giordano Bruno</i> (London, 1884); Chr. Sigwart, in
  <i>Kleine Schriften</i>, 1st series, pp. 49-124, 293-304; A. Riehl, <i>G.
  Bruno</i> (1889, ed. 1900; Eng. trans. Agnes Fry, 1905); Landsbeck,
  <i>Bruno, der Martyrer der neuen Weltanschauung</i> (1890); Owen, in
  <i>Sceptics of the Italian Renaissance</i> (London, 1893); C.H. von
  Stein, <i>G. Bruno</i> (1900); R. Adamson, <i>Development of Modern
  Philosophy</i> (Edinburgh and London, 1903); G. Louis, <i>G. Bruno, seine
  Weltanschauung und Lebensauffassung</i> (1900); O. Juliusberger, <i>G.
  Bruno und die Gegenwart</i> (1902); J. Reiner, <i>G. Bruno und seine
  Weltanschauung</i> (1907). The most important critical works are perhaps
  those of Felice Tocco, <i>Le Opere Latine di Giordano Bruno</i>
  (Florence, 1889), <i>Le Opere Inedite di Giordano Bruno</i> (Naples,
  1891), <i>Le Fonti piu recenti della filos. del Bruno</i> (Rome, 1892).
  See also H. Höffding, <i>History of Modern Philosophy</i> (Eng. trans.,
  1900); J.M. Robertson, <i>Short History of Freethought</i> (London,
  1906); G. Gentile, <i>Giordano Bruno nella Storia della cultura</i>
  (1907). For other works see G. Graziano, <i>Bibliografia Bruniana</i>
  (1900).</p>
      <p>(<ph outputclass="sc">R. Ad.;</ph> J. M. M.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>