<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e33248">
   <title>BUFFIER, CLAUDE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BUFFIER, CLAUDE--> (1661-1737), French philosopher, historian and
  educationalist, was born in Poland, on the 25th of May 1661, of French
  parents, who returned to France, and settled at Rouen, soon after his
  birth. He was educated at the Jesuit college there, and was received into
  the order at the age of nineteen. A dispute with the archbishop compelled
  him to leave Rouen, and after a short stay in Rome he returned to Paris
  to the college of the Jesuits, where he spent the rest of his life. He
  seems to have been an admirable teacher, with a great power of lucid
  exposition. His object in the <i>Traité des vérités premières</i> (1717),
  his best-known work, is to discover the ultimate principle of knowledge.
  This he finds in the sense we have of our own existence and of what we
  feel within ourselves. He thus takes substantially the same ground as
  Descartes, but he rejected the <i>a priori</i> method. In order to know
  what exists distinct from the self, "common sense" is necessary. Common
  sense he defined as "that disposition which nature has placed in all or
  most men, in order to enable them, when they have arrived at the age and
  use of reason, to form a common and uniform judgment with respect to
  objects different from the internal sentiment of their own perception,
  which judgment is not the consequence of any anterior judgment." The
  truths which this "disposition of nature" obliges us to accept can be
  neither proved nor disproved; they are practically followed even by those
  who reject them speculatively. But Buffier does not claim for these
  truths of "common sense" the absolute certainty which characterizes the
  knowledge we have of our own existence or the logical deductions we make
  from our thoughts; they possess merely the highest probability, and the
  man who rejects them is to be considered a fool, though he is not guilty
  of a contradiction. Buffier's aversion to scholastic refinements has
  given to his writings an appearance of shallowness and want of
  metaphysical insight, and unquestionably he failed entirely even to
  indicate the nature of that universality and necessity which he ascribed
  to his "eternal verities"; he was, however, one of the earliest to
  recognize the psychological as distinguished from the metaphysical side
  of Descartes's principle, and to use it, with no inconsiderable skill, as
  the basis of an analysis of the human mind, similar to that enjoined by
  Locke. In this he has anticipated the spirit and method as well as many
  of the results of Reid and the Scottish school. Voltaire described him as
  "the only Jesuit who has given a reasonable system of philosophy."</p>
      <p>He wrote also <i>Éléments de métaphysique</i> (1724), a "French
  Grammar on a new plan," and a number of historical essays. Most of his
  works appeared in a collected form in 1732, and an English translation of
  the <i>Traité</i> was published in 1780.</p>
   </body>
</topic>