<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e11617">
   <title>BRIDGWATER</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIDGWATER,--> a market town, port and municipal borough in the
  Bridgwater parliamentary division of Somerset, England, on the river
  Parret, 10 m. from its mouth, and 151¾ m. by the Great Western railway W.
  by S. of London. Pop. (1901) 15,209. It is pleasantly situated in a level
  and well-wooded country, having on the east the Mendip range and on the
  west the Quantock hills. The town lies along both sides of the river,
  here crossed by a handsome iron bridge. Among several places of worship
  the chief is St Mary Magdalene's church; this has a north porch and
  windows dating from the 14th century, besides a lofty and slender spire;
  but it has been much altered by restoration. It possesses a fine painted
  reredos. A house in Blake Street, largely restored, was the birthplace of
  Admiral Blake in 1598. Near the town are the three fine old churches of
  Weston Zoyland, Chedzoy and Middlezoy, containing some good brasses and
  carved woodwork. The battlefield of Sedgemoor, where the Monmouth
  rebellion was finally crushed in 1685, is within 3 m.; while not far off
  is Charlinch, the home of the Agapemonites (<i>q.v.</i>). Bridgwater has
  a considerable coasting trade, importing grain, coal, wine, hemp, tallow
  and timber, and exporting Bath brick, farm produce, earthenware, cement
  and plaster of Paris. The river is navigable by vessels of 700 tons,
  though liable, when spring-tides are flowing, to a bore which rises, in
  rough weather, to a height of 9 ft. Bath brick, manufactured only here,
  and made of the mingled sand and clay deposited by every tide, is the
  staple article of commerce; iron-founding is also carried on. The town is
  governed by a mayor, 6 aldermen and 18 councillors. Area, 926 acres.</p>
      <p>A settlement probably grew up in Saxon times at Bridgwater
  (<i>Briges</i>, <i>Briggewalteri</i>, <i>Brigewauter</i>), owing its
  origin as a trade centre to its position at the mouth of the chief river
  in Somerset. It became a mesne borough by the charter granted by John in
  1201, which provided that the town should be a free borough, the
  burgesses to be free and quit of all tolls, and made William de Briwere
  overlord. Other charters were granted by Henry III. in 1227 (confirmed in
  1318, 1370, 1380), which gave Bridgwater a gild merchant. It was
  incorporated by charter of Edward IV. (1468), confirmed in 1554, 1586,
  1629 and 1684. Parliamentary representation began in 1295 and continued
  until the Reform Act of 1870. A Saturday market and a fair on the 24th of
  June were granted by the charter of 1201. Another fair at the beginning
  of Lent was added in 1468, and a second market on Thursday, and fairs at
  Midsummer and on the 21st of September were added in 1554. Charles II.
  granted another fair on the 29th of December. The medieval importance of
  these markets and fairs for the sale of wool and wine and later of cloth
  has gone. The shipping trade of the port revived after the construction
  of the new dock in 1841, and corn and timber have been imported for
  centuries.</p>
      <p>See S. G. Jarman, "History of Bridgwater," <i>Historical MSS.
  Commission</i>, Report 9, Appendix; <i>Victoria County History:
  Somerset</i>, vol. ii.</p>
   </body>
</topic>