<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e11600">
   <title>BRIDGNORTH</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRIDGNORTH,--> a market town and municipal borough in the Ludlow
  parliamentary division of Shropshire, England, 150 m. N.W. by W. from
  London by the Great Western railway, on the Worcester-Shrewsbury line.
  Pop. (1901) 6052. The river Severn separates the upper town on the right
  bank from the lower on the left. A steep line of rail connects them. The
  upper town is built on the acclivities and summit of a rock which rises
  abruptly from the river to the height of 180 ft., and gives the town a
  very picturesque appearance. The railway passes under by a long tunnel.
  On the summit is the tower of the old castle, leaning about 17° from the
  perpendicular. There are also two parish churches. That of St Leonard,
  formerly collegiate, was practically rebuilt in 1862. This parish was
  held by Richard Baxter, the famous divine, in 1640. St Mary's church is
  in classic style of the late 18th century. The picturesque half-timbered
  style of domestic building is frequently seen in the streets. In this
  style are the town hall (1652), and a house dated 1580, in which was born
  in 1729 Thomas Percy, bishop of Dromore, the editor of the <i>Reliques of
  Ancient English Poetry</i>. The grammar school, founded in 1503, occupies
  an Elizabethan building; there are also a college of divinity, a
  blue-coat school, and a literary institute with library and school of
  art. There are large charities. Near the town is a curious ancient
  hermitage cave, in the sandstone. At Quatford, 1 m. south-east, the site
  of a castle dating from 1085 may be traced. This dominated the ancient
  Forest of Morf. Here Robert de Belesme originally founded the college
  which was afterwards moved to Bridgnorth. Bridgnorth manufactures
  carpets; brewing is carried on, and there is trade in agricultural
  produce. The town is governed by a mayor, 4 aldermen and 12 councillors.
  Area, 3018 acres.</p>
      <p>The early history of Bridgnorth is connected with Æthelfleda, lady of
  the Mercians, who raised a mound there in 912 as part of her offensive
  policy against the Danes of the five boroughs. After the Conquest William
  I. granted the manor of Bridgnorth to Earl Roger of Shrewsbury, whose son
  Robert de Belesme transferred his castle and borough from Quatford to
  Bridgnorth, but on Robert's attainder in 1102 the town became a royal
  borough. It is probable that Henry I. granted the burgesses certain
  privileges, for Henry II. confirmed to them all the franchises and
  customs which they had in the time of Henry I. King John in 1215 granted
  them freedom from toll throughout England except the city of London, and
  in <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page560">[v.04
  p.0560]</ph>1227 Henry III. conferred several new rights and liberties,
  among which were a gild merchant with a hanse. These early charters were
  confirmed by several succeeding kings, Henry VI. granting in addition
  assize of bread and ale and other privileges. Bridgnorth was incorporated
  by James I. in 1546. The burgesses returned two members to parliament in
  1295, and continued to do so until 1867, when they were assigned only one
  member. The town was disfranchised in 1885. A yearly fair on the feast of
  the Translation of St Leonard and three following days was granted to the
  burgesses in 1359, and in 1630 Charles I. granted them licence to hold
  another fair on the Thursday before the first week in Lent and two
  following days.</p>
   </body>
</topic>