<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e20756">
   <title>BROME, RICHARD</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROME, RICHARD--> (d. 1652), English dramatist, was originally a
  servant of Ben Jonson, and owed much to his master. The development of
  his plots, the strongly marked characters and the amount of curious
  information to be found in his work, all show Jonson's influence. The
  relation of master and servant developed into friendship, and our
  knowledge of Brome's personal character is chiefly drawn from Ben
  Jonson's lines to him, prefixed to <i>The Northern Lasse</i> (1632), the
  play which made Brome's reputation. Brome's genius lay entirely in
  comedy. He has left fifteen pieces. <i>Five New Playes</i> (ed. by Alex.
  Brome, 1652?) contained <i>Madd Couple Well Matcht</i> (acted 1639?);
  <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page632">[v.04
  p.0632]</ph>
         <i>Novella</i> (acted 1632); <i>Court Begger</i> (acted
  1632); <i>City Witt; The Damoiselle or the New Ordinary. Five New
  Playes</i> (1659) included <i>The English Moor, or The Mock Marriage; The
  Love-Sick Court, or The Ambitious Politique; Covent Garden Weeded; The
  New Academy, or The New Exchange</i>; and <i>The Queen and Concubine</i>.
  <i>The Antipodes</i> (acted 1638, pr. 1640); <i>The Sparagus Garden</i>
  (acted 1635, pr. 1640); <i>A Joviall Crew, or the Merry Beggars</i>
  (acted 1641, pr. 1652, revised in 1731 as an "opera"), and <i>The Queenes
  Exchange</i> (pr. 1657), were published separately. He collaborated with
  Thomas Heywood in <i>The late Lancashire Witches</i> (pr. 1634).</p>
      <p>See A.W. Ward, <i>History of English Dramatic Literature</i>, vol.
  iii. pp. 125-131 (1899). <i>The Dramatic Works of Richard Brome ...</i>
  were published in 1873.</p>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    

    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 2.—<i>Tillandsia
    usneoides</i>, Spanish moss, slightly reduced. 1, Small branch with
    flower; 2, flower cut vertically; 3, section of seed of
    <i>Bromelia</i>.</p>
            <p>(From <i>The Botanical Magazine</i>, by permission of
    Lovell, Reeve &amp; Co)</p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/bromeliaceae_2.png">
            <alt>Fig. 2.--Tillandsia usneoides.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <fig>
         <title>
      
    
  </title>
         <desc>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="sc">Fig.</ph> 1.—Fruit of the
    pine-apple (<i>Ananas sativa</i>), consisting of numerous flowers and
    bracts united together so as to form a collective or anthocarpous
    fruit. The crown of the pine-apple, c, consists of a series of empty
    bracts prolonged beyond the fruit.</p>
         </desc>
         <image href="images/bromeliaceae_1.png">
            <alt>Fig. 1.--Fruit of the pine-apple.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
   </body>
</topic>