<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e12716">
   <title>BRISSON, EUGÈNE HENRI</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BRISSON, EUGÈNE HENRI--> (1835- ), French statesman, was born at
  Bourges on the 31st of July 1835. He followed his father's profession of
  advocate, and having made himself conspicuous in opposition during the
  last days of the empire, was appointed deputy-mayor of Paris after its
  overthrow. He was elected to the Assembly on the 8th of February 1871, as
  a member of the extreme Left. While not approving of the Commune, he was
  the first to propose amnesty for the condemned (on the 13th of September
  1871), but the proposal was voted down. He strongly supported obligatory
  primary education, and was a firm anti-clerical. He was president of the
  chamber from 1881—replacing Gambetta—to March 1885, when he
  became prime minister upon the resignation of Jules Ferry; but he
  resigned when, after the general elections of that year, he only just
  obtained a majority for the vote of credit for the Tongking expedition.
  He remained conspicuous as a public man, took a prominent part in
  exposing the Panama scandals, was a powerful candidate for the presidency
  after the murder of President Carnot in 1894, and was again president of
  the chamber from December 1894 to 1898. In June of the latter year he
  formed a cabinet when the country was violently excited over the Dreyfus
  affair; his firmness and honesty increased the respect in which he was
  already held by good citizens, but a chance vote on an occasion of
  especial excitement overthrew his ministry in October. As one of the
  leaders of the radicals he actively supported the ministries of
  Waldeck-Rousseau and Combes, especially concerning the laws on the
  religious orders and the separation of church and state. In 1899 he was a
  candidate for the presidency. In May 1906 he was elected president of the
  chamber of deputies by 500 out of 581 votes.</p>
   </body>
</topic>