<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="d1e22834">
   <title>BROTHERS OF COMMON LIFE</title>
   <body>
      <p><!--BROTHERS OF COMMON LIFE,--> a religious community formerly
  existing in the Catholic Church. Towards the end of his career Gerhard
  Groot (<i>q.v.</i>) retired to his native town of Deventer, in the
  province of Overyssel and the diocese of Utrecht, and gathered about him
  a number of those who had been "converted" by his preaching or wished to
  place themselves under his spiritual guidance. With the assistance of
  Florentius Radewyn, who resigned for the purpose a canonry at Utrecht, he
  was able to carry out a long-cherished idea of establishing a house
  wherein devout men might live in community without the monastic vows. The
  first such community was established at Deventer in the house of
  Floentius himself (<i>c.</i> 1380); and Thomas à Kempis, who lived in it
  from 1392 to 1399, has left a description of the manner of life
  pursued:—</p>
      <p>"They humbly imitated the manner of the Apostolic life, and having one
  heart and mind in God, brought every man what was his own into the common
  stock, and receiving simple food and clothing avoided taking thought for
  the morrow. Of their own will they devoted themselves to God, and all
  busied themselves in obeying their rector or his vicar .... They laboured
  carefully in copying books, being instant continually in sacred study and
  devout meditation. In the morning, having said Matins, they went to the
  church (for Mass) .... Some who were priests and were learned in the
  divine law preached earnestly in the church."</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum" id="page652">[v.04 p.0652]</ph>
      </p>
      <p>Other houses of the Brothers of Common Life, otherwise called the
  "Modern Devotion," were in rapid succession established in the chief
  cities of the Low Countries and north and central Germany, so that there
  were in all upwards of forty houses of men; while those of women doubled
  that figure, the first having been founded by Groot himself at
  Deventer.</p>
      <p>The ground-idea was to reproduce the life of the first Christians as
  described in Acts iv. The members took no vows and were free to leave
  when they chose; but so long as they remained they were bound to observe
  chastity, to practise personal poverty, putting all their money and
  earnings into the common fund, to obey the rules of the house and the
  commands of the rector, and to exercise themselves in self-denial,
  humility and piety. The rector was chosen by the community and was not
  necessarily a priest, though in each house there were a few priests and
  clerics. The majority, however, were laymen, of all kinds and
  degrees—nobles, artisans, scholars, students, labouring men. The
  clerics preached and instructed the people, working chiefly among the
  poor; they also devoted themselves to the copying of manuscripts, in
  order thereby to earn something for the common fund; and some of them
  taught in the schools. Of the laymen, the educated copied manuscripts,
  the others worked at various handicrafts or at agriculture. After the
  religious services of the morning the Brothers scattered for the day's
  work, the artisans going to the workshops in the city,—for the idea
  was to live and work in the world, and not separated from it, like the
  monks. Their rule was that they had to earn their livelihood, and must
  not beg. This feature seemed a reflection on the mendicant orders, and
  the idea of a community life without vows and not in isolation from
  everyday life, was looked upon as something new and strange, and even as
  bearing affinities to the Beghards and other sects, at that time causing
  trouble to both Church and state. And so opposition arose to the Modern
  Devotion, and the controversy was carried to the legal faculty at Cologne
  University, which gave a judgment strongly in their favour. The question,
  for all that, was not finally settled until the council of Constance
  (1414), when their cause was triumphantly defended by Pierre d'Ailly and
  Gerson. For a century after this the Modern Devotion flourished
  exceedingly, and its influence on the revival of religion in the
  Netherlands and north Germany in the 15th century was wide and deep. It
  has been the fashion to treat Groot and the Brothers of Common Life as
  "Reformers before the Reformation"; but Schulze, in the Protestant
  <i>Realencyklopädie</i>, is surely right in pronouncing this view quite
  unhistorical—except on the theory that all interior spiritual
  religion is Protestant: he shows that at the Reformation hardly any of
  the Brothers embraced Lutheranism, only a single community going over as
  a body to the new religion. During the second half of the 16th century
  the institute gradually declined, and by the middle of the 17th all its
  houses had ceased to exist.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="sc">Authorities</ph>.—The chief authorities are
  Thomas à Kempis, <i>Lives of Groot and his Disciples</i> and <i>Chronicle
  of Mount St Agnes</i> (both works translated by J.P. Arthur, the former
  under the title <i>Founders of the New Devotion</i>, 1905); Busch,
  <i>Chronicle of Windesheim</i> (ed. Grube, 1887). Much has been written
  on the subject in Dutch and German; in English, S. Kettlewell, <i>Thomas
  à Kempis and the Brothers of Common Life</i> (1882) (but see Arthur in
  the Prefaces to above-named books); for a shorter sketch, F.R. Cruise,
  <i>Thomas à Kempis</i> (1887). An excellent article in Herzog-Hauck,
  <i>Realencyklopädie</i> (3rd ed.), "Brüder des gemeinsamen Lebens,"
  supplies copious information with references to all the literature; see
  also Max Heimbucher, <i>Orden und Kongregationen</i> (1897), ii. § 123.
  The part played by the Brothers of Common Life in the religious and
  educational movements of the time may be studied in Ludwig Pastor's
  <i>History of the Popes from the close of the Middle Ages</i>, or J.
  Janssen's <i>History of the German People</i>.</p>
      <p>(E. C. B.)</p>
   </body>
</topic>