<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p3-chapter-11" ><title>Chapter 11</title><body><p>Gideon Spilett took the box and opened it. It contained nearly two hundred grains of a
        white powder, a few particles of which he carried to his lips. The extreme bitterness of the
        substance precluded all doubt; it was certainly the precious extract of quinine, that
        pre-eminent antifebrile.</p><p>This powder must be administered to Herbert without delay. How it came there might be
        discussed later.</p><p>"Some coffee!" said Spilett.</p><p>In a few moments Neb brought a cup of the warm infusion. Gideon Spilett threw into it about
        eighteen grains of quinine, and they succeeded in making Herbert drink the mixture.</p><p>There was still time, for the third attack of the malignant fever had not yet shown itself.
        How they longed to be able to add that it would not return!</p><p>Besides, it must be remarked, the hopes of all had now revived. The mysterious influence
        had been again exerted, and in a critical moment, when they had despaired of it.</p><p>In a few hours Herbert was much calmer. The colonists could now discuss this incident. The
        intervention of the stranger was more evident than ever. But how had he been able to
        penetrate during the night into Granite House? It was inexplicable, and, in truth, the
        proceedings of the genius of the island were not less mysterious than was that genius
        himself. During this day the sulphate of quinine was administered to Herbert every three
        hours.</p><p>The next day some improvement in Herbert's condition was apparent. Certainly, he was not
        out of danger, intermittent fevers being subject to frequent and dangerous relapses, but the
        most assiduous care was bestowed on him. And besides, the specific was at hand; nor,
        doubtless, was he who had brought it far distant! And the hearts of all were animated by
        returning hope.</p><p>This hope was not disappointed. Ten days after, on the 20th of December, Herbert's
        convalescence commenced.</p><p>He was still weak, and strict diet had been imposed upon him, but no access of fever
        supervened. And then, the poor boy submitted with such docility to all the prescriptions
        ordered him! He longed so to get well!</p><p>Pencroft was as a man who has been drawn up from the bottom of an abyss. Fits of joy
        approaching delirium seized him. When the time for the third attack had passed by, he nearly
        suffocated the reporter in his embrace. Since then, he always called him Dr. Spilett.</p><p>The real doctor, however, remained undiscovered.</p><p>"We will find him!" repeated the sailor.</p><p>Certainly, this man, whoever he was, might expect a somewhat too energetic embrace from the
        worthy Pencroft!</p><p>The month of December ended, and with it the year 1867, during which the colonists of
        Lincoln Island had of late been so severely tried. They commenced the year 1868 with
        magnificent weather, great heat, and a tropical temperature, delightfully cooled by the
        sea-breeze. Herbert's recovery progressed, and from his bed, placed near one of the windows
        of Granite House, he could inhale the fresh air, charged with ozone, which could not fail to
        restore his health. His appetite returned, and what numberless delicate, savory little
        dishes Neb prepared for him!</p><p>"It is enough to make one wish to have a fever oneself!" said Pencroft.</p><p>During all this time, the convicts did not once appear in the vicinity of Granite House.
        There was no news of Ayrton, and though the engineer and Herbert still had some hopes of
        finding him again, their companions did not doubt but that the unfortunate man had perished.
        However, this uncertainty could not last, and when once the lad should have recovered, the
        expedition, the result of which must be so important, would be undertaken. But they would
        have to wait a month, perhaps, for all the strength of the colony must be put into
        requisition to obtain satisfaction from the convicts.</p><p>However, Herbert's convalescence progressed rapidly. The congestion of the liver had
        disappeared, and his wounds might be considered completely healed.</p><p>During the month of January, important work was done on the plateau of Prospect Heights;
        but it consisted solely in saving as much as was possible from the devastated crops, either
        of corn or vegetables. The grain and the plants were gathered, so as to provide a new
        harvest for the approaching half-season. With regard to rebuilding the poultry-yard, wall,
        or stables, Cyrus Harding preferred to wait. While he and his companions were in pursuit of
        the convicts, the latter might very probably pay another visit to the plateau, and it would
        be useless to give them an opportunity of recommencing their work of destruction. When the
        island should be cleared of these miscreants, they would set about rebuilding. The young
        convalescent began to get up in the second week of January, at first for one hour a day,
        then two, then three. His strength visibly returned, so vigorous was his constitution. He
        was now eighteen years of age. He was tall, and promised to become a man of noble and
        commanding presence. From this time his recovery, while still requiring care,--and Dr.
        Spilett was very strict,--made rapid progress. Towards the end of the month, Herbert was
        already walking about on Prospect Heights, and the beach.</p><p>He derived, from several sea-baths, which he took in company with Pencroft and Neb, the
        greatest possible benefit. Cyrus Harding thought he might now settle the day for their
        departure, for which the 15th of February was fixed. The nights, very clear at this time of
        year, would be favorable to the researches they intended to make all over the island.</p><p>The necessary preparations for this exploration were now commenced, and were important, for
        the colonists had sworn not to return to Granite House until their twofold object had been
        achieved; on the one hand, to exterminate the convicts, and rescue Ayrton, if he was still
        living; on the other, to discover who it was that presided so effectually over the fortunes
        of the colony.</p><p>Of Lincoln Island, the settlers knew thoroughly all the eastern coast from Claw Cape to the
        Mandible Capes, the extensive Tadorn Marsh, the neighborhood of Lake Grant, Jacamar Wood,
        between the road to the corral and the Mercy, the courses of the Mercy and Red Creek, and
        lastly, the spurs of Mount Franklin, among which the corral had been established.</p><p>They had explored, though only in an imperfect manner, the vast shore of Washington Bay
        from Claw Cape to Reptile End, the woody and marshy border of the west coast, and the
        interminable downs, ending at the open mouth of Shark Gulf. But they had in no way surveyed
        the woods which covered the Serpentine Peninsula, all to the right of the Mercy, the left
        bank of Falls River, and the wilderness of spurs and valleys which supported three quarters
        of the base of Mount Franklin, to the east, the north, and the west, and where doubtless
        many secret retreats existed. Consequently, many millions of acres of the island had still
        escaped their investigations.</p><p>It was, therefore, decided that the expedition should be carried through the Far West, so
        as to include all that region situated on the right of the Mercy.</p><p>It might, perhaps, be better worth while to go direct to the corral, where it might be
        supposed that the convicts had again taken refuge, either to pillage or to establish
        themselves there. But either the devastation of the corral would have been an accomplished
        fact by this time, and it would be too late to prevent it, or it had been the convicts'
        interest to entrench themselves there, and there would be still time to go and turn them out
        on their return.</p><p>Therefore, after some discussion, the first plan was adhered to, and the settlers resolved
        to proceed through the wood to Reptile End. They would make their way with their hatchets,
        and thus lay the first draft of a road which would place Granite House in communication with
        the end of the peninsula for a length of from sixteen to seventeen miles.</p><p>The cart was in good condition. The onagers, well rested, could go a long journey.
        Provisions, camp effects, a portable stove, and various utensils were packed in the cart, as
        also weapons and ammunition, carefully chosen from the now complete arsenal of Granite
        House. But it was necessary to remember that the convicts were, perhaps, roaming about the
        woods, and that in the midst of these thick forests a shot might quickly be fired and
        received. It was therefore resolved that the little band of settlers should remain together
        and not separate under any pretext whatever.</p><p>It was also decided that no one should remain at Granite House. Top and Jup themselves were
        to accompany the expedition; the inaccessible dwelling needed no guard. The 14th of
        February, eve of the departure, was consecrated entirely to repose, and--thanksgiving
        addressed by the colonists to the Creator. A place in the cart was reserved for Herbert,
        who, though thoroughly convalescent, was still a little weak. The next morning, at daybreak,
        Cyrus Harding took the necessary measures to protect Granite House from any invasion. The
        ladders, which were formerly used for the ascent, were brought to the Chimneys and buried
        deep in the sand, so that they might be available on the return of the colonists, for the
        machinery of the lift had been taken to pieces, and nothing of the apparatus remained.
        Pencroft stayed the last in Granite House in order to finish this work, and he then lowered
        himself down by means of a double rope held below, and which, when once hauled down, left no
        communication between the upper landing and the beach.</p><p>The weather was magnificent.</p><p>"We shall have a warm day of it," said the reporter, laughing.</p><p>"Pooh! Dr. Spilett," answered Pencroft, "we shall walk under the shade of the trees and
        shan't even see the sun!"</p><p>"Forward!" said the engineer.</p><p>The cart was waiting on the beach before the Chimneys. The reporter made Herbert take his
        place in it during the first hours at least of the journey, and the lad was obliged to
        submit to his doctor's orders.</p><p>Neb placed himself at the onagers' heads. Cyrus Harding, the reporter, and the sailor,
        walked in front. Top bounded joyfully along. Herbert offered a seat in his vehicle to Jup,
        who accepted it without ceremony. The moment for departure had arrived, and the little band
        set out.</p><p>The cart first turned the angle of the mouth of the Mercy, then, having ascended the left
        bank for a mile, crossed the bridge, at the other side of which commenced the road to Port
        Balloon, and there the explorers, leaving this road on their left, entered the cover of the
        immense woods which formed the region of the Far West.</p><p>For the first two miles the widely scattered trees allowed the cart to pass with ease; from
        time to time it became necessary to cut away a few creepers and bushes, but no serious
        obstacle impeded the progress of the colonists.</p><p>The thick foliage of the trees threw a grateful shade on the ground. Deodars, Douglas firs,
        casuarinas, banksias, gum-trees, dragon-trees, and other well-known species, succeeded each
        other far as the eye could reach. The feathered tribes of the island were all
        represented--grouse, jacamars, pheasants, lories, as well as the chattering cockatoos,
        parrots, and paroquets. Agouties, kangaroos, and capybaras fled swiftly at their approach;
        and all this reminded the settlers of the first excursions they had made on their arrival at
        the island.</p><p>"Nevertheless," observed Cyrus Harding, "I notice that these creatures, both birds and
        quadrupeds, are more timid than formerly. These woods have, therefore, been recently
        traversed by the convicts, and we shall certainly find some traces of them."</p><p>And, in fact, in several places they could distinguish traces, more or less recent, of the
        passage of a band of men--here branches broken off the trees, perhaps to mark out the way;
        there the ashes of a fire, and footprints in clayey spots; but nothing which appeared to
        belong to a settled encampment.</p><p>The engineer had recommended his companions to refrain from hunting. The reports of the
        firearms might give the alarm to the convicts, who were, perhaps, roaming through the
        forest. Moreover, the hunters would necessarily ramble some distance from the cart, which it
        was dangerous to leave unguarded.</p><p>In the afterpart of the day, when about six miles from Granite House, their progress became
        much more difficult. In order to make their way through some thickets, they were obliged to
        cut down trees. Before entering such places Harding was careful to send in Top and Jup, who
        faithfully accomplished their commission, and when the dog and orang returned without giving
        any warning, there was evidently nothing to fear, either from convicts or wild beasts, two
        varieties of the animal kingdom, whose ferocious instincts placed them on the same level. On
        the evening of the first day the colonists encamped about nine miles from Granite House, on
        the border of a little stream falling into the Mercy, and of the existence of which they had
        till then been ignorant; it evidently, however, belonged to the hydiographical system to
        which the soil owed its astonishing fertility. The settlers made a hearty meal, for their
        appetites were sharpened, and measures were then taken that the night might be passed in
        safety. If the engineer had had only to deal with wild beasts, jaguars or others, he would
        have simply lighted fires all around his camp, which would have sufficed for its defense;
        but the convicts would be rather attracted than terrified by the flames, and it was,
        therefore, better to be surrounded by the profound darkness of night.</p><p>The watch was, however, carefully organized. Two of the settlers were to watch together,
        and every two hours it was agreed that they should be relieved by their comrades. And so,
        notwithstanding his wish to the contrary, Herbert was exempted from guard. Pencroft and
        Gideon Spilett in one party, the engineer and Neb in another, mounted guard in turns over
        the camp.</p><p>The night, however, was but of few hours. The darkness was due rather to the thickness of
        the foliage than to the disappearance of the sun. The silence was scarcely disturbed by the
        howling of jaguars and the chattering of the monkeys, the latter appearing to particularly
        irritate Master Jup. The night passed without incident, and on the next day, the 15th of
        February, the journey through the forest, tedious rather than difficult, was continued. This
        day they could not accomplish more than six miles, for every moment they were obliged to cut
        a road with their hatchets.</p><p>Like true settlers, the colonists spared the largest and most beautiful trees, which would
        besides have cost immense labor to fell, and the small ones only were sacrificed, but the
        result was that the road took a very winding direction, and lengthened itself by numerous
        detours.</p><p>During the day Herbert discovered several new specimens not before met with in the island,
        such as the tree-fern, with its leaves spread out like the waters of a fountain,
        locust-trees, on the long pods of which the onagers browsed greedily, and which supplied a
        sweet pulp of excellent flavor. There, too, the colonists again found groups of magnificent
        kauries, their cylindrical trunks, crowded with a cone of verdure, rising to a height of two
        hundred feet. These were the tree-kings of New Zealand, as celebrated as the cedars of
        Lebanon.</p><p>As to the fauna, there was no addition to those species already known to the hunters.
        Nevertheless, they saw, though unable to get near them, a couple of those large birds
        peculiar to Australia, a sort of cassowary, called emu, five feet in height, and with brown
        plumage, which belong to the tribe of waders. Top darted after them as fast as his four legs
        could carry him, but the emus distanced him with ease, so prodigious was their speed.</p><p>As to the traces left by the convicts, a few more were discovered. Some footprints found
        near an apparently recently extinguished fire were attentively examined by the settlers. By
        measuring them one after the other, according to their length and breadth, the marks of five
        men's feet were easily distinguished. The five convicts had evidently camped on this spot;
        but,--and this was the object of so minute an examination,--a sixth footprint could not be
        discovered, which in that case would have been that of Ayrton.</p><p>"Ayrton was not with them!" said Herbert.</p><p>"No," answered Pencroft, "and if he was not with them, it was because the wretches had
        already murdered him! but then these rascals have not a den to which they may be tracked
        like tigers!"</p><p>"No," replied the reporter, "it is more probable that they wander at random, and it is
        their interest to rove about until the time when they will be masters of the island!"</p><p>"The masters of the island!" exclaimed the sailor; "the masters of the island!..." he
        repeated, and his voice was choked, as if his throat was seized in an iron grasp. Then in a
        calmer tone, "Do you know, Captain Harding," said he, "what the ball is which I have rammed
        into my gun?"</p><p>"No, Pencroft!"</p><p>"It is the ball that went through Herbert's chest, and I promise you it won't miss its
        mark!"</p><p>But this just retaliation would not bring Ayrton back to life, and from the examination of
        the footprints left in the ground, they must, alas! conclude that all hopes of ever seeing
        him again must be abandoned.</p><p>That evening they encamped fourteen miles from Granite House, and Cyrus Harding calculated
        that they could not be more than five miles from Reptile Point.</p><p>And indeed, the next day the extremity of the peninsula was reached, and the whole length
        of the forest had been traversed; but there was nothing to indicate the retreat in which the
        convicts had taken refuge, nor that, no less secret, which sheltered the mysterious
        unknown.</p><p/></body></topic>