<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p3-chapter-14" ><title>Chapter 14</title><body><p>Three years had passed away since the escape of the prisoners from Richmond, and how often
        during those three years had they spoken of their country, always present in their
        thoughts!</p><p>They had no doubt that the civil war was at an end, and to them it appeared impossible that
        the just cause of the North had not triumphed. But what had been the incidents of this
        terrible war? How much blood had it not cost? How many of their friends must have fallen in
        the struggle? They often spoke of these things, without as yet being able to foresee the day
        when they would be permitted once more to see their country. To return thither, were it but
        for a few days, to renew the social link with the inhabited world, to establish a
        communication between their native land and their island, then to pass the longest, perhaps
        the best, portion of their existence in this colony, founded by them, and which would then
        be dependent on their country, was this a dream impossible to realize?</p><p>There were only two ways of accomplishing it--either a ship must appear off Lincoln Island,
        or the colonists must themselves build a vessel strong enough to sail to the nearest
        land.</p><p>"Unless," said Pencroft, "our good genius, himself provides us with the means of returning
        to our country."</p><p>And, really, had any one told Pencroft and Neb that a ship of 300 tons was waiting for them
        in Shark Gulf or at Port Balloon, they would not even have made a gesture of surprise. In
        their state of mind nothing appeared improbable.</p><p>But Cyrus Harding, less confident, advised them to confine themselves to fact, and more
        especially so with regard to the building of a vessel--a really urgent work, since it was
        for the purpose of depositing, as soon as possible, at Tabor Island a document indicating
        Ayrton's new residence.</p><p>As the "Bonadventure" no longer existed, six months at least would be required for the
        construction of a new vessel. Now winter was approaching, and the voyage would not be made
        before the following spring.</p><p>"We have time to get everything ready for the fine season," remarked the engineer, who was
        consulting with Pencroft about these matters. "I think, therefore, my friend, that since we
        have to rebuild our vessel it will be best to give her larger dimensions. The arrival of the
        Scotch yacht at Tabor Island is very uncertain. It may even be that, having arrived several
        months ago, she has again sailed after having vainly searched for some trace of Ayrton. Will
        it not then he best to build a ship which, if necessary, could take us either to the
        Polynesian Archipelago or to New Zealand? What do you think?"</p><p>"I think, captain," answered the sailor; "I think that you are as capable of building a
        large vessel as a small one. Neither the wood nor the tools are wanting. It is only a
        question of time."</p><p>"And how many months would be required to build a vessel of from 250 to 300 tons?" asked
        Harding.</p><p>"Seven or eight months at least," replied Pencroft. "But it must not be forgotten that
        winter is drawing near, and that in severe frost wood is difficult to work. We must
        calculate on several weeks delay, and if our vessel is ready by next November we may think
        ourselves very lucky."</p><p>"Well," replied Cyrus Harding, "that will be exactly the most favorable time for
        undertaking a voyage of any importance, either to Tabor Island or to a more distant
        land."</p><p>"So it will, captain," answered the sailor. "Make out your plans then; the workmen are
        ready, and I imagine that Ayrton can lend us a good helping hand."</p><p>The colonists, having been consulted, approved the engineer's plan, and it was, indeed, the
        best thing to be done. It is true that the construction of a ship of from two to three
        hundred tons would be great labor, but the colonists had confidence in themselves, justified
        by their previous success.</p><p>Cyrus Harding then busied himself in drawing the plan of the vessel and making the model.
        During this time his companions employed themselves in felling and carting trees to furnish
        the ribs, timbers, and planks. The forest of the Far West supplied the best oaks and elms.
        They took advantage of the opening already made on their last excursion to form a
        practicable road, which they named the Far West Road, and the trees were carried to the
        Chimneys, where the dockyard was established. As to the road in question, the choice of
        trees had rendered its direction somewhat capricious, but at the same time it facilitated
        the access to a large part of the Serpentine Peninsula.</p><p>It was important that the trees should be quickly felled and cut up, for they could not be
        used while yet green, and some time was necessary to allow them to get seasoned. The
        carpenters, therefore, worked vigorously during the month of April, which was troubled only
        by a few equinoctial gales of some violence. Master Jup aided them dexterously, either by
        climbing to the top of a tree to fasten the ropes or by lending his stout shoulders to carry
        the lopped trunks.</p><p>All this timber was piled up under a large shed, built near the Chimneys, and there awaited
        the time for use.</p><p>The month of April was tolerably fine, as October often is in the northern zone. At the
        same time other work was actively continued, and soon all trace of devastation disappeared
        from the plateau of Prospect Heights. The mill was rebuilt, and new buildings rose in the
        poultry-yard. It had appeared necessary to enlarge their dimensions, for the feathered
        population had increased considerably. The stable now contained five onagers, four of which
        were well broken, and allowed themselves to be either driven or ridden, and a little colt.
        The colony now possessed a plow, to which the onagers were yoked like regular Yorkshire or
        Kentucky oxen. The colonists divided their work, and their arms never tired. Then who could
        have enjoyed better health than these workers, and what good humor enlivened the evenings in
        Granite House as they formed a thousand plans for the future!</p><p>As a matter of course Ayrton shared the common lot in every respect, and there was no
        longer any talk of his going to live at the corral. Nevertheless he was still sad and
        reserved, and joined more in the work than in the pleasures of his companions. But he was a
        valuable workman at need--strong, skilful, ingenious, intelligent. He was esteemed and loved
        by all, and he could not be ignorant of it.</p><p>In the meanwhile the corral was not abandoned. Every other day one of the settlers, driving
        the cart or mounted on an onager, went to look after the flock of musmons and goats and
        bring back the supply of milk required by Neb. These excursions at the same time afforded
        opportunities for hunting. Therefore Herbert and Gideon Spilett, with Top in front,
        traversed more often than their companions the road to the corral, and with the capital guns
        which they carried, capybaras, agouties, kangaroos, and wild pigs for large game, ducks,
        grouse, jacamars, and snipe for small game, were never wanting in the house. The produce of
        the warren, of the oyster-bed, several turtles which were taken, excellent salmon which came
        up the Mercy, vegetables from the plateau, wild fruit from the forest, were riches upon
        riches, and Neb, the head cook, could scarcely by himself store them away.</p><p>The telegraphic wire between the corral and Granite House had of course been repaired, and
        it was worked whenever one or other of the settlers was at the corral and found it necessary
        to spend the night there. Besides, the island was safe now and no attacks were to be feared,
        at any rate from men.</p><p>However, that which had happened might happen again. A descent of pirates, or even of
        escaped convicts, was always to be feared. It was possible that companions or accomplices of
        Bob Harvey had been in the secret of his plans, and might be tempted to imitate him. The
        colonists, therefore, were careful to observe the sea around the island, and every day their
        telescope covered the horizon enclosed by Union and Washington Bays. when they went to the
        corral they examined the sea to the west with no less attention, and by climbing the spur
        their gaze extended over a large section of the western horizon.</p><p>Nothing suspicious was discerned, but still it was necessary for them to be on their
        guard.</p><p>The engineer one evening imparted to his friends a plan which he had conceived for
        fortifying the corral. It appeared prudent to him to heighten the palisade and to flank it
        with a sort of blockhouse, which, if necessary, the settlers could hold against the enemy.
        Granite House might, by its very position, be considered impregnable; therefore the corral
        with its buildings, its stores, and the animals it contained, would always be the object of
        pirates, whoever they were, who might land on the island, and should the colonists be
        obliged to shut themselves up there they ought also to be able to defend themselves without
        any disadvantage. This was a project which might be left for consideration, and they were,
        besides, obliged to put off its execution until the next spring.</p><p>About the 15th of May the keel of the new vessel lay along the dockyard, and soon the stem
        and stern-post, mortised at each of its extremities, rose almost perpendicularly. The keel,
        of good oak, measured 110 feet in length, this allowing a width of five-and-twenty feet to
        the midship beam. But this was all the carpenters could do before the arrival of the frosts
        and bad weather. During the following week they fixed the first of the stern timbers, but
        were then obliged to suspend work.</p><p>During the last days of the month the weather was extremely bad. The wind blew from the
        east, sometimes with the violence of a tempest. The engineer was somewhat uneasy on account
        of the dockyard shed--which besides, he could not have established in any other place near
        to Granite House--for the islet only imperfectly sheltered the shore from the fury of the
        open sea, and in great storms the waves beat against the very foot of the granite cliff.</p><p>But, very fortunately, these fears were not realized. The wind shifted to the southeast,
        and there the beach of Granite House was completely covered by Flotsam Point.</p><p>Pencroft and Ayrton, the most zealous workmen at the new vessel, pursued their labor as
        long as they could. They were not men to mind the wind tearing at their hair, nor the rain
        wetting them to the skin, and a blow from a hammer is worth just as much in bad as in fine
        weather. But when a severe frost succeeded this wet period, the wood, its fibers acquiring
        the hardness of iron, became extremely difficult to work, and about the 10th of June
        shipbuilding was obliged to be entirely discontinued.</p><p>Cyrus Harding and his companions had not omitted to observe how severe was the temperature
        during the winters of Lincoln Island. The cold was comparable to that experienced in the
        States of New England, situated at almost the same distance from the equator. In the
        northern hemisphere, or at any rate in the part occupied by British America and the north of
        the United States, this phenomenon is explained by the flat conformation of the territories
        bordering on the pole, and on which there is no intumescence of the soil to oppose any
        obstacle to the north winds; here, in Lincoln Island, this explanation would not
        suffice.</p><p>"It has even been observed," remarked Harding one day to his companions, "that in equal
        latitudes the islands and coast regions are less tried by the cold than inland countries. I
        have often heard it asserted that the winters of Lombardy, for example, are not less
        rigorous than those of Scotland, which results from the sea restoring during the winter the
        heat which it received during the summer. Islands are, therefore, in a better situation for
        benefiting by this restitution."</p><p>"But then, Captain Harding," asked Herbert, "why does Lincoln Island appear to escape the
        common law?"</p><p>"That is difficult to explain," answered the engineer. "However, I should be disposed to
        conjecture that this peculiarity results from the situation of the island in the Southern
        Hemisphere, which, as you know, my boy, is colder than the Northern Hemisphere."</p><p>"Yes," said Herbert, "and icebergs are met with in lower latitudes in the south than in the
        north of the Pacific."</p><p>"That is true," remarked Pencroft, "and when I have been serving on board whalers I have
        seen icebergs off Cape Horn."</p><p>"The severe cold experienced in Lincoln Island," said Gideon Spilett, "may then perhaps be
        explained by the presence of floes or icebergs comparatively near to Lincoln Island."</p><p>"Your opinion is very admissible indeed, my dear Spilett," answered Cyrus Harding, "and it
        is evidently to the proximity of icebergs that we owe our rigorous winters. I would draw
        your attention also to an entirely physical cause, which renders the Southern colder than
        the Northern Hemisphere. In fact, since the sun is nearer to this hemisphere during the
        summer, it is necessarily more distant during the winter. This explains then the excess of
        temperature in the two seasons, for, if we find the winters very cold in Lincoln Island, we
        must not forget that the summers here, on the contrary, are very hot."</p><p>"But why, if you please, captain," asked Pencroft, knitting his brows, "why should our
        hemisphere, as you say, be so badly divided? It isn't just, that!"</p><p>"Friend Pencroft," answered the engineer, laughing, "whether just or not, we must submit to
        it, and here lies the reason for this peculiarity. The earth does not describe a circle
        around the sun, but an ellipse, as it must by the laws of rational mechanics. Now, the earth
        occupies one of the foci of the ellipse, and so at one point in its course is at its apogee,
        that is, at its farthest from the sun, and at another point it is at its perigee, or nearest
        to the sun. Now it happens that it is during the winter of the southern countries that it is
        at its most distant point from the sun, and consequently, in a situation for those regions
        to feel the greatest cold. Nothing can be done to prevent that, and men, Pencroft, however
        learned they may be, can never change anything of the cosmographical order established by
        God Himself."</p><p>"And yet," added Pencroft, "the world is very learned. What a big book, captain, might be
        made with all that is known!"</p><p>"And what a much bigger book still with all that is not known!" answered Harding.</p><p>At last, for one reason or another, the month of June brought the cold with its accustomed
        intensity, and the settlers were often confined to Granite House. Ah! how wearisome this
        imprisonment was to them, and more particularly to Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"Look here," said he to Neb one day, "I would give you by notarial deed all the estates
        which will come to me some day, if you were a good enough fellow to go, no matter where, and
        subscribe to some newspaper for me! Decidedly the thing that is most essential to my
        happiness is the knowing every morning what has happened the day before in other places than
        this!"</p><p>Neb began to laugh.</p><p>"'Pon my word," he replied, "the only thing I think about is my daily work!"</p><p>The truth was that indoors as well as out there was no want of work.</p><p>The colony of Lincoln Island was now at its highest point of prosperity, achieved by three
        years of continued hard work. The destruction of the brig had been a new source of riches.
        Without speaking of the complete rig which would serve for the vessel now on the stocks,
        utensils and tools of all sorts, weapons and ammunition, clothes and instruments, were now
        piled in the storerooms of Granite House. It had not even been necessary to resort again to
        the manufacture of the coarse felt materials. Though the colonists had suffered from cold
        during their first winter, the bad season might now come without their having any reason to
        dread its severity. Linen was plentiful also, and besides, they kept it with extreme care.
        From chloride of sodium, which is nothing else than sea salt, Cyrus Harding easily extracted
        the soda and chlorine. The soda, which it was easy to change into carbonate of soda, and the
        chlorine, of which he made chloride of lime, were employed for various domestic purposes,
        and especially in bleaching linen. Besides, they did not wash more than four times a year,
        as was done by families in the olden times, and it may be added, that Pencroft and Gideon
        Spilett, while waiting for the postman to bring him his newspaper, distinguished themselves
        as washermen.</p><p>So passed the winter months, June, July, and August. They were severe, and the average
        observations of the thermometer did not give more than eight degrees of Fahrenheit. It was
        therefore lower in temperature than the preceding winter. But then, what splendid fires
        blazed continually on the hearths of Granite House, the smoke marking the granite wall with
        long, zebra-like streaks! Fuel was not spared, as it grew naturally a few steps from them.
        Besides, the chips of the wood destined for the construction of the ship enabled them to
        economize the coal, which required more trouble to transport.</p><p>Men and animals were all well. Master Jup was a little chilly, it must be confessed. This
        was perhaps his only weakness, and it was necessary to make him a well-padded dressing-gown.
        But what a servant he was, clever, zealous, indefatigable, not indiscreet, not talkative,
        and he might have been with reason proposed as a model for all his biped brothers in the Old
        and New Worlds!</p><p>"As for that," said Pencroft, "when one has four hands at one's service, of course one's
        work ought to be done so much the better!"</p><p>And indeed the intelligent creature did it well.</p><p>During the seven months which had passed since the last researches made round the mountain,
        and during the month of September, which brought back fine weather, nothing was heard of the
        genius of the island. His power was not manifested in any way. It is true that it would have
        been superfluous, for no incident occurred to put the colonists to any painful trial.</p><p>Cyrus Harding even observed that if by chance the communication between the unknown and the
        tenants of Granite House had ever been established through the granite, and if Top's
        instinct had as it were felt it, there was no further sign of it during this period. The
        dog's growling had entirely ceased, as well as the uneasiness of the orang. The two
        friends-- for they were such--no longer prowled round the opening of the inner well, nor did
        they bark or whine in that singular way which from the first the engineer had noticed. But
        could he be sure that this was all that was to be said about this enigma, and that he should
        never arrive at a solution? Could he be certain that some conjuncture would not occur which
        would bring the mysterious personage on the scene? who could tell what the future might have
        in reserve?</p><p>At last the winter was ended, but an event, the consequences of which might be serious
        occurred in the first days of the returning spring.</p><p>On the 7th of September, Cyrus Harding, having observed the crater, saw smoke curling round
        the summit of the mountain, its first vapors rising in the air.</p><p/></body></topic>