<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p3-chapter-19" ><title>Chapter 19</title><body><p>The next day, the 8th day of January, after a day and night passed at the corral, where
        they left all in order, Cyrus Harding and Ayrton arrived at Granite House.</p><p>The engineer immediately called his companions together, and informed them of the imminent
        danger which threatened Lincoln Island, and from which no human power could deliver
        them.</p><p>"My friends," he said, and his voice betrayed the depth of his emotion, "our island is not
        among those which will endure while this earth endures. It is doomed to more or less speedy
        destruction, the cause of which it bears within itself, and from which nothing can save
        it."</p><p>The colonists looked at each other, then at the engineer. They did not clearly comprehend
        him.</p><p>"Explain yourself, Cyrus!" said Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"I will do so," replied Cyrus Harding, "or rather I will simply afford you the explanation
        which, during our few minutes of private conversation, was given me by Captain Nemo."</p><p>"Captain Nemo!" exclaimed the colonists.</p><p>"Yes, and it was the last service he desired to render us before his death!"</p><p>"The last service!" exclaimed Pencroft, "the last service! You will see that though he is
        dead he will render us others yet!"</p><p>"But what did the captain say?" inquired the reporter.</p><p>"I will tell you, my friends," said the engineer. "Lincoln Island does not resemble the
        other islands of the Pacific, and a fact of which Captain Nemo has made me cognizant must
        sooner or later bring about the subversion of its foundation."</p><p>"Nonsense! Lincoln Island, it can't be!" cried Pencroft, who, in spite of the respect he
        felt for Cyrus Harding, could not prevent a gesture of incredulity.</p><p>"Listen, Pencroft," resumed the engineer, "I will tell you what Captain Nemo communicated
        to me, and which I myself confirmed yesterday, during the exploration of Dakkar Grotto.</p><p>"This cavern stretches under the island as far as the volcano, and is only separated from
        its central shaft by the wall which terminates it. Now, this wall is seamed with fissures
        and clefts which already allow the sulphurous gases generated in the interior of the volcano
        to escape."</p><p>"Well?" said Pencroft, his brow suddenly contracting.</p><p>"Well, then, I saw that these fissures widen under the internal pressure from within, that
        the wall of basalt is gradually giving way and that after a longer or shorter period it will
        afford a passage to the waters of the lake which fill the cavern."</p><p>"Good!" replied Pencroft, with an attempt at pleasantry. "The sea will extinguish the
        volcano, and there will be an end of the matter!"</p><p>"Not so!" said Cyrus Harding, "should a day arrive when the sea, rushing through the wall
        of the cavern, penetrates by the central shaft into the interior of the island to the
        boiling lava, Lincoln Island will that day be blown into the air--just as would happen to
        the island of Sicily were the Mediterranean to precipitate itself into Mount Etna."</p><p>The colonists made no answer to these significant words of the engineer. They now
        understood the danger by which they were menaced.</p><p>It may be added that Cyrus Harding had in no way exaggerated the danger to be apprehended.
        Many persons have formed an idea that it would be possible to extinguish volcanoes, which
        are almost always situated on the shores of a sea or lake, by opening a passage for the
        admission of the water. But they are not aware that this would be to incur the risk of
        blowing up a portion of the globe, like a boiler whose steam is suddenly expanded by intense
        heat. The water, rushing into a cavity whose temperature might be estimated at thousands of
        degrees, would be converted into steam with a sudden energy which no enclosure could
        resist.</p><p>It was not therefore doubtful that the island, menaced by a frightful and approaching
        convulsion, would endure only so long as the wall of Dakkar Grotto itself should endure. It
        was not even a question of months, nor of weeks, but of days; it might be of hours.</p><p>The first sentiment which the colonists felt was that of profound sorrow. They thought not
        so much of the peril which menaced themselves personally, but of the destruction of the
        island which had sheltered them, which they had cultivated, which they loved so well, and
        had hoped to render so flourishing. So much effort ineffectually expended, so much labor
        lost.</p><p>Pencroft could not prevent a large tear from rolling down his cheek, nor did he attempt to
        conceal it.</p><p>Some further conversation now took place. The chances yet in favor of the colonists were
        discussed; but finally it was agreed that there was not an hour to be lost, that the
        building and fitting of the vessel should be pushed forward with their utmost energy, and
        that this was the sole chance of safety for the inhabitants of Lincoln Island.</p><p>All hands, therefore, set to work on the vessel. What could it avail to sow, to reap, to
        hunt, to increase the stores of Granite House? The contents of the storehouse and
        outbuildings contained more than sufficient to provide the ship for a voyage, however long
        might be its duration. But it was imperative that the ship should be ready to receive them
        before the inevitable catastrophe should arrive.</p><p>Their labors were now carried on with feverish ardor. By the 23rd of January the vessel was
        half-decked over. Up to this time no change had taken place on the summit of the volcano.
        Vapor and smoke mingled with flames and incandescent stones were thrown up from the crater.
        But during the night of the 23rd, in consequence of the lava attaining the level of the
        first stratum of the volcano, the hat-shaped cone which formed over the latter disappeared.
        A frightful sound was heard. The colonists at first thought the island was rent asunder, and
        rushed out of Granite House.</p><p>This occurred about two o'clock in the morning.</p><p>The sky appeared on fire. The superior cone, a mass of rock a thousand feet in height, and
        weighing thousands of millions of pounds, had been thrown down upon the island, making it
        tremble to its foundation. Fortunately, this cone inclined to the north, and had fallen upon
        the plain of sand and tufa stretching between the volcano and the sea. The aperture of the
        crater being thus enlarged projected towards the sky a glare so intense that by the simple
        effect of reflection the atmosphere appeared red-hot. At the same time a torrent of lava,
        bursting from the new summit, poured out in long cascades, like water escaping from a vase
        too full, and a thousand tongues of fire crept over the sides of the volcano.</p><p>"The corral! the corral!" exclaimed Ayrton.</p><p>It was, in fact, towards the corral that the lava was rushing as the new crater faced the
        east, and consequently the fertile portions of the island, the springs of Red Creek and
        Jacamar Wood, were menaced with instant destruction.</p><p>At Ayrton's cry the colonists rushed to the onagers' stables. The cart was at once
        harnessed. All were possessed by the same thought--to hasten to the corral and set at
        liberty the animals it enclosed.</p><p>Before three in the morning they arrived at the corral. The cries of the terrified musmons
        and goats indicated the alarm which possessed them. Already a torrent of burning matter and
        liquefied minerals fell from the side of the mountain upon the meadows as far as the side of
        the palisade. The gate was burst open by Ayrton, and the animals, bewildered with terror,
        fled in all directions.</p><p>An hour afterwards the boiling lava filled the corral, converting into vapor the water of
        the little rivulet which ran through it, burning up the house like dry grass, and leaving
        not even a post of the palisade to mark the spot where the corral once stood.</p><p>To contend against this disaster would have been folly--nay, madness. In presence of
        Nature's grand convulsions man is powerless.</p><p>It was now daylight--the 24th of January. Cyrus Harding and his companions, before
        returning to Granite House, desired to ascertain the probable direction this inundation of
        lava was about to take. The soil sloped gradually from Mount Franklin to the east coast, and
        it was to be feared that, in spite of the thick Jacamar Wood, the torrent would reach the
        plateau of Prospect Heights.</p><p>"The lake will cover us," said Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"I hope so!" was Cyrus Harding's only reply.</p><p>The colonists were desirous of reaching the plain upon which the superior cone of Mount
        Franklin had fallen, but the lava arrested their progress. It had followed, on one side, the
        valley of Red Creek, and on the other that of Falls River, evaporating those watercourses in
        its passage. There was no possibility of crossing the torrent of lava; on the contrary, the
        colonists were obliged to retreat before it. The volcano, without its crown, was no longer
        recognizable, terminated as it was by a sort of flat table which replaced the ancient
        crater. From two openings in its southern and eastern sides an unceasing flow of lava poured
        forth, thus forming two distinct streams. Above the new crater a cloud of smoke and ashes,
        mingled with those of the atmosphere, massed over the island. Loud peals of thunder broke,
        and could scarcely be distinguished from the rumblings of the mountain, whose mouth vomited
        forth ignited rocks, which, hurled to more than a thousand feet, burst in the air like
        shells. Flashes of lightning rivaled in intensity the volcano's eruption.</p><p>Towards seven in the morning the position was no longer tenable by the colonists, who
        accordingly took shelter in the borders of Jacamar Wood. Not only did the projectiles begin
        to rain around them, but the lava, overflowing the bed of Red Creek, threatened to cut off
        the road to the corral. The nearest rows of trees caught fire, and their sap, suddenly
        transformed into vapor, caused them to explode with loud reports, while others, less moist,
        remained unhurt in the midst of the inundation.</p><p>The colonists had again taken the road to the corral. They proceeded but slowly, frequently
        looking back; but, in consequence of the inclination of the soil, the lava gained rapidly in
        the east, and as its lower waves became solidified others, at boiling heat, covered them
        immediately.</p><p>Meanwhile, the principal stream of Red Creek Valley became more and more menacing. All this
        portion of the forest was on fare, and enormous wreaths of smoke rolled over the trees,
        whore trunks were already consumed by the lava.</p><p>The colonists halted near the lake, about half a mile from the mouth of Red Creek. A
        question of life or death was now to be decided.</p><p>Cyrus Harding, accustomed to the consideration of important crises, and aware that he was
        addressing men capable of hearing the truth, whatever it might be, then said,--</p><p>"Either the lake will arrest the progress of the lava, and a part of the island will be
        preserved from utter destruction, or the stream will overrun the forests of the Far West,
        and not a tree or plant will remain on the surface of the soil. We shall have no prospect
        but that of starvation upon these barren rocks--a death which will probably be anticipated
        by the explosion of the island."</p><p>"In that case," replied Pencroft, folding his arms and stamping his foot, "what's the use
        of working any longer on the vessel?"</p><p>"Pencroft," answered Cyrus Harding, "we must do our duty to the last!"</p><p>At this instant the river of lava, after having broken a passage through the noble trees it
        devoured in its course, reached the borders of the lake. At this point there was an
        elevation of the soil which, had it been greater, might have sufficed to arrest the
        torrent.</p><p>"To work!" cried Cyrus Harding.</p><p>The engineer's thought was at once understood. It might be possible to dam, as it were, the
        torrent, and thus compel it to pour itself into the lake.</p><p>The colonists hastened to the dockyard. They returned with shovels, picks, axes, and by
        means of banking the earth with the aid of fallen trees they succeeded in a few hours in
        raising an embankment three feet high and some hundreds of paces in length. It seemed to
        them, when they had finished, as if they had scarcely been working more than a few
        minutes.</p><p>It was not a moment too soon. The liquefied substances soon after reached the bottom of the
        barrier. The stream of lava swelled like a river about to overflow its banks, and threatened
        to demolish the sole obstacle which could prevent it from overrunning the whole Far West.
        But the dam held firm, and after a moment of terrible suspense the torrent precipitated
        itself into Grant Lake from a height of twenty feet.</p><p>The colonists, without moving or uttering a word, breathlessly regarded this strife of the
        two elements.</p><p>What a spectacle was this conflict between water and fire! What pen could describe the
        marvelous horror of this scene--what pencil could depict it? The water hissed as it
        evaporated by contact with the boiling lava. The vapor whirled in the air to an immeasurable
        height, as if the valves of an immense boiler had been suddenly opened. But, however
        considerable might be the volume of water contained in the lake, it must eventually be
        absorbed, because it was not replenished, while the stream of lava, fed from an
        inexhaustible source, rolled on without ceasing new waves of incandescent matter.</p><p>The first waves of lava which fell in the lake immediately solidified and accumulated so as
        speedily to emerge from it. Upon their surface fell other waves, which in their turn became
        stone, but a step nearer the center of the lake. In this manner was formed a pier which
        threatened to gradually fill up the lake, which could not overflow, the water displaced by
        the lava being evaporated. The hissing of the water rent the air with a deafening sound, and
        the vapor, blown by the wind, fell in rain upon the sea. The pier became longer and longer,
        and the blocks of lava piled themselves one on another. Where formerly stretched the calm
        waters of the lake now appeared an enormous mass of smoking rocks, as if an upheaving of the
        soil had formed immense shoals. Imagine the waters of the lake aroused by a hurricane, then
        suddenly solidified by an intense frost, and some conception may be formed of the aspect of
        the lake three hours alter the eruption of this irresistible torrent of lava.</p><p>This time water would be vanquished by fire.</p><p>Nevertheless it was a fortunate circumstance for the colonists that the effusion of lava
        should have been in the direction of Lake Grant. They had before them some days' respite.
        The plateau of Prospect Heights, Granite House, and the dockyard were for the moment
        preserved. And these few days it was necessary to employ in planking and carefully calking
        the vessel, and launching her. The colonists would then take refuge on board the vessel,
        content to rig her after she should be afloat on the waters. With the danger of an explosion
        which threatened to destroy the island there could be no security on shore. The walls of
        Granite House, once so sure a retreat, might at any moment fall in upon them.</p><p>During the six following days, from the 25th to the 30th of January, the colonists
        accomplished as much of the construction of their vessel as twenty men could have done. They
        hardly allowed themselves a moment's repose, and the glare of the flames which shot from the
        crater enabled them to work night and day. The flow of lava continued, but perhaps less
        abundantly. This was fortunate, for Lake Grant was almost entirely choked up, and if more
        lava should accumulate it would inevitably spread over the plateau of Prospect Heights, and
        thence upon the beach.</p><p>But if the island was thus partially protected on this side, it was not so with the western
        part.</p><p>In fact, the second stream of lava, which had followed the valley of Falls River, a valley
        of great extent, the land on both sides of the creek being flat, met with no obstacle. The
        burning liquid had then spread through the forest of the Far West. At this period of the
        year, when the trees were dried up by a tropical heat, the forest caught fire
        instantaneously, in such a manner that the conflagration extended itself both by the trunks
        of the trees and by their higher branches, whose interlacement favored its progress. It even
        appeared that the current of flame spread more rapidly among the summits of the trees than
        the current of lava at their bases.</p><p>Thus it happened that the wild animals, jaguars, wild boars, capybaras, koalas, and game of
        every kind, mad with terror, had fled to the banks of the Mercy and to the Tadorn Marsh,
        beyond the road to Port Balloon. But the colonists were too much occupied with their task to
        pay any attention to even the most formidable of these animals. They had abandoned Granite
        House, and would not even take shelter at the Chimneys, but encamped under a tent, near the
        mouth of the Mercy.</p><p>Each day Cyrus Harding and Gideon Spilett ascended the plateau of Prospect Heights.
        Sometimes Herbert accompanied them, but never Pencroft, who could not bear to look upon the
        prospect of the island now so utterly devastated.</p><p>It was, in truth, a heart-rending spectacle. All the wooded part of the island was now
        completely bare. One single clump of green trees raised their heads at the extremity of
        Serpentine Peninsula. Here and there were a few grotesque blackened and branchless stumps.
        The side of the devastated forest was even more barren than Tadorn Marsh. The eruption of
        lava had been complete. Where formerly sprang up that charming verdure, the soil was now
        nothing but a savage mass of volcanic tufa. In the valleys of the Falls and Mercy rivers no
        drop of water now flowed towards the sea, and should Lake Grant be entirely dried up, the
        colonists would have no means of quenching their thirst. But, fortunately the lava had
        spared the southern corner of the lake, containing all that remained of the drinking water
        of the island. Towards the northwest stood out the rugged and well-defined outlines of the
        sides of the volcano, like a gigantic claw hovering over the island. What a sad and fearful
        sight, and how painful to the colonists, who, from a fertile domain covered with forests,
        irrigated by watercourses, and enriched by the produce of their toils, found themselves, as
        it were, transported to a desolate rock, upon which, but for their reserves of provisions,
        they could not even gather the means of subsistence!</p><p>"It is enough to break one's heart!" said Gideon Spilett, one day.</p><p>"Yes, Spilett," answered the engineer. "May God grant us the time to complete this vessel,
        now our sole refuge!"</p><p>"Do not you think, Cyrus, that the violence of the eruption has somewhat lessened? The
        volcano still vomits forth lava, but somewhat less abundantly, if I mistake not."</p><p>"It matters little," answered Cyrus Harding. "The fire is still burning in the interior of
        the mountain, and the sea may break in at any moment. We are in the condition of passengers
        whose ship is devoured by a conflagration which they cannot extinguish, and who know that
        sooner or later the flames must reach the powder-magazine. To work, Spilett, to work, and
        let us not lose an hour!"</p><p>During eight days more, that is to say until the 7th of February, the lava continued to
        flow, but the eruption was confined within the previous limits. Cyrus Harding feared above
        all lest the liquefied matter should overflow the shore, for in that event the dockyard
        could not escape. Moreover, about this time the colonists felt in the frame of the island
        vibrations which alarmed them to the highest degree.</p><p>It was the 20th of February. Yet another month must elapse before the vessel would be ready
        for sea. Would the island hold together till then? The intention of Pencroft and Cyrus
        Harding was to launch the vessel as soon as the hull should be complete. The deck, the
        upperworks, the interior woodwork and the rigging might be finished afterwards, but the
        essential point was that the colonists should have an assured refuge away from the island.
        Perhaps it might be even better to conduct the vessel to Port Balloon, that is to say, as
        far as possible from the center of eruption, for at the mouth of the Mercy, between the
        islet and the wall of granite, it would run the risk of being crushed in the event of any
        convulsion. All the exertions of the voyagers were therefore concentrated upon the
        completion of the hull.</p><p>Thus the 3rd of March arrived, and they might calculate upon launching the vessel in ten
        days.</p><p>Hope revived in the hearts of the colonists, who had, in this fourth year of their sojourn
        on Lincoln island, suffered so many trials. Even Pencroft lost in some measure the somber
        taciturnity occasioned by the devastation and ruin of his domain. His hopes, it is true,
        were concentrated upon his vessel.</p><p>"We shall finish it," he said to the engineer, "we shall finish it, captain, and it is
        time, for the season is advancing and the equinox will soon be here. Well, if necessary, we
        must put in to Tabor island to spend the winter. But think of Tabor island after Lincoln
        Island. Ah, how unfortunate! Who could have believed it possible?"</p><p>"Let us get on," was the engineer's invariable reply.</p><p>And they worked away without losing a moment.</p><p>"Master," asked Neb, a few days later, "do you think all this could have happened if
        Captain Nemo had been still alive?"</p><p>"Certainly, Neb," answered Cyrus Harding.</p><p>"I, for one, don't believe it!" whispered Pencroft to Neb.</p><p>"Nor I!" answered Neb seriously.</p><p>During the first week of March appearances again became menacing. Thousands of threads like
        glass, formed of fluid lava, fell like rain upon the island. The crater was again boiling
        with lava which overflowed the back of the volcano. The torrent flowed along the surface of
        the hardened tufa, and destroyed the few meager skeletons of trees which had withstood the
        first eruption. The stream, flowing this time towards the southwest shore of Lake Grant,
        stretched beyond Creek Glycerine, and invaded the plateau of Prospect Heights. This last
        blow to the work of the colonists was terrible. The mill, the buildings of the inner court,
        the stables, were all destroyed. The affrighted poultry fled in all directions. Top and Jup
        showed signs of the greatest alarm, as if their instinct warned them of an impending
        catastrophe. A large number of the animals of the island had perished in the first eruption.
        Those which survived found no refuge but Tadorn Marsh, save a few to which the plateau of
        Prospect Heights afforded asylum. But even this last retreat was now closed to them, and the
        lava- torrent, flowing over the edge of the granite wall, began to pour down upon the beach
        its cataracts of fire. The sublime horror of this spectacle passed all description. During
        the night it could only be compared to a Niagara of molten fluid, with its incandescent
        vapors above and its boiling masses below.</p><p>The colonists were driven to their last entrenchment, and although the upper seams of the
        vessel were not yet calked, they decided to launch her at once.</p><p>Pencroft and Ayrton therefore set about the necessary preparations for the launching, which
        was to take place the morning of the next day, the 9th of March.</p><p>But during the night of the 8th an enormous column of vapor escaping from the crater rose
        with frightful explosions to a height of more than three thousand feet. The wall of Dakkar
        Grotto had evidently given way under the pressure of gases, and the sea, rushing through the
        central shalt into the igneous gulf, was at once converted into vapor. But the crater could
        not afford a sufficient outlet for this vapor. An explosion, which might have been heard at
        a distance of a hundred miles, shook the air. Fragments of mountains fell into the Pacific,
        and, in a few minutes, the ocean rolled over the spot where Lincoln island once stood.</p><p/></body></topic>