<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p3-chapter-1" ><title>Chapter 1</title><body><p>It was now two years and a half since the castaways from the balloon had been thrown on
        Lincoln Island, and during that period there had been no communication between them and
        their fellow-creatures. Once the reporter had attempted to communicate with the inhabited
        world by confiding to a bird a letter which contained the secret of their situation, but
        that was a chance on which it was impossible to reckon seriously. Ayrton, alone, under the
        circumstances which have been related, had come to join the little colony. Now, suddenly, on
        this day, the 17th of October, other men had unexpectedly appeared in sight of the island,
        on that deserted sea!</p><p>There could be no doubt about it! A vessel was there! But would she pass on, or would she
        put into port? In a few hours the colonists would definitely know what to expect.</p><p>Cyrus Harding and Herbert having immediately called Gideon Spilett, Pencroft, and Neb into
        the dining-room of Granite House, told them what had happened. Pencroft, seizing the
        telescope, rapidly swept the horizon, and stopping on the indicated point, that is to say,
        on that which had made the almost imperceptible spot on the photographic negative,--</p><p>"I'm blessed but it is really a vessel!" he exclaimed, in a voice which did not express any
        great amount of satisfaction.</p><p>"Is she coming here?" asked Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"Impossible to say anything yet," answered Pencroft, "for her rigging alone is above the
        horizon, and not a bit of her hull can be seen."</p><p>"What is to be done?" asked the lad.</p><p>"Wait," replied Harding.</p><p>And for a considerable time the settlers remained silent, given up to all the thoughts, and
        the emotions, all the fears, all the hopes, which were aroused by this incident--the most
        important which had occurred since their arrival in Lincoln Island. Certainly, the colonists
        were not in the situation of castaways abandoned on a sterile islet, constantly contending
        against a cruel nature for their miserable existence, and incessantly tormented by the
        longing to return to inhabited countries. Pencroft and Neb, especially, who felt themselves
        at once so happy and so rich, would not have left their island without regret. They were
        accustomed, besides, to this new life in the midst of the domain which their intelligence
        had as it were civilized. But at any rate this ship brought news from the world, perhaps
        even from their native land. It was bringing fellow-creatures to them, and it may be
        conceived how deeply their hearts were moved at the sight!</p><p>From time to time Pencroft took the glass and rested himself at the window. From thence he
        very attentively examined the vessel, which was at a distance of twenty miles to the east.
        The colonists had as yet, therefore, no means of signalizing their presence. A flag would
        not have been perceived; a gun would not have been heard; a fire would not have been
        visible. However, it was certain that the island, overtopped by Mount Franklin, could not
        escape the notice of the vessel's lookout. But why was the ship coming there? Was it simple
        chance which brought it to that part of the Pacific, where the maps mentioned no land except
        Tabor Island, which itself was out of the route usually followed by vessels from the
        Polynesian Archipelagoes, from New Zealand, and from the American coast? To this question,
        which each one asked himself, a reply was suddenly made by Herbert.</p><p>"Can it be the 'Duncan'?" he cried.</p><p>The "Duncan," as has been said, was Lord Glenarvan's yacht, which had left Ayrton on the
        islet, and which was to return there someday to fetch him. Now, the islet was not so far
        distant from Lincoln Island, but that a vessel, standing for the one, could pass in sight of
        the other. A hundred and fifty miles only separated them in longitude, and seventy in
        latitude.</p><p>"We must tell Ayrton," said Gideon Spilett, "and send for him immediately. He alone can say
        if it is the 'Duncan.'"</p><p>This was the opinion of all, and the reporter, going to the telegraphic apparatus which
        placed the corral in communication with Granite House, sent this telegram:--"Come with all
        possible speed."</p><p>In a few minutes the bell sounded.</p><p>"I am coming," replied Ayrton.</p><p>Then the settlers continued to watch the vessel.</p><p>"If it is the 'Duncan,'" said Herbert, "Ayrton will recognize her without difficulty, since
        he sailed on board her for some time."</p><p>"And if he recognizes her," added Pencroft, "it will agitate him exceedingly!"</p><p>"Yes," answered Cyrus Harding; "but now Ayrton is worthy to return on board the 'Duncan,'
        and pray Heaven that it is indeed Lord Glenarvan's yacht, for I should be suspicious of any
        other vessel. These are ill-famed seas, and I have always feared a visit from Malay pirates
        to our island."</p><p>"We could defend it,', cried Herbert.</p><p>"No doubt, my boy," answered the engineer smiling, "but it would be better not to have to
        defend it."</p><p>"A useless observation," said Spilett. "Lincoln Island is unknown to navigators, since it
        is not marked even on the most recent maps. Do you think, Cyrus, that that is a sufficient
        motive for a ship, finding herself unexpectedly in sight of new land, to try and visit
        rather than avoid it?"</p><p>"Certainly," replied Pencroft.</p><p>"I think so too," added the engineer. "It may even be said that it is the duty of a captain
        to come and survey any land or island not yet known, and Lincoln Island is in this
        position."</p><p>"Well," said Pencroft, "suppose this vessel comes and anchors there a few cables-lengths
        from our island, what shall we do?"</p><p>This sudden question remained at first without any reply. But Cyrus Harding, after some
        moments' thought, replied in the calm tone which was usual to him,--</p><p>"What we shall do, my friends? What we ought to do is this:--we will communicate with the
        ship, we will take our passage on board her, and we will leave our island, after having
        taken possession of it in the name of the United States. Then we will return with any who
        may wish to follow us to colonize it definitely, and endow the American Republic with a
        useful station in this part of the Pacific Ocean!"</p><p>"Hurrah!" exclaimed Pencroft, "and that will be no small present which we shall make to our
        country! The colonization is already almost finished; names are given to every part of the
        island; there is a natural port, fresh water, roads, a telegraph, a dockyard, and
        manufactories; and there will be nothing to be done but to inscribe Lincoln Island on the
        maps!"</p><p>"But if anyone seizes it in our absence?" observed Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"Hang it!" cried the sailor. "I would rather remain all alone to guard it: and trust to
        Pencroft, they shouldn't steal it from him, like a watch from the pocket of a swell!"</p><p>For an hour it was impossible to say with any certainty whether the vessel was or was not
        standing towards Lincoln Island. She was nearer, but in what direction was she sailing? This
        Pencroft could not determine. However, as the wind was blowing from the northeast, in all
        probability the vessel was sailing on the starboard tack. Besides, the wind was favorable
        for bringing her towards the island, and, the sea being calm, she would not be afraid to
        approach although the shallows were not marked on the chart.</p><p>Towards four o'clock--an hour after he had been sent for--Ayrton arrived at Granite House.
        He entered the dining-room saying,--</p><p>"At your service, gentlemen."</p><p>Cyrus Harding gave him his hand, as was his custom to do, and, leading him to the
        window,--</p><p>"Ayrton," said he, "we have begged you to come here for an important reason. A ship is in
        sight of the island."</p><p>Ayrton at first paled slightly, and for a moment his eyes became dim; then, leaning out the
        window, he surveyed the horizon, but could see nothing.</p><p>"Take this telescope," said Spilett, "and look carefully, Ayrton, for it is possible that
        this ship may be the 'Duncan' come to these seas for the purpose of taking you home
        again."</p><p>"The 'Duncan!'" murmured Ayrton. "Already?" This last word escaped Ayrton's lips as if
        involuntarily, and his head drooped upon his hands.</p><p>Did not twelve years' solitude on a desert island appear to him a sufficient expiation? Did
        not the penitent yet feel himself pardoned, either in his own eyes or in the eyes of
        others?</p><p>"No," said he, "no! it cannot be the 'Duncan'!"</p><p>"Look, Ayrton," then said the engineer, "for it is necessary that we should know beforehand
        what to expect."</p><p>Ayrton took the glass and pointed it in the direction indicated. During some minutes he
        examined the horizon without moving, without uttering a word. Then,--</p><p>"It is indeed a vessel," said he, "but I do not think she is the 'Duncan.'"</p><p>"Why do you not think so?" asked Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"Because the 'Duncan' is a steam-yacht, and I cannot perceive any trace of smoke either
        above or near that vessel."</p><p>"Perhaps she is simply sailing," observed Pencroft. "The wind is favorable for the
        direction which she appears to be taking, and she may be anxious to economize her coal,
        being so far from land."</p><p>"It is possible that you may be right, Mr. Pencroft," answered Ayrton, "and that the vessel
        has extinguished her fires. We must wait until she is nearer, and then we shall soon know
        what to expect."</p><p>So saying, Ayrton sat down in a corner of the room and remained silent. The colonists again
        discussed the strange ship, but Ayrton took no part in the conversation. All were in such a
        mood that they found it impossible to continue their work. Gideon Spilett and Pencroft were
        particularly nervous, going, coming, not able to remain still in one place. Herbert felt
        more curiosity. Neb alone maintained his usual calm manner. Was not his country that where
        his master was? As to the engineer, he remained plunged in deep thought, and in his heart
        feared rather than desired the arrival of the ship. In the meanwhile, the vessel was a
        little nearer the island. With the aid of the glass, it was ascertained that she was a brig,
        and not one of those Malay proas, which are generally used by the pirates of the Pacific. It
        was, therefore, reasonable to believe that the engineer's apprehensions would not be
        justified, and that the presence of this vessel in the vicinity of the island was fraught
        with no danger.</p><p>Pencroft, after a minute examination, was able positively to affirm that the vessel was
        rigged as a brig, and that she was standing obliquely towards the coast, on the starboard
        tack, under her topsails and top- gallant-sails. This was confirmed by Ayrton. But by
        continuing in this direction she must soon disappear behind Claw Cape, as the wind was from
        the southwest, and to watch her it would be then necessary to ascend the height of
        Washington Bay, near Port Balloon--a provoking circumstance, for it was already five o'clock
        in the evening, and the twilight would soon make any observation extremely difficult.</p><p>"What shall we do when night comes on?" asked Gideon Spilett. "Shall we light a fire, so as
        to signal our presence on the coast?"</p><p>This was a serious question, and yet, although the engineer still retained some of his
        presentiments, it was answered in the affirmative. During the night the ship might disappear
        and leave for ever, and, this ship gone, would another ever return to the waters of Lincoln
        Island? Who could foresee what the future would then have in store for the colonists?</p><p>"Yes," said the reporter, "we ought to make known to that vessel, whoever she may be, that
        the island is inhabited. To neglect the opportunity which is offered to us might be to
        create everlasting regrets."</p><p>It was therefore decided that Neb and Pencroft should go to Port Balloon, and that there,
        at nightfall, they should light an immense fire, the blaze of which would necessarily
        attract the attention of the brig.</p><p>But at the moment when Neb and the sailor were preparing to leave Granite House, the vessel
        suddenly altered her course, and stood directly for Union Bay. The brig was a good sailer,
        for she approached rapidly. Neb and Pencroft put off their departure, therefore, and the
        glass was put into Ayrton's hands, that he might ascertain for certain whether the ship was
        or was not the "Duncan." The Scotch yacht was also rigged as a brig. The question was,
        whether a chimney could be discerned between the two masts of the vessel, which was now at a
        distance of only five miles.</p><p>The horizon was still very clear. The examination was easy, and Ayrton soon let the glass
        fall again, saying--</p><p>"It is not the 'Duncan'! It could not be!"</p><p>Pencroft again brought the brig within the range of the telescope, and could see that she
        was of between three and four hundred tons burden, wonderfully narrow, well-masted,
        admirably built, and must be a very rapid sailer. But to what nation did she belong? That
        was difficult to say.</p><p>"And yet," added the sailor, "a flag is floating from her peak, but I cannot distinguish
        the colors of it."</p><p>"In half an hour we shall be certain about that," answered the reporter. "Besides, it is
        very evident that the intention of the captain of this ship is to land, and, consequently,
        if not today, to-morrow at the latest, we shall make his acquaintance."</p><p>"Never mind!" said Pencroft. "It is best to know whom we have to deal with, and I shall not
        be sorry to recognize that fellow's colors!"</p><p>And, while thus speaking, the sailor never left the glass. The day began to fade, and with
        the day the breeze fell also. The brig's ensign hung in folds, and it became more and more
        difficult to observe it.</p><p>"It is not the American flag," said Pencroft from time to time, "nor the English, the red
        of which could be easily seen, nor the French or German colors, nor the white flag of
        Russia, nor the yellow of Spain. One would say it was all one color. Let's see: in these
        seas, what do we generally meet with? The Chilean flag?--but that is tri-color.
        Brazilian?--it is green. Japanese?--it is yellow and black, while this--"</p><p>At that moment the breeze blew out the unknown flag. Ayrton seizing the telescope which the
        sailor had put down, put it to his eye, and in a hoarse voice,--</p><p>"The black flag!" he exclaimed.</p><p>And indeed the somber bunting was floating from the mast of the brig, and they had now good
        reason for considering her to be a suspicious vessel!</p><p>Had the engineer, then, been right in his presentiments? Was this a pirate vessel? Did she
        scour the Pacific, competing with the Malay proas which still infest it? For what had she
        come to look at the shores of Lincoln Island? Was it to them an unknown island, ready to
        become a magazine for stolen cargoes? Had she come to find on the coast a sheltered port for
        the winter months? Was the settlers' honest domain destined to be transformed into an
        infamous refuge--the headquarters of the piracy of the Pacific?</p><p>All these ideas instinctively presented themselves to the colonists' imaginations. There
        was no doubt, besides, of the signification which must be attached to the color of the
        hoisted flag. It was that of pirates! It was that which the "Duncan" would have carried, had
        the convicts succeeded in their criminal design! No time was lost before discussing it.</p><p>"My friends," said Cyrus Harding, "perhaps this vessel only wishes to survey the coast of
        the island. Perhaps her crew will not land. There is a chance of it. However that may be, we
        ought to do everything we can to hide our presence here. The windmill on Prospect Heights is
        too easily seen. Let Ayrton and Neb go and take down the sails. We must also conceal the
        windows of Granite House with thick branches. All the fires must be extinguished, so that
        nothing may betray the presence of men on the island."</p><p>"And our vessel?" said Herbert.</p><p>"Oh," answered Pencroft, "she is sheltered in Port Balloon, and I defy any of those rascals
        there to find her!"</p><p>The engineer's orders were immediately executed. Neb and Ayrton ascended the plateau, and
        took the necessary precautions to conceal any indication of a settlement. While they were
        thus occupied, their companions went to the border of Jacamar Wood, and brought back a large
        quantity of branches and creepers, which would at some distance appear as natural foliage,
        and thus disguise the windows in the granite cliff. At the same time, the ammunition and
        guns were placed ready so as to be at hand in case of an unexpected attack.</p><p>When all these precautions had been taken,--</p><p>"My friends," said Harding, and his voice betrayed some emotion, "if the wretches endeavor
        to seize Lincoln Island, we shall defend it--shall we not?"</p><p>"Yes, Cyrus," replied the reporter, "and if necessary we will die to defend it!"</p><p>The engineer extended his hand to his companions, who pressed it warmly. Ayrton remained in
        his corner, not joining the colonists. Perhaps he, the former convict, still felt himself
        unworthy to do so!</p><p>Cyrus Harding understood what was passing in Ayrton's mind, and going to him--</p><p>"And you, Ayrton," he asked, "what will you do?"</p><p>"My duty," answered Ayrton.</p><p>He then took up his station near the window and gazed through the foliage.</p><p>It was now half-past seven. The sun had disappeared twenty minutes ago behind Granite
        House. Consequently the Eastern horizon was becoming obscured. In the meanwhile the brig
        continued to advance towards Union Bay. She was now not more than two miles off, and exactly
        opposite the plateau of Prospect Heights, for after having tacked off Claw Cape, she had
        drifted towards the north in the current of the rising tide. One might have said that at
        this distance she had already entered the vast bay, for a straight line drawn from Claw Cape
        to Cape Mandible would have rested on her starboard quarter.</p><p>Was the brig about to penetrate far into the bay? That was the first question. When once in
        the bay, would she anchor there? That was the second. Would she not content herself with
        only surveying the coast, and stand out to sea again without landing her crew? They would
        know this in an hour. The colonists could do nothing but wait.</p><p>Cyrus Harding had not seen the suspected vessel hoist the black flag without deep anxiety.
        Was it not a direct menace against the work which he and his companions had till now
        conducted so successfully? Had these pirates--for the sailors of the brig could be nothing
        else--already visited the island, since on approaching it they had hoisted their colors. Had
        they formerly invaded it, so that certain unaccountable peculiarities might be explained in
        this way? Did there exist in the as yet unexplored parts some accomplice ready to enter into
        communication with them?</p><p>To all these questions which he mentally asked himself, Harding knew not what to reply; but
        he felt that the safety of the colony could not but be seriously threatened by the arrival
        of the brig.</p><p>However, he and his companions were determined to fight to the last gasp. It would have
        been very important to know if the pirates were numerous and better armed than the
        colonists. But how was this information to he obtained?</p><p>Night fell. The new moon had disappeared. Profound darkness enveloped the island and the
        sea. No light could pierce through the heavy piles of clouds on the horizon. The wind had
        died away completely with the twilight. Not a leaf rustled on the trees, not a ripple
        murmured on the shore. Nothing could be seen of the ship, all her lights being extinguished,
        and if she was still in sight of the island, her whereabouts could not be discovered.</p><p>"Well! who knows?" said Pencroft. "Perhaps that cursed craft will stand off during the
        night, and we shall see nothing of her at daybreak."</p><p>As if in reply to the sailor's observation, a bright light flashed in the darkness, and a
        cannon-shot was heard.</p><p>The vessel was still there and had guns on board.</p><p>Six seconds elapsed between the flash and the report.</p><p>Therefore the brig was about a mile and a quarter from the coast.</p><p>At the same time, the chains were heard rattling through the hawse-holes.</p><p>The vessel had just anchored in sight of Granite House!</p><p/></body></topic>