<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p3-chapter-17" ><title>Chapter 17</title><body><p>Day had returned. No ray of light penetrated into the profundity of the cavern. It being
        high-water, the entrance was closed by the sea. But the artificial light, which escaped in
        long streams from the skylights of the "Nautilus" was as vivid as before, and the sheet of
        water shone around the floating vessel.</p><p>An extreme exhaustion now overcame Captain Nemo, who had fallen back upon the divan. It was
        useless to contemplate removing him to Granite House, for he had expressed his wish to
        remain in the midst of those marvels of the "Nautilus" which millions could not have
        purchased, and to wait there for that death which was swiftly approaching.</p><p>During a long interval of prostration, which rendered him almost unconscious, Cyrus Harding
        and Gideon Spilett attentively observed the condition of the dying man. It was apparent that
        his strength was gradually diminishing. That frame, once so robust, was now but the fragile
        tenement of a departing soul. All of life was concentrated in the heart and head.</p><p>The engineer and reporter consulted in whispers. Was it possible to render any aid to the
        dying man? Might his life, if not saved, be prolonged for some days? He himself had said
        that no remedy could avail, and he awaited with tranquillity that death which had for him no
        terrors.</p><p>"We can do nothing," said Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"But of what is he dying?" asked Pencroft.</p><p>"Life is simply fading out," replied the reporter.</p><p>"Nevertheless," said the sailor, "if we move him into the open air, and the light of the
        sun, he might perhaps recover."</p><p>"No, Pencroft," answered the engineer, "it is useless to attempt it. Besides, Captain Nemo
        would never consent to leave his vessel. He has lived for a dozen years on board the
        'Nautilus,' and on board the 'Nautilus' he desires to die."</p><p>Without doubt Captain Nemo heard Cyrus Harding's reply, for he raised himself slightly, and
        in a voice more feeble, but always intelligible,--</p><p>"You are right, sir," he said. "I shall die here--it is my wish; and therefore I have a
        request to make of you."</p><p>Cyrus Harding and his companions had drawn near the divan, and now arranged the cushions in
        such a manner as to better support the dying man.</p><p>They saw his eyes wander over all the marvels of this saloon, lighted by the electric rays
        which fell from the arabesques of the luminous ceiling. He surveyed, one after the other,
        the pictures hanging from the splendid tapestries of the partitions, the chef-d'oeuvres of
        the Italian, Flemish, French, and Spanish masters; the statues of marble and bronze on their
        pedestals; the magnificent organ, leaning against the after-partition; the aquarium, in
        which bloomed the most wonderful productions of the sea-- marine plants, zoophytes, chaplets
        of pearls of inestimable value; and, finally, his eyes rested on this device, inscribed over
        the pediment of the museum--the motto of the "Nautilus"--</p><p> "Mobilis in mobile."</p><p> His glance seemed to rest fondly for the last time on these masterpieces of art and of
        nature, to which he had limited his horizon during a sojourn of so many years in the abysses
        of the seas.</p><p>Cyrus Harding respected the captain's silence, and waited till he should speak.</p><p>After some minutes, during which, doubtless, he passed in review his whole life, Captain
        Nemo turned to the colonists and said,</p><p>"You consider yourselves, gentlemen, under some obligations to me?"</p><p>"Captain, believe us that we would give our lives to prolong yours."</p><p>"Promise, then," continued Captain Nemo, "to carry out my last wishes, and I shall be
        repaid for all I have done for you."</p><p>"We promise," said Cyrus Harding.</p><p>And by this promise he bound both himself and his companions.</p><p>"Gentlemen," resumed the captain, "to-morrow I shall be dead."</p><p>Herbert was about to utter an exclamation, but a sign from the captain arrested him.</p><p>"To-morrow I shall die, and I desire no other tomb than the 'Nautilus.' It is my grave! All
        my friends repose in the depths of the ocean; their resting-place shall be mine."</p><p>These words were received with profound silence.</p><p>"Pay attention to my wishes," he continued. "The 'Nautilus' is imprisoned in this grotto,
        the entrance of which is blocked up; but, although egress is impossible, the vessel may at
        least sink in the abyss, and there bury my remains."</p><p>The colonists listened reverently to the words of the dying man.</p><p>"To-morrow, after my death, Mr. Harding," continued the captain, "yourself and companions
        will leave the 'Nautilus,' for all the treasures it contains must perish with me. One token
        alone will remain with you of Prince Dakkar, with whose history you are now acquainted. That
        coffer yonder contains diamonds of the value of many millions, most of them mementoes of the
        time when, husband and father, I thought happiness possible for me, and a collection of
        pearls gathered by my friends and myself in the depths of the ocean. Of this treasure at a
        future day, you may make good use. In the hands of such men as yourself and your comrades,
        Captain Harding, money will never be a source of danger. From on high I shall still
        participate in your enterprises, and I fear not but that they will prosper."</p><p>After a few moments' repose, necessitated by his extreme weakness, Captain Nemo
        continued,--</p><p>"To-morrow you will take the coffer, you will leave the saloon, of which you will close the
        door; then you will ascend on to the deck of the 'Nautilus,' and you will lower the
        mainhatch so as entirely to close the vessel."</p><p>"It shall be done, captain," answered Cyrus Harding.</p><p>"Good. You will then embark in the canoe which brought you hither; but, before leaving the
        'Nautilus,' go to the stern and there open two large stop-cocks which you will find upon the
        water-line. The water will penetrate into the reservoirs, and the 'Nautilus' will gradually
        sink beneath the water to repose at the bottom of the abyss."</p><p>And comprehending a gesture of Cyrus Harding, the captain added,--</p><p>"Fear nothing! You will but bury a corpse!"</p><p>Neither Cyrus Harding nor his companions ventured to offer any observation to Captain Nemo.
        He had expressed his last wishes, and they had nothing to do but to conform to them.</p><p>"I have your promise, gentlemen?" added Captain Nemo.</p><p>"You have, captain," replied the engineer.</p><p>The captain thanked the colonists by a sign, and requested them to leave him for some
        hours. Gideon Spilett wished to remain near him, in the event of a crisis coming on, but the
        dying man refused, saying, "I shall live until to-morrow, sir."</p><p>All left the saloon, passed through the library and the dining-room, and arrived forward,
        in the machine-room where the electrical apparatus was established, which supplied not only
        heat and light, but the mechanical power of the "Nautilus."</p><p>The "Nautilus" was a masterpiece containing masterpieces with itself, and the engineer was
        struck with astonishment.</p><p>The colonists mounted the platform, which rose seven or eight feet above the water. There
        they beheld a thick glass lenticular covering, which protected a kind of large eye, from
        which flashed forth light. Behind this eye was apparently a cabin containing the wheels of
        the rudder, and in which was stationed the helmsman, when he navigated the "Nautilus" over
        the bed of the ocean, which the electric rays would evidently light up to a considerable
        distance.</p><p>Cyrus Harding and his companions remained for a time silent, for they were vividly
        impressed by what they had just seen and heard, and their hearts were deeply touched by the
        thought that he whose arm had so often aided them, the protector whom they had known but a
        few hours, was at the point of death.</p><p>Whatever might be the judgment pronounced by posterity upon the events of this, so to
        speak, extra-human existence, the character of Prince Dakkar would ever remain as one of
        those whose memory time can never efface.</p><p>"What a man!" said Pencroft. "Is it possible that he can have lived at the bottom of the
        sea? And it seems to me that perhaps he has not found peace there any more than
        elsewhere!"</p><p>"The 'Nautilus,'" observed Ayrton, "might have enabled us to leave Lincoln Island and reach
        some inhabited country."</p><p>"Good Heavens!" exclaimed Pencroft, "I for one would never risk myself in such a craft. To
        sail on the seas, good, but under the seas, never!"</p><p>"I believe, Pencroft," answered the reporter, "that the navigation of a submarine vessel
        such as the 'Nautilus' ought to be very easy, and that we should soon become accustomed to
        it. There would be no storms, no lee-shore to fear. At some feet beneath the surface the
        waters of the ocean are as calm as those of a lake."</p><p>"That may be," replied the sailor, "but I prefer a gale of wind on board a well-found
        craft. A vessel is built to sail on the sea, and not beneath it."</p><p>"My friends," said the engineer, "it is useless, at any rate as regards the 'Nautilus,' to
        discuss the question of submarine vessels. The 'Nautilus' is not ours, and we have not the
        right to dispose of it. Moreover, we could in no case avail ourselves of it. Independently
        of the fact that it would be impossible to get it out of this cavern, whose entrance is now
        closed by the uprising of the basaltic rocks, Captain Nemo's wish is that it shall be buried
        with him. His wish is our law, and we will fulfil it."</p><p>After a somewhat prolonged conversation, Cyrus Harding and his companions again descended
        to the interior of the "Nautilus." There they took some refreshment and returned to the
        saloon.</p><p>Captain Nemo had somewhat rallied from the prostration which had overcome him, and his eyes
        shone with their wonted fire. A faint smile even curled his lips.</p><p>The colonists drew around him.</p><p>"Gentlemen," said the captain, "you are brave and honest men. You have devoted yourselves
        to the common weal. Often have I observed your conduct. I have esteemed you--I esteem you
        still! Your hand, Mr. Harding."</p><p>Cyrus Harding gave his hand to the captain, who clasped it affectionately.</p><p>"It is well!" he murmured.</p><p>He resumed,--</p><p>"But enough of myself. I have to speak concerning yourselves, and this Lincoln Island, upon
        which you have taken refuge. You now desire to leave it?"</p><p>"To return, captain!" answered Pencroft quickly.</p><p>"To return, Pencroft?" said the captain, with a smile. "I know, it is true, your love for
        this island. You have helped to make it what it now is, and it seems to you a paradise!"</p><p>"Our project, captain," interposed Cyrus Harding, "is to annex it to the United States, and
        to establish for our shipping a port so fortunately situated in this part of the
        Pacific."</p><p>"Your thoughts are with your country, gentlemen," continued the captain; "your toils are
        for her prosperity and glory. You are right. One's native land!--there should one live!
        there die! And I die far from all I loved!"</p><p>"You have some last wish to transmit," said the engineer with emotion, "some souvenir to
        send to those friends you have left in the mountains of India?"</p><p>"No, Captain Harding; no friends remain to me! I am the last of my race, and to all whom I
        have known I have long been as are the dead.--But to return to yourselves. Solitude,
        isolation, are painful things, and beyond human endurance. I die of having thought it
        possible to live alone! You should, therefore, dare all in the attempt to leave Lincoln
        Island, and see once more the land of your birth. I am aware that those wretches have
        destroyed the vessel you have built."</p><p>"We propose to construct a vessel," said Gideon Spilett, "sufficiently large to convey us
        to the nearest land; but if we should succeed, sooner or later we shall return to Lincoln
        Island. We are attached to it by too many recollections ever to forget it."</p><p>"It is here that we have known Captain Nemo," said Cyrus Harding.</p><p>"It is here only that we can make our home!" added Herbert.</p><p>"And here shall I sleep the sleep of eternity, if--" replied the captain.</p><p>He paused for a moment, and, instead of completing the sentence, said simply,--</p><p>"Mr. Harding, I wish to speak with you--alone!"</p><p>The engineer's companions, respecting the wish, retired.</p><p>Cyrus Harding remained but a few minutes alone with Captain Nemo, and soon recalled his
        companions; but he said nothing to them of the private matters which the dying man had
        confided to him.</p><p>Gideon Spilett now watched the captain with extreme care. It was evident that he was no
        longer sustained by his moral energy, which had lost the power of reaction against his
        physical weakness.</p><p>The day closed without change. The colonists did not quit the "Nautilus" for a moment.
        Night arrived, although it was impossible to distinguish it from day in the cavern.</p><p>Captain Nemo suffered no pain, but he was visibly sinking. His noble features, paled by the
        approach of death, were perfectly calm. Inaudible words escaped at intervals from his lips,
        bearing upon various incidents of his checkered career. Life was evidently ebbing slowly and
        his extremities were already cold.</p><p>Once or twice more he spoke to the colonists who stood around him, and smiled on them with
        that last smile which continues after death.</p><p>At length, shortly after midnight, Captain Nemo by a supreme effort succeeded in folding
        his arms across his breast, as if wishing in that attitude to compose himself for death.</p><p>By one o'clock his glance alone showed signs of life. A dying light gleamed in those eyes
        once so brilliant. Then, murmuring the words, "God and my country!" he quietly expired.</p><p>Cyrus Harding, bending low closed the eyes of him who had once been the Prince Dakkar, and
        was now not even Captain Nemo.</p><p>Herbert and Pencroft sobbed aloud. Tears fell from Ayrton's eyes. Neb was on his knees by
        the reporter's side, motionless as a statue.</p><p>Then Cyrus Harding, extending his hand over the forehead of the dead, said solemnly, "May
        his soul be with God!" Turning to his friends, he added, "Let us pray for him whom we have
        lost!"</p><p> Some hours later the colonists fulfilled the promise made to the captain by carrying out
        his dying wishes.</p><p>Cyrus Harding and his companions quitted the "Nautilus," taking with them the only memento
        left them by their benefactor, the coffer which contained wealth amounting to millions.</p><p>The marvelous saloon, still flooded with light, had been carefully closed. The iron door
        leading on deck was then securely fastened in such a manner as to prevent even a drop of
        water from penetrating to the interior of the "Nautilus."</p><p>The colonists then descended into the canoe, which was moored to the side of the submarine
        vessel.</p><p>The canoe was now brought around to the stern. There, at the water-line, were two large
        stop-cocks communicating with the reservoirs employed in the submersion of the vessel.</p><p>The stop-cocks were opened, the reservoirs filled, and the "Nautilus," slowly sinking,
        disappeared beneath the surface of the lake.</p><p>But the colonists were yet able to follow its descent through the waves. The powerful light
        it gave forth lighted up the translucent water, while the cavern became gradually obscure.
        At length this vast effusion of electric light faded away, and soon after the "Nautilus,"
        now the tomb of Captain Nemo, reposed in its ocean bed.</p><p/></body></topic>