<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p3-chapter-6" ><title>Chapter 6</title><body><p>However, the chief business of the colonists was to make that complete exploration of the
        island which had been decided upon, and which would have two objects: to discover the
        mysterious being whose existence was now indisputable, and at the same time to find out what
        had become of the pirates, what retreat they had chosen, what sort of life they were
        leading, and what was to be feared from them. Cyrus Harding wished to set out without delay;
        but as the expedition would be of some days duration, it appeared best to load the cart with
        different materials and tools in order to facilitate the organization of the encampments.
        One of the onagers, however, having hurt its leg, could not be harnessed at present, and a
        few days' rest was necessary. The departure was, therefore, put off for a week, until the
        20th of November. The month of November in this latitude corresponds to the month of May in
        the northern zones. It was, therefore, the fine season. The sun was entering the tropic of
        Capricorn, and gave the longest days in the year. The time was, therefore, very favorable
        for the projected expedition, which, if it did not accomplish its principal object, would at
        any rate be fruitful in discoveries, especially of natural productions, since Harding
        proposed to explore those dense forests of the Far West, which stretched to the extremity of
        the Serpentine Peninsula.</p><p>During the nine days which preceded their departure, it was agreed that the work on
        Prospect Heights should be finished off.</p><p>Moreover, it was necessary for Ayrton to return to the corral, where the domesticated
        animals required his care. It was decided that he should spend two days there, and return to
        Granite House after having liberally supplied the stables.</p><p>As he was about to start, Harding asked him if he would not like one of them to accompany
        him, observing that the island was less safe than formerly. Ayrton replied that this was
        unnecessary, as he was enough for the work, and that besides he apprehended no danger. If
        anything occurred at the corral, or in the neighborhood, he could instantly warn the
        colonists by sending a telegram to Granite House.</p><p>Ayrton departed at dawn on the 9th, taking the cart drawn by one onager, and two hours
        after, the electric wire announced that he had found all in order at the corral.</p><p>During these two days Harding busied himself in executing a project which would completely
        guard Granite House against any surprise. It was necessary to completely conceal the opening
        of the old outlet, which was already walled up and partly hidden under grass and plants, at
        the southern angle of Lake Grant. Nothing was easier, since if the level of the lake was
        raised two or three feet, the opening would be quite beneath it. Now, to raise this level
        they had only to establish a dam at the two openings made by the lake, and by which were fed
        Creek Glycerine and Falls River.</p><p>The colonists worked with a will, and the two dams which besides did not exceed eight feet
        in width by three in height, were rapidly erected by means of well-cemented blocks of
        stone.</p><p>This work finished, it would have been impossible to guess that at that part of the lake,
        there existed a subterranean passage through which the overflow of the lake formerly
        escaped.</p><p>Of course the little stream which fed the reservoir of Granite House and worked the lift,
        had been carefully preserved, and the water could not fail. The lift once raised, this sure
        and comfortable retreat would be safe from any surprise.</p><p>This work had been so quickly done, that Pencroft, Gideon Spilett, and Herbert found time
        to make an expedition to Port Balloon, The sailor was very anxious to know if the little
        creek in which the "Bonadventure" was moored, had been visited by the convicts.</p><p>"These gentlemen," he observed, "landed on the south coast, and if they followed the shore,
        it is to be feared that they may have discovered the little harbor, and in that case, I
        wouldn't give half-a-dollar for our 'Bonadventure.'"</p><p>Pencroft's apprehensions were not without foundation, and a visit to Port Balloon appeared
        to be very desirable. The sailor and his companions set off on the 10th of November, after
        dinner, well armed. Pencroft, ostentatiously slipping two bullets into each barrel of his
        rifle, shook his head in a way which betokened nothing good to any one who approached too
        near him, whether "man or beast," as he said. Gideon Spilett and Herbert also took their
        guns, and about three o'clock all three left Granite House.</p><p>Neb accompanied them to the turn of the Mercy, and after they had crossed, he raised the
        bridge. It was agreed that a gunshot should announce the colonists' return, and that at the
        signal Neb should return and reestablish the communication between the two banks of the
        river.</p><p>The little band advanced directly along the road which led to the southern coast of the
        island. This was only a distance of three miles and a half, but Gideon Spilett and his
        companions took two hours to traverse it. They examined all the border of the road, the
        thick forest, as well as Tabor Marsh. They found no trace of the fugitives who, no doubt,
        not having yet discovered the number of the colonists, or the means of defense which they
        had at their disposal, had gained the less accessible parts of the island.</p><p>Arrived at Port Balloon, Pencroft saw with extreme satisfaction that the "Bonadventure" was
        tranquilly floating in the narrow creek. However, Port Balloon was so well hidden among high
        rocks, that it could scarcely be discovered either from the land or the sea.</p><p>"Come," said Pencroft, "the blackguards have not been there yet. Long grass suits reptiles
        best, and evidently we shall find them in the Far West."</p><p>"And it's very lucky, for if they had found the 'Bonadventure'," added Herbert, "they would
        have gone off in her, and we should have been prevented from returning to Tabor Island."</p><p>"Indeed," remarked the reporter, "it will be important to take a document there which will
        make known the situation of Lincoln Island, and Ayrton's new residence, in case the Scotch
        yacht returns to fetch him."</p><p>"Well, the 'Bonadventure' is always there, Mr. Spilett," answered the sailor. "She and her
        crew are ready to start at a moment's notice!"</p><p>"I think, Pencroft, that that is a thing to be done after our exploration of the island is
        finished. It is possible after all that the stranger, if we manage to find him, may know as
        much about Tabor Island as about Lincoln Island. Do not forget that he is certainly the
        author of the document, and he may, perhaps, know how far we may count on the return of the
        yacht!"</p><p>"But!" exclaimed Pencroft, "who in the world can he be? The fellow knows us and we know
        nothing about him! If he is a simple castaway, why should he conceal himself! We are honest
        men, I suppose, and the society of honest men isn't unpleasant to any one. Did he come here
        voluntarily? Can he leave the island if he likes? Is he here still? Will he remain any
        longer?"</p><p>Chatting thus, Pencroft, Gideon Spilett, and Herbert got on board and looked about the deck
        of the "Bonadventure." All at once, the sailor having examined the bitts to which the cable
        of the anchor was secured,--</p><p>"Hallo," he cried, "this is queer!"</p><p>"What is the matter, Pencroft?" asked the reporter.</p><p>"The matter is, that it was not I who made this knot!"</p><p>And Pencroft showed a rope which fastened the cable to the bitt itself.</p><p>"What, it was not you?" asked Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"No! I can swear to it. This is a reef knot, and I always make a running bowline."</p><p>"You must be mistaken, Pencroft."</p><p>"I am not mistaken!" declared the sailor. "My hand does it so naturally, and one's hand is
        never mistaken!"</p><p>"Then can the convicts have been on board?" asked Herbert.</p><p>"I know nothing about that," answered Pencroft, "but what is certain, is that some one has
        weighed the 'Bonadventure's' anchor and dropped it again! And look here, here is another
        proof! The cable of the anchor has been run out, and its service is no longer at the
        hawse-hole. I repeat that some one has been using our vessel!"</p><p>"But if the convicts had used her, they would have pillaged her, or rather gone off with
        her."</p><p>"Gone off! where to--to Tabor Island?" replied Pencroft. "Do you think, they would risk
        themselves in a boat of such small tonnage?"</p><p>"We must, besides, be sure that they know of the islet," rejoined the reporter.</p><p>"However that may be," said the sailor, "as sure as my name is Bonadventure Pencroft, of
        the Vineyard, our 'Bonadventure' has sailed without us!"</p><p>The sailor was positive that neither Gideon Spilett nor Herbert could dispute his
        statement. It was evident that the vessel had been moved, more or less, since Pencroft had
        brought her to Port Balloon. As to the sailor, he had not the slightest doubt that the
        anchor had been raised and then dropped again. Now, what was the use of these two maneuvers,
        unless the vessel had been employed in some expedition?</p><p>"But how was it we did not see the 'Bonadventure' pass in the sight of the island?"
        observed the reporter, who was anxious to bring forward every possible objection.</p><p>"Why, Mr. Spilett," replied the sailor, "they would only have to start in the night with a
        good breeze, and they would be out of sight of the island in two hours."</p><p>"Well," resumed Gideon Spilett, "I ask again, what object could the convicts have had in
        using the 'Bonadventure,' and why, after they had made use of her, should they have brought
        her back to port?"</p><p>"Why, Mr. Spilett," replied the sailor, "we must put that among the unaccountable things,
        and not think anything more about it. The chief thing is that the 'Bonadventure' was there,
        and she is there now. Only, unfortunately, if the convicts take her a second time, we shall
        very likely not find her again in her place!"</p><p>"Then, Pencroft," said Herbert, "would it not be wisest to bring the 'Bonadventure' off to
        Granite House?"</p><p>"Yes and no," answered Pencroft, "or rather no. The mouth of the Mercy is a bad place for a
        vessel, and the sea is heavy there."</p><p>"But by hauling her up on the sand, to the foot of the Chimneys?"</p><p>"Perhaps yes," replied Pencroft. "At any rate, since we must leave Granite House for a long
        expedition, I think the 'Bonadventure' will be safer here during our absence, and we shall
        do best to leave her here until the island is rid of these blackguards."</p><p>"That is exactly my opinion," said the reporter. "At any rate in the event of bad weather,
        she will not be exposed here as she would be at the mouth of the Mercy."</p><p>"But suppose the convicts pay her another visit," said Herbert.</p><p>"Well, my boy," replied Pencroft, "not finding her here, they would not be long in finding
        her on the sands of Granite House, and, during our absence, nothing could hinder them from
        seizing her! I agree, therefore, with Mr. Spilett, that she must be left in Port Balloon.
        But, if on our return we have not rid the island of those rascals, it will be prudent to
        bring our boat to Granite House, until the time when we need not fear any unpleasant
        visits."</p><p>"That's settled. Let us be off," said the reporter.</p><p>Pencroft, Herbert, and Gideon Spilett, on their return to Granite House, told the engineer
        all that had passed, and the latter approved of their arrangements both for the present and
        the future. He also promised the sailor that he would study that part of the channel
        situated between the islet and the coast, so as to ascertain if it would not be possible to
        make an artificial harbor there by means of dams. In this way, the "Bonadventure" would be
        always within reach, under the eyes of the colonists, and if necessary, under lock and
        key.</p><p>That evening a telegram was sent to Ayrton, requesting him to bring from the corral a
        couple of goats, which Neb wished to acclimatize to the plateau. Singularly enough, Ayrton
        did not acknowledge the receipt of the despatch, as he was accustomed to do. This could not
        but astonish the engineer. But it might be that Ayrton was not at that moment in the corral,
        or even that he was on his way back to Granite House. In fact, two days had already passed
        since his departure, and it had been decided that on the evening of the 10th or at the
        latest the morning of the 11th, he should return. The colonists waited, therefore, for
        Ayrton to appear on Prospect Heights. Neb and Herbert even watched at the bridge so as to be
        ready to lower it the moment their companion presented himself.</p><p>But up to ten in the evening, there were no signs of Ayrton. It was, therefore, judged best
        to send a fresh despatch, requiring an immediate reply.</p><p>The bell of the telegraph at Granite House remained mute.</p><p>The colonists' uneasiness was great. What had happened? Was Ayrton no longer at the corral,
        or if he was still there, had he no longer control over his movements? Could they go to the
        corral in this dark night?</p><p>They consulted. Some wished to go, the others to remain.</p><p>"But," said Herbert, "perhaps some accident has happened to the telegraphic apparatus, so
        that it works no longer?"</p><p>"That may be," said the reporter.</p><p>"Wait till to-morrow," replied Cyrus Harding. "It is possible, indeed, that Ayrton has not
        received our despatch, or even that we have not received his."</p><p>They waited, of course not without some anxiety.</p><p>At dawn of day, the 11th of November, Harding again sent the electric current along the
        wire and received no reply.</p><p>He tried again: the same result.</p><p>"Off to the corral," said he.</p><p>"And well armed!" added Pencroft.</p><p>It was immediately decided that Granite House should not be left alone and that Neb should
        remain there. After having accompanied his friends to Creek Glycerine, he raised the bridge;
        and waiting behind a tree he watched for the return of either his companions or Ayrton.</p><p>In the event of the pirates presenting themselves and attempting to force the passage, he
        was to endeavor to stop them by firing on them, and as a last resource he was to take refuge
        in Granite House, where, the lift once raised, he would be in safety.</p><p>Cyrus Harding, Gideon Spilett, Herbert, and Pencroft were to repair to the corral, and if
        they did not find Ayrton, search the neighboring woods.</p><p>At six o'clock in the morning, the engineer and his three companions had passed Creek
        Glycerine, and Neb posted himself behind a small mound crowned by several dragon trees, on
        the left bank of the stream.</p><p>The colonists, after leaving the plateau of Prospect Heights, immediately took the road to
        the corral. They shouldered their guns, ready to fire on the slightest hostile
        demonstration. The two rifles and the two guns had been loaded with ball.</p><p>The wood was thick on each side of the road and might easily have concealed the convicts,
        who owing to their weapons would have been really formidable.</p><p>The colonists walked rapidly and in silence. Top preceded them, sometimes running on the
        road, sometimes taking a ramble into the wood, but always quiet and not appearing to fear
        anything unusual. And they could be sure that the faithful dog would not allow them to be
        surprised, but would bark at the least appearance of danger.</p><p>Cyrus Harding and his companions followed beside the road the wire which connected the
        corral with Granite House. After walking for nearly two miles, they had not as yet
        discovered any explanation of the difficulty. The posts were in good order, the wire
        regularly extended. However, at that moment the engineer observed that the wire appeared to
        be slack, and on arriving at post No. 74, Herbert, who was in advance stopped,
        exclaiming,--</p><p>"The wire is broken!"</p><p>His companions hurried forward and arrived at the spot where the lad was standing. The post
        was rooted up and lying across the path. The unexpected explanation of the difficulty was
        here, and it was evident that the despatches from Granite House had not been received at the
        corral, nor those from the corral at Granite House.</p><p>"It wasn't the wind that blew down this post," observed Pencroft.</p><p>"No," replied Gideon Spilett. "The earth has been dug up round its foot, and it has been
        torn up by the hand of man."</p><p>"Besides, the wire is broken," added Herbert, showing that the wire had been snapped.</p><p>"Is the fracture recent?" asked Harding.</p><p>"Yes," answered Herbert, "it has certainly been done quite lately."</p><p>"To the corral! to the corral!" exclaimed the sailor.</p><p>The colonists were now half way between Granite House and the corral, having still two
        miles and a half to go. They pressed forward with redoubled speed.</p><p>Indeed, it was to be feared that some serious accident had occurred in the corral. No
        doubt, Ayrton might have sent a telegram which had not arrived, but this was not the reason
        why his companions were so uneasy, for, a more unaccountable circumstance, Ayrton, who had
        promised to return the evening before, had not reappeared. In short, it was not without a
        motive that all communication had been stopped between the corral and Granite House, and who
        but the convicts could have any interest in interrupting this communication?</p><p>The settlers hastened on, their hearts oppressed with anxiety. They were sincerely attached
        to their new companion. Were they to find him struck down by the hands of those of whom he
        was formerly the leader?</p><p>Soon they arrived at the place where the road led along the side of the little stream which
        flowed from the Red Creek and watered the meadows of the corral. They then moderated their
        pace so that they should not be out of breath at the moment when a struggle might be
        necessary. Their guns were in their hands ready cocked. The forest was watched on every
        side. Top uttered sullen groans which were rather ominous.</p><p>At last the palisade appeared through the trees. No trace of any damage could be seen. The
        gate was shut as usual. Deep silence reigned in the corral. Neither the accustomed bleating
        of the sheep nor Ayrton's voice could be heard.</p><p>"Let us enter," said Cyrus Harding.</p><p>And the engineer advanced, while his companions, keeping watch about twenty paces behind
        him, were ready to fire at a moment's notice.</p><p>Harding raised the inner latch of the gate and was about to push it back, when Top barked
        loudly. A report sounded and was responded to by a cry of pain.</p><p>Herbert, struck by a bullet, lay stretched on the ground.</p><p/></body></topic>