<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p3-chapter-5" ><title>Chapter 5</title><body><p>So, then, all was explained by the submarine explosion of this torpedo. Cyrus Harding could
        not be mistaken, as, during the war of the Union, he had had occasion to try these terrible
        engines of destruction. It was under the action of this cylinder, charged with some
        explosive substance, nitro- glycerine, picrate, or some other material of the same nature,
        that the water of the channel had been raised like a dome, the bottom of the brig crushed
        in, and she had sunk instantly, the damage done to her hull being so considerable that it
        was impossible to refloat her. The "Speedy" had not been able to withstand a torpedo that
        would have destroyed an ironclad as easily as a fishing-boat!</p><p>Yes! all was explained, everything--except the presence of the torpedo in the waters of the
        channel!</p><p>"My friends, then," said Cyrus Harding, "we can no longer be in doubt as to the presence of
        a mysterious being, a castaway like us, perhaps, abandoned on our island, and I say this in
        order that Ayrton may be acquainted with all the strange events which have occurred during
        these two years. Who this beneficent stranger is, whose intervention has, so fortunately for
        us, been manifested on many occasions, I cannot imagine. What his object can be in acting
        thus, in concealing himself after rendering us so many services, I cannot understand: But
        his services are not the less real, and are of such a nature that only a man possessed of
        prodigious power, could render them. Ayrton is indebted to him as much as we are, for, if it
        was the stranger who saved me from the waves after the fall from the balloon, evidently it
        was he who wrote the document, who placed the bottle in the channel, and who has made known
        to us the situation of our companion. I will add that it was he who guided that chest,
        provided with everything we wanted, and stranded it on Flotsam Point; that it was he who
        lighted that fire on the heights of the island, which permitted you to land; that it was he
        who fired that bullet found in the body of the peccary; that it was he who plunged that
        torpedo into the channel, which destroyed the brig; in a word, that all those inexplicable
        events, for which we could not assign a reason, are due to this mysterious being. Therefore,
        whoever he may be, whether shipwrecked, or exiled on our island, we shall be ungrateful, if
        we think ourselves freed from gratitude towards him. We have contracted a debt, and I hope
        that we shall one day pay it."</p><p>"You are right in speaking thus, my dear Cyrus," replied Gideon Spilett. "Yes, there is an
        almost all-powerful being, hidden in some part of the island, and whose influence has been
        singularly useful to our colony. I will add that the unknown appears to possess means of
        action which border on the supernatural, if in the events of practical life the supernatural
        were recognizable. Is it he who is in secret communication with us by the well in Granite
        House, and has he thus a knowledge of all our plans? Was it he who threw us that bottle,
        when the vessel made her first cruise? Was it he who threw Top out of the lake, and killed
        the dugong? Was it he, who as everything leads us to believe, saved you from the waves, and
        that under circumstances in which any one else would not have been able to act? If it was
        he, he possesses a power which renders him master of the elements."</p><p>The reporter's reasoning was just, and every one felt it to be so.</p><p>"Yes," rejoined Cyrus Harding, "if the intervention of a human being is not more
        questionable for us, I agree that he has at his disposal means of action beyond those
        possessed by humanity. There is a mystery still, but if we discover the man, the mystery
        will be discovered also. The question, then, is, ought we to respect the incognito of this
        generous being, or ought we to do everything to find him out? What is your opinion on the
        matter?"</p><p>"My opinion," said Pencroft, "is that, whoever he may be, he is a brave man, and he has my
        esteem!"</p><p>"Be it so," answered Harding, "but that is not an answer, Pencroft."</p><p>"Master," then said Neb, "my idea is, that we may search as long as we like for this
        gentleman whom you are talking about, but that we shall not discover him till he
        pleases."</p><p>"That's not bad, what you say, Neb," observed Pencroft.</p><p>"I am of Neb's opinion," said Gideon Spilett, "but that is no reason for not attempting the
        adventure. Whether we find this mysterious being or not, we shall at least have fulfilled
        our duty towards him."</p><p>"And you, my boy, give us your opinion," said the engineer, turning to Herbert.</p><p>"Oh," cried Herbert, his countenance full of animation, "how I should like to thank him, he
        who saved you first, and who has now saved us!"</p><p>"Of course, my boy," replied Pencroft, "so would I and all of us. I am not inquisitive, but
        I would give one of my eyes to see this individual face to face! It seems to me that he must
        be handsome, tall, strong, with a splendid beard, radiant hair, and that he must be seated
        on clouds, a great ball in his hands!"</p><p>"But, Pencroft," answered Spilett, "you are describing a picture of the Creator."</p><p>"Possibly, Mr. Spilett," replied the sailor, "but that is how I imagine him!"</p><p>"And you, Ayrton?" asked the engineer.</p><p>"Captain Harding," replied Ayrton, "I can give you no better advice in this matter.
        Whatever you do will be best; when you wish me to join you in your researches, I am ready to
        follow you.</p><p>"I thank you, Ayrton," answered Cyrus Harding, "but I should like a more direct answer to
        the question I put to you. You are our companion; you have already endangered your life
        several times for us, and you, as well as the rest, ought to be consulted in the matter of
        any important decision. Speak, therefore."</p><p>"Captain Harding," replied Ayrton, "I think that we ought to do everything to discover this
        unknown benefactor. Perhaps he is alone. Perhaps he is suffering. Perhaps he has a life to
        be renewed. I, too, as you said, have a debt of gratitude to pay him. It was he, it could be
        only he who must have come to Tabor Island, who found there the wretch you knew, and who
        made known to you that there was an unfortunate man there to be saved. Therefore it is,
        thanks to him, that I have become a man again. No, I will never forget him!"</p><p>"That is settled, then," said Cyrus Harding. "We will begin our researches as soon as
        possible. We will not leave a corner of the island unexplored. We will search into its most
        secret recesses, and will hope that our unknown friend will pardon us in consideration of
        our intentions!"</p><p>For several days the colonists were actively employed in haymaking and the harvest. Before
        putting their project of exploring the yet unknown parts of the island into execution, they
        wished to get all possible work finished. It was also the time for collecting the various
        vegetables from the Tabor Island plants. All was stowed away, and happily there was no want
        of room in Granite House, in which they might have housed all the treasures of the island.
        The products of the colony were there, methodically arranged, and in a safe place, as may be
        believed, sheltered as much from animals as from man.</p><p>There was no fear of damp in the middle of that thick mass of granite. Many natural
        excavations situated in the upper passage were enlarged either by pick-axe or mine, and
        Granite House thus became a general warehouse, containing all the provisions, arms, tools,
        and spare utensils--in a word, all the stores of the colony.</p><p>As to the guns obtained from the brig, they were pretty pieces of ordnance, which, at
        Pencroft's entreaty, were hoisted by means of tackle and pulleys, right up into Granite
        House; embrasures were made between the windows, and the shining muzzles of the guns could
        soon be seen through the granite cliff. From this height they commanded all Union Bay. It
        was like a little Gibraltar, and any vessel anchored off the islet would inevitably be
        exposed to the fire of this aerial battery.</p><p>"Captain," said Pencroft one day, it was the 8th of November, "now that our fortifications
        are finished, it would be a good thing if we tried the range of our guns."</p><p>"Do you think that is useful?" asked the engineer.</p><p>"It is more than useful, it is necessary! Without that how are we to know to what distance
        we can send one of those pretty shot with which we are provided?"</p><p>"Try them, Pencroft," replied the engineer. "However, I think that in making the
        experiment, we ought to employ, not the ordinary powder, the supply of which, I think,
        should remain untouched, but the pyroxyle which will never fail us."</p><p>"Can the cannon support the shock of the pyroxyle?" asked the reporter, who was not less
        anxious than Pencroft to try the artillery of Granite House.</p><p>"I believe so. However," added the engineer, "we will be prudent." The engineer was right
        in thinking that the guns were of excellent make. Made of forged steel, and breech-loaders,
        they ought consequently to be able to bear a considerable charge, and also have an enormous
        range. In fact, as regards practical effect, the transit described by the ball ought to be
        as extended as possible, and this tension could only be obtained under the condition that
        the projectile should be impelled with a very great initial velocity.</p><p>"Now," said Harding to his companions, "the initial velocity is in proportion to the
        quantity of powder used. In the fabrication of these pieces, everything depends on employing
        a metal with the highest possible power of resistance, and steel is incontestably that metal
        of all others which resists the best. I have, therefore, reason to believe that our guns
        will bear without risk the expansion of the pyroxyle gas, and will give excellent
        results."</p><p>"We shall be a great deal more certain of that when we have tried them!" answered
        Pencroft.</p><p>It is unnecessary to say that the four cannons were in perfect order. Since they had been
        taken from the water, the sailor had bestowed great care upon them. How many hours he had
        spent, in rubbing, greasing, and polishing them, and in cleaning the mechanism! And now the
        pieces were as brilliant as if they had been on board a frigate of the United States
        Navy.</p><p>On this day, therefore, in presence of all the members of the colony, including Master Jup
        and Top, the four cannon were successively tried. They were charged with pyroxyle, taking
        into consideration its explosive power, which, as has been said, is four times that of
        ordinary powder: the projectile to be fired was cylindroconic.</p><p>Pencroft, holding the end of the quick-match, stood ready to fire.</p><p>At Harding's signal, he fired. The shot, passing over the islet, fell into the sea at a
        distance which could not be calculated with exactitude.</p><p>The second gun was pointed at the rocks at the end of Flotsam Point, and the shot striking
        a sharp rock nearly three miles from Granite House, made it fly into splinters. It was
        Herbert who had pointed this gun and fired it, and very proud he was of his first shot.
        Pencroft only was prouder than he! Such a shot, the honor of which belonged to his dear
        boy.</p><p>The third shot, aimed this time at the downs forming the upper side of Union Bay, struck
        the sand at a distance of four miles, then having ricocheted: was lost in the sea in a cloud
        of spray.</p><p>For the fourth piece Cyrus Harding slightly increased the charge, so as to try its extreme
        range. Then, all standing aside for fear of its bursting, the match was lighted by means of
        a long cord.</p><p>A tremendous report was heard, but the piece had held good, and the colonists rushing to
        the windows, saw the shot graze the rocks of Mandible Cape, nearly five miles from Granite
        House, and disappear in Shark Gulf.</p><p>"Well, captain," exclaimed Pencroft, whose cheers might have rivaled the reports
        themselves, "what do you say of our battery? All the pirates in the Pacific have only to
        present themselves before Granite House! Not one can land there now without our
        permission!"</p><p>"Believe me, Pencroft," replied the engineer, "it would be better not to have to make the
        experiment."</p><p>"Well," said the sailor, "what ought to be done with regard to those six villains who are
        roaming about the island? Are we to leave them to overrun our forests, our fields, our
        plantations? These pirates are regular jaguars, and it seems to me we ought not to hesitate
        to treat them as such! What do you think, Ayrton?" added Pencroft, turning to his
        companion.</p><p>Ayrton hesitated at first to reply, and Cyrus Harding regretted that Pencroft had so
        thoughtlessly put this question. And he was much moved when Ayrton replied in a humble
        tone,--</p><p>"I have been one of those jaguars, Mr. Pencroft. I have no right to speak."</p><p>And with a slow step he walked away.</p><p>Pencroft understood.</p><p>"What a brute I am!" he exclaimed. "Poor Ayrton! He has as much right to speak here as any
        one!"</p><p>"Yes," said Gideon Spilett, "but his reserve does him honor, and it is right to respect the
        feeling which he has about his sad past."</p><p>"Certainly, Mr. Spilett," answered the sailor, "and there is no fear of my doing so again.
        I would rather bite my tongue off than cause Ayrton any pain! But to return to the question.
        It seems to me that these ruffians have no right to any pity, and that we ought to rid the
        island of them as soon as possible."</p><p>"Is that your opinion, Pencroft?" asked the engineer.</p><p>"Quite my opinion."</p><p>"And before hunting them mercilessly, you would not wait until they had committed some
        fresh act of hostility against us?"</p><p>"Isn't what they have done already enough?" asked Pencroft, who did not understand these
        scruples.</p><p>"They may adopt other sentiments!" said Harding, "and perhaps repent."</p><p>"They repent!" exclaimed the sailor, shrugging his shoulders.</p><p>"Pencroft, think of Ayrton!" said Herbert, taking the sailor's hand. "He became an honest
        man again!"</p><p>Pencroft looked at his companions one after the other. He had never thought of his proposal
        being met with any objection. His rough nature could not allow that they ought to come to
        terms with the rascals who had landed on the island with Bob Harvey's accomplices, the
        murderers of the crew of the "Speedy," and he looked upon them as wild beasts which ought to
        be destroyed without delay and without remorse.</p><p>"Come!" said be. "Everybody is against me! You wish to be generous to those villains! Very
        well; I hope we mayn't repent it!"</p><p>"What danger shall we run," said Herbert, "if we take care to be always on our guard?"</p><p>"Hum!" observed the reporter, who had not given any decided opinion. "They are six and well
        armed. If they each lay hid in a corner, and each fired at one of us, they would soon be
        masters of the colony!"</p><p>"Why have they not done so?" said Herbert. "No doubt because it was not their interest to
        do it. Besides, we are six also."</p><p>"Well, well!" replied Pencroft, whom no reasoning could have convinced. "Let us leave these
        good people to do what they like, and don't think anything more about them!"</p><p>"Come, Pencroft," said Neb, "don't make yourself out so bad as all that! Suppose one of
        these unfortunate men were here before you, within good range of your guns, you would not
        fire."</p><p>"I would fire on him as I would on a mad dog, Neb," replied Pencroft coldly.</p><p>"Pencroft," said the engineer, "you have always shown much deference to my advice; will
        you, in this matter, yield to me?"</p><p>"I will do as you please, Captain Harding," answered the sailor, who was not at all
        convinced.</p><p>"Very well, wait, and we will not attack them unless we are attacked first."</p><p>Thus their behavior towards the pirates was agreed upon, although Pencroft augured nothing
        good from it. They were not to attack them, but were to be on their guard. After all, the
        island was large and fertile. If any sentiment of honesty yet remained in the bottom of
        their hearts, these wretches might perhaps be reclaimed. Was it not their interest in the
        situation in which they found themselves to begin a new life? At any rate, for humanity's
        sake alone, it would be right to wait. The colonists would no longer as before, be able to
        go and come without fear. Hitherto they had only wild beasts to guard against, and now six
        convicts of the worst description, perhaps, were roaming over their island. It was serious,
        certainly, and to less brave men, it would have been security lost! No matter! At present,
        the colonists had reason on their side against Pencroft. Would they be right in the future?
        That remained to be seen.</p><p/></body></topic>