<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p3-chapter-20" ><title>Chapter 20</title><body><p>An isolated rock, thirty feet in length, twenty in breadth, scarcely ten from the water's
        edge, such was the only solid point which the waves of the Pacific had not engulfed.</p><p>It was all that remained of the structure of Granite House! The wall had fallen headlong
        and been then shattered to fragments, and a few of the rocks of the large room were piled
        one above another to form this point. All around had disappeared in the abyss; the inferior
        cone of Mount Franklin, rent asunder by the explosion; the lava jaws of Shark Gulf, the
        plateau of Prospect Heights, Safety Islet, the granite rocks of Port Balloon, the basalts of
        Dakkar Grotto, the long Serpentine Peninsula, so distant nevertheless from the center of the
        eruption. All that could now be seen of Lincoln Island was the narrow rock which now served
        as a refuge to the six colonists and their dog Top.</p><p>The animals had also perished in the catastrophe; the birds, as well as those representing
        the fauna of the island--all either crushed or drowned, and the unfortunate Jup himself had,
        alas! found his death in some crevice of the soil.</p><p>If Cyrus Harding, Gideon Spilett, Herbert, Pencroft, Neb, and Ayrton had survived, it was
        because, assembled under their tent, they had been hurled into the sea at the instant when
        the fragments of the island rained down on every side.</p><p>When they reached the surface they could only perceive, at half a cable's length, this mass
        of rocks, towards which they swam and on which they found footing.</p><p>On this barren rock they had now existed for nine days. A few provisions taken from the
        magazine of Granite House before the catastrophe, a little fresh water from the rain which
        had fallen in a hollow of the rock, was all that the unfortunate colonists possessed. Their
        last hope, the vessel, had been shattered to pieces. They had no means of quitting the reef;
        no fire, nor any means of obtaining it. It seemed that they must inevitably perish.</p><p>This day, the 18th of March, there remained only provisions for two days, although they
        limited their consumption to the bare necessaries of life. All their science and
        intelligence could avail them nothing in their present position. They were in the hand of
        God.</p><p>Cyrus Harding was calm, Gideon Spilett more nervous, and Pencroft, a prey to sullen anger,
        walked to and fro on the rock. Herbert did not for a moment quit the engineer's side, as if
        demanding from him that assistance he had no power to give. Neb and Ayrton were resigned to
        their fate.</p><p>"Ah, what a misfortune! what a misfortune!" often repeated Pencroft. "If we had but a
        walnut-shell to take us to Tabor Island! But we have nothing, nothing!"</p><p>"Captain Nemo did right to die," said Neb.</p><p>During the five ensuing days Cyrus Harding and his unfortunate companions husbanded their
        provisions with the most extreme care, eating only what would prevent them from dying of
        starvation. Their weakness was extreme. Herbert and Neb began to show symptoms of
        delirium.</p><p>Under these circumstances was it possible for them to retain even the shadow of a hope? No!
        What was their sole remaining chance? That a vessel should appear in sight of the rock? But
        they knew only too well from experience that no ships ever visited this part of the Pacific.
        Could they calculate that, by a truly providential coincidence, the Scotch yacht would
        arrive precisely at this time in search of Ayrton at Tabor Island? It was scarcely probable;
        and, besides, supposing she should come there, as the colonists had not been able to deposit
        a notice pointing out Ayrton's change of abode, the commander of the yacht, after having
        explored Tabor Island without results, would again set sail and return to lower
        latitudes.</p><p>No! no hope of being saved could be retained, and a horrible death, death from hunger and
        thirst, awaited them upon this rock.</p><p>Already they were stretched on the rock, inanimate, and no longer conscious of what passed
        around them. Ayrton alone, by a supreme effort, from time to time raised his head, and cast
        a despairing glance over the desert ocean.</p><p>But on the morning of the 24th of March Ayrton's arms were extended toward a point in the
        horizon; he raised himself, at first on his knees, then upright, and his hand seemed to make
        a signal.</p><p>A sail was in sight off the rock. She was evidently not without an object. The reef was the
        mark for which she was making in a direct line, under all steam, and the unfortunate
        colonists might have made her out some hours before if they had had the strength to watch
        the horizon.</p><p>"The 'Duncan'!" murmured Ayrton--and fell back without sign of life.</p><p>When Cyrus Harding and his companions recovered consciousness, thanks to the attention
        lavished upon them, they found themselves in the cabin of a steamer, without being able to
        comprehend how they had escaped death.</p><p>A word from Ayrton explained everything.</p><p>"The 'Duncan'!" he murmured.</p><p>"The 'Duncan'!" exclaimed Cyrus Harding. And raising his hand to Heaven, he said, "Oh!
        Almighty God! mercifully hast Thou preserved us!"</p><p>It was, in fact, the "Duncan," Lord Glenarvan's yacht, now commanded by Robert, son of
        Captain Grant, who had been despatched to Tabor Island to find Ayrton, and bring him back to
        his native land alter twelve years of expiation.</p><p>The colonists were not only saved, but already on the way to their native country.</p><p>"Captain Grant," asked Cyrus Harding, "who can have suggested to you the idea, after having
        left Tabor Island, where you did not find Ayrton, of coming a hundred miles farther
        northeast?"</p><p>"Captain Harding," replied Robert Grant, "it was in order to find, not only Ayrton, but
        yourself and your companions."</p><p>"My companions and myself?"</p><p>"Doubtless, at Lincoln Island."</p><p>"At Lincoln Island!" exclaimed in a breath Gideon Spilett, Herbert, Neb, and Pencroft, in
        the highest degree astonished.</p><p>"How could you be aware of the existence of Lincoln Island?" inquired Cyrus Harding, "it is
        not even named in the charts."</p><p>"I knew of it from a document left by you on Tabor Island," answered Robert Grant.</p><p>"A document!" cried Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"Without doubt, and here it is," answered Robert Grant, producing a paper which indicated
        the longitude and latitude of Lincoln Island, "the present residence of Ayrton and five
        American colonists."</p><p>"It is Captain Nemo!" cried Cyrus Harding, after having read the notice, and recognized
        that the handwriting was similar to that of the paper found at the corral.</p><p>"Ah!" said Pencroft, "it was then he who took our 'Bonadventure' and hazarded himself alone
        to go to Tabor Island!"</p><p>"In order to leave this notice," added Herbert.</p><p>"I was then right in saying," exclaimed the sailor, "that even after his death the captain
        would render us a last service."</p><p>"My friends," said Cyrus Harding, in a voice of the profoundest emotion, "may the God of
        mercy have had pity on the soul of Captain Nemo, our benefactor."</p><p>The colonists uncovered themselves at these last words of Cyrus Harding, and murmured the
        name of Captain Nemo.</p><p>Then Ayrton, approaching the engineer, said simply, "Where should this coffer be
        deposited?"</p><p>It was the coffer which Ayrton had saved at the risk of his life, at the very instant that
        the island had been engulfed, and which he now faithfully handed to the engineer.</p><p>"Ayrton! Ayrton!" said Cyrus Harding, deeply touched. Then, addressing Robert Grant, "Sir,"
        he added, "you left behind you a criminal; you find in his place a man who has become honest
        by penitence, and whose hand I am proud to clasp in mine."</p><p>Robert Grant was now made acquainted with the strange history of Captain Nemo and the
        colonists of Lincoln Island. Then, observation being taken of what remained of this shoal,
        which must henceforward figure on the charts of the Pacific, the order was given to make all
        sail.</p><p>A few weeks afterwards the colonists landed in America, and found their country once more
        at peace alter the terrible conflict in which right and justice had triumphed.</p><p>Of the treasures contained in the coffer left by Captain Nemo to the colonists of Lincoln
        Island, the larger portion was employed in the purchase of a vast territory in the State of
        Iowa. One pearl alone, the finest, was reserved from the treasure and sent to Lady Glenarvan
        in the name of the castaways restored to their country by the "Duncan."</p><p>There, upon this domain, the colonists invited to labor, that is to say, to wealth and
        happiness, all those to whom they had hoped to offer the hospitality of Lincoln Island.
        There was founded a vast colony to which they gave the name of that island sunk beneath the
        waters of the Pacific. A river there was called the Mercy, a mountain took the name of Mount
        Franklin, a small lake was named Lake Grant, and the forests became the forests of the Far
        West. It might have been an island on terra firma.</p><p>There, under the intelligent hands of the engineer and his companions, everything
        prospered. Not one of the former colonists of Lincoln Island was absent, for they had sworn
        to live always together. Neb was with his master; Ayrton was there ready to sacrifice
        himself for all; Pencroft was more a farmer than he had ever been a sailor; Herbert, who
        completed his studies under the superintendence of Cyrus Harding, and Gideon Spilett, who
        founded the New Lincoln Herald, the best-informed journal in the world.</p><p>There Cyrus Harding and his companions received at intervals visits from Lord and Lady
        Glenarvan, Captain John Mangles and his wife, the sister of Robert Grant, Robert Grant
        himself, Major McNab, and all those who had taken part in the history both of Captain Grant
        and Captain Nemo.</p><p>There, to conclude, all were happy, united in the present as they had been in the past; but
        never could they forget that island upon which they had arrived poor and friendless, that
        island which, during four years had supplied all their wants, and of which there remained
        but a fragment of granite washed by the waves of the Pacific, the tomb of him who had borne
        the name of Captain Nemo.</p></body></topic>