<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p3-chapter-2" ><title>Chapter 2</title><body><p>There was no longer any doubt as to the pirates' intentions. They had dropped anchor at a
        short distance from the island, and it was evident that the next day by means of their boats
        they purposed to land on the beach!</p><p>Cyrus Harding and his companions were ready to act, but, determined though they were, they
        must not forget to be prudent. Perhaps their presence might still be concealed in the event
        of the pirates contenting themselves with landing on the shore without examining the
        interior of the island. It might be, indeed, that their only intention was to obtain fresh
        water from the Mercy, and it was not impossible that the bridge, thrown across a mile and a
        half from the mouth, and the manufactory at the Chimneys might escape their notice.</p><p>But why was that flag hoisted at the brig's peak? What was that shot fired for? Pure
        bravado doubtless, unless it was a sign of the act of taking possession. Harding knew now
        that the vessel was well armed. And what had the colonists of Lincoln Island to reply to the
        pirates' guns? A few muskets only.</p><p>"However," observed Cyrus Harding, "here we are in an impregnable position. The enemy
        cannot discover the mouth of the outlet, now that it is hidden under reeds and grass, and
        consequently it would be impossible for them to penetrate into Granite House."</p><p>"But our plantations, our poultry-yard, our corral, all, everything!" exclaimed Pencroft,
        stamping his foot. "They may spoil everything, destroy everything in a few hours!"</p><p>"Everything, Pencroft," answered Harding, "and we have no means of preventing them."</p><p>"Are they numerous? that is the question," said the reporter. "If they are not more than a
        dozen, we shall be able to stop them, but forty, fifty, more perhaps!"</p><p>"Captain Harding," then said Ayrton, advancing towards the engineer, "will you give me
        leave?"</p><p>"For what, my friend?"</p><p>"To go to that vessel to find out the strength of her crew."</p><p>"But Ayrton--" answered the engineer, hesitating, "you will risk your life--"</p><p>"Why not, sir?"</p><p>"That is more than your duty."</p><p>"I have more than my duty to do," replied Ayrton.</p><p>"Will you go to the ship in the boat?" asked Gideon Spilett.</p><p>"No, sir, but I will swim. A boat would be seen where a man may glide between wind and
        water."</p><p>"Do you know that the brig is a mile and a quarter from the shore?" said Herbert.</p><p>"I am a good swimmer, Mr. Herbert."</p><p>"I tell you it is risking your life," said the engineer.</p><p>"That is no matter," answered Ayrton. "Captain Harding, I ask this as a favor. Perhaps it
        will be a means of raising me in my own eyes!"</p><p>"Go, Ayrton," replied the engineer, who felt sure that a refusal would have deeply wounded
        the former convict, now become an honest man.</p><p>"I will accompany you," said Pencroft.</p><p>"You mistrust me!" said Ayrton quickly.</p><p>Then more humbly,--</p><p>"Alas!"</p><p>"No! no!" exclaimed Harding with animation, "no, Ayrton, Pencroft does not mistrust you.
        You interpret his words wrongly."</p><p>"Indeed," returned the sailor, "I only propose to accompany Ayrton as far as the islet. It
        may be, although it is scarcely possible, that one of these villains has landed, and in that
        case two men will not be too many to hinder him from giving the alarm. I will wait for
        Ayrton on the islet, and he shall go alone to the vessel, since he has proposed to do so."
        These things agreed to, Ayrton made preparations for his departure. His plan was bold, but
        it might succeed, thanks to the darkness of the night. Once arrived at the vessel's side,
        Ayrton, holding on to the main chains, might reconnoiter the number and perhaps overhear the
        intentions of the pirates.</p><p>Ayrton and Pencroft, followed by their companions, descended to the beach. Ayrton undressed
        and rubbed himself with grease, so as to suffer less from the temperature of the water,
        which was still cold. He might, indeed, be obliged to remain in it for several hours.</p><p>Pencroft and Neb, during this time, had gone to fetch the boat, moored a few hundred feet
        higher up, on the bank of the Mercy, and by the time they returned, Ayrton was ready to
        start. A coat was thrown over his shoulders, and the settlers all came round him to press
        his hand.</p><p>Ayrton then shoved off with Pencroft in the boat.</p><p>It was half-past ten in the evening when the two adventurers disappeared in the darkness.
        Their companions returned to wait at the Chimneys.</p><p>The channel was easily traversed, and the boat touched the opposite shore of the islet.
        This was not done without precaution, for fear lest the pirates might be roaming about
        there. But after a careful survey, it was evident that the islet was deserted. Ayrton then,
        followed by Pencroft, crossed it with a rapid step, scaring the birds nestled in the holes
        of the rocks; then, without hesitating, he plunged into the sea, and swam noiselessly in the
        direction of the ship, in which a few lights had recently appeared, showing her exact
        situation. As to Pencroft, he crouched down in a cleft of the rock, and awaited the return
        of his companion.</p><p>In the meanwhile, Ayrton, swimming with a vigorous stroke, glided through the sheet of
        water without producing the slightest ripple. His head just emerged above it and his eyes
        were fixed on the dark hull of the brig, from which the lights were reflected in the water.
        He thought only of the duty which he had promised to accomplish, and nothing of the danger
        which he ran, not only on board the ship, but in the sea, often frequented by sharks. The
        current bore him along and he rapidly receded from the shore.</p><p>Half an hour afterwards, Ayrton, without having been either seen or heard, arrived at the
        ship and caught hold of the main-chains. He took breath, then, hoisting himself up, he
        managed to reach the extremity of the cutwater. There were drying several pairs of sailors'
        trousers. He put on a pair. Then settling himself firmly, he listened. They were not
        sleeping on board the brig. On the contrary, they were talking, singing, laughing. And these
        were the sentences, accompanied with oaths, which principally struck Ayrton:--</p><p>"Our brig is a famous acquisition."</p><p>"She sails well, and merits her name of the 'Speedy.'"</p><p>"She would show all the navy of Norfolk a clean pair of heels."</p><p>"Hurrah for her captain!"</p><p>"Hurrah for Bob Harvey!"</p><p>What Ayrton felt when he overheard this fragment of conversation may be understood when it
        is known that in this Bob Harvey he recognized one of his old Australian companions, a
        daring sailor, who had continued his criminal career. Bob Harvey had seized, on the shores
        of Norfolk Island this brig, which was loaded with arms, ammunition, utensils, and tools of
        all sorts, destined for one of the Sandwich Islands. All his gang had gone on board, and
        pirates after having been convicts, these wretches, more ferocious than the Malays
        themselves, scoured the Pacific, destroying vessels, and massacring their crews.</p><p>The convicts spoke loudly, they recounted their deeds, drinking deeply at the same time,
        and this is what Ayrton gathered. The actual crew of the "Speedy" was composed solely of
        English prisoners, escaped from Norfolk Island.</p><p>Here it may be well to explain what this island was. In 29deg 2' south latitude, and 165deg
        42' east longitude, to the east of Australia, is found a little island, six miles in
        circumference, overlooked by Mount Pitt, which rises to a height of 1,100 feet above the
        level of the sea. This is Norfolk Island, once the seat of an establishment in which were
        lodged the most intractable convicts from the English penitentiaries. They numbered 500,
        under an iron discipline, threatened with terrible punishments, and were guarded by 150
        soldiers, and 150 employed under the orders of the governor. It would be difficult to
        imagine a collection of greater ruffians. Sometimes,--although very rarely,--notwithstanding
        the extreme surveillance of which they were the object, many managed to escape, and seizing
        vessels which they surprised, they infested the Polynesian Archipelagoes.</p><p>Thus had Bob Harvey and his companions done. Thus had Ayrton formerly wished to do. Bob
        Harvey had seized the brig "Speedy," anchored in sight of Norfolk Island; the crew had been
        massacred; and for a year this ship had scoured the Pacific, under the command of Harvey,
        now a pirate, and well known to Ayrton!</p><p>The convicts were, for the most part, assembled under the poop; but a few, stretched on the
        deck, were talking loudly.</p><p>The conversation still continued amid shouts and libations. Ayrton learned that chance
        alone had brought the "Speedy" in sight of Lincoln Island; Bob Harvey had never yet set foot
        on it; but, as Cyrus Harding had conjectured, finding this unknown land in his course, its
        position being marked on no chart, he had formed the project of visiting it, and, if he
        found it suitable, of making it the brig's headquarters.</p><p>As to the black flag hoisted at the "Speedy's" peak, and the gun which had been fired, in
        imitation of men-of-war when they lower their colors, it was pure piratical bravado. It was
        in no way a signal, and no communication yet existed between the convicts and Lincoln
        Island.</p><p>The settlers' domain was now menaced with terrible danger. Evidently the island, with its
        water, its harbor, its resources of all kinds so increased in value by the colonists, and
        the concealment afforded by Granite House, could not but be convenient for the convicts; in
        their hands it would become an excellent place of refuge, and, being unknown, it would
        assure them, for a long time perhaps, impunity and security. Evidently, also, the lives of
        the settlers would not be respected, and Bob Harvey and his accomplices' first care would be
        to massacre them without mercy. Harding and his companions had, therefore, not even the
        choice of flying and hiding themselves in the island, since the convicts intended to reside
        there, and since, in the event of the "Speedy" departing on an expedition, it was probable
        that some of the crew would remain on shore, so as to settle themselves there. Therefore, it
        would be necessary to fight, to destroy every one of these scoundrels, unworthy of pity, and
        against whom any means would be right. So thought Ayrton, and he well knew that Cyrus
        Harding would be of his way of thinking.</p><p>But was resistance and, in the last place, victory possible? That would depend on the
        equipment of the brig, and the number of men which she carried.</p><p>This Ayrton resolved to learn at any cost, and as an hour after his arrival the
        vociferations had begun to die away, and as a large number of the convicts were already
        buried in a drunken sleep, Ayrton did not hesitate to venture onto the "Speedy's" deck,
        which the extinguished lanterns now left in total darkness. He hoisted himself onto the
        cutwater, and by the bowsprit arrived at the forecastle. Then, gliding among the convicts
        stretched here and there, he made the round of the ship, and found that the "Speedy" carried
        four guns, which would throw shot of from eight to ten pounds in weight. He found also, on
        touching them that these guns were breech-loaders. They were therefore, of modern make,
        easily used, and of terrible effect.</p><p>As to the men lying on the deck, they were about ten in number, but it was to be supposed
        that more were sleeping down below. Besides, by listening to them, Ayrton had understood
        that there were fifty on board. That was a large number for the six settlers of Lincoln
        Island to contend with! But now, thanks to Ayrton's devotion, Cyrus Harding would not be
        surprised, he would know the strength of his adversaries, and would make his arrangements
        accordingly.</p><p>There was nothing more for Ayrton to do but to return, and render to his companions an
        account of the mission with which he had charged himself, and he prepared to regain the bows
        of the brig, so that he might let himself down into the water. But to this man, whose wish
        was, as he had said, to do more than his duty, there came an heroic thought. This was to
        sacrifice his own life, but save the island and the colonists. Cyrus Harding evidently could
        not resist fifty ruffians, all well armed, who, either by penetrating by main force into
        Granite House, or by starving out the besieged, could obtain from them what they wanted. And
        then he thought of his preservers--those who had made him again a man, and an honest mm,
        those to whom he owed all--murdered without pity, their works destroyed, their island turned
        into a pirates' den! He said to himself that he, Ayrton, was the principal cause of so many
        disasters, since his old companion, Bob Harvey, had but realized his own plans, and a
        feeling of horror took possession of him. Then he was seized with an irresistible desire to
        blow up the brig and with her, all whom she had on board. He would perish in the explosion,
        but he would have done his duty.</p><p>Ayrton did not hesitate. To reach the powder-room, which is always situated in the
        after-part of a vessel, was easy. There would be no want of powder in a vessel which
        followed such a trade, and a spark would be enough to destroy it in an instant.</p><p>Ayrton stole carefully along the between-decks, strewn with numerous sleepers, overcome
        more by drunkenness than sleep. A lantern was lighted at the foot of the mainmast, round
        which was hung a gun-rack, furnished with weapons of all sorts.</p><p>Ayrton took a revolver from the rack, and assured himself that it was loaded and primed.
        Nothing more was needed to accomplish the work of destruction. He then glided towards the
        stern, so as to arrive under the brig's poop at the powder-magazine.</p><p>It was difficult to proceed along the dimly lighted deck without stumbling over some
        half-sleeping convict, who retorted by oaths and kicks. Ayrton was, therefore, more than
        once obliged to halt. But at last he arrived at the partition dividing the aftercabin, and
        found the door opening into the magazine itself.</p><p>Ayrton, compelled to force it open, set to work. It was a difficult operation to perform
        without noise, for he had to break a padlock. But under his vigorous hand, the padlock
        broke, and the door was open.</p><p>At that moment a hand was laid on Ayrton's shoulder.</p><p>"What are you doing here?" asked a tail man, in a harsh voice, who, standing in the shadow,
        quickly threw the light of a lantern in Ayrton's face.</p><p>Ayrton drew beck. In the rapid flash of the lantern, he had recognized his former
        accomplice, Bob Harvey, who could not have known him, as he must have thought Ayrton long
        since dead.</p><p>"What are you doing here?" again said Bob Harvey, seizing Ayrton by the waistband.</p><p>But Ayrton, without replying, wrenched himself from his grasp and attempted to rush into
        the magazine. A shot fired into the midst of the powder-casks, and all would be over!</p><p>"Help, lads!" shouted Bob Harvey.</p><p>At his shout two or three pirates awoke, jumped up, and, rushing on Ayrton, endeavored to
        throw him down. He soon extricated himself from their grasp. He fired his revolver, and two
        of the convicts fell, but a blow from a knife which he could not ward off made a gash in his
        shoulder.</p><p>Ayrton perceived that he could no longer hope to carry out his project. Bob Harvey had
        reclosed the door of the powder-magazine, and a movement on the deck indicated a general
        awakening of the pirates. Ayrton must reserve himself to fight at the side of Cyrus Harding.
        There was nothing for him but flight!</p><p>But was flight still possible? It was doubtful, yet Ayrton resolved to dare everything in
        order to rejoin his companions.</p><p>Four barrels of the revolver were still undischarged. Two were fired-- one, aimed at Bob
        Harvey, did not wound him, or at any rate only slightly, and Ayrton, profiting by the
        momentary retreat of his adversaries, rushed towards the companion-ladder to gain the deck.
        Passing before the lantern, he smashed it with a blow from the butt of his revolver. A
        profound darkness ensued, which favored his flight. Two or three pirates, awakened by the
        noise, were descending the ladder at the same moment.</p><p>A fifth shot from Ayrton laid one low, and the others drew back, not understanding what was
        going on. Ayrton was on deck in two bounds, and three seconds later, having discharged his
        last barrel in the face of a pirate who was about to seize him by the throat, he leaped over
        the bulwarks into the sea.</p><p>Ayrton had not made six strokes before shots were splashing around him like hail.</p><p>What were Pencroft's feelings, sheltered under a rock on the islet! What were those of
        Harding, the reporter, Herbert, and Neb, crouched in the Chimneys, when they heard the
        reports on board the brig! They rushed out on to the beach, and, their guns shouldered, they
        stood ready to repel any attack.</p><p>They had no doubt about it themselves! Ayrton, surprised by the pirates, had been murdered,
        and, perhaps, the wretches would profit by the night to make a descent on the island!</p><p>Half an hour was passed in terrible anxiety. The firing had ceased, and yet neither Ayrton
        nor Pencroft had reappeared. Was the islet invaded? Ought they not to fly to the help of
        Ayrton and Pencroft? But how? The tide being high at that time, rendered the channel
        impassable. The boat was not there! We may imagine the horrible anxiety which took
        possession of Harding and his companions!</p><p>At last, towards half-past twelve, a boat, carrying two men, touched the beach. It was
        Ayrton, slightly wounded in the shoulder, and Pencroft, safe and sound, whom their friends
        received with open arms.</p><p>All immediately took refuge in the Chimneys. There Ayrton recounted all that had passed,
        even to his plan for blowing up the brig, which he had attempted to put into execution.</p><p>All hands were extended to Ayrton, who did not conceal from them that their situation was
        serious. The pirates had been alarmed. They knew that Lincoln Island was inhabited. They
        would land upon it in numbers and well armed. They would respect nothing. Should the
        settlers fall into their hands, they must expect no mercy!</p><p>"Well, we shall know how to die!" said the reporter.</p><p>"Let us go in and watch," answered the engineer.</p><p>"Have we any chance of escape, captain?" asked the sailor.</p><p>"Yes, Pencroft."</p><p>"Hum! six against fifty!"</p><p>"Yes! six! without counting--"</p><p>"Who?" asked Pencroft.</p><p>Cyrus did not reply, but pointed upwards.</p><p/></body></topic>