<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic  id="p3-chapter-4" ><title>Chapter 4</title><body><p>"She has blown up!" cried Herbert.</p><p>"Yes! blown up, just as if Ayrton had set fire to the powder!" returned Pencroft, throwing
        himself into the lift together with Neb and the lad.</p><p>"But what has happened?" asked Gideon Spilett, quite stunned by this unexpected
        catastrophe.</p><p>"Oh! this time, we shall know--" answered the engineer quickly.</p><p>"What shall we know?--"</p><p>"Later! later! Come, Spilett. The main point is that these pirates have been
        exterminated!"</p><p>And Cyrus Harding, hurrying away the reporter and Ayrton, joined Pencroft, Neb, and Herbert
        on the beach.</p><p>Nothing could be seen of the brig, not even her masts. After having been raised by the
        water-spout, she had fallen on her side, and had sunk in that position, doubtless in
        consequence of some enormous leak. But as in that place the channel was not more than twenty
        feet in depth, it was certain that the sides of the submerged brig would reappear at low
        water.</p><p>A few things from the wreck floated on the surface of the water, a raft could be seen
        consisting of spare spars, coops of poultry with their occupants still living, boxes and
        barrels, which gradually came to the surface, after having escaped through the hatchways,
        but no pieces of the wreck appeared, neither planks from the deck, nor timber from the
        hull,-- which rendered the sudden disappearance of the "Speedy" perfectly inexplicable.</p><p>However, the two masts, which had been broken and escaped from the shrouds and stays came
        up, and with their sails, some furled and the others spread. But it was not necessary to
        wait for the tide to bring up these riches, and Ayrton and Pencroft jumped into the boat
        with the intention of towing the pieces of wreck either to the beach or to the islet. But
        just as they were shoving off, an observation from Gideon Spilett arrested them.</p><p>"What about those six convicts who disembarked on the right bank of the Mercy?" said
        he.</p><p>In fact, it would not do to forget that the six men whose boat had gone to pieces on the
        rocks had landed at Flotsam Point.</p><p>They looked in that direction. None of the fugitives were visible. It was probable that,
        having seen their vessel engulfed in the channel, they had fled into the interior of the
        island.</p><p>"We will deal with them later," said Harding. "As they are armed, they will still be
        dangerous; but as it is six against six, the chances are equal. To the most pressing
        business first."</p><p>Ayrton and Pencroft pulled vigorously towards the wreck.</p><p>The sea was calm and the tide very high, as there had been a new moon but two days before.
        A whole hour at least would elapse before the hull of the brig could emerge from the water
        of the channel.</p><p>Ayrton and Pencroft were able to fasten the masts and spars by means of ropes, the ends of
        which were carried to the beach. There, by the united efforts of the settlers the pieces of
        wreck were hauled up. Then the boat picked up all that was floating, coops, barrels, and
        boxes, which were immediately carried to the Chimneys.</p><p>Several bodies floated also. Among them, Ayrton recognized that of Bob Harvey, which he
        pointed out to his companion, saying with some emotion,--</p><p>"That is what I have been, Pencroft."</p><p>"But what you are no longer, brave Ayrton!" returned the sailor warmly.</p><p>It was singular enough that so few bodies floated. Only five or six were counted, which
        were already being carried by the current towards the open sea. Very probably the convicts
        had not had time to escape, and the ship lying over on her side, the greater number of them
        had remained below. Now the current, by carrying the bodies of these miserable men out to
        sea, would spare the colonists the sad task of burying them in some corner of their
        island.</p><p>For two hours, Cyrus Harding and his companions were solely occupied in hauling up the
        spars on to the sand, and then in spreading the sails which were perfectly uninjured, to
        dry. They spoke little, for they were absorbed in their work, but what thoughts occupied
        their minds!</p><p>The possession of this brig, or rather all that she contained, was a perfect mine of
        wealth. In fact, a ship is like a little world in miniature, and the stores of the colony
        would be increased by a large number of useful articles. It would be, on a large scale,
        equivalent to the chest found at Flotsam Point.</p><p>"And besides," thought Pencroft, "why should it be impossible to refloat the brig? If she
        has only a leak, that may be stopped up; a vessel from three to four hundred tons, why she
        is a regular ship compared to our 'Bonadventure'! And we could go a long distance in her! We
        could go anywhere we liked! Captain Harding, Ayrton and I must examine her! She would be
        well worth the trouble!"</p><p>In fact, if the brig was still fit to navigate, the colonists' chances of returning to
        their native land were singularly increased. But, to decide this important question, it was
        necessary to wait until the tide was quite low, so that every part of the brig's hull might
        be examined.</p><p>When their treasures had been safely conveyed on shore, Harding and his companions agreed
        to devote some minutes to breakfast. They were almost famished; fortunately, the larder was
        not far off, and Neb was noted for being an expeditious cook. They breakfasted, therefore,
        near the Chimneys, and during their repast, as may be supposed, nothing was talked of but
        the event which had so miraculously saved the colony.</p><p>"Miraculous is the word," repeated Pencroft, "for it must be acknowledged that those
        rascals blew up just at the right moment! Granite House was beginning to be uncomfortable as
        a habitation!"</p><p>"And can you guess, Pencroft," asked the reporter, "how it happened, or what can have
        occasioned the explosion?"</p><p>"Oh! Mr. Spilett, nothing is more simple," answered Pencroft. "A convict vessel is not
        disciplined like a man-of-war! Convicts are not sailors. Of course the powder-magazine was
        open, and as they were firing incessantly, some careless or clumsy fellow just blew up the
        vessel!"</p><p>"Captain Harding," said Herbert, "what astonishes me is that the explosion has not produced
        more effect. The report was not loud, and besides there are so few planks and timbers torn
        out. It seems as if the ship had rather foundered than blown up."</p><p>"Does that astonish you, my boy?" asked the engineer.</p><p>"Yes, captain."</p><p>"And it astonishes me also, Herbert," replied he, "but when we visit the hull of the brig,
        we shall no doubt find the explanation of the matter."</p><p>"Why, captain," said Pencroft, "you don't suppose that the 'Speedy' simply foundered like a
        ship which has struck on a rock?"</p><p>"Why not," observed Neb, "if there are rocks in the channel?"</p><p>"Nonsense, Neb," answered Pencroft, "you did not look at the right moment. An instant
        before she sank, the brig, as I saw perfectly well, rose on an enormous wave, and fell back
        on her larboard side. Now, if she had only struck, she would have sunk quietly and gone to
        the bottom like an honest vessel."</p><p>"It was just because she was not an honest vessel!" returned Neb.</p><p>"Well, we shall soon see, Pencroft," said the engineer.</p><p>"We shall soon see," rejoined the sailor, "but I would wager my head there are no rocks in
        the channel. Look here, captain, to speak candidly, do you mean to say that there is
        anything marvelous in the occurrence?"</p><p>Cyrus Harding did not answer.</p><p>"At any rate," said Gideon Spilett, "whether rock or explosion, you will agree, Pencroft,
        that it occurred just in the nick of time!"</p><p>"Yes! yes!" replied the sailor, "but that is not the question. I ask Captain Harding if he
        sees anything supernatural in all this."</p><p>"I cannot say, Pencroft," said the engineer. "That is all the answer I can make."</p><p>A reply which did not satisfy Pencroft at all. He stuck to "an explosion," and did not wish
        to give it up. He would never consent to admit that in that channel, with its fine sandy
        bed, just like the beach, which he had often crossed at low water, there could be an unknown
        rock.</p><p>And besides, at the time the brig foundered, it was high water, that is to say, there was
        enough water to carry the vessel clear over any rocks which would not be uncovered at low
        tide. Therefore, there could not have been a collision. Therefore, the vessel had not
        struck. So she had blown up.</p><p>And it must be confessed that the sailor's arguments were reasonable.</p><p>Towards half-past one, the colonists embarked in the boat to visit the wreck. It was to be
        regretted that the brig's two boats had not been saved; but one, as has been said, had gone
        to pieces at the mouth of the Mercy, and was absolutely useless; the other had disappeared
        when the brig went down, and had not again been seen, having doubtless been crushed.</p><p>The hull of the "Speedy" was just beginning to issue from the water. The brig was lying
        right over on her side, for her masts being broken, pressed down by the weight of the
        ballast displaced by the shock, the keel was visible along her whole length. She had been
        regularly turned over by the inexplicable but frightful submarine action, which had been at
        the same time manifested by an enormous water-spout.</p><p>The settlers rowed round the hull, and in proportion as the tide went down, they could
        ascertain, if not the cause which had occasioned the catastrophe, at least the effect
        produced.</p><p>Towards the bows, on both sides of the keel, seven or eight feet from the beginning of the
        stem, the sides of the brig were frightfully torn. Over a length of at least twenty feet
        there opened two large leaks, which would be impossible to stop up. Not only had the copper
        sheathing and the planks disappeared, reduced, no doubt, to powder, but also the ribs, the
        iron bolts, and treenalls which united them. From the entire length of the hull to the stern
        the false keel had been separated with an unaccountable violence, and the keel itself, torn
        from the carline in several places, was split in all its length.</p><p>"I've a notion!" exclaimed Pencroft, "that this vessel will be difficult to get afloat
        again."</p><p>"It will be impossible," said Ayrton.</p><p>"At any rate," observed Gideon Spilett to the sailor, "the explosion, if there has been
        one, has produced singular effects! It has split the lower part of the hull, instead of
        blowing up the deck and topsides! These great rents appear rather to have been made by a
        rock than by the explosion of a powder-magazine."</p><p>"There is not a rock in the channel!" answered the sailor. "I will admit anything you like,
        except the rock."</p><p>"Let us try to penetrate into the interior of the brig," said the engineer; "perhaps we
        shall then know what to think of the cause of her destruction."</p><p>This was the best thing to be done, and it was agreed, besides, to take an inventory of all
        the treasures on board, and to arrange their preservation.</p><p>Access to the interior of the brig was now easy. The tide was still going down and the deck
        was practicable. The ballast, composed of heavy masses of iron, had broken through in
        several places. The noise of the sea could be heard as it rushed out at the holes in the
        hull.</p><p>Cyrus Harding and his companions, hatchets in hand, advanced along the shattered deck.
        Cases of all sorts encumbered it, and, as they had been but a very short time in the water,
        their contents were perhaps uninjured.</p><p>They then busied themselves in placing all this cargo in safety. The water would not return
        for several hours, and these hours must be employed in the most profitable way. Ayrton and
        Pencroft had, at the entrance made in the hull, discovered tackle, which would serve to
        hoist up the barrels and chests. The boat received them and transported them to the shore.
        They took the articles as they came, intending to sort them afterwards.</p><p>At any rate, the settlers saw at once, with extreme satisfaction, that the brig possessed a
        very varied cargo--an assortment of all sorts of articles, utensils, manufactured goods, and
        tools--such as the ships which make the great coasting-trade of Polynesia are usually laden
        with. It was probable that they would find a little of everything, and they agreed that it
        was exactly what was necessary for the colony of Lincoln Island.</p><p>However--and Cyrus Harding observed it in silent astonishment--not only, as has been said,
        had the hull of the brig enormously suffered from the shock, whatever it was, that had
        occasioned the catastrophe, but the interior arrangements had been destroyed, especially
        towards the bows. Partitions and stanchions were smashed, as if some tremendous shell had
        burst in the interior of the brig. The colonists could easily go fore and aft, after having
        removed the cases as they were extricated. They were not heavy bales, which would have been
        difficult to remove, but simple packages, of which the stowage, besides, was no longer
        recognizable.</p><p>The colonists then reached the stern of the brig--the part formerly surmounted by the poop.
        It was there that, following Ayrton's directions, they must look for the powder-magazine.
        Cyrus Harding thought that it had not exploded; that it was possible some barrels might be
        saved, and that the powder, which is usually enclosed in metal coverings might not have
        suffered from contact with the water.</p><p>This, in fact, was just what had happened. They extricated from among a large number of
        shot twenty barrels, the insides of which were lined with copper. Pencroft was convinced by
        the evidence of his own eyes that the destruction of the "Speedy" could not be attributed to
        an explosion. That part of the hull in which the magazine was situated was, moreover, that
        which had suffered least.</p><p>"It may be so," said the obstinate sailor; "but as to a rock, there is not one in the
        channel!"</p><p>"Then, how did it happen?" asked Herbert.</p><p>"I don't know," answered Pencroft, "Captain Harding doesn't know, and nobody knows or ever
        will know!"</p><p>Several hours had passed during these researches, and the tide began to flow. Work must be
        suspended for the present. There was no fear of the brig being carried away by the sea, for
        she was already fixed as firmly as if moored by her anchors.</p><p>They could, therefore, without inconvenience, wait until the next day to resume operations;
        but, as to the vessel itself, she was doomed, and it would be best to hasten to save the
        remains of her hull, as she would not be long in disappearing in the quicksands of the
        channel.</p><p>It was now five o'clock in the evening. It had been a hard day's work for the men. They ate
        with good appetite, and notwithstanding their fatigue, they could not resist, after dinner,
        their desire of inspecting the cases which composed the cargo of the "Speedy."</p><p>Most of them contained clothes, which, as may be believed, was well received. There were
        enough to clothe a whole colony--linen for every one's use, shoes for every one's feet.</p><p>"We are too rich!" exclaimed Pencroft, "But what are we going to do with all this?"</p><p>And every moment burst forth the hurrahs of the delighted sailor when he caught sight of
        the barrels of gunpowder, firearms and sidearms, balls of cotton, implements of husbandry,
        carpenter's, joiner's, and blacksmith's tools, and boxes of all kinds of seeds, not in the
        least injured by their short sojourn in the water. Ah, two years before, how these things
        would have been prized! And now, even though the industrious colonists had provided
        themselves with tools, these treasures would find their use.</p><p>There was no want of space in the store-rooms of Granite House, but that daytime would not
        allow them to stow away the whole. It would not do also to forget that the six survivors of
        the "Speedy's" crew had landed on the island, for they were in all probability scoundrels of
        the deepest dye, and it was necessary that the colonists should be on their guard against
        them. Although the bridges over the Mercy were raised, the convicts would not be stopped by
        a river or a stream and, rendered desperate, these wretches would be capable of
        anything.</p><p>They would see later what plan it would be best to follow; but in the meantime it was
        necessary to mount guard over cases and packages heaped up near the Chimneys, and thus the
        settlers employed themselves in turn during the night.</p><p>The morning came, however, without the convicts having attempted any attack. Master Jup and
        Top, on guard at the foot of Granite House, would have quickly given the alarm. The three
        following day--the 19th, 20th, and 21st of October--were employed in saving everything of
        value, or of any use whatever, either from the cargo or rigging of the brig. At low tide
        they overhauled the hold--at high tide they stowed away the rescued articles. A great part
        of the copper sheathing had been torn from the hull, which every day sank lower. But before
        the sand had swallowed the heavy things which had fallen through the bottom, Ayrton and
        Pencroft, diving to the bed of the channel, recovered the chains and anchors of the brig,
        the iron of her ballast, and even four guns, which, floated by means of empty casks, were
        brought to shore.</p><p>It may be seen that the arsenal of the colony had gained by the wreck, as well as the
        storerooms of Granite House. Pencroft, always enthusiastic in his projects, already spoke of
        constructing a battery to command the channel and the mouth of the river. With four guns, he
        engaged to prevent any fleet, "however powerful it might be," from venturing into the waters
        of Lincoln Island!</p><p>In the meantime, when nothing remained of the brig but a useless hulk, bad weather came on,
        which soon finished her. Cyrus Harding had intended to blow her up, so as to collect the
        remains on the shore, but a strong gale from the northeast and a heavy sea compelled him to
        economize his powder.</p><p>In fact, on the night of the 23rd, the hull entirely broke up, and some of the wreck was
        cast up on the beach.</p><p>As to the papers on board, it is useless to say that, although he carefully searched the
        lockers of the poop, Harding did not discover any trace of them. The pirates had evidently
        destroyed everything that concerned either the captain or the owners of the "Speedy," and,
        as the name of her port was not painted on her counter, there was nothing which would tell
        them her nationality. However, by the shape of her boats Ayrton and Pencroft believed that
        the brig was of English build.</p><p>A week after the castrophe--or, rather, after the fortunate, though inexplicable, event to
        which the colony owed its preservation--nothing more could be seen of the vessel, even at
        low tide. The wreck had disappeared, and Granite House was enriched by nearly all it had
        contained.</p><p>However, the mystery which enveloped its strange destruction would doubtless never have
        been cleared away if, on the 30th of November, Neb, strolling on the beach, had not found a
        piece of a thick iron cylinder, bearing traces of explosion. The edges of this cylinder were
        twisted and broken, as if they had been subjected to the action of some explosive
        substance.</p><p>Neb brought this piece of metal to his master, who was then occupied with his companions in
        the workshop of the Chimneys.</p><p>Cyrus Harding examined the cylinder attentively, then, turning to Pencroft,--</p><p>"You persist, my friend," said he, "in maintaining that the 'Speedy' was not lost in
        consequence of a collision?"</p><p>"Yes, captain," answered the sailor. "You know as well as I do that there are no rocks in
        the channel."</p><p>"But suppose she had run against this piece of iron?" said the engineer, showing the broken
        cylinder.</p><p>"What, that bit of pipe!" exclaimed Pencroft in a tone of perfect incredulity.</p><p>"My friends," resumed Harding, "you remember that before she foundered the brig rose on the
        summit of a regular waterspout?"</p><p>"Yes, captain," replied Herbert.</p><p>"Well, would you like to know what occasioned that waterspout? It was this," said the
        engineer, holding up the broken tube.</p><p>"That?" returned Pencroft.</p><p>"Yes! This cylinder is all that remains of a torpedo!"</p><p>"A torpedo!" exclaimed the engineer's companions.</p><p>"And who put the torpedo there?" demanded Pencroft, who did not like to yield.</p><p>"All that I can tell you is, that it was not I," answered Cyrus Harding; "but it was there,
        and you have been able to judge of its incomparable power!"</p><p/></body></topic>