<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="chapter_06">
   <title>
      <ph outputclass="title-line">V</ph> 
      <ph outputclass="title-line">THE ASCENT OF MAN</ph> 
   </title>
   <body><!--hr--></body>
   <topic id="d1e5092">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE ASCENT OF MAN</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 1</p>
         <p>No one thinks less of Sir Isaac Newton because he was born as a very puny
 infant, and no one should think less of the human race because it sprang from
 a stock of arboreal mammals. There is no doubt as to man's apartness from
 the rest of creation when he is seen at his best—"a little lower
 than the angels, crowned with glory and honour." "What a piece of
 work is a man! How noble in reason! How infinite in faculty! in form and
 moving how express and admirable! in action how like an angel! in
 apprehension so like a God." Nevertheless, all the facts point to his
 affiliation to the stock to which monkeys and apes also belong. Not, indeed,
 that man is descended from any living ape or monkey; it is rather that he and
 they have sprung from a common ancestry—are branches of the same stem.
 This conclusion is so momentous that the reasons for accepting it must be
 carefully considered. They were expounded with masterly skill in Darwin's
 <i>Descent of Man</i> in 1871—a book which was but an expansion of a
 chapter in <i>The Origin of Species</i> (1859).</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e5105">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Anatomical Proof of Man's Relationship with a Simian
 Stock</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The anatomical structure of man is closely similar to that of the
 anthropoid apes—the gorilla, the orang, the chimpanzee, and the gibbon.
 Bone for bone, muscle for muscle, blood-vessel for blood-vessel, nerve for
 nerve, man and ape agree. As the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 156]</ph> conservative anatomist, Sir Richard Owen,
 said, there is between them "an all-pervading similitude of
 structure." Differences, of course, there are, but they are not
 momentous except man's big brain, which may be three times as heavy as
 that of a gorilla. The average human brain weighs about 48 ounces; the
 gorilla brain does not exceed 20 ounces at its best. The capacity of the
 human skull is never less than 55 cubic inches; in the orang and the
 chimpanzee the figures are 26 and 27½ respectively. We are not suggesting
 that the most distinctive features of man are such as can be measured and
 weighed, but it is important to notice that the main seat of his mental
 powers is physically far ahead of that of the highest of the anthropoid
 apes.</p>
            <p>Man alone is thoroughly erect after his infancy is past; his head weighted
 with the heavy brain does not droop forward as the ape's does; with his
 erect attitude there is perhaps to be associated his more highly developed
 vocal organs. Compared with an anthropoid ape, man has a bigger and more
 upright forehead, a less protrusive face region, smaller cheek-bones and
 eyebrow ridges, and more uniform teeth. He is almost unique in having a chin.
 Man plants the sole of his foot flat on the ground, his big toe is usually in
 a line with the other toes, and he has a better heel than any monkey has. The
 change in the shape of the head is to be thought of in connection with the
 enlargement of the brain, and also in connection with the natural reduction
 of the muzzle region when the hand was freed from being an organ of support
 and became suited for grasping the food and conveying it to the mouth.</p>
            <p>Everyone is familiar in man's clothing with traces of the past
 persisting in the present, though their use has long since disappeared. There
 are buttons on the back of the waist of the morning coat to which the tails
 of the coat used to be fastened up, and there are buttons, occasionally with
 buttonholes, at the wrist which were once useful in turning up the sleeve.
 The same is true of man's body, which is a veritable museum of relics.
 Some<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 157]</ph> anatomists have made out a list of over a hundred of these
 <i>vestigial</i> structures, and though this number is perhaps too high,
 there is no doubt that the list is long. In the inner upper corner of the eye
 there is a minute tag—but larger in some races than in
 others—which is the last dwindling relic of the third eyelid, used in
 cleaning the front of the eye, which most mammals possess in a large and
 well-developed form. It can be easily seen, for instance, in ox and rabbit.
 In man and in monkeys it has become a useless vestige, and the dwindling must
 be associated with the fact that the upper eyelid is much more mobile in man
 and monkeys than in the other mammals. The vestigial third eyelid in man is
 enough of itself to prove his relationship with the mammals, but it is only
 one example out of many. Some of these are discussed in the article dealing
 with the human body, but we may mention the vestigial muscles going to the
 ear-trumpet, man's dwindling counterpart of the skin-twitching muscle
 which we see a horse use when he jerks a fly off his flanks, and the short
 tail which in the seven-weeks-old human embryo is actually longer than the
 leg. Without committing ourselves to a belief in the entire uselessness of
 the vermiform appendix, which grows out as a blind alley at the junction of
 the small intestine with the large, we are safe in saying that it is a
 dwindling structure—the remains of a blind gut which must have been
 capacious and useful in ancestral forms. In some mammals, like the rabbit,
 the blind gut is the bulkiest structure in the body, and bears the vermiform
 appendix at its far end. In man the appendix alone is left, and it tells its
 tale. It is interesting to notice that it is usually longer in the orang than
 in man, and that it is very variable, as dwindling structures tend to be. One
 of the unpleasant expressions of this variability is the liability to go
 wrong: hence appendicitis. Now these vestigial structures are, as Darwin
 said, like the unsounded, i.e. functionless, letters in words, such as the
 <i>o</i> in "leopard," the <i>b</i> in "doubt," the
 <i>g</i> in "reign." They are of no use, but they tell us something
 of the history of the words. So do man's vestigial<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 158]</ph> structures
 reveal his pedigree. They must have an historical or evolutionary
 significance. No other interpretation is possible.</p>
            <fig id="image250a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: New York Zoological Park.</i>
               </p>

               <p>CHIMPANZEE, SITTING</p>

               <p>The head shows certain facial characteristics, e.g. the
   beetling eyebrow ridges, which were marked in the Neanderthal race of men.
   Note the shortening of the thumb and the enlargement of the big toe.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image250a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>CHIMPANZEE, SITTING</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image250b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: New York Zoological Park.</i>
               </p>

               <p>CHIMPANZEE, ILLUSTRATING WALKING POWERS</p>

               <p>Note the great length of the arms and the relative shortness of the
   legs.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image250b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>CHIMPANZEE, ILLUSTRATING WALKING POWERS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image251a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>SURFACE VIEW OF THE BRAINS OF MAN (1) AND CHIMPANZEE (2)</p>

               <p>The human brain is much larger and heavier, more dome-like,
   and with much more numerous and complicated convolutions.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image251a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SURFACE VIEW OF THE BRAINS OF MAN (1) AND CHIMPANZEE (2)</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image251b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: New York Zoological Park.</i>
               </p>

               <p>SIDE-VIEW OF CHIMPANZEE'S HEAD.</p>

               <p>(Compare with opposite picture.)</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image251b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SPECTROSCOPE IS AN INSTRUMENT FOR ANALYSING LIGHT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image251b1"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>After a model by J. H. McGregor.</i>
               </p>

               <p>PROFILE VIEW OF HEAD OF PITHECANTHROPUS, THE JAVA APE MAN, RECONSTRUCTED
   FROM THE SKULL-CAP.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image251b1_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROFILE VIEW OF HEAD OF PITHECANTHROPUS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image251c">
               <image href="images/image251c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE FLIPPER OF A WHALE AND THE HAND OF A MAN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="d1e5238"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE FLIPPER OF A WHALE AND THE HAND OF A MAN</p>

               <p>In the bones and in their arrangement there is a close
   resemblance in the two cases, yet the outcome is very different. The
   multiplication of finger joints in the whale is a striking feature.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image251c1_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE FLIPPER OF A WHALE AND THE HAND OF A MAN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>Some men, oftener than women, show on the inturned margin of the
 ear-trumpet or pinna, a little conical projection of great interest. It is a
 vestige of the tip of the pointed ear of lower mammals, and it is well named
 <i>Darwin's point</i>. It was he who described it as a "surviving
 symbol of the stirring times and dangerous days of man's animal
 youth."</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 2</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e5260">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Physiological Proof of Man's Relationship with a Simian
 Stock</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The everyday functions of the human body are practically the same as those
 of the anthropoid ape, and similar disorders are common to both. Monkeys may
 be infected with certain microbes to which man is peculiarly liable, such as
 the bacillus of tuberculosis. Darwin showed that various human gestures and
 facial expressions have their counterparts in monkeys. The sneering curl of
 the upper lip, which tends to expose the canine tooth, is a case in point,
 though it may be seen in many other mammals besides monkeys—in dogs,
 for instance, which are at some considerable distance from the simian branch
 to which man's ancestors belonged.</p>
            <p>When human blood is transfused into a dog or even a monkey, it behaves in
 a hostile way to the other blood, bringing about a destruction of the red
 blood corpuscles. But when it is transfused into a chimpanzee there is an
 harmonious mingling of the two. This is a very literal demonstration of
 man's blood-relationship with the higher apes. But there is a finer form
 of the same experiment. When the blood-fluid (or serum) of a rabbit, which
 has had human blood injected into it, is mingled with human blood, it forms a
 cloudy precipitate. It forms almost as marked a precipitate when it is
 mingled with the blood of an anthropoid ape. But when it is mingled with the
 blood of an American monkey<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 159]</ph> there is only a slight clouding after a
 considerable time and no actual precipitate. When it is added to the blood of
 one of the distantly related "half-monkeys" or lemurs there is no
 reaction or only a very weak one. With the blood of mammals off the simian
 line altogether there is no reaction at all. Thus, as a distinguished
 anthropologist, Professor Schwalbe, has said: "We have in this not only
 a proof of the literal blood-relationship between man and apes, but the
 degree of relationship with the different main groups of apes can be
 determined beyond possibility of mistake." We can imagine how this
 modern line of experiment would have delighted Darwin.</p>
            <fig id="image254"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE GORILLA, INHABITING THE FOREST TRACT OF THE GABOON IN AFRICA</p>

               <p>A full-grown individual stands about 5 feet high. The gait
   is shuffling, the strength enormous, the diet mainly vegetarian, the temper
   rather ferocious.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image254_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE GORILLA, INHABITING THE FOREST TRACT OF THE GABOON IN AFRICA</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e5286">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Embryological Proof of Man's Relationship with a Simian
 Stock</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>In his individual development, man does in some measure climb up his own
 genealogical tree. Stages in the development of the body during its nine
 months of ante-natal life are closely similar to stages in the development of
 the anthropoid embryo. Babies born in times of famine or siege are sometimes,
 as it were, imperfectly finished, and sometimes have what may be described as
 monkeyish features and ways. A visit to an institution for the care of
 children who show arrested, defective, or disturbed development leaves one
 sadly impressed with the risk of slipping down the rungs of the steep ladder
 of evolution; and even in adults the occurrence of serious nervous
 disturbance, such as "shell-shock," is sometimes marked by relapses
 to animal ways. It is a familiar fact that a normal baby reveals the past in
 its surprising power of grip, and the careful experiments of Dr. Louis
 Robinson showed that an infant three weeks old could support its own weight
 for over two minutes, holding on to a horizontal bar. "In many cases no
 sign of distress is evinced and no cry uttered, until the grasp begins to
 give way." This persistent grasp probably points back to the time when
 the baby had to cling to its arboreal mother. The human tail is represented
 in the adult by a fusion of four or five vertebræ forming the
 "coccyx" at the end of the backbone,<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 160]</ph> and is normally concealed
 beneath the flesh, but in the embryo the tail projects freely and is movable.
 Up to the sixth month of the ante-natal sleep the body is covered, all but
 the palms and soles, with longish hair (the lanugo), which usually disappears
 before birth. This is a stage in the normal development, which is reasonably
 interpreted as a recapitulation of a stage in the racial evolution. We draw
 this inference when we find that the unborn offspring of an almost hairless
 whale has an abundant representation of hairs; we must draw a similar
 inference in the case of man.</p>
            <p>It must be noticed that there are two serious errors in the careless
 statement often made that man in his development is at one time like a little
 fish, at a later stage like a little reptile, at a later stage like a little
 primitive mammal, and eventually like a little monkey. The first error here
 is that the comparison should be made with <i>embryo</i>-fish,
 <i>embryo</i>-reptile, <i>embryo</i>-mammal, and so on. It is in the making
 of the embryos that the great resemblance lies. When the human embryo shows
 the laying down of the essential vertebrate characters, such as brain and
 spinal cord, then it is closely comparable to the embryo of a lower
 vertebrate at a similar stage. When, at a subsequent stage, its heart, for
 instance, is about to become a four-chambered mammalian heart, it is closely
 comparable to the heart of, let us say, a turtle, which never becomes more
 than three-chambered. The point is that in the making of the organs of the
 body, say brain and kidneys, the embryo of man pursues a path closely
 corresponding to the path followed by the embryos of other backboned animals
 lower in the scale, but at successive stages it parts company with these,
 with the lowest first and so on in succession. A human embryo is never like a
 little reptile, but the developing organs pass through stages which very
 closely resemble the corresponding stages in lower types which are in a
 general way ancestral.</p>
            <p>The second error is that every kind of animal, man included,<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 161]</ph> has from the
 first a certain individuality, with peculiar characteristics which are all
 its own. This is expressed by the somewhat difficult word <i>specificity</i>,
 which just means that every species is itself and no other. So in the
 development of the human embryo, while there are close resemblances to the
 embryos of apes, monkeys, other mammals, and even, at earlier stages still,
 to the embryos of reptile and fish, it has to be admitted that we are dealing
 from first to last with a human embryo with peculiarities of its own.</p>
            <fig id="image258"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>"DARWIN'S POINT" ON HUMAN EAR (MARKED D.P.)</p>

               <p>It corresponds to the tip (T) of the ear of an ordinary
   mammal, as shown in the hare's ear below. In the young orang the part
   corresponding to Darwin's point is still at the tip of the ear.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image258_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>'DARWIN'S POINT' ON HUMAN EAR</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image259a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: J. Russell &amp; Sons.</i>
               </p>

               <p>PROFESSOR SIR ARTHUR KEITH, M.D., LL.D., F.R.S.</p>

               <p>Conservator of the Museum and Hunterian Professor, Royal
   College of Surgeons of England. One of the foremost living anthropologists
   and a leading authority on the antiquity of man.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image259a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROFESSOR SIR ARTHUR KEITH</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image259b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>After T. H. Huxley (by permission of Messrs. Macmillan).</i>
               </p>

               <p>SKELETONS OF THE GIBBON, ORANG, CHIMPANZEE, GORILLA, MAN</p>

               <p>Photographically reduced from diagrams of the natural size
   (except that of the gibbon, which was twice as large as nature) drawn by
   Mr. Waterhouse Hawkins from specimens in the Museum of the Royal College of
   Surgeons.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image259b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SKELETONS OF THE GIBBON, ORANG, CHIMPANZEE, GORILLA, MAN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>Every human being begins his or her life as a single cell—a
 fertilised egg-cell, a treasure-house of all the ages. For in this living
 microcosm, only a small fraction (1/125) of an inch in diameter, there is
 condensed—who can imagine how?—all the natural inheritance of
 man, all the legacy of his parentage, of his ancestry, of his long pre-human
 pedigree. Darwin called the pinhead brain of the ant the most marvellous atom
 of matter in the world, but the human ovum is more marvellous still. It has
 more possibilities in it than any other thing, yet without fertilisation it
 will die. The fertilised ovum divides and redivides; there results a ball of
 cells and a sack of cells; gradually division of labour becomes the rule;
 there is a laying down of nervous system and food-canal, muscular system and
 skeleton, and so proceeds what is learnedly called differentiation. Out of
 the apparently simple there emerges the obviously complex. As Aristotle
 observed more than two thousand years ago, in the developing egg of the hen
 there soon appears the beating heart! There is nothing like this in the
 non-living world. But to return to the developing human embryo, there is
 formed from and above the embryonic food-canal a skeletal rod, which is
 called the notochord. It thrills the imagination to learn that this is the
 only supporting axis that the lower orders of the backboned race possess. The
 curious thing is that it does not become the backbone, which is certainly one
 of the essential features of the vertebrate race. The notochord is the
 supporting axis of the pioneer backboned animals,<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 162]</ph> namely the
 Lancelets and the Round-mouths (Cyclostomes), such as the Lamprey. They have
 no backbone in the strict sense, but they have this notochord. It can easily
 be dissected out in the lamprey—a long gristly rod. It is surrounded by
 a sheath which becomes the backbone of most fishes and of all higher animals.
 The interesting point is that although the notochord is only a vestige in the
 adults of these types, it is never absent from the embryo. It occurs even in
 man, a short-lived relic of the primeval supporting axis of the body. It
 comes and then it goes, leaving only minute traces in the adult. We cannot
 say that it is of any use, unless it serves as a stimulus to the development
 of its substitute, the backbone. It is only a piece of preliminary
 scaffolding, but there is no more eloquent instance of the living hand of the
 past.</p>
            <p>One other instance must suffice of what Professor Lull calls the wonderful
 changes wrought in the dark of the ante-natal period, which recapitulate in
 rapid abbreviation the great evolutionary steps which were taken by man's
 ancestors "during the long night of the geological past." On the
 sides of the neck of the human embryo there are four pairs of slits, the
 "visceral clefts," openings from the beginning of the food-canals
 to the surface. There is no doubt as to their significance. They correspond
 to the gill-slits of fishes and tadpoles. Yet in reptiles, birds, and mammals
 they have no connection with breathing, which is their function in fishes and
 amphibians. Indeed, they are not of any use at all, except that the first
 becomes the Eustachian tube bringing the ear-passage into connection with the
 back of the mouth, and that the second and third have to do with the
 development of a curious organ called the thymus gland. Persistent,
 nevertheless, these gill-slits are, recalling even in man an aquatic ancestry
 of many millions of years ago.</p>
            <p>When all these lines of evidence are considered, they are seen to converge
 in the conclusion that man is derived from a simian<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 163]</ph> stock of
 mammals. He is solidary with the rest of creation. To quote the closing words
 of Darwin's <i>Descent of Man</i>:</p>
            <lq>
               <p>We must, however, acknowledge, as it seems to me, that man with all his
  noble qualities, with sympathy which feels for the most debased, with
  benevolence which extends not only to other men but to the humblest living
  creature, with his God-like intellect, which has penetrated into the
  movements and constitution of the solar system—with all these exalted
  powers—man still bears in his bodily frame the indelible stamp of his
  lowly origin.</p>
            </lq>
            <p>We should be clear that this view does not say more than that man sprang
 from a stock common to him and to the higher apes. Those who are repelled by
 the idea of man's derivation from a simian type should remember that the
 theory implies rather more than this, namely, that man is the outcome of a
 genealogy which has implied many millions of years of experimenting and
 sifting—the groaning and travailing of a whole creation. Speaking of
 man's mental qualities, Sir Ray Lankester says: "They justify the
 view that man forms a new departure in the gradual unfolding of Nature's
 predestined plan." In any case, we have to try to square our views with
 the facts, not the facts with our views, and while one of the facts is that
 man stands unique and apart, the other is that man is a scion of a
 progressive simian stock. Naturalists have exposed the pit whence man has
 been digged and the rock whence he has been hewn, but it is surely a
 heartening encouragement to know that it is an ascent, not a descent, that we
 have behind us. There is wisdom in Pascal's maxim:</p>
            <lq>
               <p>It is dangerous to show man too plainly how like he is to the animals,
  without, at the same time, reminding him of his greatness. It is equally
  unwise to impress him with his greatness and not with his lowliness. It is
  worse to leave him in ignorance of both. But it is very profitable to
  recognise the two facts.</p>
            </lq>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 164]</ph>
            </p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 3</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e5406">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Man's Pedigree</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The facts of anatomy, physiology, and embryology, of which we have given
 illustrations, all point to man's affiliation with the order of monkeys
 and apes. To this order is given the name Primates, and our first and second
 question must be when and whence the Primates began. The rock record answers
 the first question: the Primates emerged about the dawn of the Eocene era,
 when grass was beginning to cover the earth with a garment. Their ancestral
 home was in the north in both hemispheres, and then they migrated to Africa,
 India, Malay, and South America. In North America the Primates soon became
 extinct, and the same thing happened later on in Europe. In this case,
 however, there was a repeopling from the South (in the Lower Miocene) and
 then a second extinction (in the Upper Pliocene) before man appeared. There
 is considerable evidence in support of Professor R. S. Lull's conclusion,
 that in Southern Asia, Africa, and South America the evolution of Primates
 was continuous since the first great southward migration, and there is, of
 course, an abundant modern representation of Primates in these regions
 to-day.</p>
            <p>As to the second question: Whence the Primates sprang, the answer must be
 more conjectural. But it is a reasonable view that Carnivores and Primates
 sprang from a common Insectivore stock, the one order diverging towards
 flesh-eating and hunting on the ground, the other order diverging towards
 fruit-eating and arboreal habits. There is no doubt that the Insectivores
 (including shrews, tree-shrews, hedgehog, mole, and the like) were very
 plastic and progressive mammals.</p>
            <p>What followed in the course of ages was the divergence of branch after
 branch from the main Primate stem. First there diverged the South American
 monkeys on a line of their own, and then the Old World monkeys, such as the
 macaques and<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 165]</ph> baboons. Ages passed and the main stems gave off (in the
 Oligocene period) the branch now represented by the small anthropoid
 apes—the gibbon and the siamang. Distinctly later there diverged the
 branch of the large anthropoid apes—the gorilla, the chimpanzee, and
 the orang. That left a generalised humanoid stock separated off from all
 monkeys and apes, and including the immediate precursors of man. When this
 sifting out of a generalised humanoid stock took place remains very
 uncertain, some authorities referring it to the Miocene, others to the early
 Pliocene. Some would estimate its date at half a million years ago, others at
 two millions! The fact is that questions of chronology do not as yet admit of
 scientific statement.</p>
            <fig id="image264a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>SIDE-VIEW OF SKULL OF MAN (M) AND GORILLA (G)</p>

               <p>Notice in the gorilla's skull the protrusive face
   region, the big eyebrow ridges, the much less domed cranial cavity, the
   massive lower jaw, the big canine teeth. Notice in man's skull the
   well-developed forehead, the domed and spacious cranial cavity, the absence
   of any snout, the chin process, and many other marked differences
   separating the human skull from the ape's.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image264a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SIDE-VIEW OF SKULL OF MAN (M) AND GORILLA (G)</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image264b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE SKULL AND BRAIN-CASE OF PITHECANTHROPUS, THE JAVA APE-MAN, AS
   RESTORED. BY J. H. McGREGOR FROM THE SCANTY REMAINS</p>

               <p>The restoration shows the low, retreating forehead and the
   prominent eyebrow ridges.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image264b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SKULL AND BRAIN-CASE OF PITHECANTHROPUS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image265"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>SUGGESTED GENEALOGICAL TREE OF MAN AND ANTHROPOID APES</p>

               <p>From Sir Arthur Keith; the lettering to the right has been slightly
   simplified.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image265_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SUGGESTED GENEALOGICAL TREE OF MAN AND ANTHROPOID APES</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>We are on firmer, though still uncertain, ground when we state the
 probability that it was in Asia that the precursors of man were separated off
 from monkeys and apes, and began to be terrestrial rather than arboreal.
 Professor Lull points out that Asia is nearest to the oldest known human
 remains (in Java), and that Asia was the seat of the most ancient
 civilisations and the original home of many domesticated animals and
 cultivated plants. The probability is that the cradle of the human race was
 in Asia.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e5469">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Man's Arboreal Apprenticeship</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>At this point it will be useful to consider man's arboreal
 apprenticeship and how he became a terrestrial journeyman. Professor Wood
 Jones has worked out very convincingly the thesis that man had no direct
 four-footed ancestry, but that the Primate stock to which he belongs was from
 its first divergence arboreal. He maintains that the leading peculiarities of
 the immediate precursors of man were wrought out during a long arboreal
 apprenticeship. The first great gain of arboreal life on bipedal erect lines
 (not after the quadrupedal fashion of tree-sloths, for instance) was the
 emancipation of the hand. The foot<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 166]</ph> became the supporting and branch-gripping
 member, and the hand was set free to reach upward, to hang on by, to seize
 the fruit, to lift it and hold it to the mouth, and to hug the young one
 close to the breast. The hand thus set free has remained plastic—a
 generalised, not a specialised member. Much has followed from man's
 "handiness."</p>
            <p>The arboreal life had many other consequences. It led to an increased
 freedom of movement of the thigh on the hip joint, to muscular arrangements
 for balancing the body on the leg, to making the backbone a supple yet stable
 curved pillar, to a strongly developed collar-bone which is only found
 well-formed when the fore-limb is used for more than support, and to a power
 of "opposing" the thumb and the big toe to the other digits of the
 hand and foot—an obvious advantage for branch-gripping. But the
 evolution of a free hand made it possible to dispense with protrusive lips
 and gripping teeth. Thus began the recession of the snout region, the
 associated enlargement of the brain-box, and the bringing of the eyes to the
 front. The overcrowding of the teeth that followed the shortening of the
 snout was one of the taxes on progress of which modern man is often reminded
 in his dental troubles.</p>
            <p>Another acquisition associated with arboreal life was a greatly increased
 power of turning the head from side to side—a mobility very important
 in locating sounds and in exploring with the eyes. Furthermore, there came
 about a flattening of the chest and of the back, and the movements of the
 midriff (or diaphragm) came to count for more in respiration than the
 movements of the ribs. The sense of touch came to be of more importance and
 the sense of smell of less; the part of the brain receiving tidings from hand
 and eye and ear came to predominate over the part for receiving olfactory
 messages. Finally, the need for carrying the infant about among the branches
 must surely have implied an intensification of family relations, and favoured
 the evolution of gentleness.</p>
            <fig id="image268a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: New York Zoological Park.</i>
               </p>

               <p>THE GIBBON IS LOWER THAN THE OTHER APES AS REGARDS ITS SKULL AND
   DENTITION, BUT IT IS HIGHLY SPECIALIZED IN THE ADAPTATION OF ITS LIMBS TO
   ARBOREAL LIFE</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image268a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE GIBBON IS LOWER THAN THE OTHER APES AS REGARDS ITS SKULL AND DENTITION</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image268b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: New York Zoological Park.</i>
               </p>

               <p>THE ORANG HAS A HIGH ROUNDED SKULL AND A LONG FACE</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image268b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE ORANG HAS A HIGH ROUNDED SKULL AND A LONG FACE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image269"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: British Museum (Natural History).</i>
               </p>

               <p>COMPARISONS OF THE SKELETONS OF HORSE AND MAN</p>

               <p>Bone for bone, the two skeletons are like one another,
   though man is a biped and the horse a quadruped. The backbone in man is
   mainly vertical; the backbone in the horse is horizontal except in the neck
   and the tail. Man's skull is mainly in a line with the backbone; the
   horse's at an angle to it. Both man and horse have seven neck vertebræ.
   Man has five digits on each limb; the horse has only one digit well
   developed on each limb.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image269_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>COMPARISONS OF THE SKELETONS OF HORSE AND MAN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 167]</ph>
            </p>
            <p>It may be urged that we are attaching too much importance to the arboreal
 apprenticeship, since many tree-loving animals remain to-day very innocent
 creatures. To this reasonable objection there are two answers, first that in
 its many acquisitions the arboreal evolution of the <i>humanoid</i>
 precursors of man prepared the way for the survival of a <i>human</i> type
 marked by a great step in brain-development; and second that the passage from
 the humanoid to the human was probably associated with <i>a return to mother
 earth</i>.</p>
            <p>According to Professor Lull, to whose fine textbook, <i>Organic
 Evolution</i> (1917), we are much indebted, "climatic conditions in Asia
 in the Miocene or early Pliocene were such as to compel the descent of the
 pre-human ancestor from the trees, a step which was absolutely essential to
 further human development." Continental elevation and consequent aridity
 led to a dwindling of the forests, and forced the ape-man to come to earth.
 "And at the last arose the man."</p>
            <p>According to Lull, the descent from the trees was associated with the
 assumption of a more erect posture, with increased liberation and plasticity
 of the hand, with becoming a hunter, with experiments towards clothing and
 shelter, with an exploring habit, and with the beginning of communal
 life.</p>
            <p>It is a plausible view that the transition from the humanoid to the human
 was effected by a discontinuous variation of considerable magnitude, what is
 nowadays called a <i>mutation</i>, and that it had mainly to do with the
 brain and the vocal organs. But given the gains of the arboreal
 apprenticeship, the stimulus of an enforced descent to terra firma, and an
 evolving brain and voice, we can recognise accessory factors which helped
 success to succeed. Perhaps the absence of great physical strength prompted
 reliance on wits; the prolongation of infancy would help to educate the
 parents in gentleness; the strengthening of the feeling of kinship would
 favour the evolution of family and social life—of which there are many
 anticipations at lower levels. There is<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 168]</ph> much truth in the saying:
 "Man did not make society, society made man."</p>
            <p>A continuation of the story will deal with the emergence of the primitive
 types of man and the gradual ascent of the modern species.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 4</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e5572">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Tentative Men</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>So far the story has been that of the sifting out of a humanoid stock and
 of the transition to human kind, from the ancestors of apes and men to the
 man-ape, and from the man-ape to man. It looks as if the sifting-out process
 had proceeded further, for there were several human branches that did not
 lead on to the modern type of man.</p>
            <p>1. The first of these is represented by the scanty fossil remains known as
 <i>Pithecanthropus erectus</i>, found in Java in fossiliferous beds which
 date from the end of the Pliocene or the beginning of the Pleistocene era.
 Perhaps this means half a million years ago, and the remains occurred along
 with those of some mammals which are now extinct. Unfortunately the remains
 of Pithecanthropus the Erect consisted only of a skull-cap, a thigh-bone, and
 two back teeth, so it is not surprising that experts should differ
 considerably in their interpretation of what was found. Some have regarded
 the remains as those of a large gibbon, others as those of a pre-human
 ape-man, and others as those of a primitive man off the main line of ascent.
 According to Sir Arthur Keith, Pithecanthropus was "a being human in
 stature, human in gait, human in all its parts, save its brain." The
 thigh-bone indicates a height of about 5 feet 7 inches, one inch less than
 the average height of the men of to-day. The skull-cap indicates a low, flat
 forehead, beetling brows, and a capacity about two-thirds of the modern size.
 The remains were found by Dubois, in 1894, in Trinil in Central Java.</p>
            <p>2. The next offshoot is represented by the Heidelberg man<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 169]</ph> (<i>Homo
 heidelbergensis</i>), discovered near Heidelberg in 1907 by Dr. Schoetensack.
 But the remains consisted only of a lower jaw and its teeth. Along with this
 relic were bones of various mammals, including some long since extinct in
 Europe, such as elephant, rhinoceros, bison, and lion. The circumstances
 indicate an age of perhaps 300,000 years ago. There were also very crude
 flint implements (or eoliths). But the teeth are human teeth, and the jaw
 seems transitional between that of an anthropoid ape and that of man. Thus
 there was no chin. According to most authorities the lower jaw from the
 Heidelberg sand-pit must be regarded as a relic of a primitive type off the
 main line of human ascent.</p>
            <fig id="image272"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>A RECONSTRUCTION OF THE JAVA MAN</p>

               <p>(<i>Pithecanthropus erectus.</i>)</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image272_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A RECONSTRUCTION OF THE JAVA MAN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>3. It was in all probability in the Pliocene that there took origin the
 Neanderthal species of man, <i>Homo neanderthalensis</i>, first known from
 remains found in 1856 in the Neanderthal ravine near Düsseldorf. According to
 some authorities Neanderthal man was living in Europe a quarter of a million
 years ago. Other specimens were afterwards found elsewhere, e.g. in Belgium
 ("the men of Spy"), in France, in Croatia, and at Gibraltar, so
 that a good deal is known of Neanderthal man. He was a loose-limbed fellow,
 short of stature and of slouching gait, but a skilful artificer, fashioning
 beautifully worked flints with a characteristic style. He used fire; he
 buried his dead reverently and furnished them with an outfit for a long
 journey; and he had a big brain. But he had great beetling, ape-like eyebrow
 ridges and massive jaws, and he showed "simian characters swarming in
 the details of his structure." In most of the points in which he differs
 from modern man he approaches the anthropoid apes, and he must be regarded as
 a low type of man off the main line. Huxley regarded the Neanderthal man as a
 low form of the modern type, but expert opinion seems to agree rather with
 the view maintained in 1864 by Professor William King of Galway, that the
 Neanderthal man represents a distinct species off the main line of ascent. He
 disappeared with apparent suddenness (like some aboriginal races to-day)
 about the end of the Fourth Great Ice Age; but<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 170]</ph> there is evidence that before he
 ceased to be there had emerged a successor rather than a descendant—the
 modern man.</p>
            <p>4. Another offshoot from the main line is probably represented by the
 Piltdown man, found in Sussex in 1912. The remains consisted of the walls of
 the skull, which indicate a large brain, and a high forehead without the
 beetling eyebrows of the Neanderthal man and Pithecanthropus. The
 "find" included a tooth and part of a lower jaw, but these perhaps
 belong to some ape, for they are very discrepant. The Piltdown skull
 represents the most ancient human remains as yet found in Britain, and Dr.
 Smith Woodward's establishment of a separate genus Eoanthropus expresses
 his conviction that the Piltdown man was off the line of the evolution of the
 modern type. If the tooth and piece of lower jaw belong to the Piltdown
 skull, then there was a remarkable combination of ape-like and human
 characters. As regards the brain, <i>inferred</i> from the skull-walls, Sir
 Arthur Keith says:</p>
            <lq>
               <p>All the essential features of the brain of modern man are to be seen in
  the brain cast. There are some which must be regarded as primitive. There
  can be no doubt that it is built on exactly the same lines as our modern
  brains. A few minor alterations would make it in all respects a modern
  brain.... Although our knowledge of the human brain is limited—there
  are large areas to which we can assign no definite function—we may
  rest assured that a brain which was shaped in a mould so similar to our own
  was one which responded to the outside world as ours does. Piltdown man saw,
  heard, felt, thought, and dreamt much as we do still.</p>
            </lq>
            <p>And this was 150,000 years ago at a modern estimate, and some would say
 half a million.</p>
            <p>There is neither agreement nor certainty as to the antiquity of man,
 except that the modern type was distinguishable from its collaterals hundreds
 of thousands of years ago. The general impression left is very grand. In
 remote antiquity the Primate<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 171]</ph> stem diverged from the other orders of
 mammals; it sent forth its tentative branches, and the result was a tangle of
 monkeys; ages passed and the monkeys were left behind, while the main stem,
 still probing its way, gave off the Anthropoid apes, both small and large.
 But they too were left behind, and the main line gave off other
 experiments—indications of which we know in Java, at Heidelberg, in the
 Neanderthal, and at Piltdown. None of these lasted or was made perfect. They
 represent <i>tentative</i> men who had their day and ceased to be, our
 predecessors rather than our ancestors. Still, the main stem goes on
 evolving, and who will be bold enough to say what fruit it has yet to
 bear!</p>
            <fig id="image276a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>After a model by J. H. McGregor.</i>
               </p>

               <p>PROFILE VIEW OF THE HEAD OF PITHECANTHROPUS, THE JAVA APE-MAN—AN
   EARLY OFFSHOOT FROM THE MAIN LINE OF MAN'S ASCENT</p>

               <p>The animal remains found along with the skull-cap,
   thigh-bone, and two teeth of Pithecanthropus seem to indicate the lowest
   Pleistocene period, perhaps 500,000 years ago.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image276a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROFILE VIEW OF THE HEAD OF PITHECANTHROPUS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image276b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>From the reconstruction by J. H. McGregor.</i>
               </p>

               <p>PILTDOWN SKULL. THE DARK PARTS ONLY ARE PRESERVED, NAMELY PORTIONS OF
   THE CRANIAL WALLS AND THE NASAL BONES</p>

               <p>Some authorities include a canine tooth and part of the
   lower jaw which were found close by. The remains were found in 1912 in
   Thames gravels in Sussex, and are usually regarded as vastly more ancient
   than those of Neanderthal Man. It has been suggested that Piltdown Man
   lived 100,000 to 150,000 years ago, in the Third Interglacial period.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image276b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PILTDOWN SKULL</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image277"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Reproduced by permission from Osborn's "Men of the Old Stone
   Age."</i>
               </p>

               <p>SAND-PIT AT MAUER, NEAR HEIDELBERG: DISCOVERY SITE OF THE JAW OF
   HEIDELBERG MAN</p>

               <p>
                  <i>a-b.</i> "Newer loess," either of Third
   Interglacial or of Postglacial times.
   <ph outputclass="br"/>
                  <i>b-c.</i> "Older loess" (sandy loess), of the close of Second
   Interglacial times.
   <ph outputclass="br"/>
                  <i>c-f.</i> The "sands of Mauer."
   <ph outputclass="br"/>
                  <i>d-e.</i> An intermediate layer of clay.
   <ph outputclass="br"/>
               </p>

               <p>The white cross (X) indicates the spot at the base of the
   "sands of Mauer" at which the jaw of Heidelberg was
   discovered.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image277_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SAND-PIT AT MAUER, NEAR HEIDELBERG</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e5723">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Primitive Men</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Ancient skeletons of men of the modern type have been found in many
 places, e.g. Combe Capelle in Dordogne, Galley Hill in Kent, Cro-Magnon in
 Périgord, Mentone on the Riviera; and they are often referred to as
 "Cave-men" or "men of the Early Stone Age." They had
 large skulls, high foreheads, well-marked chins, and other features such as
 modern man possesses. They were true men at last—that is to say, like
 ourselves! The spirited pictures they made on the walls of caves in France
 and Spain show artistic sense and skill. Well-finished statuettes
 representing nude female figures are also known. The elaborate burial customs
 point to a belief in life after death. They made stone
 implements—knives, scrapers, gravers, and the like, of the type known
 as Palæolithic, and these show interesting gradations of skill and
 peculiarities of style. The "Cave-men" lived between the third and
 fourth Ice Ages, along with cave-bear, cave-lion, cave-hyæna, mammoth, woolly
 rhinoceros, Irish elk, and other mammals now extinct—taking us back to
 30,000-50,000 years ago, and many would say much more. Some of the
 big-brained skulls of these Palæolithic cave-men show not a single feature
 that could be called primitive. They show teeth which in size and form are
 exactly the same as those of a thousand generations<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 172]</ph>
 afterwards—and suffering from gumboil too! There seems little doubt
 that these vigorous Palæolithic Cave-men of Europe were living for a while
 contemporaneously with the men of Neanderthal, and it is possible that they
 directly or indirectly hastened the disappearance of their more primitive
 collaterals. Curiously enough, however, they had not themselves adequate
 lasting power in Europe, for they seem for the most part to have dwindled
 away, leaving perhaps stray present-day survivors in isolated districts. The
 probability is that after their decline Europe was repeopled by immigrants
 from Asia. It cannot be said that there is any inherent biological necessity
 for the decline of a vigorous race—many animal races go back for
 millions of years—but in mankind the historical fact is that a period
 of great racial vigour and success is often followed by a period of decline,
 sometimes leading to practical disappearance as a definite race. The causes
 of this waning remain very obscure—sometimes environmental, sometimes
 constitutional, sometimes competitive. Sometimes the introduction of a new
 parasite, like the malaria organism, may have been to blame.</p>
            <p>After the Ice Ages had passed, perhaps 25,000 years ago, the Palæolithic
 culture gave place to the Neolithic. The men who made rudely dressed but
 often beautiful stone implements were succeeded or replaced by men who made
 polished stone implements. The earliest inhabitants of Scotland were of this
 Neolithic culture, migrating from the Continent when the ice-fields of the
 Great Glaciation had disappeared. Their remains are often associated with the
 "Fifty-foot Beach" which, though now high and dry, was the seashore
 in early Neolithic days. Much is known about these men of the polished
 stones. They were hunters, fowlers, and fishermen; without domesticated
 animals or agriculture; short folk, two or three inches below the present
 standard; living an active strenuous life. Similarly, for the south, Sir
 Arthur Keith pictures for us a Neolithic community at Coldrum in Kent, dating
 from about 4,000 years ago—a few ticks of the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 173]</ph> geological
 clock. It consisted, in this case, of agricultural pioneers, men with large
 heads and big brains, about two inches shorter in stature than the modern
 British average (5 ft. 8 in.), with better teeth and broader palates than men
 have in these days of soft food, with beliefs concerning life and death
 similar to those that swayed their contemporaries in Western and Southern
 Europe. Very interesting is the manipulative skill they showed on a large
 scale in erecting standing stones (probably connected with calendar-keeping
 and with worship), and on a small scale in making daring operations on the
 skull. Four thousand years ago is given as a probable date for that early
 community in Kent, but evidences of Neolithic man occur in situations which
 demand a much greater antiquity—perhaps 30,000 years. And man was not
 young then!</p>
            <fig id="image280"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>PAINTINGS ON THE ROOF OF THE ALTAMIRA CAVE IN NORTHERN SPAIN, SHOWING A
   BISON ABOVE AND A GALLOPING BOAR BELOW</p>

               <p>The artistic drawings, over 2 feet in length, were made by
   the Reindeer Men or "Cromagnards" in the time of the Upper or
   Post-Glacial Pleistocene, before the appearance of the Neolithic men.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image280_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PAINTINGS ON THE ROOF OF THE ALTAMIRA CAVE IN NORTHERN SPAIN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>We must open one more chapter in the thrilling story of the Ascent of
 Man—the Metal Ages, which are in a sense still continuing. Metals began
 to be used in the late Polished Stone (Neolithic) times, for there were
 always overlappings. Copper came first, Bronze second, and Iron last. The
 working of copper in the East has been traced back to the fourth millennium
 <ph outputclass="smcap">B.C.</ph>, and there was also a very ancient Copper Age
 in the New World. It need hardly be said that where copper is scarce, as in
 Britain, we cannot expect to find much trace of a Copper Age.</p>
            <p>The ores of different metals seem to have been smelted together in an
 experimental way by many prehistoric metallurgists, and bronze was the alloy
 that rewarded the combination of tin with copper. There is evidence of a more
 or less definite Bronze Age in Egypt and Babylonia, Greece and Europe.</p>
            <p>It is not clear why iron should not have been the earliest metal to be
 used by man, but the Iron Age dates from about the middle of the second
 millennium <ph outputclass="smcap">B.C.</ph> From Egypt the usage spread
 through the Mediterranean region to North Europe, or it may have been that
 discoveries made in Central Europe, so rich in iron-mines, saturated
 southwards, following for instance, the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 174]</ph> route of the amber trade from
 the Baltic. Compared with stone, the metals afforded much greater
 possibilities of implements, instruments, and weapons, and their discovery
 and usage had undoubtedly great influence on the Ascent of Man. Occasionally,
 however, on his descent.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e5769">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Retrospect</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Looking backwards, we discern the following stages: (1) The setting apart
 of a Primate stock, marked off from other mammals by a tendency to big
 brains, a free hand, gregariousness, and good-humoured talkativeness. (2) The
 divergence of marmosets and New World monkeys and Old World monkeys, leaving
 a stock—an anthropoid stock—common to the present-day and extinct
 apes and to mankind. (3) From this common stock the Anthropoid apes diverged,
 far from ignoble creatures, and a humanoid stock was set apart. (4) From the
 latter (we follow Sir Arthur Keith and other authorities) there arose what
 may be called, without disparagement, tentative or experimental men,
 indicated by Pithecanthropus "the Erect," the Heidelberg man, the
 Neanderthalers, and, best of all, the early men of the Sussex
 Weald—hinted at by the Piltdown skull. It matters little whether
 particular items are corroborated or disproved—e.g. whether the
 Heidelberg man came before or after the Neanderthalers—the general
 trend of evolution remains clear. (5) In any case, the result was the
 evolution of <i>Homo sapiens, the man we are</i>—a quite different
 fellow from the Neanderthaler. (6) Then arose various stocks of primitive
 men, proving everything and holding fast to that which is good. There were
 the Palæolithic peoples, with rude stone implements, a strong vigorous race,
 but probably, in most cases, supplanted by fresh experiments. These may have
 arisen as shoots from the growing point of the old race, or as a fresh
 offshoot from more generalised members at a lower level. This is the eternal
 possible victory alike of aristocracy and democracy. (7) Palæolithic men were
 involved in the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 175]</ph> succession of four Great Ice Ages or Glaciations, and it may
 be that the human race owes much to the alternation of hard times and easy
 times—glacial and interglacial. When the ice-fields cleared off
 Neolithic man had his innings. (8) And we have closed the story, in the
 meantime, with the Metal Ages.</p>
            <fig id="image284"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>After the restoration modelled by J. H. McGregor.</i>
               </p>

               <p>PILTDOWN MAN, PRECEDING NEANDERTHAL MAN, PERHAPS 100,000 TO 150,000
   YEARS AGO</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image284_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PILTDOWN MAN, PRECEDING NEANDERTHAL MAN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image285"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>After the restoration modelled by J. H. McGregor.</i>
               </p>

               <p>THE NEANDERTHAL MAN OF LA CHAPELLE-AUX-SAINTS</p>

               <p>The men of this race lived in Europe from the Third
   Interglacial period through the Fourth Glacial. They disappeared somewhat
   suddenly, being replaced by the Modern Man type, such as the Cromagnards.
   Many regard the Neanderthal Men as a distinct species.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image285_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE NEANDERTHAL MAN OF LA CHAPELLE-AUX-SAINTS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>It seems not unfitting that we should at this point sound another
 note—that of the man of feeling. It is clear in William James's
 words:</p>
            <lq>
               <p>Bone of our bone, and flesh of our flesh, are these half-brutish
  prehistoric brothers. Girdled about with the immense darkness of this
  mysterious universe even as we are, they were born and died, suffered and
  struggled. Given over to fearful crime and passion, plunged in the blackest
  ignorance, preyed upon by hideous and grotesque delusions, yet steadfastly
  serving the profoundest of ideals in their fixed faith that existence in any
  form is better than non-existence, they ever rescued triumphantly from the
  jaws of ever imminent destruction the torch of life which, thanks to them,
  now lights the world for us.</p>
            </lq>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e5825">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Races of Mankind</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Given a variable stock spreading over diverse territory, we expect to find
 it splitting up into varieties which may become steadied into races or
 incipient species. Thus we have races of hive-bees, "Italians,"
 "Punics," and so forth; and thus there arose races of men. Certain
 types suited certain areas, and periods of in-breeding tended to make the
 distinctive peculiarities of each incipient race well-defined and stable.
 When the original peculiarities, say, of negro and Mongol, Australian and
 Caucasian, arose as brusque variations or "mutations," then they
 would have great staying power from generation to generation. They would not
 be readily swamped by intercrossing or averaged off. Peculiarities and
 changes of climate and surroundings, not to speak of other change-producing
 factors, would provoke new departures from age to age, and so fresh racial
 ventures<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 176]</ph> were made. Moreover, the occurrence of out-breeding when two
 races met, in peace or in war, would certainly serve to induce fresh starts.
 Very important in the evolution of human races must have been the alternating
 occurrence of periods of in-breeding (endogamy), tending to stability and
 sameness, and periods of out-breeding (exogamy), tending to changefulness and
 diversity.</p>
            <p>Thus we may distinguish several more or less clearly defined primitive
 races of mankind—notably the African, the Australian, the Mongolian,
 and the Caucasian. The woolly-haired African race includes the negroes and
 the very primitive bushmen. The wavy-to curly-haired Australian race includes
 the Jungle Tribes of the Deccan, the Vedda of Ceylon, the Jungle Folk or
 Semang, and the natives of unsettled parts of Australia—all sometimes
 slumped together as "Pre-Dravidians." The straight-haired Mongols
 include those of Tibet, Indo-China, China, and Formosa, those of many oceanic
 islands, and of the north from Japan to Lapland. The Caucasians include
 Mediterraneans, Semites, Nordics, Afghans, Alpines, and many more.</p>
            <p>There are very few corners of knowledge more difficult than that of the
 Races of Men, the chief reason being that there has been so much movement and
 migration in the course of the ages. One physical type has mingled with
 another, inducing strange amalgams and novelties. If we start with what might
 be called "zoological" races or strains differing, for instance, in
 their hair (woolly-haired Africans, straight-haired Mongols, curly-or
 wavy-haired Pre-Dravidians and Caucasians), we find these replaced by
 <i>peoples</i> who are mixtures of various races, "brethren by
 civilisation more than by blood." As Professor Flinders Petrie has said,
 the only meaning the term "race" now can have is that of a group of
 human beings whose type has been unified by their rate of assimilation
 exceeding the rate of change produced by the infiltration of foreign
 elements. It is probable, however, that the progress of precise anthropology
 will make it possible to distinguish the various racial "strains"
 that make up<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 177]</ph> any people. For the human sense of race is so strong that it
 convinces us of reality even when scientific definition is impossible. It was
 this the British sailor expressed in his answer to the question "What is
 a Dago?" "Dagoes," he replied, "is anything wot isn't
 our sort of chaps."</p>
            <fig id="image288"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>RESTORATION BY A. FORESTIER OF THE RHODESIAN MAN WHOSE SKULL WAS
   DISCOVERED IN 1921</p>

               <p>Attention may be drawn to the beetling eyebrow ridges, the
   projecting upper lip, the large eye-sockets, the well-poised head, the
   strong shoulders.</p>

               <p>The squatting figure is crushing seeds with a stone, and a
   crusher is lying on the rock to his right.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image288_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>RESTORATION BY A. FORESTIER OF THE RHODESIAN MAN WHOSE SKULL WAS DISCOVERED IN 1921</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image289"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>RESTORATION BY A. FORESTIER OF THE RHODESIAN MAN WHOSE SKULL WAS
   DISCOVERED IN 1921</p>

               <p>The figure in the foreground, holding a staff, shows the
   erect attitude and the straight legs. His left hand holds a flint
   implement.</p>

               <p>On the left, behind the sitting figure, is seen the
   entrance to the cave. This new Rhodesian cave-man may be regarded as a
   southern representative of a Neanderthal race, or as an extinct type
   intermediate between the Neanderthal Men and the Modern Man type.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image289_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>RESTORATION BY A. FORESTIER OF THE RHODESIAN MAN WHOSE SKULL WAS DISCOVERED IN 1921</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e5884">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Steps in Human Evolution</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Real men arose, we believe, by variational uplifts of considerable
 magnitude which led to big and complex brains and to the power of reasoned
 discourse. In some other lines of mammalian evolution there were from time to
 time great advances in the size and complexity of the brain, as is clear, for
 instance, in the case of horses and elephants. The same is true of birds as
 compared with reptiles, and everyone recognises the high level of excellence
 that has been attained by their vocal powers. How these great cerebral
 advances came about we do not know, but it has been one of the main trends of
 animal evolution to improve the nervous system. Two suggestions may be made.
 First, the prolongation of the period of ante-natal life, in intimate
 physiological partnership with the mother, may have made it practicable to
 start the higher mammal with a much better brain than in the lower orders,
 like Insectivores and Rodents, and still more Marsupials, where the period
 before birth (gestation) is short. Second, we know that the individual
 development of the brain is profoundly influenced by the internal secretions
 of certain ductless glands notably the thyroid. When this organ is not
 functioning properly the child's brain development is arrested. It may be
 that increased production of certain hormones—itself, of course, to be
 accounted for—may have stimulated brain development in man's remote
 ancestors.</p>
            <p>Given variability along the line of better brains and given a process of
 discriminate sifting which would consistently offer rewards to alertness and
 foresight, to kin-sympathy and parental care, there seems no great difficulty
 in imagining how Man would<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 178]</ph> evolve. We must not think of an Aristotle or a
 Newton except as fine results which justify all the groaning and travailing;
 we must think of average men, of primitive peoples to-day, and of our
 forbears long ago. We must remember how much of man's advance is
 dependent on the external registration of the social heritage, not on the
 slowly changing natural inheritance.</p>
            <p>Looking backwards it is impossible, we think, to fail to recognise
 progress. There is a ring of truth in the fine description Æschylus gave of
 primitive men that—</p>
            <lq>
               <p>first, beholding they beheld in vain, and, hearing, heard not, but, like
  shapes in dreams, mixed all things wildly down the tedious time, nor knew to
  build a house against the sun with wicketed sides, nor any woodwork knew,
  but lived like silly ants, beneath the ground, in hollow caves unsunned.
  There came to them no steadfast sign of winter, nor of spring
  flower-perfumed, nor of summer full of fruit, but blindly and lawlessly they
  did all things.</p>
            </lq>
            <p>Contrast this picture with the position of man to-day. He has mastered the
 forces of Nature and is learning to use their resources more and more
 economically; he has harnessed electricity to his chariot and he has made the
 ether carry his messages. He tapped supplies of material which seemed for
 centuries unavailable, having learned, for instance, how to capture and
 utilise the free nitrogen of the air. With his telegraph and
 "wireless" he has annihilated distance, and he has added to his
 navigable kingdom the depths of the sea and the heights of the air. He has
 conquered one disease after another, and the young science of heredity is
 showing him how to control in his domesticated animals and cultivated plants
 the nature of the generations yet unborn. With all his faults he has his
 ethical face set in the right direction. The main line of movement is towards
 the fuller embodiment of the true, the beautiful, and the good in healthy
 lives which are increasingly a satisfaction in themselves.</p>
            <fig id="image292a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: British Museum (Natural History).</i>
               </p>

               <p>SIDE-VIEW OF A PREHISTORIC HUMAN SKULL DISCOVERED IN 1921 IN BROKEN HILL
   CAVE, NORTHERN RHODESIA</p>

               <p>Very striking are the prominent eyebrow ridges and the
   broad massive face. The skull looks less domed than that of modern man, but
   its cranial capacity is far above the lowest human limit. The teeth are
   interesting in showing marked rotting or "caries," hitherto
   unknown in prehistoric skulls. In all probability the Rhodesian man was an
   African representative of the extinct Neanderthal species hitherto known
   only from Europe.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image292a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SIDE-VIEW OF A PREHISTORIC HUMAN SKULL DISCOVERED IN 1921 IN BROKEN HILL CAVE, NORTHERN RHODESIA</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image292b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>After the restoration modelled by J. H. McGregor.</i>
               </p>

               <p>A CROMAGNON MAN OR CROMAGNARD, REPRESENTATIVE OF A STRONG ARTISTIC RACE
   LIVING IN THE SOUTH OF FRANCE IN THE UPPER PLEISTOCENE, PERHAPS 25,000
   YEARS AGO</p>

               <p>They seemed to have lived for a while contemporaneously
   with the Neanderthal Men, and there may have been interbreeding. Some
   Cromagnards probably survive, but the race as a whole declined, and there
   was repopulation of Europe from the East.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image292b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A CROMAGNON MAN OR CROMAGNARD</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image293a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Reproduced by permission from Osborn's "Men of the Old Stone
   Age."</i>
               </p>

               <p>PHOTOGRAPH SHOWING A NARROW PASSAGE IN THE CAVERN OF FONT-DE-GAUME ON
   THE BEUNE</p>

               <p>Throughout the cavern the walls are crowded with
   engravings; on the left wall, shown in the photograph, are two painted
   bison. In the great gallery there may be found not less than eighty
   figures—bison, reindeer, and mammoths. A specimen of the last is
   reproduced below.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image293a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PHOTOGRAPH SHOWING A NARROW PASSAGE IN THE CAVERN OF FONT-DE-GAUME ON THE BEUNE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image293b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>A MAMMOTH DRAWN ON THE WALL OF THE FONT-DE-GAUME CAVERN</p>

               <p>The mammoth age was in the Middle Pleistocene, while
   Neanderthal Men still flourished, probably far over 30,000 years ago.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image293b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A MAMMOTH DRAWN ON THE WALL OF THE FONT-DE-GAUME CAVERN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image293c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>A GRAZING BISON, DELICATELY AND CAREFULLY DRAWN, ENGRAVED ON A WALL OF
   THE ALTAMIRA CAVE, NORTHERN SPAIN</p>

               <p>This was the work of a Reindeer Man or Cromagnard, in the
   Upper or Post-Glacial Pleistocene, perhaps 25,000 years ago. Firelight must
   have been used in making these cave drawings and engravings.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image293c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A GRAZING BISON, DELICATELY AND CAREFULLY DRAWN, ENGRAVED ON A WALL OF THE ALTAMIRA CAVE, NORTHERN SPAIN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 179]</ph>
            </p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6003">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Factors in Human Progress</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Many, we believe, were the gains that rewarded the arboreal apprenticeship
 of man's ancestors. Many, likewise, were the results of leaving the trees
 and coming down to the solid earth—a transition which marked the
 emergence of more than tentative men. What great steps followed?</p>
            <p>Some of the greatest were—the working out of a spoken language and
 of external methods of registration; the invention of tools; the discovery of
 the use of fire; the utilisation of iron and other metals; the taming of wild
 animals such as dog and sheep, horses and cattle; the cultivation of wild
 plants such as wheat and rice; and the irrigation of fields. All through the
 ages necessity has been the mother of invention and curiosity its father; but
 perhaps we miss the heart of the matter if we forget the importance of some
 leisure time—wherein to observe and think. If our earth had been so
 clouded that the stars were hidden from men's eyes the whole history of
 our race would have been different. For it was through his leisure-time
 observations of the stars that early man discovered the regularity of the
 year and got his fundamental impressions of the order of Nature—on
 which all his science is founded.</p>
            <p>If we are to think clearly of the factors of human progress we must recall
 the three great biological ideas—the living organism, its environment,
 and its functioning. For man these mean (1) the living creature, the outcome
 of parents and ancestors, a fresh expression of a bodily and mental
 inheritance; (2) the surroundings, including climate and soil, the plants and
 animals these allow; and (3) the activities of all sorts, occupations and
 habits, all the actions and reactions between man and his milieu. In short,
 we have to deal with <ph outputclass="smcap">Folk, Place, Work</ph>; the
 <i>Famille</i>, <i>Lieu</i>, <i>Travail</i> of the LePlay school.</p>
            <p>As to <ph outputclass="smcap">Folk</ph>, human progress depends on intrinsic
 racial qualities—notably health and vigour of body, clearness and
 alertness of mind, and an indispensable sociality. The most
 powerful<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 180]</ph> factors in the world are clear ideas in the minds of
 energetic men of good will. The differences in bodily and mental health which
 mark races, and stocks within a people, just as they mark individuals, are
 themselves traceable back to germinal variations or mutations, and to the
 kind of sifting to which the race or stock has been subjected. Easygoing
 conditions are not only without stimulus to new departures, they are without
 the sifting which progress demands.</p>
            <p>As to <ph outputclass="smcap">Place</ph>, it is plain that different areas
 differ greatly in their material resources and in the availability of these.
 Moreover, even when abundant material resources are present, they will not
 make for much progress unless the climate is such that they can be readily
 utilised. Indeed, climate has been one of the great factors in civilisation,
 here stimulating and there depressing energy, in one place favouring certain
 plants and animals important to man, in another place preventing their
 presence. Moreover, climate has slowly changed from age to age.</p>
            <p>As to <ph outputclass="smcap">Work</ph>, the form of a civilisation is in
 some measure dependent on the primary occupations, whether hunting or
 fishing, farming or shepherding; and on the industries of later ages which
 have a profound moulding effect on the individual at least. We cannot,
 however, say more than that the factors of human progress have always had
 these three aspects, Folk, Place, Work, and that if progress is to continue
 on stable lines it must always recognise the essential correlation of fitter
 folk in body and mind: improved habits and functions, alike in work and
 leisure; and bettered surroundings in the widest and deepest sense.</p>
            <!--hr--></body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e6044">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">BIBLIOGRAPHY</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Darwin, Charles</ph>, <i>Descent of Man</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Haddon, A. C.</ph>, <i>Races of Men</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Haddon, A. C.</ph>, <i>History of Anthropology</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Keane, A. H.</ph>, <i>Man Past and Present</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 181]</ph>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Keith, Arthur</ph>, <i>Antiquity of
 Man</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Lull, R. S.</ph>, <i>Organic Evolution</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">McCabe, Joseph</ph>, <i>Evolution of Civilization</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Marett, R. R.</ph>, <i>Anthropology</i> (Home
 University Library).
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Osborn, H. F.</ph>, <i>Men of the Early Stone Age</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Sollas, W. J.</ph>, <i>Ancient Hunters and their Modern
 Representatives</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Tylor, E. B.</ph>, <i>Anthropology and Primitive
 Culture</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 182]</ph>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 183]</ph>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 184]</ph>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 185]</ph>
         </p>
         <!--hr--></body>
   </topic>
</topic>