<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="chapter_05">
   <title>
      <ph outputclass="title-line">IV</ph> 
      <ph outputclass="title-line">THE STRUGGLE FOR EXISTENCE</ph> 
   </title>
   <body><!--hr--></body>
   <topic id="d1e4621">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">ANIMAL AND BIRD MIMICRY AND DISGUISE</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 1</p>
         <p>For every animal one discovers when observing carefully, there must be ten
 unseen. This is partly because many animals burrow in the ground or get in
 underneath things and into dark corners, being what is called cryptozoic or
 elusive. But it is partly because many animals put on disguise or have in
 some way acquired a garment of invisibility. This is very common among
 animals, and it occurs in many forms and degrees. The reason why it is so
 common is because the struggle for existence is often very keen, and the
 reasons why the struggle for existence is keen are four. First, there is the
 tendency to over-population in many animals, especially those of low degree.
 Second, there is the fact that the scheme of nature involves nutritive chains
 or successive incarnations, one animal depending upon another for food, and
 all in the long run on plants; thirdly, every vigorous animal is a bit of a
 hustler, given to insurgence and sticking out his elbows. There is a fourth
 great reason for the struggle for existence, namely, the frequent
 changefulness of the physical environment, which forces animals to answer
 back or die; but the first three reasons have most to do with the very common
 assumption of some sort of disguise. Even when an animal is in no sense a
 weakling, it may be very advantageous for it to be inconspicuous when it is
 resting or when it is taking care of its young. Our problem is the evolution
 of elusiveness, so far at least as that depends on likeness to surroundings,
 on protective resemblance to other objects, and in its highest reaches on
 true mimicry.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 138]</ph>
         </p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e4630">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Colour Permanently Like That of Surroundings</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Many animals living on sandy places have a light-brown colour, as is seen
 in some lizards and snakes. The green lizard is like the grass and the green
 tree-snake is inconspicuous among the branches. The spotted leopard is suited
 to the interrupted light of the forest, and it is sometimes hard to tell
 where the jungle ends and the striped tiger begins. There is no better case
 than the hare or the partridge sitting a few yards off on the ploughed field.
 Even a donkey grazing in the dusk is much more readily heard than seen.</p>
            <p>The experiment has been made of tethering the green variety of Praying
 Mantis on green herbage, fastening them with silk threads. They escape the
 notice of birds. The same is true when the brown variety is tethered on
 withered herbage. But if the green ones are put on brown plants, or the brown
 ones on green plants, the birds pick them off. Similarly, out of 300 chickens
 in a field, 240 white or black and therefore conspicuous, 60 spotted and
 inconspicuous, 24 were soon picked off by crows, but only one of these was
 spotted. This was not the proportion that there should have been if the
 mortality had been fortuitous. There is no doubt that it often pays an animal
 to be like its habitual surroundings, like a little piece of scenery if the
 animal is not moving. It is safe to say that in process of time wide
 departures from the safest coloration will be wiped out in the course of
 Nature's ceaseless sifting.</p>
            <p>But we must not be credulous, and there are three cautions to be borne in
 mind. (1) An animal may be very like its surroundings without there being any
 protection implied. The arrow-worms in the sea are as clear as glass, and so
 are many open-sea animals. But this is because their tissues are so watery,
 with a specific gravity near that of the salt water. And the invisibility
 does not save them, always or often, from being swallowed by larger animals
 that gather the harvest of the sea. (2) Among the cleverer animals it looks
 as if the creature sometimes sought out a spot where it was most
 inconspicuous. A spider may place itself<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 139]</ph> in the middle of a little patch
 of lichen, where its self-effacement is complete. Perhaps it is more
 comfortable as well as safer to rest in surroundings the general colour of
 which is like that of the animal's body. (3) The fishes that live among
 the coral-reefs are startling in their brilliant coloration, and there are
 many different patterns. To explain this it has been suggested that these
 fishes are so safe among the mazy passages and endless nooks of the reefs,
 that they can well afford to wear any colour that suits their constitution.
 In some cases this may be true, but naturalists who have put on a diving suit
 and walked about among the coral have told us that each kind of fish is
 particularly suited to some particular place, and that some are suited for
 midday work and others for evening work. Sometimes there is a sort of Box and
 Cox arrangement by which two different fishes utilise the same corner at
 different times.</p>
            <fig id="image222a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE PRAYING MANTIS (<i>Mantis Religiosa</i>)</p>

               <p>A very voracious insect with a quiet, unobtrusive
   appearance. It holds its formidable forelegs as if in the attitude of
   prayer; its movements are very slow and stealthy; and there is a suggestion
   of a leaf in the forewing. But there is no reason to credit the creature
   with conscious guile!</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image222a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE PRAYING MANTIS (Mantis Religiosa&gt;)</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image222b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>PROTECTIVE COLORATION: A WINTER SCENE IN NORTH SCANDINAVIA</p>

               <p>Showing Variable Hare, Willow Grouse, and Arctic Fox, all
   white in winter and inconspicuous against the snow. But the white dress is
   also the dress that is physiologically best, for it loses least of the
   animal heat.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image222b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROTECTIVE COLORATION: A WINTER SCENE IN NORTH SCANDINAVIA</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image223"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE VARIABLE MONITOR (<i>Varanus</i>)</p>

               <p>The monitors are the largest of existing lizards, the
   Australian species represented in the photograph attaining a length of four
   feet. It has a brown colour with yellow spots, and in spite of its size it
   is not conspicuous against certain backgrounds, such as the bark of a
   tree.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image223_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE VARIABLE MONITOR (Varanus)</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 2</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4699">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Gradual Change of Colour</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The common shore-crab shows many different colours and mottlings,
 especially when it is young. It may be green or grey, red or brown, and so
 forth, and it is often in admirable adjustment to the colour of the rock-pool
 where it is living. Experiments, which require extension, have shown that
 when the crab has moulted, which it has to do very often when it is young,
 the colour of the new shell tends to harmonise with the general colour of the
 rocks and seaweed. How this is brought about, we do not know. The colour does
 not seem to change till the next moult, and not then unless there is some
 reason for it. A full-grown shore-crab is well able to look after itself, and
 it is of interest to notice, therefore, that the variety of coloration is
 mainly among the small individuals, who have, of course, a much less secure
 position. It is possible, moreover, that the resemblance to the surroundings
 admits of more successful hunting, enabling the small crab to take its victim
 unawares.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 140]</ph>
            </p>
            <p>Professor Poulton's experiments with the caterpillars of the small
 tortoise-shell butterfly showed that in black surroundings the pupæ tend to
 be darker, in white surroundings lighter, in gilded boxes golden; and the
 same is true in other cases. It appears that the surrounding colour affects
 the caterpillars through the skin during a sensitive period—the twenty
 hours immediately preceding the last twelve hours of the larval state. The
 result will tend to make the quiescent pupæ less conspicuous during the
 critical time of metamorphosis. The physiology of this sympathetic colouring
 remains obscure.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4708">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Seasonal Change of Colouring</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The ptarmigan moults three times in the year. Its summer plumage is rather
 grouselike above, with a good deal of rufous brown; the back becomes much
 more grey in autumn; almost all the feathers of the winter plumage are white.
 That is to say, they develop without any pigment and with numerous
 gas-bubbles in their cells. Now there can be no doubt that this white winter
 plumage makes the ptarmigan very inconspicuous amidst the snow. Sometimes one
 comes within a few feet of the crouching bird without seeing it, and this
 garment of invisibility may save it from the hungry eyes of golden
 eagles.</p>
            <p>Similarly the brown stoat becomes the white ermine, mainly by the growth,
 of a new suit of white fur, and the same is true of the mountain hare. The
 ermine is all white except the black tip of its tail; the mountain hare in
 its winter dress is all white save the black tips of its ears. In some cases,
 especially in the mountain hare, it seems that individual hairs may turn
 white, by a loss of pigment, as may occur in man. According to Metchnikoff,
 the wandering amœboid cells of the body, called phagocytes, may creep
 up into the hairs and come back again with microscopic burdens of pigment.
 The place of the pigment is taken by gas-bubbles, and that is what causes the
 whiteness. In no animals is there any white <i>pigment</i>; the white
 <i>colour</i> is like that of snow or<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 141]</ph> foam, it is due to the complete reflection
 of the light from innumerable minute surfaces of crystals or bubbles.</p>
            <fig id="image226a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: W. S. Berridge, F.Z.S.</i>
               </p>

               <p>BANDED KRAIT: A VERY POISONOUS SNAKE WITH ALTERNATING YELLOW AND DARK
   BANDS</p>

               <p>It is very conspicuous and may serve as an illustration of
   warning coloration. Perhaps, that is to say, its striking coloration serves
   as an advertisement, impressing other creatures with the fact that the
   Banded Krait should be left alone. It is very unprofitable for a snake to
   waste its venom on creatures it does not want.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image226a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>BANDED KRAIT: A VERY POISONOUS SNAKE WITH ALTERNATING YELLOW AND DARK BANDS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image226b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photos: W. S. Berridge, F.Z.S.</i>
               </p>

               <p>THE WARTY CHAMELEON</p>

               <p>The upper photograph shows the Warty Chameleon inflated and
   conspicuous. At another time, however, with compressed body and adjusted
   coloration, the animal is very inconspicuous. The lower photograph shows
   the sudden protrusion of the very long tongue on a fly.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image226b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE WARTY CHAMELEON</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image227"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>SEASONAL COLOUR-CHANGE: A SUMMER SCENE IN NORTH SCANDINAVIA</p>

               <p>Showing a brown Variable Hare, Willow Grouse, and Arctic
   Fox, all inconspicuous in their coloration when seen in their natural
   surroundings.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image227_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SEASONAL COLOUR-CHANGE: A SUMMER SCENE IN NORTH SCANDINAVIA</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>The mountain hare may escape the fox the more readily because its
 whiteness makes it so inconspicuous against a background of snow; and yet, at
 other times, we have seen the creature standing out like a target on the dark
 moorland. So it cuts both ways. The ermine has almost no enemies except the
 gamekeeper, but its winter whiteness may help it to sneak upon its victims,
 such as grouse or rabbit, when there is snow upon the ground. In both cases,
 however, the probability is that the constitutional rhythm which leads to
 white hair in winter has been fostered and fixed for a reason quite apart
 from protection. The fact is that for a warm-blooded creature, whether bird
 or mammal, the physiologically best dress is a white one, for there is less
 radiation of the precious animal heat from white plumage or white pelage than
 from any other colour. The quality of warm-bloodedness is a prerogative of
 birds and mammals, and it means that the body keeps an almost constant
 temperature, day and night, year in and year out. This is effected by
 automatic internal adjustments which regulate the supply of heat, chiefly
 from the muscles, to the loss of heat, chiefly through the skin and from the
 lungs. The chief importance of this internal heat is that it facilitates the
 smooth continuance of the chemical processes on which life depends. If the
 temperature falls, as in hibernating mammals (whose warm-bloodedness is
 imperfect), the rate of the vital process is slowed down—sometimes
 dangerously. Thus we see how the white coat helps the life of the
 creature.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 3</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4786">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Rapid Colour-change</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Bony flat-fishes, like plaice and sole, have a remarkable power of
 adjusting their hue and pattern to the surrounding gravel and sand, so that
 it is difficult to find them even when we know that they are there. It must
 be admitted that they<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 142]</ph> are also very quick to get a sprinkling of
 sand over their upturned side, so that only the eyes are left showing. But
 there is no doubt as to the exactness with which they often adjust themselves
 to be like a little piece of the substratum on which they lie; they will do
 this within limits in experimental conditions when they are placed on a quite
 artificial floor. As these fishes are very palatable and are much sought
 after by such enemies as cormorants and otters, it is highly probably that
 their power of self-effacement often saves their life. And it may be effected
 within a few minutes, in some cases within a minute.</p>
            <p>In these self-effacing flat-fishes we know with some precision what
 happens. The adjustment of colour and pattern is due to changes in the size,
 shape, and position of mobile pigment-cells (chromatophores) and the skin.
 But what makes the pigment-cells change? The fact that a blind flat-fish does
 not change its colour gives us the first part of the answer. The colour and
 the pattern of the surroundings must affect the eye. The message travels by
 the optic nerve to the brain; from the brain, instead of passing down the
 spinal cord, the message travels down the chain of sympathetic ganglia. From
 these it passes along the nerves which comes out of the spinal cord and
 control the skin. Thus the message reaches the colour-cells in the skin, and
 before you have carefully read these lines the flat-fish has slipped on its
 Gyges ring and become invisible.</p>
            <p>The same power of rapid colour-change is seen in cuttlefishes, where it is
 often an expression of nervous excitement, though it sometimes helps to
 conceal. It occurs with much subtlety in the Æsop prawn, Hippolyte, which may
 be brown on a brown seaweed, green on sea-lettuce or sea-grass, red on red
 seaweed, and so on through an extensive repertory.</p>
            <lq>
               <p>According to the nature of the background, [Professor Gamble writes] so
  is the mixture of the pigments compounded so as to form a close reproduction
  both of its colour and its pattern. A sweep of the shrimp net detaches a
  battalion<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
  143]</ph> of these sleeping prawns, and if we turn the motley into a
  dish and give a choice of seaweed, each variety after its kind will select
  the one with which it agrees in colour, and vanish. Both when young and when
  full-grown, the Æsop prawn takes on the colour of its immediate
  surroundings. At nightfall Hippolyte, of whatever colour, changes to a
  transparent azure blue: its stolidity gives place to a nervous restlessness;
  at the least tremor it leaps violently, and often swims actively from one
  food-plant to another. This blue fit lasts till daybreak, and is then
  succeeded by the prawn's diurnal tint.</p>
            </lq>
            <p>Thus, Professor Gamble continues, the colour of an animal may express a
 nervous rhythm.</p>
            <fig id="image230"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: J. J. Ward, F.E.S.</i>
               </p>

               <p>PROTECTIVE RESEMBLANCE</p>

               <p>Hawk Moth, settled down on a branch, and very difficult to
   detect as long as it remains stationary. Note its remarkable sucking
   tongue, which is about twice the length of its body. The tongue can be
   quickly coiled up and put safely away beneath the lower part of the
   head.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image230_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROTECTIVE RESEMBLANCE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image231"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>WHEN ONLY A FEW DAYS OLD, YOUNG BITTERN BEGIN TO STRIKE THE SAME
   ATTITUDE AS THEIR PARENTS THRUSTING THEIR BILLS UPWARDS AND DRAWING THEIR
   BODIES UP SO THAT THEY RESEMBLE A BUNCH OF REEDS</p>

               <p>The soft browns and blue-greens harmonise with the dull
   sheaths of the young reeds; the nestling bittern is thus completely
   camouflaged.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image231_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>WHEN ONLY A FEW DAYS OLD, YOUNG BITTERN BEGIN TO STRIKE THE SAME ATTITUDE AS THEIR PARENTS THRUSTING THEIR BILLS UPWARDS AND DRAWING THEIR BODIES UP SO THAT THEY RESEMBLE A BUNCH OF REEDS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4847">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Case of Chameleons</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The highest level at which rapid colour-change occurs is among lizards,
 and the finest exhibition of it is among the chameleons. These quaint
 creatures are characteristic of Africa; but they occur also in Andalusia,
 Arabia, Ceylon, and Southern India. They are adapted for life on trees, where
 they hunt insects with great deliberateness and success. The protrusible
 tongue, ending in a sticky club, can be shot out for about seven inches in
 the common chameleon. Their hands and feet are split so that they grip the
 branches firmly, and the prehensile tail rivals a monkey's. When they
 wish they can make themselves very slim, contracting the body from side to
 side, so that they are not very readily seen. In other circumstances,
 however, they do not practise self-effacement, but the very reverse. They
 inflate their bodies, having not only large lungs, but air-sacs in connection
 with them. The throat bulges; the body sways from side to side; and the
 creature expresses its sentiments in a hiss. The power of colour-change is
 very remarkable, and depends partly on the contraction and expansion of the
 colour-cells (chromatophores) in the under-skin (or dermis) and partly on
 close-packed refractive granules and crystals of a waste-product called
 guanin. The repertory of possible<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 144]</ph> colours in the common chameleon is greater
 than in any other animal except the Æsop prawn. There is a legend of a
 chameleon which was brown in a brown box, green in a green box, and blue in a
 blue box, and died when put into one lined with tartan; and there is no doubt
 that one and the same animal has a wide range of colours. The so-called
 "chameleon" (<i>Anolis</i>) of North America is so sensitive that a
 passing cloud makes it change its emerald hue.</p>
            <p>There is no doubt that a chameleon may make itself more inconspicuous by
 changing its colour, being affected by the play of light on its eyes. A
 bright-green hue is often seen on those that are sitting among strongly
 illumined green leaves. But the colour also changes with the time of day and
 with the animal's moods. A sudden irritation may bring about a rapid
 change; in other cases the transformation comes about very gradually. When
 the colour-change expresses the chameleon's feelings it might be compared
 to blushing, but that is due to an expansion of the arteries of the face,
 allowing more blood to get into the capillaries of the under-skin. The case
 of the chameleon is peculiarly interesting because the animal has two kinds
 of tactics—self-effacement on the one hand and bluffing on the other.
 There can be little doubt that the power of colour-change sometimes justifies
 itself by driving off intruders. Dr. Cyril Crossland observed that a
 chameleon attacked by a fox-terrier "turned round and opened its great
 pink mouth in the face of the advancing dog, at the same time rapidly
 changing colour, becoming almost black. This ruse succeeded every time, the
 dog turning off at once." In natural leafy surroundings the startling
 effect would be much greater—a sudden throwing off of the mantle of
 invisibility and the exposure of a conspicuous black body with a large red
 mouth.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 4</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4862">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Likeness to Other Things</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Dr. H. O. Forbes tells of a flat spider which presents a striking
 resemblance to a bird's dropping on a leaf. Years after he<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 145]</ph> first found it
 he was watching in a forest in the Far East when his eye fell on a leaf
 before him which had been blotched by a bird. He wondered idly why he had not
 seen for so long another specimen of the bird-dropping spider
 (<i>Ornithoscatoides decipiens</i>), and drew the leaf towards him.
 Instantaneously he got a characteristic sharp nip; it was the spider after
 all! Here the colour-resemblance was enhanced by a form-resemblance.</p>
            <fig id="image234"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>A. PROTECTIVE COLORATION OR CAMOUFLAGING, GIVING ANIMALS A GARMENT OF
   INVISIBILITY</p>

               <p>At the foot of the plate is a Nightjar, with plumage like
   bark and withering leaves; to the right, resting on a branch, is shown a
   Chameleon in a green phase amid green surroundings; the insects on the
   reeds are Locusts; while a green Frog, merged into its surroundings, rests
   on a leaf near the centre at the top of the picture.</p>

               <p>B. ANOTHER EXAMPLE OF PROTECTIVE COLORATION OR CAMOUFLAGE</p>

               <p>A shore scene showing Trout in the pool almost invisible
   against their background. The Stone Curlews, both adult and young, are very
   inconspicuous among the stones on the beach.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image234_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROTECTIVE COLORATION OR CAMOUFLAGING</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>But why should it profit a spider to be like a bird-dropping? Perhaps
 because it thereby escapes attention; but there is another possibility. It
 seems that some butterflies, allied to our Blues, are often attracted to
 excrementitious material, and the spider Dr. Forbes observed had actually
 caught its victim. This is borne out by a recent observation by Dr. D. G. H.
 Carpenter, who found a Uganda bug closely resembling a bird-dropping on sand.
 The bug actually settled down on a bird-dropping on sand, and caught a blue
 butterfly which came to feed there!</p>
            <p>Some of the walking-stick insects, belonging to the order of crickets and
 grasshoppers (Orthoptera), have their body elongated and narrow, like a thin
 dry branch, and they have a way of sticking out their limbs at abrupt and
 diverse angles, which makes the resemblance to twigs very close indeed. Some
 of these quaint insects rest through the day and have the remarkable habit of
 putting themselves into a sort of kataleptic state. Many creatures turn stiff
 when they get a shock, or pass suddenly into new surroundings, like some of
 the sand-hoppers when we lay them on the palm of our hand; but these
 twig-insects put themselves into this strange state. The body is rocked from
 side to side for a short time, and then it stiffens. An advantage may be that
 even if they were surprised by a bird or a lizard, they will not be able to
 betray themselves by even a tremor. Disguise is perfected by a remarkable
 habit, a habit which leads us to think of a whole series of different ways of
 lying low and saying nothing which are often of life-preserving value. The
 top end of the series is seen when a fox plays 'possum.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 146]</ph>
            </p>
            <p>The leaf-butterfly <i>Kallima</i>, conspicuously coloured on its upper
 surface, is like a withered leaf when it settles down and shows the under
 side of its wings. Here, again, there is precise form-resemblance, for the
 nervures on the wings are like the mid-rib and side veins on a leaf, and the
 touch of perfection is given in the presence of whitish spots which look
 exactly like the discolorations produced by lichens on leaves. An old
 entomologist, Mr. Jenner Weir, confessed that he repeatedly pruned off a
 caterpillar on a bush in mistake for a superfluous twig, for many brownish
 caterpillars fasten themselves by their posterior claspers and by an
 invisible thread of silk from their mouth, and project from the branch at a
 twig-like angle. An insect may be the very image of a sharp prickle or a
 piece of soft moss; a spider may look precisely like a tiny knob on a branch
 or a fragment of lichen; one of the sea-horses (<i>Phyllopteryx</i>) has
 frond-like tassels on various parts of its body, so that it looks
 extraordinarily like the seaweeds among which it lives. In a few cases, e.g.
 among spiders, it has been shown that animals with a special protective
 resemblance to something else seek out a position where this resemblance
 tells, and there is urgent need for observations bearing on this selection of
 environment.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 5</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4913">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Mimicry in the True Sense</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It sometimes happens that in one and the same place there are two groups
 of animals not very nearly related which are "doubles" of one
 another. Investigation shows that the members of the one group, <i>always in
 the majority</i>, are in some way specially protected, e.g. by being
 unpalatable. They are the "mimicked." The members of the other
 group, <i>always in the minority</i>, have not got the special protection
 possessed by the others. They are the "mimickers," though the
 resemblance is not, of course, associated with any conscious imitation. The
 theory is that the mimickers live on the reputation of the mimicked. If the
 mimicked are left alone<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 147]</ph> by birds because they have a reputation for
 unpalatability, or because they are able to sting, the mimickers
 survive—although they are palatable and stingless. They succeed, not
 through any virtue of their own, but because of their resemblance to the
 mimicked, for whom they are mistaken. There are many cases of mimetic
 resemblance so striking and so subtle that it seems impossible to doubt that
 the thing works; there are other cases which are rather far-fetched, and may
 be somewhat of the nature of coincidences. Thus although Mr. Bates tells us
 that he repeatedly shot humming-bird moths in mistake for humming-birds, we
 cannot think that this is a good illustration of mimicry. What is needed for
 many cases is what is forthcoming for some, namely, experimental evidence,
 e.g. that the unpalatable mimicked butterflies are left in relative peace
 while similar palatable butterflies are persecuted. It is also necessary to
 show that the mimickers do actually consort with the mimicked. Some beetles
 and moths are curiously wasplike, which may be a great advantage; the common
 drone-fly is superficially like a small bee; some harmless snakes are very
 like poisonous species; and Mr. Wallace maintained that the powerful
 "friar-birds" of the Far East are mimicked by the weak and timid
 orioles. When the model is unpalatable or repulsive or dangerous, and the
 mimic the reverse, the mimicry is called "Batesian" (after Mr.
 Bates), but there is another kind of mimicry called Müllerian (after Fritz
 Müller) where the mimic is also unpalatable. The theory in this case is that
 the mimicry serves as mutual assurance, the members of the ring getting on
 better by consistently presenting the same appearance, which has come to mean
 to possible enemies a signal, <i>Noli me tangere</i> ("Leave me
 alone"). There is nothing out of the question in this theory, but it
 requires to be taken in a critical spirit. It leads us to think of
 "warning colours," which are the very opposite of the disguises
 which we are now studying. Some creatures like skunks, magpies, coral-snakes,
 cobras, brightly coloured tree-frogs are obtrusive rather<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 148]</ph> than elusive,
 and the theory of Alfred Russel Wallace was that the flaunting
 conspicuousness serves as a useful advertisement, impressing itself on the
 memories of inexperienced enemies, who soon learn to leave creatures with
 "warning colours" alone. In any case it is plain that an animal
 which is as safe as a wasp or a coral-snake can afford to wear any suit of
 clothes it likes.</p>
            <fig id="image238a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>DEAD-LEAF BUTTERFLY (<i>Kallima Inachis</i>) FROM INDIA</p>

               <p>It is conspicuous on its upper surface, but when it settles
   down on a twig and shows the underside of its wings it is practically
   invisible. The colouring of the under surface of the wings is like that of
   the withering leaf; there are spots like fungas spots; and the venation of
   the wings suggests the mid-rib and veins of the leaf. A, showing upper
   surface; B, showing under surface; C, a leaf.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image238a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>DEAD-LEAF BUTTERFLY (Kallima Inachis) FROM INDIA</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image238b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>PROTECTIVE RESEMBLANCE BETWEEN A SMALL SPIDER (<i>to the left</i>) AND
   AN ANT (<i>to the right</i>)</p>

               <p>As ants are much dreaded, it is probably profitable to the
   spider to be like an ant. It will be noted that the spider has four pairs
   of legs and no feelers, whereas the ant has three pairs of legs and a pair
   of feelers.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image238b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROTECTIVE RESEMBLANCE BETWEEN A SMALL SPIDER AND AN ANT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image239a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: J. J. Ward, F.E.S.</i>
               </p>

               <p>THE WASP BEETLE, WHICH, WHEN MOVING AMONGST THE BRANCHES GIVES A
   WASP-LIKE IMPRESSION</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image239a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE WASP BEETLE, WHICH, WHEN MOVING AMONGST THE BRANCHES GIVES A WASP-LIKE IMPRESSION</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image239b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>HERMIT-CRAB WITH PARTNER SEA-ANEMONES</p>

               <p>Hermit-crabs hide their soft tail in the shell of a whelk
   or some other sea-snail. But some hermit-crabs place sea-anemones on the
   back of their borrowed shell. The sea-anemones mask the hermit-crab and
   their tentacles can sting. As for the sea-anemones, they are carried about
   by the hermit-crab and they get crumbs from its table. This kind of
   mutually beneficial external partnership is called commensalism, i.e.
   eating at the same table.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image239b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>HERMIT-CRAB WITH PARTNER SEA-ANEMONES</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image239c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: G. P. Duffus.</i>
               </p>

               <p>CUCKOO-SPIT</p>

               <p>The white mass in the centre of the picture is a soapy
   froth which the young frog-hopper makes, and within which it lies safe both
   from the heat of the sun and almost all enemies. After sojourning for a
   time in the cuckoo-spit, the frog-hopper becomes a winged insect.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image239c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>CUCKOO-SPIT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e5029">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Masking</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The episode in Scottish history called "The Walking Wood of
 Birnam," when the advancing troop masked their approach by cutting down
 branches of the trees, has had its counterpart in many countries. But it is
 also enacted on the seashore. There are many kinds of crabs that put on
 disguise with what looks like deliberateness. The sand-crab takes a piece of
 seaweed, nibbles at the end of it, and then rubs it on the back of the
 carapace or on the legs so that it fixes to the bristles. As the seaweed
 continues to live, the crab soon has a little garden on its back which masks
 the crab's real nature. It is most effective camouflaging, but if the
 crab continues to grow it has to moult, and that means losing the disguise.
 It is then necessary to make a new one. The crab must have on the shore
 something corresponding to a reputation; that is to say, other animals are
 clearly or dimly aware that the crab is a voracious and combative creature.
 How useful to the crab, then, to have its appearance cloaked by a growth of
 innocent seaweed, or sponge, or zoophyte. It will enable the creature to
 sneak upon its victims or to escape the attention of its own enemies.</p>
            <p>If a narrow-beaked crab is cleaned artificially it will proceed to clothe
 itself again, the habit has become instinctive; and it must be admitted that
 while a particular crab prefers a particular kind of seaweed for its dress,
 it will cover itself with unsuitable and even conspicuous material, such as
 pieces of coloured cloth, if nothing better is available. The disguise
 differs greatly, for one crab is masked by a brightly coloured and
 unpalatable sponge<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 149]</ph> densely packed with flinty needles; another cuts off the
 tunic of a sea-squirt and throws it over its shoulders; another trundles
 about a bivalve shell. The facts recall the familiar case of the hermit-crab,
 which protects its soft tail by tucking it into the empty shell of a
 periwinkle or a whelk or some other sea-snail, and that case leads on to the
 elaboration known as commensalism, where the hermit-crab fixes sea-anemones
 on the back of its borrowed house. The advantage here is beyond that of
 masking, for the sea-anemone can sting, which is a useful quality in a
 partner. That this second advantage may become the main one is evident in
 several cases where the sea-anemone is borne, just like a weapon, on each of
 the crustacean's great claws. Moreover, as the term commensalism (eating
 at the same table) suggests, the partnership is <i>mutually</i> beneficial.
 For the sea-anemone is carried about by the hermit-crab, and it doubtless
 gets its share of crumbs from its partner's frequent meals. There is a
 very interesting sidelight on the mutual benefit in the case of a dislodged
 sea-anemone which sulked for a while and then waited in a state of
 preparedness until a hermit-crab passed by and touched it. Whereupon the
 sea-anemone gripped and slowly worked itself up on to the back of the
 shell.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 6</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e5045">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Other Kinds of Elusiveness</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>There are various kinds of disguise which are not readily classified. A
 troop of cuttlefish swimming in the sea is a beautiful sight. They keep time
 with one another in their movements and they show the same change of colour
 almost at the same moment. They are suddenly attacked, however, by a small
 shark, and then comes a simultaneous discharge of sepia from their ink-bags.
 There are clouds of ink in the clear water, for, as Professor Hickson puts
 it, the cuttlefishes have thrown dust in the eyes of their enemies. One can
 see a newborn cuttlefish do this a minute after it escapes from the
 egg.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 150]</ph>
            </p>
            <p>Very beautiful is the way in which many birds, like our common chaffinch,
 disguise the outside of their nest with moss and lichen and other trifles
 felted together, so that the cradle is as inconspicuous as possible. There
 seems to be a touch of art in fastening pieces of spider's web on the
 outside of a nest!</p>
            <p>How curious is the case of the tree-sloth of South American forests, that
 walks slowly, back downwards, along the undersides of the branches, hanging
 on by its long, curved fingers and toes. It is a nocturnal animal, and
 therefore not in special danger, but when resting during the day it is almost
 invisible because its shaggy hair is so like certain lichens and other
 growths on the branches. But the protective resemblance is enhanced by the
 presence of a green alga, which actually lives on the surface of the
 sloth's hairs—an alga like the one that makes tree-stems and
 gate-posts green in damp weather.</p>
            <p>There is no commoner sight in the early summer than the cuckoo-spit on the
 grasses and herbage by the wayside. It is conspicuous and yet it is said to
 be left severely alone by almost all creatures. In some way it must be a
 disguise. It is a sort of soap made by the activity of small frog-hoppers
 while they are still in the wingless larval stage, before they begin to hop.
 The insect pierces with its sharp mouth-parts the skin of the plant and sucks
 in sweet sap which by and by overflows over its body. It works its body up
 and down many times, whipping in air, which mixes with the sugary sap,
 reminding one of how "whipped egg" is made. But along with the
 sugary sap and the air, there is a little ferment from the food-canal and a
 little wax from glands on the skin, and the four things mixed together make a
 kind of soap which lasts through the heat of the day.</p>
            <p>There are many other modes of disguise besides those which we have been
 able to illustrate. Indeed, the biggest fact is that there are so many, for
 it brings us back to the idea that life is not an easy business. It is true,
 as Walt Whitman says, that animals do not sweat and whine about their
 condition; perhaps it is true,<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 151]</ph> as he says, that not one is unhappy over the
 whole earth. But there is another truth, that this world is not a place for
 the unlit lamp and the ungirt loin, and that when a creature has not armour
 or weapons or cleverness it must find some path of safety or go back. One of
 these paths of safety is disguise, and we have illustrated its
 evolution.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 152]</ph>
            </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 153]</ph>
            </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 154]</ph>
            </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 155]</ph>
            </p>
            <!--hr--></body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
</topic>