<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="chapter_04">
   <title>
      <ph outputclass="title-line">III</ph> 
      <ph outputclass="title-line">ADAPTATIONS TO ENVIRONMENT</ph> 
   </title>
   <body><!--hr--></body>
   <topic id="d1e3921">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">ADAPTATIONS TO ENVIRONMENT</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>We saw in a previous chapter how the process of evolution led to a mastery
 of all the haunts of life. But it is necessary to return to these haunts or
 homes of animals in some detail, so as to understand the peculiar
 circumstances of each, and to see how in the course of ages of struggle all
 sorts of self-preserving and race-continuing adaptations or fitnesses have
 been wrought out and firmly established. Living creatures have spread over
 all the earth and in the waters under the earth; some of them have conquered
 the underground world and others the air. It is possible, however, as has
 been indicated, to distinguish six great haunts of life, each tenanted by a
 distinctive fauna, namely, the shore of the sea, the open sea, the depths of
 the sea, the freshwaters, the dry land, and the air. In the deep sea there
 are no plants at all; in the air the only plants are floating bacteria,
 though there is a sense in which a tree is very aerial, and the orchid
 perched on its branches still more so; in the other four haunts there is a
 flora as well as a fauna—the two working into one another's hands
 in interesting and often subtle inter-relations—the subject of a
 separate study.</p>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e3925">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">I. THE SHORE OF THE SEA</ph> 
      </title>
      <body/>
      <topic id="d1e3927">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Seaweed Area</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>By the shore of the sea the zoologist means much more than the narrow zone
 between tide-marks; he means the whole of the relatively shallow,
 well-illumined, seaweed-growing shelf around the continents and continental
 islands. Technically, this is called<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 116]</ph> the littoral area, and it is divisible into
 zones, each with its characteristic population. It may be noted that the
 green seaweeds are highest up on the shore; the brown ones come next; the
 beautiful red ones are lowest. All of them have got green chlorophyll, which
 enables them to utilise the sun's rays in photosynthesis (i.e. building
 up carbon compounds from air, water, and salts), but in the brown and red
 seaweeds the green pigment is masked by others. It is maintained by some
 botanists that these other pigments enable their possessors to make more of
 the scantier light in the deeper waters. However this may be, we must always
 think of the shore-haunt as the seaweed-growing area. Directly and indirectly
 the life of the shore animals is closely wrapped up with the seaweeds, which
 afford food and foothold, and temper the force of the waves. The minute
 fragments broken off from seaweeds and from the sea-grass (a flowering plant
 called Zostera) form a sort of nutritive sea-dust which is swept slowly down
 the slope from the shore, to form a very useful deposit in the quietness of
 deepish water. It is often found in the stomachs of marine animals living a
 long way offshore.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e3936">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Conditions of Shore Life</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The littoral area as defined is not a large haunt of life; it occupies
 only about 9 million square miles, a small fraction of the 197,000,000 of the
 whole earth's surface. But it is a very long haunt, some 150,000 miles,
 winding in and out by bay and fiord, estuary and creek. Where deep water
 comes close to cliffs there may be no shore at all; in other places the
 relatively shallow water, with seaweeds growing over the bottom, may extend
 outwards for miles. The nature of the shore varies greatly according to the
 nature of the rocks, according to what the streams bring down from inland,
 and according to the jetsam that is brought in by the tides. The shore is a
 changeful place; there is, in the upper reaches, a striking difference
 between "tide in" and "tide out"; there are vicissitudes
 due to storms, to freshwater floods, to<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 117]</ph> wind-blown sand, and to slow
 changes of level, up and down. The shore is a very crowded haunt, for it is
 comparatively narrow, and every niche among the rocks may be precious.</p>
            <fig id="image190a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>AN EIGHT-ARMED CUTTLEFISH OR OCTOPUS ATTACKING A SMALL CRAB</p>

               <p>These molluscs are particularly fond of crustaceans, which
   they crunch with their parrot's beak-like jaws. Their salivary juice
   has a paralysing effect on their prey. To one side, below the eye, may be
   seen the funnel through which water is very forcibly ejected in the process
   of locomotion.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image190a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>AN EIGHT-ARMED CUTTLEFISH OR OCTOPUS ATTACKING A SMALL CRAB</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image190b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>A COMMON STARFISH, WHICH HAS LOST THREE ARMS AND IS REGROWING THEM</p>

               <p>The lowest arm is being regrown double.</p>

               <p>(<i>After Professor W. C. McIntosh.</i>)</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image190b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A COMMON STARFISH, WHICH HAS LOST THREE ARMS AND IS REGROWING THEM</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image191a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>A PHOTOGRAPH SHOWING A STARFISH (<i>Asterias Forreri</i>) WHICH HAS
   CAPTURED A LARGE FISH</p>

               <p>The suctorial tube-feet are seen gripping the fish firmly.
   (After an observation on the Californian coast.)</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image191a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A PHOTOGRAPH SHOWING A STARFISH (Asterias Forreri) WHICH HAS CAPTURED A LARGE FISH</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image191b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: J. J. Ward, F.E.S.</i>
               </p>

               <p>THE PAPER NAUTILUS (ARGONAUTA), AN ANIMAL OF THE OPEN SEA</p>

               <p>The delicate shell is made by the female only, and is used
   as a shelter for the eggs and young ones. It is secreted by two of the
   arms, not by the mantle as other mollusc shells are. It is a
   single-chambered shell, very different from that of the Pearly
   Nautilus.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image191b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE PAPER NAUTILUS (ARGONAUTA), AN ANIMAL OF THE OPEN SEA</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4022">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Keen Struggle for Existence</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It follows that the shore must be the scene of a keen struggle for
 existence—which includes all the answers-back that living creatures
 make to environing difficulties and limitations. There is struggle for food,
 accentuated by the fact that small items tend to be swept away by the
 outgoing tide or to sink down the slope to deep water. Apart from direct
 competition, e.g. between hungry hermit-crabs, it often involves hard work to
 get a meal. This is true even of apparently sluggish creatures. Thus the
 Crumb-of-Bread Sponge, or any other seashore sponge, has to lash large
 quantities of water through the intricate canal system of its body before it
 can get a sufficient supply of the microscopic organisms and organic
 particles on which it feeds. An index of the intensity of the struggle for
 food is afforded by the nutritive chains which bind animals together. The
 shore is almost noisy with the conjugation of the verb to eat in its many
 tenses. One pound of rock-cod requires for its formation ten pounds of whelk;
 one pound of whelk requires ten pounds of sea-worms; and one pound of worms
 requires ten pounds of sea-dust. Such is the circulation of matter, ever
 passing from one embodiment or incarnation to another.</p>
            <p>Besides struggle for food there is struggle for foothold and for fresh
 air, struggle against the scouring tide and against the pounding breakers.
 The risk of dislodgment is often great and the fracture of limbs is a common
 accident. Of kinds of armour—the sea-urchin's hedgehog-like test,
 the crab's shard, the limpet's shell—there is great variety,
 surpassed only by that of weapons—the sea-anemone's stinging-cells,
 the sea-urchin's snapping-blades, the hermit-crab's forceps, the
 grappling tentacles and parrot's-beak jaws of the octopus.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 118]</ph>
            </p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4031">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Shifts for a Living</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>We get another glimpse of the intensity of the seashore struggle for
 existence in the frequency of "shifts for a living," adaptations of
 structure or of behaviour which meet frequently recurrent vicissitudes. The
 starfish is often in the dilemma of losing a limb or its life; by a reflex
 action it jettisons the captured arm and escapes. And what is lost is
 gradually regrown. The crab gets its leg broken past all mending; it casts
 off the leg across a weak breakage plane near the base, and within a
 preformed bandage which prevents bleeding a new leg is formed in miniature.
 Such is the adaptive device—more reflex than reflective—which is
 called self-mutilation or autotomy.</p>
            <p>In another part of this book there is a discussion of camouflaging and
 protective resemblance; how abundantly these are illustrated on the shore!
 But there are other "shifts for a living." Some of the sand-hoppers
 and their relatives illustrate the puzzling phenomenon of "feigning
 death," becoming suddenly so motionless that they escape the eyes of
 their enemies. Cuttlefishes, by discharging sepia from their ink-bags, are
 able to throw dust in the eyes of their enemies. Some undisguised
 shore-animals, e.g. crabs, are adepts in a hide-and-seek game; some fishes,
 like the butterfish or gunnel, escape between stones where there seemed no
 opening and are almost uncatchable in their slipperiness. Subtlest of all,
 perhaps, is the habit some hermit-crabs have of entering into mutually
 beneficial partnership (commensalism) with sea-anemones, which mask their
 bearers and also serve as mounted batteries, getting transport as their
 reward and likewise crumbs from the frequently spread table. But enough has
 been said to show that the shore-haunt exhibits an extraordinary variety of
 shifts for a living.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4038">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Parental Care on the Shore</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>According to Darwin, the struggle for existence, as a big fact in the
 economy of Animate Nature, includes not only competition<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 119]</ph> but all the
 endeavours which secure the welfare of the offspring, and give them a good
 send-off in life. So it is without a jolt that we pass from struggle for food
 and foothold to parental care. The marine leech called Pontobdella, an
 interesting greenish warty creature fond of fixing itself to skate, places
 its egg-cocoons in the empty shell of a bivalve mollusc, and guards them for
 weeks, removing any mud that might injure their development. We have seen a
 British starfish with its fully-formed young ones creeping about on its body,
 though the usual mode of development for shore starfishes is that the young
 ones pass through a free-swimming larval period in the open water. The father
 sea-spider carries about the eggs attached to two of his limbs; the father
 sea-horse puts his mate's eggs into his breast pocket and carries them
 there in safety until they are hatched; the father stickleback of the
 shore-pools makes a seaweed nest and guards the eggs which his wives are
 induced to lay there; the father lumpsucker mounts guard over the bunch of
 pinkish eggs which his mate has laid in a nook of a rocky shore-pool, and
 drives off intruders with zest. He also aerates the developing eggs by
 frequent paddling with his pectoral fins and tail, as the Scots name
 Cock-paidle probably suggests. It is interesting that the salient examples of
 parental care in the shore-haunt are mostly on the male parent's side.
 But there is maternal virtue as well.</p>
            <fig id="image194a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>TEN-ARMED CUTTLEFISH OR SQUID IN THE ACT OF CAPTURING A FISH</p>

               <p>The arms bear numerous prehensile suckers, which grip the
   prey. In the mouth there are strong jaws shaped like a parrot's beak.
   The cuttlefishes are molluscs and may be regarded as the highest of the
   backboneless or Invertebrate animals. Many occur near shore, others in the
   open sea, and others in the great depths.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image194a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>TEN-ARMED CUTTLEFISH OR SQUID IN THE ACT OF CAPTURING A FISH</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image194b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>GREENLAND WHALE</p>

               <p>Showing the double blowhole or nostrils on the top of the
   head and the whalebone plates hanging down from the roof of the mouth.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image194b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>GREENLAND WHALE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image195a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>MINUTE TRANSPARENT EARLY STAGE OF A SEA-CUCUMBER</p>

               <p>It swims in the open sea by means of girdles of microscopic
   cilia shown in the figure. After a period of free swimming and a remarkable
   metamorphosis, the animal settles down on the floor of the sea in
   relatively shallow water.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image195a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>MINUTE TRANSPARENT EARLY STAGE OF A SEA-CUCUMBER</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image195b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: British Museum (Natural History)</i>
               </p>

               <p>AN INTRICATE COLONY OF OPEN-SEA ANIMALS (<i>Physophora Hydrostatica</i>)
   RELATED TO THE PORTUGUESE MAN-OF-WAR</p>

               <p>There is great division of labor in the colony. At the top
   are floating and swimming "persons"; the long ones below are
   offensive "persons" bearing batteries of stinging cells; in the
   middle zone there are nutritive, reproductive, and other
   "persons." The color of the colony is a fine translucent blue.
   Swimmers and bathers are often badly stung by this strange animal and its
   relatives.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image195b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>AN INTRICATE COLONY OF OPEN-SEA ANIMALS (Physophora Hydrostatica) RELATED TO THE PORTUGUESE MAN-OF-WAR</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image195c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>A SCENE IN THE GREAT DEPTHS</p>

               <p>Showing a deep-sea fish of large gape, two feather-stars on
   the end of long stalks, a "sea-spider" (or Pycnogon) walking on
   lanky legs on the treacherous ooze, likewise a brittle-star, and some
   deep-sea corals.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image195c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A SCENE IN THE GREAT DEPTHS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>The fauna of the shore is remarkably <i>representative</i>—from
 unicellular Protozoa to birds like the oyster-catcher and mammals like the
 seals. Almost all the great groups of animals have apparently served an
 apprenticeship in the shore-haunt, and since lessons learned for millions of
 years sink in and become organically enregistered, it is justifiable to look
 to the shore as a great school in which were gained racial qualities of
 endurance, patience, and alertness.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e4139">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">II. THE OPEN SEA</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>In great contrast to the narrow, crowded, difficult conditions of the
 shore-haunt (littoral area) are the spacious, bountiful, and<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 120]</ph> relatively
 easygoing conditions of the open sea (pelagic area), which means the
 well-lighted surface waters quite away from land. Many small organisms have
 their maximum abundance at about fifty fathoms, so that the word
 "surface" is to be taken generously. The light becomes very dim at
 250 fathoms, and the open sea, as a zoological haunt, stops with the light.
 It is hardly necessary to say that the pelagic plants are more abundant near
 the surface, and that below a certain depth the population consists almost
 exclusively of animals. Not a few of the animals sink and rise in the water
 periodically; there are some that come near the surface by day, and others
 that come near the surface by night. Of great interest is the habit of the
 extremely delicate Ctenophores or "sea-gooseberries," which the
 splash of a wave would tear into shreds. Whenever there is any hint of a
 storm they sink beyond its reach, and the ocean's surface must have
 remained flat as a mirror for many hours before they can be lured upwards
 from the calm of their deep retreat.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e4148">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Floating Sea-meadows</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>To understand the vital economy of the open sea, we must recognise the
 incalculable abundance of minute unicellular plants, for they form the
 fundamental food-supply. Along with these must also be included numerous
 microscopic animals which have got possession of chlorophyll, or have entered
 into internal partnership with unicellular Algæ (symbiosis). These green or
 greenish plants and animals are the <i>producers</i>, using the energy of the
 sunlight to help them in building up carbon compounds out of air, water, and
 salts. The animals which feed on the producers, or on other animals, are the
 <i>consumers</i>. Between the two come those open-sea bacteria that convert
 nitrogenous material, e.g. from dead plants or animals that other bacteria
 have rotted, into forms, e.g. nitrates, which plants can re-utilise. The
 importance of these <i>middlemen</i> is great in keeping "the
 circulation of matter" agoing.</p>
            <fig id="image198"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>1. SEA-HORSE IN SARGASSO WEED. In its frond-like tags of
   skin and in its colouring this kind of sea-horse is well concealed among
   the floating seaweed of the so-called Sargasso Sea.</p>

               <p>2. THE LARGE MARINE LAMPREYS (<i>PETROMYZON MARINUS</i>),
   WHICH MAY BE AS LONG AS ONE'S ARM, SPAWN IN FRESH WATER. Stones and
   pebbles, gripped in the suctorial mouth, are removed from a selected spot
   and piled around the circumference, so that the eggs, which are laid within
   the circle, are not easily washed away.</p>

               <p>3. THE DEEP-SEA FISH <i>CHIASMODON NIGER</i> IS FAMOUS FOR
   ITS VORACITY. It sometimes manages to swallow a fish larger than itself,
   which causes an extraordinary protrusion of the stomach.</p>

               <p>4. DEEP-SEA FISHES. Two of them—<i>Melanocetus
   murrayi</i> and <i>Melanocetus indicus</i>—are related to the Angler
   of British coasts, but adapted to life in the great abysses. They are very
   dark in colour, and delicately built; they possess well-developed luminous
   organs. The third form is called Chauliodus, a predatory animal with large
   gape and formidable teeth.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image198_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE DEEP-SEA FISH</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image199a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FLINTY SKELETON OF VENUS FLOWER BASKET (EUPLECTELLA), A JAPANESE
   DEEP-SEA SPONGE</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image199a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>FLINTY SKELETON OF VENUS FLOWER BASKET (EUPLECTELLA), A JAPANESE DEEP-SEA SPONGE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image199b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>EGG DEPOSITORY OF <i>Semotilus Atromaculatus</i>
               </p>

               <p>In the building of this egg depository, the male fish takes
   stones from the bottom of the stream, gripping them in his mouth, and heaps
   them up into the dam. In the egg depository he arranges the stones so that
   when the eggs are deposited in the interstices they are thoroughly
   protected, and cannot be washed down-stream.</p>

               <p>1, dam of stones; 2, egg depository; 3, hillock of sand.
   The arrow shows the direction of the stream. Upper fish, male; lower,
   female.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image199b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>EGG DEPOSITORY OF Semotilus Atromaculatus</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 121]</ph>
            </p>
            <p>The "floating sea-meadows," as Sir John Murray called them, are
 always receiving contributions from inshore waters, where the conditions are
 favourable for the prolific multiplication of unicellular Algæ, and there is
 also a certain amount of non-living sea-dust always being swept out from the
 seaweed and sea-grass area.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4236">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Swimmers and Drifters</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The animals of the open sea are conveniently divided into the active
 swimmers (Nekton) and the more passive drifters (Plankton). The swimmers
 include whales great and small, such birds as the storm petrel, the
 fish-eating turtles and sea-snakes, such fishes as mackerel and herring, the
 winged snails or sea-butterflies on which whalebone whales largely feed, some
 of the active cuttles or squids, various open-sea prawns and their relatives,
 some worms like the transparent arrow-worm, and such active Protozoa as
 Noctiluca, whose luminescence makes the waves sparkle in the short summer
 darkness. Very striking as an instance of the insurgence of life are the
 sea-skimmers (Halobatidæ), wingless insects related to the water-measurers in
 the ditch. They are found hundreds of miles from land, skimming on the
 surface of the open sea, and diving in stormy weather. They feed on floating
 dead animals.</p>
            <p>The drifters or easygoing swimmers—for there is no hard and fast
 line—are represented, for instance, by the flinty-shelled Radiolarians
 and certain of the chalk-forming animals (Globigerinid Foraminifera); by
 jellyfishes, swimming-bells, and Portuguese men-of-war; by the comb-bearers
 or Ctenophores; by legions of minute Crustaceans; by strange animals called
 Salps, related to the sedentary sea-squirts; and by some sluggish fishes like
 globe-fishes, which often float idly on the surface.</p>
            <p>Open-sea animals tend to be delicately built, with a specific gravity near
 that of the sea-water, with adaptations, such as projecting filaments, which
 help flotation, and with capacities of<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 122]</ph> rising and sinking according to
 the surrounding conditions. Many of them are luminescent, and many of them
 are very inconspicuous in the water owing to their transparency or their
 bluish colour. In both cases the significance is obscure.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4249">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Hunger and Love</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Hunger is often very much in evidence in the open sea, especially in areas
 where the Plankton is poor. For there is great diversity in this respect,
 most of the Mediterranean, for instance, having a scanty Plankton as compared
 with the North Sea. In the South Pacific, west of Patagonia, there is said to
 be an immense "sea desert" where there is little Plankton, and
 therefore little in the way of fishes. The success of fisheries in the North,
 e.g. on the Atlantic cod-banks, is due to the richness of the floating
 sea-meadows and the abundance of the smaller constituents of the animal
 Plankton.</p>
            <p>Hunger is plain enough when the Baleen Whale rushes through the water with
 open jaws, engulfing in the huge cavern of its mouth, where the pendent
 whalebone plates form a huge sieve, incalculable millions of small fry.</p>
            <p>But there is love as well as hunger in the open sea. The maternal care
 exhibited by the whale reaches a very high level, and the delicate shell of
 the female Paper Nautilus or Argonaut, in which the eggs and the young ones
 are sheltered, may well be described as "the most beautiful cradle in
 the world."</p>
            <p>Besides the permanent inhabitants of the open sea, there are the larval
 stages of many shore-animals which are there only for a short time. For there
 is an interesting give and take between the shore-haunt and the open sea.
 From the shore come nutritive contributions and minute organisms which
 multiply quickly in the open waters. But not less important is the fact that
 the open waters afford a safe cradle or nursery for many a delicate larva,
 e.g. of crab and starfish, acorn-shell and sea-urchin, which could not
 survive for a day in the rough-and-tumble conditions of the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 123]</ph> shore and the
 shallow water. After undergoing radical changes and gaining strength, the
 young creatures return to the shore in various ways.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e4263">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">III. THE DEEP SEA</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>Very different from all the other haunts are the depths of the sea,
 including the floor of the abysses and the zones of water near the bottom.
 This haunt, forever unseen, occupies more than a third of the earth's
 surface, and it is thickly peopled. It came into emphatic notice in
 connection with the mending of telegraph cables, but the results of the
 <i>Challenger</i> expedition (1873-6) gave the first impressive picture of
 what was practically a new world.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e4270">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Physical Conditions</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The average depth of the ocean is about two and a half miles; therefore,
 since many parts are relatively shallow, there must be enormous depths. A few
 of these, technically called "deeps," are about six miles deep, in
 which Mount Everest would be engulfed. There is enormous pressure in such
 depths; even at 2,500 fathoms it is two and a half tons on the square inch.
 The temperature is on and off the freezing-point of fresh water (28°-34°
 Fahr.), due to the continual sinking down of cold water from the Poles,
 especially from the South. Apart from the fitful gleams of luminescent
 animals, there is utter darkness in the deep waters. The rays of sunlight are
 practically extinguished at 250 fathoms, though very sensitive bromogelatine
 plates exposed at 500 fathoms have shown faint indications even at that
 depth. It is a world of absolute calm and silence, and there is no scenery on
 the floor. A deep, cold, dark, silent, monotonous world!</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4274">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Biological Conditions</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>While some parts of the floor of the abysses are more thickly peopled than
 others, there is no depth limit to the distribution of<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 124]</ph> life. Wherever
 the long arm of the dredge has reached, animals have been found, e.g.
 Protozoa, sponges, corals, worms, starfishes, sea-urchins, sea-lilies,
 crustaceans, lamp-shells, molluscs, ascidians, and fishes—a very
 representative fauna. In the absence of light there can be no
 chlorophyll-possessing plants, and as the animals cannot all be eating one
 another there must be an extraneous source of food-supply. This is found in
 the sinking down of minute organisms which are killed on the surface by
 changes of temperature and other causes. What is left of them, before or
 after being swallowed, and of sea-dust and mineral particles of various kinds
 forms the diversified "ooze" of the sea-floor, a soft muddy
 precipitate, which is said to have in places the consistence of butter in
 summer weather.</p>
            <p>There seems to be no bacteria in the abysses, so there can be no rotting.
 Everything that sinks down, even the huge carcase of a whale, must be nibbled
 away by hungry animals and digested, or else, in the case of most bones,
 slowly dissolved away. Of the whale there are left only the ear-bones, of the
 shark his teeth.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e4285">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Adaptations to Deep-sea Life</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>In adaptation to the great pressure the bodies of deep-sea animals are
 usually very permeable, so that the water gets through and through them, as
 in the case of Venus' Flower Basket, a flinty sponge which a child's
 finger would shiver. But when the pressure inside is the same as that outside
 nothing happens. In adaptation to the treacherous ooze, so apt to smother,
 many of the active deep-sea animals have very long, stilt-like legs, and many
 of the sedentary types are lifted into safety on the end of long stalks which
 have their bases embedded in the mud. In adaptation to the darkness, in which
 there is only luminescence that eyes could use, there is a great development
 of tactility. The interesting problem of luminescence will be discussed
 elsewhere.</p>
            <p>As to the origin of the deep-sea fauna, there seems no doubt<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 125]</ph> that it has
 arisen by many contributions from the various shore-haunts. Following the
 down-drifting food, many shore-animals have in the course of many generations
 reached the world of eternal night and winter, and become adapted to its
 strange conditions. For the animals of the deep-sea are as fit, beautiful,
 and vigorous as those elsewhere. There are no slums in Nature.</p>
            <fig id="image204a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE BITTERLING (<i>Rhodeus Amarus</i>)</p>

               <p>A Continental fish which lays its eggs by means of a long
   ovipositor inside the freshwater mussel. The eggs develop inside the
   mollusc's gill-plates.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image204a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE BITTERLING (Rhodeus Amarus)</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image204b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: W. S. Berridge.</i>
               </p>

               <p>WOOLLY OPOSSUM CARRYING HER FAMILY</p>

               <p>One of the young ones is clinging to its mother and has its
   long prehensile tail coiled round hers.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image204b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>WOOLLY OPOSSUM CARRYING HER FAMILY</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image205a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>SURINAM TOAD (<i>Pipa Americana</i>) WITH YOUNG ONES HATCHING OUT OF
   LITTLE POCKETS ON HER BACK</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image205a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SURINAM TOAD (Pipa Americana) WITH YOUNG ONES HATCHING OUT OF LITTLE POCKETS ON HER BACK</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image205b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>STORM PETREL OR MOTHER CAREY'S CHICKEN</p>

               <p>(<i>Procellaria Pelagica</i>)</p>

               <p>This characteristic bird of the open sea does not come to
   land at all except to nest. It is the smallest web-footed bird, about four
   inches long. The legs are long and often touch the water as the bird flies.
   The storm petrel is at home in the Atlantic, and often nests on islands off
   the west coast of Britain.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image205b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>STORM PETREL OR MOTHER CAREY'S CHICKEN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e4373">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">IV. THE FRESH WATERS</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>Of the whole earth's surface the freshwaters form a very small
 fraction, about a hundredth, but they make up for their smallness by their
 variety. We think of deep lake and shallow pond, of the great river and the
 purling brook, of lagoon and swamp, and more besides. There is a striking
 resemblance in the animal population of widely separated freshwater basins:
 and this is partly because birds carry many small creatures on their muddy
 feet from one water-shed to another; partly because some of the freshwater
 animals are descended from types which make their way from the sea and the
 seashore through estuaries and marshes, and only certain kinds of
 constitution could survive the migration; and partly because some lakes are
 landlocked dwindling relics of ancient seas, and similar forms again would
 survive the change.</p>
         <p>A typical assemblage of freshwater animals would include many Protozoa,
 like Amœbæ and the Bell-Animalcules, a representative of one family of
 sponges (Spongillidæ), the common Hydra, many unsegmented worms (notably
 Planarians and Nematodes), many Annelids related to the earthworms, many
 crustaceans, insects, and mites, many bivalves and snails, various fishes, a
 newt or two, perhaps a little mud-turtle or in warm countries a huge
 Crocodilian, various interesting birds like the water-ouzel or dipper, and
 mammals like the water-vole and the water-shrew.</p>
         <p>Freshwater animals have to face certain difficulties, the greatest of
 which are drought, frost, and being washed away in<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 126]</ph> times of
 flood. There is no more interesting study in the world than an inquiry into
 the adaptations by which freshwater animals overcome the difficulties of the
 situation. We cannot give more than a few illustrations.</p>
         <p>(1) Drought is circumvented by the capacity that many freshwater animals
 have of lying low and saying nothing. Thus the African mudfish may spend half
 the year encased in the mud, and many minute crustaceans can survive being
 dried up for years. (2) Escape from the danger of being frozen hard in the
 pool is largely due to the almost unique property of water that it expands as
 it approaches the freezing-point. Thus the colder water rises to the surface
 and forms or adds to the protecting blanket of ice. The warmer water remains
 unfrozen at the bottom, and the animals live on. (3) The risk of being washed
 away, e.g. to the sea, is lessened by all sorts of gripping, grappling, and
 anchoring structures, and by shortening the juvenile stages when the risks
 are greatest.</p>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e4388">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">V. THE DRY LAND</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>Over and over again in the history of animal life there have been attempts
 to get out of the water on to terra firma, and many of these have been
 successful, notably those made (1) by worms, (2) by air-breathing Arthropods,
 and (3) by amphibians.</p>
         <p>In thinking of the conquest of the dry land by animals, we must recognise
 the indispensable rôle of plants in preparing the way. The dry ground would
 have proved too inhospitable had not terrestrial plants begun to establish
 themselves, affording food, shelter, and humidity. There had to be plants
 before there could be earthworms, which feed on decaying leaves and the like,
 but how soon was the debt repaid when the earthworms began their worldwide
 task of forming vegetable mould, opening up the earth with their burrows,
 circulating the soil by means of their castings, and bruising the particles
 in their gizzard—certainly the most important mill in the
 world.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 127]</ph>
         </p>
         <p>Another important idea is that littoral haunts, both on the seashore and
 in the freshwaters, afforded the necessary apprenticeship and transitional
 experience for the more strenuous life on dry land. Much that was perfected
 on land had its beginnings on the shore. Let us inquire, however, what the
 passage from water to dry land actually implied. This has been briefly
 discussed in a previous article (on Evolution), but the subject is one of
 great interest and importance.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e4399">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Difficulties and Results of the Transition from Water to
 Land</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Leaving the water for dry land implied a loss in freedom of movement, for
 the terrestrial animal is primarily restricted to the surface of the earth.
 Thus it became essential that movements should be very rapid and very
 precise, needs with which we may associate the acquisition of fine
 cross-striped, quickly contracting muscles, and also, in time, their
 multiplication into very numerous separate engines. We exercise fifty-four
 muscles in the half-second that elapses between raising the heel of our foot
 in walking and planting it firmly on the ground again. Moreover, the need for
 rapid precisely controlled movements implied an improved nervous system, for
 the brain was a movement-controlling organ for ages before it did much in the
 way of thinking. The transition to terra firma also involved a greater
 compactness of body, so that there should not be too great friction on the
 surface. An animal like the jellyfish is unthinkable on land, and the
 elongated bodies of some land animals like centipedes and snakes are
 specially adapted so that they do not "sprawl." They are exceptions
 that prove the rule.</p>
            <p>Getting on to dry land meant entering a kingdom where the differences
 between day and night, between summer and winter are more felt than in the
 sea. This made it advantageous to have protections against evaporation and
 loss of heat and other such dangers. Hence a variety of ways in which the
 surface of the body acquired a thickened skin, or a dead cuticle, or a shell,
 or a<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 128]</ph> growth of hair, and so forth. In many cases there is an
 increase of the protection before the winter sets in, e.g. by growing thicker
 fur or by accumulating a layer of fat below the skin.</p>
            <p>But the thickening or protection of the skin involved a partial or total
 loss of the skin as a respiratory surface. There is more oxygen available on
 dry land than in the water, but it is not so readily captured. Thus we see
 the importance of moist internal surfaces for capturing the oxygen which has
 been drawn into the interior of the body into some sort of lung. A unique
 solution was offered by Tracheate Arthropods, such as Peripatus, Centipedes,
 Millipedes, and Insects, where the air is carried to every hole and corner of
 the body by a ramifying system of air-tubes or tracheæ. In most animals the
 blood goes to the air, in insects the air goes to the blood. In the
 Robber-Crab, which has migrated from the shore inland, the dry air is
 absorbed by vascular tufts growing under the shelter of the gill-cover.</p>
            <p>The problem of disposing of eggs or young ones is obviously much more
 difficult on land than in the water. For the water offers an immediate
 cradle, whereas on the dry land there were many dangers, e.g. of drought,
 extremes of temperature, and hungry sharp-eyed enemies, which had to be
 circumvented. So we find all manner of ways in which land animals hide their
 eggs or their young ones in holes and nests, on herbs and on trees. Some
 carry their young ones about after they are born, like the Surinam toad and
 the kangaroo, while others have prolonged the period of ante-natal life
 during which the young ones develop in safety within their mother, and in
 very intimate partnership with her in the case of the placental mammals. It
 is very interesting to find that the pioneer animal called Peripatus, which
 bridges the gap between worms and insects, carries its young for almost a
 year before birth.</p>
            <p>Enough has been said to show that the successive conquests of the dry land
 had great evolutionary results. It is hardly too much to say that the
 invasion which the Amphibians led was the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 129]</ph> beginning of better brains, more
 controlled activities, and higher expressions of family life.</p>
            <fig id="image210"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>ALBATROSS: A CHARACTERISTIC PELAGIC BIRD OF THE SOUTHERN SEA</p>

               <p>It may have a spread of wing of over 11 feet from tip to
   tip. It is famous for its extraordinary power of "sailing" round
   the ship without any apparent strokes of its wings.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image210_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>ALBATROSS: A CHARACTERISTIC PELAGIC BIRD OF THE SOUTHERN SEA</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e4436">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">VI. THE AIR</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>There are no animals thoroughly aerial, but many insects spend much of
 their adult life in the free air, and the swift hardly pauses in its flight
 from dawn to dusk of the long summer day, alighting only for brief moments at
 the nest to deliver insects to the young. All the active life of bats
 certainly deserves to be called aerial.</p>
         <p>The air was the last haunt of life to be conquered, and it is interesting
 to inquire what the conquest implied. (1) It meant transcending the radical
 difficulty of terrestrial life which confines the creatures of the dry land
 to moving on one plane, the surface of the earth. But the power of flight
 brought its possessors back to the universal freedom of movement which water
 animals enjoy. When we watch a sparrow rise into the air just as the cat has
 completed her stealthy stalking, we see that flight implies an enormous
 increase of safety. (2) The power of flight also opened up new possibilities
 of following the prey, of exploring new territories, of prospecting for
 water. (3) Of great importance too was the practicability of placing the eggs
 and the young, perhaps in a nest, in some place inaccessible to most enemies.
 When one thinks of it, the rooks' nests swaying on the tree-tops express
 the climax of a brilliant experiment. (4) The crowning advantage was the
 possibility of migrating, of conquering time (by circumventing the arid
 summer and the severe winter) and of conquering space (by passing quickly
 from one country to another and sometimes almost girdling the globe). There
 are not many acquisitions that have meant more to their possessors than the
 power of flight. It was a key opening the doors of a new freedom.</p>
         <p>The problem of flight, as has been said in a previous chapter,<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 130]</ph> has been
 solved four times, and the solution has been different in each case. The four
 solutions are those offered by insects, extinct Pterodactyls, birds, and
 bats. Moreover, as has been pointed out, there have been numerous attempts at
 flight which remain glorious failures, notably the flying fishes, which take
 a great leap and hold their pectoral fins taut; the Flying Tree-Toad, whose
 webbed fingers and toes form a parachute; the Flying Lizard (<i>Draco
 volans</i>), which has its skin pushed out on five or six greatly elongated
 mobile ribs; and various "flying" mammals, e.g. Flying Phalangers
 and Flying Squirrels, which take great swooping leaps from tree to tree.</p>
         <p>The wings of an insect are hollow flattened sacs which grow out from the
 upper parts of the sides of the second and third rings of the region called
 the thorax. They are worked by powerful muscles, and are supported, like a
 fan, by ribs of chitin, which may be accompanied by air-tubes,
 blood-channels, and nerves. The insect's body is lightly built and very
 perfectly aerated, and the principle of the insect's flight is the
 extremely rapid striking of the air by means of the lightly built elastic
 wings. Many an insect has over two hundred strokes of its wings in one
 <i>second</i>. Hence, in many cases, the familiar hum, comparable on a small
 scale to that produced by the rapidly revolving blades of an aeroplane's
 propeller. For a short distance a bee can outfly a pigeon, but few insects
 can fly far, and they are easily blown away or blown back by the wind.
 Dragon-flies and bees may be cited as examples of insects that often fly for
 two or three miles. But this is exceptional, and the usual shortness of
 insect flight is an important fact for man since it limits the range of
 insects like house-flies and mosquitoes which are vehicles of typhoid fever
 and malaria respectively. The most primitive insects (spring-tails and
 bristle-tails) show no trace of wings, while fleas and lice have become
 secondarily wingless. It is interesting to notice that some insects only fly
 once in their lifetime, namely, in connection with mating. The evolution of
 the insect's wing remains quite<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 131]</ph> obscure, but it is probable that insects
 could run, leap, and parachute before they could actually fly.</p>
         <p>The extinct Flying Dragons or Pterodactyls had their golden age in the
 Cretaceous era, after which they disappeared, leaving no descendants. A fold
 of skin was spread out from the sides of the body by the enormously elongated
 outermost finger (usually regarded as corresponding to our little finger); it
 was continued to the hind-legs and thence to the tail.</p>
         <p>It is unlikely that the Pterodactyls could fly far, for they have at most
 a weak keel on their breast-bone; on the other hand, some of them show a
 marked fusion of dorsal vertebræ, which, as in flying birds, must have served
 as a firm fulcrum for the stroke of the wings. The quaint creatures varied
 from the size of a sparrow up to a magnificent spread of 15-20 feet from tip
 to tip of the wings. They were the largest of all flying creatures.</p>
         <p>The bird's solution of the problem of flight, which will be discussed
 separately, is centred in the feather, which forms a coherent vane for
 striking the air. In Pterodactyl and bat the wing is a web-wing or patagium,
 and a small web is to be seen on the front side of the bird's wing. But
 the bird's patagium is unimportant, and the bird's wing is on an
 evolutionary tack of its own—a fore-limb transformed for bearing the
 feathers of flight. Feathers are in a general way comparable to the scales of
 reptiles, but only in a general way, and no transition stage is known between
 the two. Birds evolved from a bipedal Dinosaur stock, as has been noticed
 already, and it is highly probable that they began their ascent by taking
 running leaps along the ground, flapping their scaly fore-limbs, and
 balancing themselves in kangaroo-like fashion with an extended tail. A second
 chapter was probably an arboreal apprenticeship, during which they made a
 fine art of parachuting—a persistence of which is to be seen in the
 pigeon "gliding" from the dovecot to the ground. It is in birds
 that the mastery of the air reaches its climax, and the mysterious
 "sailing" of the albatross and the vulture is surely the
 most<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 132]</ph> remarkable locomotor triumph that has ever been achieved.
 Without any apparent stroke of the wings, the bird sails for half an hour at
 a time with the wind and against the wind, around the ship and in majestic
 spirals in the sky, probably taking advantage of currents of air of different
 velocities, and continually changing energy of position into energy of motion
 as it sinks, and energy of motion into energy of position as it rises. It is
 interesting to know that some dragon-flies are also able to
 "sail."</p>
         <p>The web-wing of bats involves much more than the fore-arm. The double fold
 of skin begins on the side of the neck, passes along the front of the arm,
 skips the thumb, and is continued over the elongated palm-bones and fingers
 to the sides of the body again, and to the hind-legs, and to the tail if
 there is a tail. It is interesting to find that the bones of the bat's
 skeleton tend to be lightly built as in birds, that the breast-bone has
 likewise a keel for the better insertion of the pectoral muscles, and that
 there is a solidifying of the vertebræ of the back, affording as in birds a
 firm basis for the wing action. Such similar adaptations to similar needs,
 occurring in animals not nearly related to one another, are called
 "convergences," and form a very interesting study. In addition to
 adaptations which the bat shares with the flying bird, it has many of its
 own. There are so many nerve-endings on the wing, and often also on special
 skin-leaves about the ears and nose, that the bat flying in the dusk does not
 knock against branches or other obstacles. Some say that it is helped by the
 echoes of its high-pitched voice, but there is no doubt as to its exquisite
 tactility. That it usually produces only a single young one at a time is a
 clear adaptation to flight, and similarly the sharp, mountain-top-like cusps
 on the back teeth are adapted in insectivorous bats for crunching
 insects.</p>
         <p>Whether we think of the triumphant flight of birds, reaching a climax in
 migration, or of the marvel that a creature of the earth—as a mammal
 essentially is—should evolve such a mastery of the air as we see in
 bats, or even of the repeated but<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 133]</ph> splendid failures which parachuting animals
 illustrate, we gain an impression of the insurgence of living creatures in
 their characteristic endeavour after fuller well-being.</p>
         <p>We have said enough to show how well adapted many animals are to meet the
 particular difficulties of the haunt which they tenant. But difficulties and
 limitations are ever arising afresh, and so one fitness follows on another.
 It is natural, therefore, to pass to the frequent occurrence of protective
 resemblance, camouflage, and mimicry—the subject of the next
 article.</p>
         <!--hr--></body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e4482">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">BIBLIOGRAPHY</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Elmhirst, R.</ph>, <i>Animals of the Shore</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Flattely and Walton</ph>, <i>The Biology of the
 Shore</i> (1921).
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Furneaux</ph>, <i>Life of Ponds and Streams</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Hickson, S. J.</ph>, <i>Story of Life in the Seas</i>
 and <i>Fauna of the Deep Sea</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Johnstone, J.</ph>, <i>Life in the Sea</i> (Cambridge
 Manual of Science).
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Miall, L. C.</ph>, <i>Aquatic Insects</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Murray, Sir John</ph>, <i>The Ocean</i> (Home
 University Library).
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Murray, Sir John and Hjort, Dr. J.</ph>, <i>The Depths
 of the Ocean</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Newbigin, M. I.</ph>, <i>Life by the Sea Shore</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Pycraft, W. P.</ph>, <i>History of Birds</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Scharff, R. F.</ph>, <i>History of the European
 Fauna</i> (Contemp. Sci. Series).
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Thomson, J. Arthur</ph>, <i>The Wonder of Life</i>
 (1914) and <i>The Haunts of Life</i> (1921).
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 135]</ph>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 134]</ph>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 136]</ph>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 137]</ph>
         </p>
         <!--hr--></body>
   </topic>
</topic>