<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="chapter_07">
   <title>
      <ph outputclass="title-line">VI</ph> 
      <ph outputclass="title-line">EVOLUTION GOING ON</ph> 
   </title>
   <body><!--hr--></body>
   <topic id="d1e6171">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">EVOLUTION GOING ON</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>Evolution, as we have seen in a previous chapter, is another word for
 race-history. It means the ceaseless process of Becoming, linking generation
 to generation of living creatures. The Doctrine of Evolution states the fact
 that the present is the child of the past and the parent of the future. It
 comes to this, that the living plants and animals we know are descended from
 ancestors on the whole simpler, and these from others likewise simpler, and
 so on, back and back—till we reach the first living creatures, of
 which, unfortunately, we know nothing. Evolution is a process of racial
 change in a definite direction, whereby new forms arise, take root, and
 flourish, alongside of or in the place of their ancestors, which were in most
 cases rather simpler in structure and behaviour.</p>
         <p>The rock-record, which cannot be wrong, though we may read it wrongly,
 shows clearly that there was once a time in the history of the Earth when the
 only backboned animals were Fishes. Ages passed, and there evolved
 Amphibians, with fingers and toes, scrambling on to dry land. Ages passed,
 and there evolved Reptiles, in bewildering profusion. There were fish-lizards
 and sea-serpents, terrestrial dragons and flying dragons, a prolific and
 varied stock. From the terrestrial Dinosaurs it seems that Birds and Mammals
 arose. In succeeding ages there evolved all the variety of Birds and all the
 variety of Mammals. Until at last arose the Man. The question is whether
 similar processes of evolution are still going on.</p>
         <p>We are so keenly aware of rapid changes in mankind, though<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 186]</ph> these concern
 the social heritage much more than the flesh-and-blood natural inheritance,
 that we find no difficulty in the idea that evolution is going on in mankind.
 We know the contrast between modern man and primitive man, and we are
 convinced that in the past, at least, progress has been a reality. That
 degeneration may set in is an awful possibility—involution rather than
 evolution—but even if going back became for a time the rule, we cannot
 give up the hope that the race would recover itself and begin afresh to go
 forward. For although there have been retrogressions in the history of life,
 continued through unthinkably long ages, and although great races, the Flying
 Dragons for instance, have become utterly extinct, leaving no successors
 whatsoever, we feel sure that there has been on the whole a progress towards
 nobler, more masterful, more emancipated, more intelligent, and <i>better</i>
 forms of life—a progress towards what mankind at its best has always
 regarded as best, i.e. affording most enduring satisfaction. So we think of
 evolution going on in mankind, evolution chequered by involution, but on the
 whole <i>progressive evolution</i>.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e6190">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Evolutionary Prospect for Man</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It is not likely that man's body will admit of <i>great</i> change,
 but there is room for some improvement, e.g. in the superfluous length of the
 food-canal and the overcrowding of the teeth. It is likely, however, that
 there will be constitutional changes, e.g. of prolonged youthfulness, a
 higher standard of healthfulness, and a greater resistance to disease. It is
 justifiable to look forward to great improvements in intelligence and in
 control. The potentialities of the human brain, as it is, are far from being
 utilised to the full, and new departures of promise are of continual
 occurrence. What is of great importance is that the new departures or
 variations which emerge in fine children should be fostered, not nipped in
 the bud, by the social environment, education included. The evolutionary
 prospect for man is promising.</p>
            <fig id="image302a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>PHOTOGRAPH OF A MEDIAN SECTION THROUGH THE SHELL OF THE PEARLY
   NAUTILUS</p>

               <p>It is only the large terminal chamber that is occupied by
   the animal.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image302a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PHOTOGRAPH OF A MEDIAN SECTION THROUGH THE SHELL OF THE PEARLY NAUTILUS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image302b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>PHOTOGRAPH OF THE ENTIRE SHELL OF THE PEARLY NAUTILUS</p>

               <p>The headquarters of the Nautilus are in the Indian and
   Pacific Oceans. They sometimes swim at the surface of the sea, but they
   usually creep slowly about on the floor of comparatively shallow water.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image302b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PHOTOGRAPH OF THE ENTIRE SHELL OF THE PEARLY NAUTILUS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image302c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>NAUTILUS</p>

               <p>A section through the Pearly Nautilus, <i>Nautilus
   pompilius</i>, common from Malay to Fiji. The shell is often about 9 inches
   long. The animal lives in the last chamber only, but a tube (S) runs
   through the empty chambers, perforating the partitions (SE). The bulk of
   the animal is marked VM; the eye is shown at E; a hood is marked H; round
   the mouth there are numerous lobes (L) bearing protrusible tentacles, some
   of which are shown. When the animal is swimming near the surface the
   tentacles radiate out in all directions, and it has been described as
   "a shell with something like a cauliflower sticking out of it."
   The Pearly Nautilus is a good example of a conservative type, for it began
   in the Triassic Era. But the family of Nautiloids to which it belongs
   illustrates very vividly what is meant by a dwindling race. The Nautiloids
   began in the Cambrian, reached their golden age in the Silurian, and began
   to decline markedly in the Carboniferous. There are 2,500 extinct or fossil
   species of Nautiloids, and only 4 living to-day.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image302c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>NAUTILUS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image303"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: W. S. Berridge.</i>
               </p>

               <p>SHOEBILL</p>

               <p>A bird of a savage nature, never mixing with other marsh
   birds. According to Dr. Chalmers Mitchell, it shows affinities to herons,
   storks, pelicans, and gannets, and is a representative of a type equal to
   both herons and storks and falling between the two.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image303_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SHOEBILL</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 187]</ph>
            </p>
            <p>But it is very important to realise that among plant and animals likewise,
 <i>Evolution is going on</i>.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6277">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Fountain of Change: Variability</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>On an ordinary big clock we do not readily see that even the minute hand
 is moving, and if the clock struck only once in a hundred years we can
 conceive of people arguing whether the hands did really move at all. So it
 often is with the changes that go on from generation to generation in living
 creatures. The flux is so slow, like the flowing of a glacier, that some
 people fail to be convinced of its reality. And it must, of course, be
 admitted that some kinds of living creatures, like the Lamp-shell
 <i>Ligula</i> or the Pearly Nautilus, hardly change from age to age, whereas
 others, like some of the birds and butterflies, are always giving rise to
 something new. The Evening Primrose among plants, and the Fruit-fly,
 Drosophila, among animals, are well-known examples of organisms which are at
 present in a sporting or mutating mood.</p>
            <p>Certain dark varieties of moth, e.g. of the Peppered Moth, are taking the
 place of the paler type in some parts of England, and the same is true of
 some dark forms of Sugar-bird in the West Indian islands. Very important is
 the piece of statistics worked out by Professor R. C. Punnett, that "if
 a population contains .001 per cent of a new variety, and if that variety has
 even a 5 per cent selection advantage over the original form, the latter will
 almost completely disappear in less than a hundred generations." This
 sort of thing has been going on all over the world for untold ages, and the
 face of animate nature has consequently changed.</p>
            <p>We are impressed by striking novelties that crop up—a clever dwarf,
 a musical genius, a calculating boy, a cock with a 10 ft. tail, a
 "wonder-horse" with a mane reaching to the ground, a tailless cat,
 a white blackbird, a copper beech, a Greater Celandine with much cut up
 leaves; but this sort of mutation is common, and smaller, less brusque
 variations are commoner still. <i>They form the raw materials of possible
 evolution.</i> We are<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 188]</ph> actually standing before an apparently
 inexhaustible fountain of change. This is evolution going on.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6296">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Sporting Jellyfish</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It is of interest to consider a common animal like the jellyfish Aurelia.
 It is admirably suited for a leisurely life in the open sea, where it swims
 about by contracting its saucer-shaped body, thus driving water out from its
 concavity. By means of millions of stinging cells on its four frilled lips
 and on its marginal tentacles it is able to paralyse and lasso minute
 crustaceans and the like, which it then wafts into its mouth. It has a very
 eventful life-history, for it has in its early youth to pass through a fixed
 stage, fastened to rock or seaweed, but it is a successful animal, well
 suited for its habitat, and practically cosmopolitan in its distribution. It
 is certainly an old-established creature. Yet it is very variable in colour
 and in size, and even in internal structure. Very often it is the size of a
 saucer or a soup-plate, but giants over two feet in diameter are well known.
 Much more important, however, than variation in colour and size are the
 inborn changes in structure. Normally a jellyfish has its parts in four or
 multiples of four. Thus it has four frilled lips, four tufts of digestive
 filaments in its stomach, and four brightly coloured reproductive organs. It
 has eight sense-organs round the margin of its disc, eight branched and eight
 unbranched radial canals running from the central stomach to a canal round
 the circumference. The point of giving these details is just this, that every
 now and then we find a jellyfish with its parts in sixes, fives, or threes,
 and with a multitude of minor idiosyncrasies. <i>Even in the well-established
 jellyfish there is a fountain of change.</i>
            </p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 1</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6304">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Evolution of Plants</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It is instructive to look at the various kinds of cabbages, such as
 cauliflower and Brussels sprouts, kale and curly greens, and<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 189]</ph> remember that
 they are all scions of the not very promising wild cabbage found on our
 shores. And are not all the aristocrat apple-trees of our orchards descended
 from the plebeian crab-apple of the roadside? We know far too little about
 the precise origin of our cultivated plants, but there is no doubt that after
 man got a hold of them he took advantage of their variability to establish
 race after race, say, of rose and chrysanthemum, of potato and cereal. The
 evolution of cultivated plants is continuing before our eyes, and the
 creations of Mr. Luther Burbank, such as the stoneless plum and the primus
 berry, the spineless cactus and the Shasta daisy, are merely striking
 instances of what is always going on.</p>
            <p>There is reason to believe that the domestic dog has risen three times,
 from three distinct ancestors—a wolf, a jackal, and a coyote. So a
 multiple pedigree must be allowed for in the case of the dog, and the same is
 true in regard to some other domesticated animals. But the big fact is the
 great variety of breeds that man has been able to fix, after he once got
 started with a domesticated type. There are over 200 well-marked breeds of
 domestic pigeons, and there is very strong evidence that all are descended
 from the wild rock-dove, just as the numerous kinds of poultry are descended
 from the jungle-fowl of some parts of India and the Malay Islands. Even more
 familiar is the way in which man has, so to speak, unpacked the complex fur
 of the wild rabbit, and established all the numerous colour-varieties which
 we see among domestic rabbits. And apart from colour-varieties there are
 long-haired Angoras and quaint lop-eared forms, and many more besides. All
 this points to evolution going on.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6314">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Romance of the Wheat</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It is well-known that Neolithic man grew wheat, and some authorities have
 put the date of the first wheat harvest at between fifteen thousand and ten
 thousand years ago. The ancient civilisations<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 190]</ph> of Babylonia, Egypt, Crete,
 Greece, and Rome were largely based on wheat, and it is highly probable that
 the first great wheatfields were in the fertile land between the Tigris and
 the Euphrates. The oldest Egyptian tombs that contain wheat, which, by the
 way, never germinates after its millennia of rest, belong to the First
 Dynasty, and are about six thousand years old. But there must have been a
 long history of wheat before that.</p>
            <p>Now it is a very interesting fact that the almost certain ancestor of the
 cultivated wheat is at present living on the arid and rocky slopes of Mount
 Hermon. It is called <i>Triticum hermonis</i>, and it is varying notably
 to-day, as it did long ago when it gave rise to the emmer, which was
 cultivated in the Neolithic Age and is the ancestor of all our ordinary
 wheats. We must think of Neolithic man noticing the big seeds of this Hermon
 grass, gathering some of the heads, breaking the brittle spikelet-bearing
 axis in his fingers, knocking off the rough awns or bruising the spikelets in
 his hand till the glumes or chaff separated off and could be blown away,
 chewing a mouthful of the seeds—and resolving to sow and sow again.</p>
            <p>That was the beginning of a long story, in the course of which man took
 advantage of the numerous variations that cropped up in this sporting stock
 and established one successful race after another on his fields. Virgil
 refers in the "Georgics" to the gathering of the largest and
 fullest ears of wheat in order to get good seed for another sowing, but it
 was not till the first quarter of the nineteenth century that the great step
 was taken, by men like Patrick Sheriff of Haddington, of deliberately
 selecting individual ears of great excellence and segregating their progeny
 from mingling with mediocre stock. This is the method which has been followed
 with remarkable success in modern times.</p>
            <p>One of the factors that assisted the Allies in overcoming the food crisis
 in the darkest period of the war was the virtue of Marquis Wheat, a very
 prolific, early ripening, hard red spring wheat<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 191]</ph> with excellent milling and
 baking qualities. It is now the dominant spring wheat in Canada and the
 United States, and it has enormously increased the real wealth of the world
 in the last ten years (1921). Now our point is simply that this Marquis Wheat
 is a fine example of evolution going on. In 1917 upwards of 250,000,000
 bushels of this wheat were raised in North America, and in 1918 upwards of
 300,000,000 bushels; yet the whole originated from a single grain planted in
 an experimental plot at Ottawa by Dr. Charles E. Saunders so recently as the
 spring of 1903.</p>
            <fig id="image308a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE WALKING-FISH OR MUD-SKIPPER (PERIOPHTHALMUS), COMMON AT THE MOUTHS
   OF RIVERS IN TROPICAL AFRICA, ASIA, AND NORTH-WEST AUSTRALIA</p>

               <p>It skips about by means of its strong pectoral fins on the
   mud-flats; it jumps from stone to stone hunting small shore-animals; it
   climbs up the roots of the mangrove-trees. The close-set eyes protrude
   greatly and are very mobile. The tail seems to help in respiration.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image308a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE WALKING-FISH OR MUD-SKIPPER (PERIOPHTHALMUS), COMMON AT THE MOUTHS OF RIVERS IN TROPICAL AFRICA, ASIA, AND NORTH-WEST AUSTRALIA</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image308b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: "The Times."</i>
               </p>

               <p>THE AUSTRALIAN MORE-PORK OR PODARGUS</p>

               <p>A bird with a frog-like mouth, allied to the British
   Nightjar. Now in the London Zoological Gardens.</p>

               <p>The capacious mouth is well suited for engulfing large
   insects such as locusts and mantises, which are mostly caught on the trees.
   During the day the More-pork or Frog-mouth sleeps upright on a branch, and
   its mottled brown plumage makes it almost invisible.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image308b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE AUSTRALIAN MORE-PORK OR PODARGUS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image309a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>PELICAN'S BILL, ADAPTED FOR CATCHING AND STORING FISHES</p>

               <p>There is an enormous dilatable sac beneath the lower jaw.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image309a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PELICAN'S BILL, ADAPTED FOR CATCHING AND STORING FISHES</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image309b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>SPOONBILL'S BILL, ADAPTED FOR SIFTING THE MUD AND CATCHING THE SMALL
   ANIMALS, E.G. FISHES, CRUSTACEANS, INSECT LARVÆ, WHICH LIVE THERE</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image309b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SPOONBILL'S BILL</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image309c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>AVOCET'S BILL, ADAPTED FOR A CURIOUS SIDEWAYS SCOOPING IN THE
   SHORE-POOLS AND CATCHING SMALL ANIMALS</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image309c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>AVOCET'S BILL</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image309d"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>HORNBILL'S BILL, ADAPTED FOR EXCAVATING A NEST IN A TREE, AND ALSO
   FOR SEIZING AND BREAKING DIVERSE FORMS OF FOOD, FROM MAMMALS TO TORTOISES,
   FROM ROOTS TO FRUITS</p>

               <p>The use of the helmet or casque is obscure.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image309d_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>HORNBILL'S BILL</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image309e"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FALCON'S BILL, ADAPTED FOR SEIZING, KILLING, AND TEARING SMALL
   MAMMALS AND BIRDS.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image309e_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>FALCON'S BILL</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image309f"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>PUFFIN'S BILL, ADAPTED FOR CATCHING SMALL FISHES NEAR THE SURFACE OF
   THE SEA, AND FOR HOLDING THEM WHEN CAUGHT AND CARRYING THEM TO THE NEST</p>

               <p>The scaly covering is moulted in the autumn.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image309f_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PUFFIN'S BILL</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>We must not dwell too long on this particular instance of evolution,
 though it has meant much to our race. We wish, however, following Professor
 Buller's <i>Essays on Wheat</i> (1919), to explain the method by which
 this good seed was discovered. From one we may learn all. The parent of
 Marquis Wheat on the male side was the mid-Europe Red Fife—a
 first-class cereal. The parent on the female side was less promising, a
 rather nondescript, not pure-bred wheat, called Red Calcutta, which was
 imported from India into Canada about thirty years ago. The father was part
 of a cargo that came from the Baltic to Glasgow, and was happily included in
 a sample sent on to David Fife in Ontario about 1842. From one kernel of this
 sample David Fife started his stock of Red Fife, which was crossed by Dr.
 Saunders with Hard Red Calcutta. The result of the cross was a medley of
 types, nearly a hundred varieties altogether, and it was in scrutinising
 these that Dr. Saunders hit upon Marquis. He worked steadily through the
 material, studying head after head of what resulted from sowing, and
 selecting out those that gave most promise. Each of the heads selected was
 propagated; most of the results were rejected; the elect were sifted again
 and yet again, and finally Marquis Wheat emerged, rich in constructive
 possibilities, probably the most valuable food-plant in the world. It is like
 a romance to read that "the first crop of the wheat that was destined
 within a dozen years to overtax the mightiest elevators<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 192]</ph> in the land
 was stored away in the winter of 1904-5 in a paper packet no larger than an
 envelope."</p>
            <p>Thus from the Wild Wheat of Mount Hermon there evolved one of the most
 important food-plants of the world. This surely is <i>Evolution going
 on</i>.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 2</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6480">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Changes in the Animal Life of a Country</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Nothing gives us a more convincing impression of evolution in being than a
 succession of pictures of the animal life of a country in different ages. Dr.
 James Ritchie, a naturalist of distinction, has written a masterly book,
 <i>The Influence of Man on Animal Life in Scotland</i> (1920), in which we
 get this succession of pictures. "Within itself," he says, "a
 fauna is in a constant state of uneasy restlessness, an assemblage of
 creatures which in its parts ebbs and flows as one local influence or another
 plays upon it." There are temporary and local changes, endless
 disturbances and readjustments of the "balance of nature." One year
 there is a plague of field-voles, perhaps next year "grouse
 disease" is rife; in one place there is huge increase of starlings, in
 another place of rabbits; here cockchafers are in the ascendant, and there
 the moles are spoiling the pasture. "But while the parts fluctuate, the
 fauna as a whole follows a path of its own. As well as internal tides which
 swing to and fro about an average level, there is a drift which carries the
 fauna bodily along an 'irretraceable course.'" This is partly
 due to considerable changes of climate, for climate calls the tune to which
 living creatures dance, but it is also due to new departures among the
 animals themselves. We need not go back to the extinct animals and lost
 faunas of past ages—for Britain has plenty of relics of
 these—which "illustrate the reality of the faunal drift," but
 it may be very useful, in illustration of evolution in being, to notice what
 has happened in Scotland since the end of the Great Ice Age.</p>
            <p>Some nine thousand years ago or more, certain long-headed,<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 193]</ph> square-jawed,
 short-limbed, but agile hunters and fishermen, whom we call Neolithic Man,
 established themselves in Scotland. What was the state of the country
 then?</p>
            <lq>
               <p>It was a country of swamps, low forests of birch, alder, and willow,
  fertile meadows, and snow-capped mountains. Its estuaries penetrated further
  inland than they now do, and the sea stood at the level of the Fifty-Foot
  Beach. On its plains and in its forests roamed many creatures which are
  strange to the fauna of to-day—the Elk and the Reindeer, Wild Cattle,
  the Wild Boar and perhaps Wild Horses, a fauna of large animals which paid
  toll to the European Lynx, the Brown Bear and the Wolf. In all likelihood,
  the marshes resounded to the boom of the Bittern and the plains to the
  breeding calls of the Crane and the Great Bustard.</p>
            </lq>
            <p>Such is Dr. Ritchie's initial picture.</p>
            <fig id="image312a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>LIFE-HISTORY OF A FROG</p>

               <p>1, Before hatching; 2, newly hatched larvæ hanging on to
   water-weed; 3, with external gills; 4, external gills are covered over and
   are absorbed; 5, limbless larva about a month old with internal gills; 6,
   tadpole with hind-legs, about two months old; 7, with the fore-limbs
   emerging; 8, with all four legs free; 9, a young frog, about three months
   old, showing the almost complete absorption of the tail and the change of
   the tadpole mouth into a frog mouth.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image312a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>LIFE-HISTORY OF A FROG</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image312b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: J. J. Ward. F.E.S.</i>
               </p>

               <p>HIND-LEG OF WHIRLIGIG BEETLE WHICH HAS BECOME BEAUTIFULLY MODIFIED FOR
   AQUATIC LOCOMOTION</p>

               <p>The flattened tips form an expanding "fan" or
   paddle, which opens and closes with astonishing rapidity. The closing of
   the "fan," like the "feathering" of an oar, reduces
   friction when the leg is being moved forwards for the next stroke.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image312b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>HIND-LEG OF WHIRLIGIG BEETLE WHICH HAS BECOME BEAUTIFULLY MODIFIED FOR AQUATIC LOCOMOTION</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image313"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE BIG ROBBER-CRAB (<i>Birgus Latro</i>), THAT CLIMBS THE COCO-NUT PALM
   AND BREAKS OFF THE NUTS</p>

               <p>It occurs on islands in the Indian Ocean and Pacific, and
   is often found far above sea-level. It is able to breathe dry air. One is
   seen emerging from its burrow, which is often lined with coco-nut fibre.
   The empty coco-nut shell is sometimes used by the Robber-Crab for the
   protection of its tail.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image313_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE BIG ROBBER-CRAB (Birgus Latro), THAT CLIMBS THE COCO-NUT PALM AND BREAKS OFF THE NUTS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>Now what happened in this kingdom of Caledonia which Neolithic Man had
 found? He began to introduce domesticated animals, and that meant a thinning
 of the ranks of predacious creatures. "Safety first" was the
 dangerous motto in obedience to which man exterminated the lynx, the brown
 bear, and the wolf. Other creatures, such as the great auk, were destroyed
 for food, and others like the marten for their furs. Small pests were
 destroyed to protect the beginnings of agriculture; larger animals like the
 boar were hunted out of existence; others, like the pearl-bearing
 river-mussels, yielded to subtler demands. No doubt there was protection
 also—protection for sport, for utility, for æsthetic reasons, and
 because of humane sentiments; even wholesome superstitions have safeguarded
 the robin redbreast and the wren. There were introductions too—the
 rabbit for utility, the pheasant for sport, and the peacock for amenity. And
 every introduction, every protection, every killing out had its far-reaching
 influences.</p>
            <p>But if we are to picture the evolution going on, we must think also of
 man's indirect interference with animal life. He destroyed<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 194]</ph> the forests,
 he cultivated the wild, he made bridges, he allowed aliens, like rats and
 cockroaches, to get in unawares. Of course, he often did good, as when he
 drained swamps and got rid of the mosquitoes which once made malaria rife in
 Scotland.</p>
            <p>What has been the net result? Not, as one might think for a moment, a
 reduction in the <i>number</i> of different kinds of animals. Fourteen or so
 species of birds and beasts have been banished from Scotland since man
 interfered, but as far as numbers go they have been more than replaced by
 deliberate introductions like fallow deer, rabbit, squirrel, and pheasant,
 and by accidental introductions like rats and cockroaches. But the change is
 rather in <i>quality</i> than in quantity; the smaller have taken the place
 of the larger, rather paltry pigmies of noble giants. Thus we get a vivid
 idea that evolution, especially when man interferes, is not necessarily
 progressive. That depends on the nature of the sieves with which the living
 materials are sifted. As Dr. Ritchie well says, the standard of the wild
 fauna as regards size has fallen and is falling, and it is not in size only
 that there is loss, there is a deterioration of quality. "For how can
 the increase of Rabbits and Sparrows and Earthworms and Caterpillars, and the
 addition of millions of Rats and Cochroaches and Crickets and Bugs, ever take
 the place of those fine creatures round the memories of which the glamour of
 Scotland's past still plays—the Reindeer and the Elk, the Wolf, the
 Brown Bear, the Lynx, and the Beaver, the Bustard, the Crane, the Bumbling
 Bittern, and many another, lost or disappearing." Thus we see again that
 evolution is going on.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 3</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6576">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Adventurers</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>All through the millions of years during which animals have tenanted the
 earth and the waters under the earth, there has been a search for new
 kingdoms to conquer, for new corners in which to make a home. And this still
 goes on. <i>It has been and<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 195]</ph> is one of the methods of evolution to fill
 every niche of opportunity.</i> There is a spider that lives inside a
 pitcher-plant, catching some of the inquisitive insects which slip down the
 treacherous internal surface of the trap. There is another that makes its
 home in crevices among the rocks on the shore of the Mediterranean, or even
 in empty tubular shells, keeping the water out, more or less successfully, by
 spinning threads of silk across the entrance to its retreat. The beautiful
 brine-shrimp, <i>Artemia salina</i>, that used to occur in British salterns
 has found a home in the dense waters of the Great Salt Lake of Utah. Several
 kinds of earthworms have been found up trees, and there is a fish, Arges,
 that climbs on the stones of steep mountain torrents of the Andes. The
 intrepid explorers of the <i>Scotia</i> voyage found quite a number of Arctic
 terns spending our winter within the summer of the Antarctic
 Circle—which means girdling the globe from pole to pole; and every now
 and then there are incursions of rare birds, like Pallas's Sand-grouse,
 into Britain, just as if they were prospecting in search of a promised land.
 Twice or thrice the distinctively North American Killdeer Plover has been
 found in Britain, having somehow or other got across the Atlantic. We miss
 part of the meaning of evolution if we do not catch this note of insurgence
 and adventure, which some animal or other never ceases to sound, though many
 establish themselves in a security not easily disturbed, and though a small
 minority give up the struggle against the stream and are content to
 acquiesce, as parasites or rottenness eaters, in a drifting life of ease.</p>
            <p>More important than very peculiar cases is the broad fact that over and
 over again in different groups of animals there have been attempts to master
 different kinds of haunts—such as the underground world, the trees, the
 freshwaters, and the air. There are burrowing amphibians, burrowing reptiles,
 burrowing birds, and burrowing mammals; there are tree-toads, tree-snakes,
 tree-lizards, tree-kangaroos, tree-sloths, tree-shrews, tree-mice,
 tree-porcupines, and so on; enough of a list to show, without<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 196]</ph> mentioning
 birds, how many different kinds of animals have entered upon an arboreal
 apprenticeship—an apprenticeship often with far-reaching consequences.
 What the freeing of the hand from being an organ of terrestrial support has
 meant in the evolution of monkeys is a question that gives a spur to our
 imagination.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6599">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Case of the Robber Crab</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>On some of the coral islands of the Indian and Pacific Oceans there lives
 a land-crab, Birgus, which has learned to breathe on land. It breathes dry
 air by means of curious blood-containing tufts in the upper part of its
 gill-cavity, and it has also rudimentary gills. It is often about a foot
 long, and it has very heavy great claws, especially on the left-hand side.
 With this great claw it hammers on the "eye-hole" of a coconut,
 from which it has torn off the fibrous husk. It hammers until a hole is made
 by which it can get at the pulp. Part of the shell is sometimes used as a
 protection for the soft abdomen—for the robber-crab, as it is called,
 is an offshoot from the hermit-crab stock. Every year this quaint explorer,
 which may go far up the hills and climb the coco-palms, has to go back to the
 sea to spawn. The young ones are hatched in the same state as in our common
 shore-crab. That is to say, they are free-swimming larvæ which pass through
 an open-water period before they settle down on the shore, and eventually
 creep up on to dry land. Just as open-water turtles lay their eggs on sandy
 shores, going back to their old terrestrial haunt, so the robber-crab, which
 has almost conquered the dry land, has to return to the seashore to breed.
 There is a peculiar interest in the association of the robber-crab with the
 coco-palm, for that tree is not a native of these coral islands, but has been
 introduced, perhaps from Mexico, by the Polynesian mariners before the
 discovery of America by Columbus. So the learning to deal with coconuts is a
 recent achievement, and we are face to face with a very good example of
 evolution going on.</p>
            <fig id="image318"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>EARLY LIFE-HISTORY OF THE SALMON</p>

               <p>1. The fertilised egg, shed in the gravelly bed of the
   river.</p>

               <p>2. The embryo within the egg, just before hatching. The
   embryo has been constricted off from the yolk-laden portion of the egg.</p>

               <p>3. The newly hatched salmon, or alevin, encumbered with its
   legacy of yolk (Y.S.).</p>

               <p>4 and 5. The larval salmon, still being nourished from the
   yolk-sac (Y.S.), which is diminishing in size as the fish grows larger.</p>

               <p>6. The salmon fry about six weeks old, with the yolk fully
   absorbed, so that the young fish has now to feed for itself. The fry become
   parr, which go to the sea as smolts, and return as grilse.</p>

               <p>In all cases the small figures to the right indicate the
   natural size.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image318_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>EARLY LIFE-HISTORY OF THE SALMON</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image319"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE SALMON LEAPING AT THE FALL IS A MOST FASCINATING SPECTACLE</p>

               <p>Again and again we see them jumping out of the seething
   foam beneath the fall, casting themselves into the curtain of the
   down-rushing water, only to be carried back by it into the depths whence
   they have risen. One here and another there makes its effort good, touches
   the upper lip of the cataract, gives a swift stroke of its tail, and rushes
   on towards those upper reaches which are the immemorial spawning beds of
   its race.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image319_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SALMON LEAPING AT THE FALL IS A MOST FASCINATING SPECTACLE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 197]</ph>
            </p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6656">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Story of the Salmon</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>In late autumn or in winter the salmon spawn in the rivers. The female
 makes a shallow trough in the gravel by moving her tail from side to side,
 and therein lays many eggs. The male, who is in attendance, fertilises these
 with the milt, and then the female covers them deeply with gravel. The
 process is repeated over and over again for a week or more till all the eggs
 are shed. For three to four months the eggs develop, and eventually there
 emerge the larvæ or <i>alevins</i>, which lurk among the pebbles. They cannot
 swim much, for they are encumbered by a big legacy of yolk. In a few weeks,
 perhaps eight, the protruding bag of yolk has disappeared and the <i>fry</i>,
 about an inch long, begin to move about more actively and to fend for
 themselves. By the end of the year they have grown to be rather trout-like
 <i>parr</i>, about four inches long. In two years these are double that
 length. Usually in the second year, but it may be earlier or later, the parr
 become silvery <i>smolts</i>, which go out to sea, usually about the month of
 May. They feed on young herring and the like and grow large and strong. When
 they are about three and a half years old they come up the rivers as
 <i>grilse</i> and may spawn. Or they may pass through the whole grilse stage
 in the sea and come up the rivers with all the characters of the full-grown
 fish. In many cases the salmon spawn only once, and some (they are called
 <i>kelts</i> after spawning) are so much exhausted by starting a new
 generation that they die or fall a victim to otters and other enemies. In the
 case of the salmon of the North Pacific (in the genus <i>Oncorhynchus</i>,
 not <i>Salmo</i>) all the individuals die after spawning, none being able to
 return to the sea. It must be remembered that full-grown salmon do not as a
 rule feed in fresh water, though they may be unable to resist snapping at the
 angler's strange creations. A very interesting fact is that the salmon
 keeps as it were a diary of its movements, which vary a good deal in
 different rivers. This diary is written in the scales, and a careful reading
 of the concentric lines on the scales shows the age of the fish,
 and<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 198]</ph>
 when it went out to sea, and whether it has spawned or not, and more
 besides.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6689">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Interpretation of the Salmon's Story</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>When an animal frequents two different haunts, in one of which it breeds,
 it is very often safe to say that the breeding-place represents the original
 home. The flounder is quite comfortable far up the rivers, but it has to go
 to the shore-waters to spawn, and there is no doubt that the flounder is a
 marine fish which has recently learned to colonise the fresh waters. Its
 relatives, like plaice and sole, are strictly marine. But it is impossible to
 make a dogma of the rule that the breeding-place corresponds to the original
 home. Thus some kinds of bass, which belong to the marine family of
 sea-perches, live in the sea or in estuaries, while two have become permanent
 residents in fresh water. Or, again, the members of the herring family are
 very distinctively marine, but the shad, which belong to this family, spawn
 in rivers and may spend their lives there.</p>
            <p>So there are two different ways of interpreting the life-history of the
 salmon. Some authorities regard the salmon as a marine fish which is
 establishing itself in fresh water. But others read the story the other way
 and regard the salmon as a member of a freshwater race, that has taken to the
 sea for feeding purposes. In regard to trout, we know that the ranks of those
 in rivers and lakes are continually being reinforced by migrants from the
 sea, and that some trout go down to the sea while others remain in the
 freshwater. We know also in regard to a related fish, the char, that while
 the great majority of kinds are now permanent residents in cold and deep,
 isolated northern lakes, there are Arctic forms which live in the sea but
 enter the rivers to spawn. These facts favour the view that the salmon was
 originally a marine fish. But there are arguments on both sides, and, for our
 present purpose, the important fact is that the salmon is conquering
 <i>two</i> haunts. Its evolution is going on.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 199]</ph>
            </p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6701">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Romance of the Eel</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Early in summer, at dates varying with the distance of the rivers from the
 open Atlantic, crowds of young eels or elvers come up-stream. Sometimes the
 procession or eel-fare includes thousands of individuals, each about the
 length of our first finger, and as thick as a stout knitting needle. They
 obey an inborn impulse to swim against the stream, seeking automatically to
 have both sides of their body equally stimulated by the current. So they go
 straight ahead. The obligation works only during the day, for when the sun
 goes down behind the hills the elvers snuggle under stones or beneath the
 bank and rest till dawn. In the course of time they reach the quiet upper
 reaches of the river or go up rivulets and drainpipes to the isolated ponds.
 Their impulse to go on must be very imperious, for they may wriggle up the
 wet moss by the side of a waterfall or even make a short excursion in a damp
 meadow.</p>
            <p>In the quiet-flowing stretches of the river or in the ponds they feed and
 grow for years and years. They account for a good many young fishes.
 Eventually, after five or six years in the case of the males, six to eight
 years in the case of the females, the well-grown fishes, perhaps a foot and a
 half to two feet long, are seized by a novel restlessness. They are beginning
 to be mature. They put on a silvery jacket and become large of eye, and they
 return to the sea. In getting away from the pond it may be necessary to
 wriggle through the damp meadow-grass before reaching the river. They travel
 by night and rather excitedly. The Arctic Ocean is too cold for them and the
 North Sea too shallow. They must go far out to sea, to where the old margin
 of the once larger continent of Europe slopes down to the great abysses, from
 the Hebrides southwards. Eels seem to spawn in the deep dark water; but the
 just liberated eggs have not yet been found. The young fry rises to near the
 surface and becomes a knife-blade-like larva, transparent all but its eye. It
 lives for many months in this state, growing to be about three inches long,
 rising and sinking<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 200]</ph> in the water, and swimming gently. These open-sea young eels
 are known as Leptocephali, a name given to them before their real nature was
 proved. They gradually become shorter, and the shape changes from
 knife-blade-like to cylindrical. During this change they fast, and the weight
 of their delicate body decreases. They turn into glass-eels, about 2½ inches
 long, like a knitting-needle in girth. They begin to move towards the distant
 shores and rivers, and they may be a year and a half old before they reach
 their destination and go up-stream as elvers. Those that ascend the rivers of
 the Eastern Baltic must have journeyed three thousand miles. It is certain
 that no eel ever matures or spawns in fresh water. It is practically certain
 that all the young eels ascending the rivers of North Europe have come in
 from the Atlantic, some of them perhaps from the Azores or further out still.
 It is interesting to inquire how the young eels circumvent the Falls of the
 Rhine and get into Lake Constance, or how their kindred on the other side of
 the Atlantic overcome the obstacle of Niagara; but it is more important to
 lay emphasis on the variety of habitats which this fish is trying—the
 deep waters, the open sea, the shore, the river, the pond, and even, it may
 be, a little taste of solid earth. It seems highly probable that the common
 eel is a deep-water marine fish which has learned to colonise the
 freshwaters. It has been adventurous and it has succeeded. The only shadow on
 the story of achievement is that there seems to be no return from the
 spawning. There is little doubt that death is the nemesis of their
 reproduction. In any case, no adult eel ever comes back from the deep sea. We
 are minded of Goethe's hard saying: "Death is Nature's expert
 advice to get plenty of life."</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 4</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6713">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Forming New Habits</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>There is a well-known mudfish of Australia, Neoceratodus by name, which
 has turned its swim-bladder into a lung and comes to the surface to spout. It
 expels vitiated air with considerable<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 201]</ph> force and takes fresh gulps. At the same
 time, like an ordinary fish, it has gills which allow the usual interchange
 of gases between the blood and the water. Now this Australian mudfish or
 double-breather (Dipnoan), which may be a long way over a yard in length, is
 a direct and little-changed descendant of an ancient extinct fish, Ceratodus,
 which lived in Mesozoic times, as far back as the Jurassic, which probably
 means over five millions of years ago. The Queensland mudfish is an
 antiquity, and there has not been much change in its lineage for millions of
 years. We might take it as an illustration of the inertia of evolution. And
 yet, though its structure has changed but little, the fish probably
 illustrates evolution in process, for it is a fish that is learning to
 breathe dry air. It cannot leave the water; but it can live comfortably in
 pools which are foul with decomposing animal and vegetable matter. In
 partially dried-up and foul waterholes, full of dead fishes of various kinds,
 Neoceratodus has been found vigorous and lively. Unless we take the view,
 which is <i>possible</i>, that the swim-bladder of fishes was originally a
 lung, the mud-fishes are learning to breathe dry air. They illustrate
 evolution agoing.</p>
            <fig id="image324"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>DIAGRAM OF THE LIFE HISTORY OF THE COMMON EEL (<i>Anguilla
   Vulgalis</i>)</p>

               <p>1. The transparent open-sea knife-blade-like larva called a
   Leptocephalus.</p>

               <p>2 and 3. The gradual change of shape from knife-blade-like
   to cylindrical. The body becomes shorter and loses weight.</p>

               <p>4. The young elver, at least a year old, which makes its
   way from the open sea to the estuaries and rivers. It is 2/3 inches long
   and almost cylindrical.</p>

               <p>5. The fully-formed eel.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image324_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>DIAGRAM OF THE LIFE HISTORY OF THE COMMON EEL (Anguilla Vulgalis)</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image325a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Gambier Bolton.</i>
               </p>

               <p>CASSOWARY</p>

               <p>Its bare head is capped with a helmet. Unlike the plumage
   of most birds its feathers are loose and hair-like, whilst its wings are
   merely represented by a few black quills. It is flightless and entirely
   dependent on its short powerful legs to carry it out of danger.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image325a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>CASSOWARY</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image325b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Gambier Bolton.</i>
               </p>

               <p>THE KIWI, ANOTHER FLIGHTLESS BIRD, OF REMARKABLE APPEARANCE, HABITS, AND
   STRUCTURE</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image325b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE KIWI</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>The herring-gull is by nature a fish-eater; but of recent
 years, in some parts of Britain, it has been becoming in the summer months
 more and more of a vegetarian, scooping out the turnips, devouring potatoes,
 settling on the sheaves in the harvest field and gorging itself with grain.
 Similar experiments, usually less striking, are known in many birds; but the
 most signal illustration is that of the kea or Nestor parrot of New Zealand,
 which has taken to lighting on the loins of the sheep, tearing away the
 fleece, cutting at the skin, and gouging out fat. Now the parrot belongs to a
 vegetarian or frugivorous stock, and this change of diet in the relatively
 short time since sheep-ranches were established in New Zealand is very
 striking. Here, since we know the dates, we may speak of evolution going on
 under our eyes. It must be remembered that variations in habit may give
 an<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 202]</ph>
 animal a new opportunity to test variations in structure which arise
 mysteriously from within, as expressions of germinal changefulness rather
 than as imprints from without. For of the transmissibility of the latter
 there is little secure evidence.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6796">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Experiments in Locomotion</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It is very interesting to think of the numerous types of locomotion which
 animals have discovered—pulling and punting, sculling and rowing, and
 of the changes that are rung on these four main methods. How striking is the
 case of the frilled lizard (Chlamydosaurus) of Australia, which at the
 present time is, as it were, experimenting in bipedal
 progression—always a rather eventful thing to do. It gets up on its
 hind-legs and runs totteringly for a few feet, just like a baby learning to
 walk.</p>
            <p>How beautiful is the adventure which has led our dipper or
 water-ouzel—a bird allied to the wrens—to try walking and flying
 under water! How admirable is the volplaning of numerous
 parachutists—"flying fish," "flying frog,"
 "flying dragon," "flying phalanger," "flying
 squirrel," and more besides, which take great leaps through the air. For
 are these not the splendid failures that might have succeeded in starting new
 modes of flight?</p>
            <p>Most daring of all, perhaps, are the aerial journeys undertaken by many
 small spiders. On a breezy morning, especially in the autumn, they mount on
 gate-posts and palings and herbage, and, standing with their head to the
 wind, pay out three or four long threads of silk. When the wind tugs at these
 threads, the spinners let go, and are borne, usually back downwards, on the
 wings of the wind from one parish to another. It is said that if the wind
 falls they can unfurl more sail, or furl if it rises. In any case, these
 wingless creatures make aerial journeys. When tens of thousands of the used
 threads sink to earth, there is a "shower of gossamer." On his
 <i>Beagle</i> voyage Darwin observed that vast numbers of small gossamer
 spiders were borne on to the ship when it was sixty miles distant from the
 land.</p>
            <fig id="image328a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE AUSTRALIAN FRILLED LIZARD, WHICH IS AT PRESENT TRYING TO BECOME A
   BIPED</p>

               <p>When it gets up on its hind-legs and runs for a short
   distance it folds its big collar round its neck.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image328a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE AUSTRALIAN FRILLED LIZARD, WHICH IS AT PRESENT TRYING TO BECOME A BIPED</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image328b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>A CARPET OF GOSSAMER</p>

               <p>The silken threads used by thousands of gossamer spiders in
   their migrations are here seen entangled in the grass, forming what is
   called a shower of gossamer. At the edge of the grass the gossamer forms a
   curtain, floating out and looking extraordinarily like waves breaking on a
   seashore.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image328b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A CARPET OF GOSSAMER</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image329a">
               <image href="images/image329a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE WATER-SPIDER</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="d1e6848"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE WATER-SPIDER</p>

               <p>The spider is seen just leaving its diving-bell to ascend
   to the surface to capture air.</p>

               <p>The spider jerks its body and legs out at the surface and
   then dives—</p>

               <p>—carrying with it what looks like a silvery
   air-bubble—air entangled in the hair.</p>

               <p>The spider reaches its air-dome. Note how the touch of its
   legs indents the inflated balloon.</p>

               <p>Running down the side of the nest, the spider</p>

               <p>—brushes off the air at the entrance, and the bubble
   ascends into the silken balloon.</p>

               <p>
                  <i>Photos: J. J. Ward, F.E.S.</i>
               </p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image329b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE WATER-SPIDER</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 203]</ph>
            </p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6886">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">New Devices</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It is impossible, we must admit, to fix dates, except in a few cases,
 relatively recent; but there is a smack of modernity in some striking devices
 which we can observe in operation to-day. Thus no one will dispute the
 statement that spiders are thoroughly terrestrial animals breathing dry air,
 but we have the fact of the water-spider conquering the under-water world.
 There are a few spiders about the seashore, and a few that can survive
 douching with freshwater, but the particular case of the true water-spider,
 <i>Argyroneta natans</i>, stands by itself because the creature, as regards
 the female at least, has <i>conquered</i> the sub-aquatic environment. A
 flattish web is woven, somehow, underneath the water, and pegged down by
 threads of silk. Along a special vertical line the mother spider ascends to
 the surface and descends again, having entangled air in the hairs of her
 body. She brushes off this air underneath her web, which is thereby buoyed up
 into a sort of dome. She does this over and over again, never getting wet all
 the time, until the domed web has become like a diving-bell, full of dry air.
 In this eloquent anticipation of man's rational device, this
 creature—far from being endowed with reason—lays her eggs and
 looks after her young. The general significance of the facts is that when
 competition is keen, a new area of exploitation is a promised land. Thus
 spiders have spread over all the earth except the polar areas. But here is a
 spider with some spirit of adventure, which has endeavoured, instead of
 trekking, to find a new corner near at home. It has tackled a problem surely
 difficult for a terrestrial animal, the problem of living in great part under
 water, and it has solved it in a manner at once effective and beautiful.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e6896">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">In Conclusion</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>We have given but a few representative illustrations of a great theme.
 When we consider the changefulness of living creatures, the transformations
 of cultivated plants and domesticated<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 204]</ph> animals, the gradual alterations in the
 fauna of a country, the search after new haunts, the forming of new habits,
 and the discovery of many inventions, are we not convinced that Evolution is
 going on? And why should it stop?<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 205]</ph>
            </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 206]</ph>
            </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 207]</ph>
            </p>
            <!--hr--></body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
</topic>