<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="chapter_09">
   <title>
      <ph outputclass="title-line">VIII</ph> 
      <ph outputclass="title-line">FOUNDATIONS OF THE UNIVERSE</ph> 
   </title>
   <body><!--hr--></body>
   <topic id="d1e7869">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE WORLD OF ATOMS</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>Most people have heard of the oriental race which puzzled over the
 foundations of the universe, and decided that it must be supported on the
 back of a giant elephant. But the elephant? They put it on the back of a
 monstrous tortoise, and there they let the matter end. If every animal in
 nature had been called upon, they would have been no nearer a foundation.
 Most ancient peoples, indeed, made no effort to find a foundation. The
 universe was a very compact little structure, mainly composed of the earth
 and the great canopy over the earth which they called the sky. They left it,
 as a whole, floating in nothing. And in this the ancients were wiser than
 they knew. Things do not fall down unless they are pulled down by that
 mysterious force which we call gravitation. The earth, it is true, is pulled
 by the sun, and would fall into it; but the earth escapes this fiery fate by
 circulating at great speed round the sun. The stars pull each other; but it
 has already been explained that they meet this by travelling rapidly in
 gigantic orbits. Yet we do, in a new sense of the word, need foundations of
 the universe. Our mind craves for some explanation of the matter out of which
 the universe is made. For this explanation we turn to modern Physics and
 Chemistry. Both these sciences study, under different aspects, matter and
 energy; and between them they have put together a conception of the
 fundamental nature of things which marks an epoch in the history of human
 thought.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 246]</ph>
         </p>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 1</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e7879">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Bricks of the Cosmos</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>More than two thousand years ago the first men of science, the Greeks of
 the cities of Asia Minor, speculated on the nature of matter. You can grind a
 piece of stone into dust. You can divide a spoonful of water into as many
 drops as you like. Apparently you can go on dividing as long as you have got
 apparatus fine enough for the work. But there must be a limit, these Greeks
 said, and so they supposed that all matter was ultimately composed of minute
 particles which were indivisible. That is the meaning of the Greek word
 "atom."</p>
            <p>Like so many other ideas of these brilliant early Greek thinkers, the atom
 was a sound conception. We know to-day that matter is composed of atoms. But
 science was then so young that the way in which the Greeks applied the idea
 was not very profound. A liquid or a gas, they said, consisted of round,
 smooth atoms, which would not cling together. Then there were atoms with
 rough surfaces, "hooky" surfaces, and these stuck together and
 formed solids. The atoms of iron or marble, for instance, were so very hooky
 that, once they got together, a strong man could not tear them apart. The
 Greeks thought that the explanation of the universe was that an infinite
 number of these atoms had been moving and mixing in an infinite space during
 an infinite time, and had at last hit by chance on the particular combination
 which is our universe.</p>
            <p>This was too simple and superficial. The idea of atoms was cast aside,
 only to be advanced again in various ways. It was the famous Manchester
 chemist, John Dalton, who restored it in the early years of the nineteenth
 century. He first definitely formulated the atomic theory as a scientific
 hypothesis. The whole physical and chemical science of that century was now
 based upon the atom, and it is quite a mistake to suppose that recent
 discoveries have discredited "atomism." An atom is the smallest
 particle<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 247]</ph> of a chemical element. No one has ever seen an atom. Even the
 wonderful new microscope which has just been invented cannot possibly show us
 particles of matter which are a million times smaller than the breadth of a
 hair; for that is the size of atoms. We can weigh them and measure them,
 though they are invisible, and we know that all matter is composed of them.
 It is a new discovery that atoms are not indivisible. They consist themselves
 of still smaller particles, as we shall see. But the atoms exist all the
 same, and we may still say that they are the bricks of which the material
 universe is built.</p>
            <fig id="image388a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Elliott &amp; Fry.</i>
               </p>

               <p>SIR ERNEST RUTHERFORD</p>

               <p>One of our most eminent physicists who has succeeded Sir J.
   J. Thomson as Cavendish Professor of Physics at the University of
   Cambridge. The modern theory of the structure of the atom is largely due to
   him.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image388a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SIR ERNEST RUTHERFORD</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image388b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Rischgitz Collection.</i>
               </p>

               <p>J. CLERK-MAXWELL</p>

               <p>One of the greatest scientific men who have ever lived. He
   revolutionised physics with his electro-magnetic theory of light, and
   practically all modern researches have had their origin, direct or
   indirect, in his work. Together with Faraday he constitutes one of the main
   scientific glories of the nineteenth century.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image388b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>J. CLERK-MAXWELL</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image389a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Ernest H. Mills.</i>
               </p>

               <p>SIR WILLIAM CROOKES</p>

               <p>Sir William Crookes experimented on the electric discharge
   in vacuum tubes and described the phenomena as a "fourth state of
   matter." He was actually observing the flight of electrons, but he did
   not fully appreciate the nature of his experiments.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image389a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SIR WILLIAM CROOKES</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image389b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Photo Press</i>
               </p>

               <p>PROFESSOR SIR W. H. BRAGG</p>

               <p>One of the most distinguished physicists of the present day.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image389b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROFESSOR SIR W. H. BRAGG</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>But if we had some magical glass by means of which we could see into the
 structure of material things, we should not see the atoms put evenly together
 as bricks are in a wall. As a rule, two or more atoms first come together to
 form a larger particle, which we call a "molecule." Single atoms do
 not, as a rule, exist apart from other atoms; if a molecule is broken up, the
 individual atoms seek to unite with other atoms of another kind or amongst
 themselves. For example, three atoms of oxygen form what we call ozone; two
 atoms of hydrogen uniting with one atom of oxygen form water. It is molecules
 that form the mass of matter; a molecule, as it has been expressed, is a
 little building of which atoms are the bricks.</p>
            <p>In this way we get a useful first view of the material things we handle.
 In a liquid the molecules of the liquid cling together loosely. They remain
 together as a body, but they roll over and away from each other. There is
 "cohesion" between them, but it is less powerful than in a solid.
 Put some water in a kettle over the lighted gas, and presently the tiny
 molecules of water will rush through the spout in a cloud of steam and
 scatter over the kitchen. The heat has broken their bond of association and
 turned the water into something like a gas; though we know that the particles
 will come together again, as they cool, and form once more drops of
 water.</p>
            <p>In a gas the molecules have full individual liberty. They<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 248]</ph> are in a state
 of violent movement, and they form no union with each other. If we want to
 force them to enter into the loose sort of association which molecules have
 in a liquid, we have to slow down their individual movements by applying
 severe cold. That is how a modern man of science liquefies gases. No power
 that we have will liquefy air at its ordinary temperature. In <i>very</i>
 severe cold, on the other hand, the air will spontaneously become liquid.
 Some day, when the fires of the sun have sunk very low, the temperature of
 the earth will be less than -200° C.: that is to say, more than two hundred
 degrees Centigrade below freezing-point. It will sink to the temperature of
 the moon. Our atmosphere will then be an ocean of liquid air, 35 feet deep,
 lying upon the solidly frozen masses of our water-oceans.</p>
            <p>In a solid the molecules cling firmly to each other. We need a force equal
 to twenty-five tons to tear asunder the molecules in a bar of iron an inch
 thick. Yet the structure is not "solid" in the popular sense of the
 word. If you put a piece of solid gold in a little pool of mercury, the gold
 will take in the mercury <i>between</i> its molecules, as if it were porous
 like a sponge. The hardest solid is more like a lattice-work than what we
 usually mean by "solid"; though the molecules are not fixed, like
 the bars of a lattice-work, but are in violent motion; they vibrate about
 equilibrium positions. If we could see right into the heart of a bit of the
 hardest steel, we should see billions of separate molecules, at some distance
 from each other, all moving rapidly to and fro.</p>
            <p>This molecular movement can, in a measure, be made visible. It was noticed
 by a microscopist named Brown that, in a solution containing very fine
 suspended particles, the particles were in constant movement. Under a
 powerful microscope these particles are seen to be violently agitated; they
 are each independently darting hither and thither somewhat like a lot of
 billiard balls on a billiard table, colliding and bounding about in all
 directions. Thousands of times a second these encounters occur, and this
 lively commotion is always going on, this incessant colliding of<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 249]</ph> one molecule
 with another is the normal condition of affairs; not one of them is at rest.
 The reason for this has been worked out, and it is now known that these
 particles move about because they are being incessantly bombarded by the
 molecules of the liquid. The molecules cannot, of course, be seen, but the
 fact of their incessant movement is revealed to the eye by the behaviour of
 the visible suspended particles. This incessant movement in the world of
 molecules is called the Brownian movement, and is a striking proof of the
 reality of molecular motions.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 2</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e7998">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Wonder-World of Atoms</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The exploration of this wonder-world of atoms and molecules by the
 physicists and chemists of to-day is one of the most impressive triumphs of
 modern science. Quite apart from radium and electrons and other sensational
 discoveries of recent years, the study of ordinary matter is hardly inferior,
 either in interest or audacity, to the work of the astronomer. And there is
 the same foundation in both cases—marvellous apparatus, and trains of
 mathematical reasoning that would have astonished Euclid or Archimedes.
 Extraordinary, therefore, as are some of the facts and figures we are now
 going to give in connection with the minuteness of atoms and molecules, let
 us bear in mind that we owe them to the most solid and severe processes of
 human thought.</p>
            <p>Yet the principle can in most cases be made so clear that the reader will
 not be asked to take much on trust. It is, for instance, a matter of common
 knowledge that gold is soft enough to be beaten into gold leaf. It is a
 matter of common sense, one hopes, that if you beat a measured cube of gold
 into a leaf six inches square, the mathematician can tell the thickness of
 that leaf without measuring it. As a matter of fact, a single grain of gold
 has been beaten into a leaf seventy-five inches square. Now the mathematician
 can easily find that when a single grain of gold is beaten out to that size,
 the leaf must be 1/367,000 of an inch thick,<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 250]</ph> or about a thousand times
 thinner than the paper on which these words are printed; yet the leaf must be
 several molecules thick.</p>
            <p>The finest gold leaf is, in fact, too thick for our purpose, and we turn
 with a new interest to that toy of our boyhood the soap-bubble. If you
 carefully examine one of these delicate films of soapy water, you notice
 certain dark spots or patches on them. These are their thinnest parts, and by
 two quite independent methods—one using electricity and the other
 light—we have found that at these spots the bubble is less than the
 three-millionth of an inch thick! But the molecules in the film cling
 together so firmly that they must be at least twenty or thirty deep in the
 thinnest part. A molecule, therefore, must be far less than the
 three-millionth of an inch thick.</p>
            <p>We found next that a film of oil on the surface of water may be even
 thinner than a soap-bubble. Professor Perrin, the great French authority on
 atoms, got films of oil down to the fifty-millionth of an inch in thickness!
 He poured a measured drop of oil upon water. Then he found the exact limits
 of the area of the oil-sheet by blowing upon the water a fine powder which
 spread to the edge of the film and clearly outlined it. The rest is safe and
 simple calculation, as in the case of the beaten grain of gold. Now this film
 of oil must have been at least two molecules deep, so a single molecule of
 oil is considerably less than a hundred-millionth of an inch in diameter.</p>
            <p>Innumerable methods have been tried, and the result is always the same. A
 single grain of indigo, for instance, will colour a ton of water. This
 obviously means that the grain contains billions of molecules which spread
 through the water. A grain of musk will scent a room—pour molecules
 into every part of it—for several years, yet not lose one-millionth of
 its mass in a year. There are a hundred ways of showing the minuteness of the
 ultimate particles of matter, and some of these enable us to give definite
 figures. On a careful comparison of the best methods we can say that the
 average molecule of matter is less<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 251]</ph> than the 1/125,000,000 of an inch in
 diameter. In a single cubic centimetre of air—a globule about the size
 of a small marble—there are thirty million trillion molecules. And
 since the molecule is, as we saw, a group or cluster of atoms, the atom
 itself is smaller. Atoms, for reasons which we shall see later, differ very
 greatly from each other in size and weight. It is enough to say that some of
 them are so small that it would take 400,000,000 of them, in a line, to cover
 an inch of space; and that it takes at least a quintillion atoms of gold to
 weigh a single gramme. Five million atoms of helium could be placed in a line
 across the diameter of a full stop.</p>
            <fig id="image394a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>An atom is the smallest particle of a chemical element. Two
   or more atoms come together to form a molecule: thus molecules form the
   mass of matter. A molecule of water is made up of two atoms of hydrogen and
   one atom of oxygen. Molecules of different substances, therefore, are of
   different sizes according to the number and kind of the particular atoms of
   which they are composed. A starch molecule contains no less than 25,000
   atoms.</p>

               <p>Molecules, of course, are invisible. The above diagram
   illustrates the <i>comparative</i> sizes of molecules.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image394a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>An atom is the smallest particle of a chemical element.</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image394b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>INCONCEIVABLE NUMBERS AND INCONCEIVABLY SMALL PARTICLES</p>

               <p>The molecules, which are inconceivably small, are, on the
   other hand, so numerous that if one was able to place, end to end, all
   those contained in, for example, a cubic centimetre of gas (less than a
   fifteenth of a cubic inch), one would obtain a line capable of passing two
   hundred times round the earth.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image394b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>INCONCEIVABLE NUMBERS AND INCONCEIVABLY SMALL PARTICLES</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image394c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>WHAT IS A MILLION?</p>

               <p>In dealing with the infinitely small, it is difficult to
   apprehend the vast figures with which scientists confront us. A million is
   one thousand thousand. We may realise what this implies if we consider that
   a clock, beating seconds, takes approximately 278 hours (i.e. one week four
   days fourteen hours) to tick one million times. A billion is one million
   million. To tick a billion the clock would tick for over 31,735 years.</p>

               <p>(In France and America a thousand millions is called a
   billion.)</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image394c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>&gt;WHAT IS A MILLION?</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image395"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE BROWNIAN MOVEMENT</p>

               <p>A diagram, constructed from actual observations, showing
   the erratic paths pursued by very fine particles suspended in a liquid,
   when bombarded by the molecules of the liquid. This movement is called the
   Brownian movement, and it furnishes a striking illustration of the truth of
   the theory that the molecules of a body are in a state of continual
   motion.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image395_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE BROWNIAN MOVEMENT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8089">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Energy of Atoms</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>And this is only the beginning of the wonders that were done with
 "ordinary matter," quite apart from radium and its revelations, to
 which we will come presently. Most people have heard of "atomic
 energy," and the extraordinary things that might be accomplished if we
 could harness this energy and turn it to human use. A deeper and more
 wonderful source of this energy has been discovered in the last twenty years,
 but it is well to realise that the atoms themselves have stupendous energy.
 The atoms of matter are vibrating or gyrating with extraordinary vigour. The
 piece of cold iron you hold in your hand, the bit of brick you pick up, or
 the penny you take from your pocket is a colossal reservoir of energy, since
 it consists of trillions of moving atoms. To realise the total energy, of
 course, we should have to witness a transformation such as we do in atoms of
 radio-active elements, about which we shall have something to say
 presently.</p>
            <p>If we put a grain of indigo in a glass of water, or a grain of musk in a
 perfectly still room, we soon realise that molecules travel. Similarly, the
 fact that gases spread until they fill every "empty" available
 space shows definitely that they consist of small particles travelling at
 great speed. The physicist brings his refined methods to bear on these
 things, and he measures the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 252]</ph> energy and velocity of these infinitely minute
 molecules. He tells us that molecules of oxygen, at the temperature of
 melting ice, travel at the rate of about 500 yards a second—more than a
 quarter of a mile a second. Molecules of hydrogen travel at four times that
 speed, or three times the speed with which a bullet leaves a rifle. Each
 molecule of the air, which seems so still in the house on a summer's day,
 is really travelling faster than a rifle bullet does at the beginning of its
 journey. It collides with another molecule every twenty-thousandth of an inch
 of its journey. It is turned from its course 5,000,000,000 times in every
 second by collisions. If we could stop the molecules of hydrogen gas, and
 utilise their energy, as we utilise the energy of steam or the energy of the
 water at Niagara, we should find enough in every gramme of gas (about
 two-thousandths of a pound) to raise a third of a ton to a height of forty
 inches.</p>
            <p>I have used for comparison the speed of a rifle bullet, and in an earlier
 generation people would have thought it impossible even to estimate this. It
 is, of course, easy. We put two screens in the path of the bullet, one near
 the rifle and the other some distance away. We connect them electrically and
 use a fine time-recording machine, and the bullet itself registers the time
 it takes to travel from the first to the second screen.</p>
            <p>Now this is very simple and superficial work in comparison with the system
 of exact and minute measurements which the physicist and chemist use. In one
 of his interesting works Mr. Charles R. Gibson gives a photograph of two
 exactly equal pieces of paper in the opposite pans of a fine balance. A
 single word has been written in pencil on one of these papers, and that
 little scraping of lead has been enough to bring down the scale! The
 spectroscope will detect a quantity of matter four million times smaller even
 than this; and the electroscope is a million times still more sensitive than
 the spectroscope. We have a heat-measuring instrument, the bolometer, which
 makes the best thermometer seem Early Victorian. It records the millionth of
 a degree of<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 253]</ph> temperature. It is such instruments, multiplied by the score,
 which enable us to do the fine work recorded in these pages.</p>
            <fig id="image398"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Reproduced from "The Forces of Nature" (Messrs.
   Macmillan).</i>
               </p>

               <p>A SOAP BUBBLE</p>

               <p>The iridescent colours sometimes seen on a soap bubble, as
   in the illustration, may also be seen in very fine sections of crystals, in
   glass blown into extremely fine bulbs, on the wings of dragon-flies and the
   surface of oily water. The different colours correspond to different
   thicknesses of the surface. Part of the light which strikes these thin
   coatings is reflected from the upper surface, but another part of the light
   penetrates the transparent coating and is reflected from the lower surface.
   It is the mixture of these two reflected rays, their
   "interference" as it is called, which produces the colours
   observed. The "black spots" on a soap bubble are the places where
   the soapy film is thinnest. At the black spots the thickness of the bubble
   is about the three-millionth part of an inch. If the whole bubble were as
   thin as this it would be completely invisible.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image398_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A SOAP BUBBLE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 3</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e8130">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE DISCOVERY OF X-RAYS AND RADIUM</ph> 
      </title>
      <body/>
      <topic id="d1e8132">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Discovery of Sir Wm. Crookes</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>But these wonders of the atom are only a prelude to the more romantic and
 far-reaching discoveries of the new physics—the wonders of the
 electron. Another and the most important phase of our exploration of the
 material universe opened with the discovery of radium in 1898.</p>
            <p>In the discovery of radio-active elements, a new property of matter was
 discovered. What followed on the discovery of radium and of the X-rays we
 shall see.</p>
            <p>As Sir Ernest Rutherford, one of our greatest authorities, recently said,
 the new physics has dissipated the last doubt about the reality of atoms and
 molecules. The closer examination of matter which we have been able to make
 shows positively that it is composed of atoms. But we must not take the word
 now in its original Greek meaning (an "indivisible" thing). The
 atoms are not indivisible. They can be broken up. They are composed of still
 smaller particles.</p>
            <p>The discovery that the atom was composed of smaller particles was the
 welcome realisation of a dream that had haunted the imagination of the
 nineteenth century. Chemists said that there were about eighty different
 kinds of atoms—different kinds of matter—but no one was satisfied
 with the multiplicity. Science is always aiming at simplicity and unity. It
 may be that science has now taken a long step in the direction of explaining
 the fundamental unity of all the matter. The chemist was unable to break up
 these "elements" into something simpler, so he called their atoms
 "indivisible" in that sense. But one man of science after another
 expressed the hope that we would yet discover<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 254]</ph> some fundamental matter of which
 the various atoms were composed—<i>one primordial substance from which
 all the varying forms of matter have been evolved or built up</i>. Prout
 suggested this at the very beginning of the century, when atoms were
 rediscovered by Dalton. Father Secchi, the famous Jesuit astronomer said that
 all the atoms were probably evolved from ether; and this was a very favoured
 speculation. Sir William Crookes talked of "prothyl" as the
 fundamental substance. Others thought hydrogen was the stuff out of which all
 the other atoms were composed.</p>
            <p>The work which finally resulted in the discovery of radium began with some
 beautiful experiments of Professor (later Sir William) Crookes in the
 eighties.</p>
            <p>It had been noticed in 1869 that a strange colouring was caused when an
 electric charge was sent through a vacuum tube—the walls of the glass
 tube began to glow with a greenish phosphorescence. A vacuum tube is one from
 which nearly all the air has been pumped, although we can never completely
 empty the tube. Crookes used such ingenious methods that he reduced the gas
 in his tubes until it was twenty million times thinner than the atmosphere.
 He then sent an electric discharge through, and got very remarkable results.
 The negative pole of the electric current (the "cathode") <i>gave
 off rays which faintly lit the molecules of the thin gas in the tube</i>, and
 caused a pretty fluorescence on the glass walls of the tube. What were these
 Rays? Crookes at first thought they corresponded to a "new or fourth
 state of matter." Hitherto we had only been familiar with matter in the
 three conditions of solid, liquid, and gaseous.</p>
            <p>Now Crookes really had the great secret under his eyes. But about twenty
 years elapsed before the true nature of these rays was finally and
 independently established by various experiments. The experiments proved
 "that the rays consisted of a stream of negatively charged particles
 travelling with enormous velocities from 10,000 to 100,000 miles a second. In
 addition, it was found<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 255]</ph> that the mass of each particle was exceedingly
 small, about 1/1800 of the mass of a hydrogen atom, the lightest atom known
 to science." <i>These particles or electrons, as they are now called,
 were being liberated from the atom.</i> The atoms of matter were breaking
 down in Crookes tubes. At that time, however, it was premature to think of
 such a thing, and Crookes preferred to say that the particles of the gas were
 electrified and hurled against the walls of the tube. He said that it was
 ordinary matter in a new state—"radiant matter." Another
 distinguished man of science, Lenard, found that, when he fitted a little
 plate of aluminum in the glass wall of the tube, the mysterious rays passed
 through this as if it were a window. They must be waves in the ether, he
 said.</p>
            <fig id="image402a">
               <image href="images/image402a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>DETECTING A SMALL QUANTITY OF MATTER</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="d1e8172"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>From "Scientific Ideas of To-day</i>."</p>

               <p>DETECTING A SMALL QUANTITY OF MATTER</p>

               <p>In the left-hand photograph the two pieces of paper exactly
   balance. The balance used is very sensitive, and when the single word
   "atoms" has been written with a lead pencil upon one of the
   papers the additional weight is sufficient to depress one of the pans as
   shown in the second photograph. The spectroscope will detect less than
   one-millionth of the matter contained in the word pencilled above.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image402a1_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>DETECTING A SMALL QUANTITY OF MATTER</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image402b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Reproduced by permission of X-Rays Ltd.</i>
               </p>

               <p>THIS X-RAY PHOTOGRAPH IS THAT OF A HAND OF A SOLDIER WOUNDED IN THE
   GREAT WAR</p>

               <p>Note the pieces of shrapnel which are revealed.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image402b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THIS X-RAY PHOTOGRAPH IS THAT OF A HAND OF A SOLDIER WOUNDED IN THE GREAT WAR</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image402c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: National Physical Laboratory.</i>
               </p>

               <p>AN X-RAY PHOTOGRAPH OF A GOLF BALL, REVEALING AN IMPERFECT CORE</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image402c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>AN X-RAY PHOTOGRAPH OF A GOLF BALL, REVEALING AN IMPERFECT CORE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image403"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Reproduced by permission of X-Rays Ltd.</i>
               </p>

               <p>A WONDERFUL X-RAY PHOTOGRAPH</p>

               <p>Note the fine details revealed, down to the metal tags of
   the bootlace and the nails in the heel of the boot.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image403_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A WONDERFUL X-RAY PHOTOGRAPH</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 4</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8252">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Discovery of X-rays</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>So the story went on from year to year. We shall see in a moment to what
 it led. Meanwhile the next great step was when, in 1895, Röntgen discovered
 the X-rays, which are now known to everybody. He was following up the work of
 Lenard, and he one day covered a "Crookes tube" with some black
 stuff. To his astonishment a prepared chemical screen which was near the tube
 began to glow. <i>The rays had gone through the black stuff; and on further
 experiment he found that they would go through stone, living flesh, and all
 sorts of "opaque" substances.</i> In a short time the world was
 astonished to learn that we could photograph the skeleton in a living
 man's body, locate a penny in the interior of a child that had swallowed
 one, or take an impression of a coin through a slab of stone.</p>
            <p>And what are these X-rays? They are not a form of matter; they are not
 material particles. X-rays were found to be a new variety of <i>light</i>
 with a remarkable power of penetration. We have seen what the spectroscope
 reveals about the varying nature of light wave-lengths. Light-waves are set
 up by vibrations in<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 256]</ph> ether,<xref href="#unknown/Footnote_2_2" type="fn"><!--[2]--></xref> and, as we shall see, these ether
 disturbances are all of the same kind; they only differ as regards
 wave-lengths. The X-rays which Röntgen discovered, then, are light, but a
 variety of light previously unknown to us; they are ether waves of very short
 length. X-rays have proved of great value in many directions, as all the
 world knows, but that we need not discuss at this point. Let us see what
 followed Röntgen's discovery.</p>
            <p outputclass="fn-holder">
               <fn id="Footnote_2_2"> We refer throughout to
  the "ether" because, although modern theories dispense largely
  with this conception, the theories of physics are so inextricably interwoven
  with it that it is necessary, in an elementary exposition, to assume its
  existence. The modern view will be explained later in the article on
  Einstein's Theory.</fn>
            </p>
            <p>While the world wondered at these marvels, the men of science were eagerly
 following up the new clue to the mystery of matter which was exercising the
 mind of Crookes and other investigators. In 1896 Becquerel brought us to the
 threshold of the great discovery.</p>
            <p>Certain substances are phosphorescent—they become luminous after
 they have been exposed to sunlight for some time, and Becquerel was trying to
 find if any of these substances give rise to X-rays. One day he chose a salt
 of the metal uranium. He was going to see if, after exposing it to sunlight,
 he could photograph a cross with it through an opaque substance. He wrapped
 it up and laid it aside, to wait for the sun, but he found the uranium salt
 did not wait for the sun. Some strong radiation from it went through the
 opaque covering and made an impression of the cross upon the plate
 underneath. Light or darkness was immaterial. The mysterious rays streamed
 night and day from the salt. This was something new. Here was a substance
 which appeared to be producing X-rays; the rays emitted by uranium would
 penetrate the same opaque substances as the X-rays discovered by Röntgen.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8285">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Discovery of Radium</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Now, at the same time as many other investigators, Professor Curie and his
 Polish wife took up the search. They decided to<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 257]</ph> find out whether the emission
 came from the uranium itself or <i>from something associated with it</i>, and
 for this purpose they made a chemical analysis of great quantities of
 minerals. They found a certain kind of pitchblende which was very active, and
 they analysed tons of it, concentrating always on the radiant element in it.
 After a time, as they successively worked out the non-radiant matter, the
 stuff began to glow. In the end they extracted from eight tons of pitchblende
 about half a teaspoonful of something <i>that was a million times more
 radiant than uranium</i>. There was only one name for it—Radium.</p>
            <p>That was the starting-point of the new development of physics and
 chemistry. From every laboratory in the world came a cry for radium salts (as
 pure radium was too precious), and hundreds of brilliant workers fastened on
 the new element. The inquiry was broadened, and, as year followed year, one
 substance after another was found to possess the power of emitting rays, that
 is, to be radio-active. We know to-day that nearly every form of matter can
 be stimulated to radio-activity; which, as we shall see, means that <i>its
 atoms break up into smaller and wonderfully energetic particles which we call
 "electrons."</i> This discovery of electrons has brought about a
 complete change in our ideas in many directions.</p>
            <p>So, instead of atoms being indivisible, they are actually dividing
 themselves, spontaneously, and giving off throughout the universe tiny
 fragments of their substance. We shall explain presently what was later
 discovered about the electron; meanwhile we can say that every glowing metal
 is pouring out a stream of these electrons. Every arc-lamp is discharging
 them. Every clap of thunder means a shower of them. Every star is flooding
 space with them. We are witnessing the spontaneous breaking up of atoms,
 atoms which had been thought to be indivisible. The sun not only pours out
 streams of electrons from its own atoms, but the ultra-violet light which it
 sends to the earth is one of the most powerful agencies for releasing
 electrons from the surface-atoms<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 258]</ph> of matter on the earth. It is fortunate for us
 that our atmosphere absorbs most of this ultra-violet or invisible light of
 the sun—a kind of light which will be explained presently. It has been
 suggested that, if we received the full flood of it from the sun, our metals
 would disintegrate under its influence and this "steel
 civilisation" of ours would be impossible!</p>
            <p>But we are here anticipating, we are going beyond radium to the wonderful
 discoveries which were made by the chemists and physicists of the world who
 concentrated upon it. The work of Professor and Mme. Curie was merely the
 final clue to guide the great search. How it was followed up, how we
 penetrated into the very heart of the minute atom and discovered new and
 portentous mines of energy, and how we were able to understand, not only
 matter, but electricity and light, will be told in the next chapter.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e8313">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE DISCOVERY OF THE ELECTRON AND HOW IT EFFECTED A REVOLUTION IN
 IDEAS</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>What the discovery of radium implied was only gradually realised. Radium
 captivated the imagination of the world; it was a boon to medicine, but to
 the man of science it was at first a most puzzling and most attractive
 phenomenon. It was felt that some great secret of nature was dimly unveiled
 in its wonderful manifestations, and there now concentrated upon it as gifted
 a body of men—conspicuous amongst them Sir J. J. Thomson, Sir Ernest
 Rutherford, Sir W. Ramsay, and Professor Soddy—as any age could boast,
 with an apparatus of research as far beyond that of any other age as the
 <i>Aquitania</i> is beyond a Roman galley. Within five years the secret was
 fairly mastered. Not only were all kinds of matter reduced to a common basis,
 but the forces of the universe were brought into a unity and understood as
 they had never been understood before.</p>
         <fig id="image408a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>ELECTRIC DISCHARGE IN A VACUUM TUBE</p>

            <p>The two ends, marked + and -, of a tube from which nearly
   all air has been exhausted are connected to electric terminals, thus
   producing an electric discharge in the vacuum tube. This discharge travels
   straight along the tube, as in the upper diagram. When a magnetic field is
   applied, however, the rays are deflected, as shown in the lower diagram.
   The similarity of the behaviour of the electric discharge with the radium
   rays (see diagram of deflection of radium rays, <i>post</i>) shows that the
   two phenomena may be identified. It was by this means that the
   characteristics of electrons were first discovered.</p>
            <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image408a_sm.jpg">
               <alt>ELECTRIC DISCHARGE IN A VACUUM TUBE</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig id="image408b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE RELATIVE SIZES OF ATOMS AND ELECTRONS</p>

            <p>An atom is far too small to be seen. In a bubble of
   hydrogen gas no larger than the letter "O" there are billions of
   atoms, whilst an electron is more than a thousand times smaller than the
   smallest atom. How their size is ascertained is described in the text. In
   this diagram a bubble of gas is magnified to the size of the world.
   Adopting this scale, <i>each atom</i> in the bubble would then be as large
   as a tennis ball.</p>
            <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image408b_sm.jpg">
               <alt>THE RELATIVE SIZES OF ATOMS AND ELECTRONS</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig id="image408c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>IF AN ATOM WERE MAGNIFIED TO THE SIZE OF ST. PAUL'S CATHEDRAL, EACH
   ELECTRON IN THE ATOM (AS REPRESENTED BY THE CATHEDRAL) WOULD THEN BE ABOUT
   THE SIZE OF A SMALL BULLET</p>
            <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image408c_sm.jpg">
               <alt>IF AN ATOM WERE MAGNIFIED TO THE SIZE OF ST. PAUL'S CATHEDRAL</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <fig id="image409"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>ELECTRONS STREAMING FROM THE SUN TO THE EARTH</p>

            <p>There are strong reasons for supposing that sun-spots are
   huge electronic cyclones. The sun is constantly pouring out vast streams of
   electrons into space. Many of these streams encounter the earth, giving
   rise to various electrical phenomena.</p>
            <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image409_sm.jpg">
               <alt>ELECTRONS STREAMING FROM THE SUN TO THE EARTH</alt>
            </image>
         </fig>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 259]</ph>
         </p>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 5</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e8394">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Discovery of the Electron</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Physicists did not take long to discover that the radiation from radium
 was very like the radiation in a "Crookes tube." It was quickly
 recognised, moreover, that both in the tube and in radium (and other metals)
 the atoms of matter were somehow breaking down.</p>
            <p>However, the first step was to recognise that there were three distinct
 and different rays that were given off by such metals as radium and uranium.
 Sir Ernest Rutherford christened them, after the first three letters of the
 Greek alphabet, the Alpha, the Beta, and Gamma rays. We are concerned chiefly
 with the second group and purpose here to deal with that group only.<xref href="#unknown/Footnote_3_3" type="fn"><!--[3]--></xref>
            </p>
            <p outputclass="fn-holder">
               <fn id="Footnote_3_3"> The "Alpha
  rays" were presently recognised as atoms of helium gas, shot out at the
  rate of 12,000 miles a second.

               <p>The "Gamma rays" are <i>waves</i>, like the X-rays, not
  material particles. They appear to be a type of X-rays. They possess the
  remarkable power of penetrating opaque substances; they will pass through a
  foot of solid iron, for example.</p></fn>
            </p>
            <p>The "Beta rays," as they were at first called, have proved to be
 one of the most interesting discoveries that science ever made. They proved
 what Crookes had surmised about the radiations he discovered in his vacuum
 tube. But it was <i>not</i> a fourth state of matter that had been found, but
 a new <i>property</i> of matter, a property common to all atoms of matter.
 The Beta rays were later christened Electrons. They are particles of
 disembodied electricity, here spontaneously liberated from the atoms of
 matter: only when the electron was isolated from the atom was it recognised
 for the first time as a separate entity. Electrons, therefore, are a
 constituent of the atoms of matter, and we have discovered that they can be
 released from the atom by a variety of agencies. Electrons are to be found
 everywhere, forming part of every atom.</p>
            <p>"An electron," Sir William Bragg says, "can only maintain a
 separate existence if it is travelling at an immense rate, from one
 three-hundredth of the velocity of light upwards, that is to<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 260]</ph> say, at least
 600 <i>miles a second, or thereabouts</i>. Otherwise the electron sticks to
 the first atom it meets." These amazing particles may travel with the
 enormous velocity of from 10,000 to more than 100,000 miles a second. It was
 first learned that they are of an electrical nature, because they are bent
 out of their normal path if a magnet is brought near them. And this fact led
 to a further discovery: to one of those sensational estimates which the
 general public is apt to believe to be founded on the most abstruse
 speculations. The physicist set up a little chemical screen for the
 "Beta rays" to hit, and he so arranged his tube that only a narrow
 sheaf of the rays poured on to the screen. He then drew this sheaf of rays
 out of its course with a magnet, and he accurately measured the shift of the
 luminous spot on the screen where the rays impinged on it. But when he knows
 the exact intensity of his magnetic field—which he can control as he
 likes—and the amount of deviation it causes, and the mass of the moving
 particles, he can tell the speed of the moving particles which he thus
 diverts. These particles were being hurled out of the atoms of radium, or
 from the negative pole in a vacuum tube, at a speed which, in good
 conditions, reached nearly the velocity of light, i.e. nearly 186,000 miles a
 second.</p>
            <p>Their speed has, of course, been confirmed by numbers of experiments; and
 another series of experiments enabled physicists to determine the size of the
 particles. Only one of these need be described, to give the reader an idea
 how men of science arrived at their more startling results.</p>
            <p>Fog, as most people know, is thick in our great cities because the
 water-vapour gathers on the particles of dust and smoke that are in the
 atmosphere. This fact was used as the basis of some beautiful experiments.
 Artificial fogs were created in little glass tubes, by introducing dust, in
 various proportions, for supersaturated vapour to gather on. In the end it
 was possible to cause tiny drops of rain, each with a particle of dust at its
 core, to fall upon a silver mirror and be counted. It was a method of
 counting<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 261]</ph> the quite invisible particles of dust in the tube; and the
 method was now successfully applied to the new rays. Yet another method was
 to direct a slender stream of the particles upon a chemical screen. The
 screen glowed under the cannonade of particles, and a powerful lens resolved
 the glow into distinct sparks, which could be counted.</p>
            <p>In short, a series of the most remarkable and beautiful experiments,
 checked in all the great laboratories of the world, settled the nature of
 these so-called rays. They were streams of particles more than a thousand
 times smaller than the smallest known atom. The mass of each particle is,
 according to the latest and finest measurements 1/1845 of that of an atom of
 hydrogen. The physicist has not been able to find any character except
 electricity in them, and the name "electrons" has been generally
 adopted.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8445">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Key to many Mysteries</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The Electron is an atom, of disembodied electricity; it occupies an
 exceedingly small volume, and its "mass" is entirely electrical.
 These electrons are the key to half the mysteries of matter. Electrons in
 rapid motion, as we shall see, explain what we mean by an "electric
 current," not so long ago regarded as one of the most mysterious
 manifestations in nature.</p>
            <p>"What a wonder, then, have we here!" says Professor R. K.
 Duncan. "An innocent-looking little pinch of salt and yet possessed of
 special properties utterly beyond even the fanciful imaginings of men of past
 time; for nowhere do we find in the records of thought even the hint of the
 possibility of things which we now regard as established fact. This pinch of
 salt projects from its surface bodies [i.e. electrons] possessing the
 inconceivable velocity of over 100,000 miles a second, a velocity sufficient
 to carry them, if unimpeded, five times around the earth in a second, and
 possessing with this velocity, masses a thousand times smaller than the
 smallest atom known to science. Furthermore,<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 262]</ph> they are charged with negative
 electricity; they pass straight through bodies considered opaque with a
 sublime indifference to the properties of the body, with the exception of its
 mere density; they cause bodies which they strike to shine out in the dark;
 they affect a photographic plate; they render the air a conductor of
 electricity; they cause clouds in moist air; they cause chemical action and
 have a peculiar physiological action. Who, to-day, shall predict the ultimate
 service to humanity of the beta-rays from radium!"</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 6</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e8458">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE ELECTRON THEORY, OR THE NEW VIEW OF MATTER</ph> 
      </title>
      <body/>
      <topic id="d1e8460">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Structure of the Atom</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>There is general agreement amongst all chemists, physicists, and
 mathematicians upon the conclusions which we have so far given. We know that
 the atoms of matter are constantly—either spontaneously or under
 stimulation—giving off electrons, or breaking up into electrons; and
 they therefore contain electrons. Thus we have now complete proof of the
 independent existence of atoms and also of electrons.</p>
            <p>When, however, the man of science tries to tell us <i>how</i> electrons
 compose atoms, he passes from facts to speculation, and very difficult
 speculation. Take the letter "o" as it is printed on this page. In
 a little bubble of hydrogen gas no larger than that letter there are
 <i>trillions</i> of atoms; and they are not packed together, but are
 circulating as freely as dancers in a ball-room. We are asking the physicist
 to take one of these minute atoms and tell us how the still smaller electrons
 are arranged in it. Naturally he can only make mental pictures, guesses or
 hypotheses, which he tries to fit to the facts, and discards when they will
 <i>not</i> fit.</p>
            <p>At present, after nearly twenty years of critical discussion, there are
 two chief theories of the structure of the atom. At first<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 263]</ph> Sir J. J.
 Thomson imagined the electrons circulating in shells (like the layers of an
 onion) round the nucleus of the atom. This did not suit, and Sir E.
 Rutherford and others worked out a theory that the electrons circulated round
 a nucleus rather like the planets of our solar system revolving round the
 central sun. Is there a nucleus, then, round which the electrons revolve? The
 electron, as we saw, is a disembodied atom of electricity; we should say, of
 "negative" electricity. Let us picture these electrons all moving
 round in orbits with great velocity. Now it is suggested that there is a
 nucleus of "positive" electricity attracting or pulling the
 revolving electrons to it, and so forming an equilibrium, otherwise the
 electrons would fly off in all directions. This nucleus has been recently
 named the proton. We have thus two electricities in the atom: the positive =
 the nucleus; the negative = the electron. Of recent years Dr. Langmuir has
 put out a theory that the electrons do not <i>revolve round</i> the nucleus,
 but remain in a state of violent agitation of some sort at fixed distances
 from the nucleus.</p>
            <fig id="image414a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>PROFESSOR SIR J. J. THOMSON</p>

               <p>Experimental discoverer of the electronic constitution of
   matter, in the Cavendish Physical Laboratory, Cambridge. A great
   investigator, noted for the imaginative range of his hypotheses and his
   fertility in experimental devices.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image414a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROFESSOR SIR J. J. THOMSON</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image414b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>From the Smithsonian Report</i>, 1915.</p>

               <p>ELECTRONS PRODUCED BY PASSAGE OF X-RAYS THROUGH AIR</p>

               <p>A photograph clearly showing that electrons are definite
   entities. As electrons leave atoms they may traverse matter or pass through
   the air in a straight path The illustration shows the tortuous path of
   electrons resulting from collision with atoms.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image414b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>ELECTRONS PRODUCED BY PASSAGE OF X-RAYS THROUGH AIR</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image415a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>MAGNETIC DEFLECTION OF RADIUM RAYS</p>

               <p>The radium rays are made to strike a screen, producing
   visible spots of light. When a magnetic field is applied the rays are seen
   to be deflected, as in the diagram. This can only happen if the rays carry
   an electric charge, and it was by experiments of this kind that we obtained
   our knowledge respecting the electric charges carried by radium rays.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image415a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>MAGNETIC DEFLECTION OF RADIUM RAYS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image415b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Reproduced by permission of "Scientific American."</i>
               </p>

               <p>PROFESSOR R. A. MILLIKAN'S APPARATUS FOR COUNTING ELECTRONS</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image415b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROFESSOR R. A. MILLIKAN'S APPARATUS FOR COUNTING ELECTRONS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>But we will confine ourselves here to the facts, and leave the contending
 theories to scientific men. It is now pretty generally accepted that an atom
 of matter consists of a number of electrons, or charges of negative
 electricity, held together by a charge of positive electricity. It is not
 disputed that these electrons are in a state of violent motion or strain, and
 that therefore a vast energy is locked up in the atoms of matter. To that we
 will return later. Here, rather, we will notice another remarkable discovery
 which helps us to understand the nature of matter.</p>
            <p>A brilliant young man of science who was killed in the war, Mr. Moseley,
 some years ago showed that, when the atoms of different substances are
 arranged in order of their weight, <i>they are also arranged in the order of
 increasing complexity of structure</i>. That is to say, the heavier the atom,
 the more electrons it contains. There is a gradual building up of atoms
 containing more and more electrons from the lightest atom to the
 heaviest.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 264]</ph> Here it is enough to say that as he took element after
 element, from the lightest (hydrogen) to the heaviest (uranium) he found a
 strangely regular relation between them. If hydrogen were represented by the
 figure one, helium by two, lithium three, and so on up to uranium, then
 uranium should have the figure ninety-two. This makes it probable that there
 are in nature ninety-two elements—we have found eighty-seven—and
 that the number Mr. Moseley found is the number of electrons in the atom of
 each element; that is to say, the number is arranged in order of the atomic
 numbers of the various elements.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 7</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8568">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The New View of Matter</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Up to the point we have reached, then, we see what the new view of Matter
 is. Every atom of matter, of whatever kind throughout the whole universe, is
 built up of electrons in conjunction with a nucleus. From the smallest atom
 of all—the atom of hydrogen—which consists of one electron,
 rotating round a positively charged nucleus, to a heavy complicated atom,
 such as the atom of gold, constituted of many electrons and a complex
 nucleus, <i>we have only to do with positive and negative units of
 electricity</i>. The electron and its nucleus are particles of electricity.
 All Matter, therefore, is nothing but a manifestation of electricity. The
 atoms of matter, as we saw, combine and form molecules. Atoms and molecules
 are the bricks out of which nature has built up everything; ourselves, the
 earth, the stars, the whole universe.</p>
            <p>But more than bricks are required to build a house. There are other
 fundamental existences, such as the various forms of energy, which give rise
 to several complex problems. And we have also to remember, that there are
 more than eighty distinct elements, each with its own definite type of atom.
 We shall deal with energy later. Meanwhile it remains to be said that,
 although we have discovered a great deal about the electron and the
 constitution<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 265]</ph> of matter, and that while the physicists of our own day seem
 to see a possibility of explaining positive and negative electricity, the
 nature of them both is unknown. There exists the theory that the particles of
 positive and negative electricity, which make up the atoms of matter, are
 points or centres of disturbances of some kind in a universal ether, and that
 all the various forms of energy are, in some fundamental way, aspects of the
 same primary entity which constitutes matter itself.</p>
            <p>But the discovery of the property of radio-activity has raised many other
 interesting questions, besides that which we have just dealt with. In
 radio-active elements, such as uranium for example, the element is breaking
 down; in what we call radio-activity we have a manifestation of the
 spontaneous change of elements. What is really taking place is a
 transmutation of one element into another, from a heavier to a lighter. The
 element uranium spontaneously becomes radium, and radium passes through a
 number of other stages until it, in turn, becomes lead. Each descending
 element is of lighter atomic weight than its predecessor. The changing
 process, of course, is a very slow one. It may be that all matter is
 radio-active, or can be made so. This raises the question whether all the
 matter in the universe may not undergo disintegration.</p>
            <p>There is, however, another side of the question, which the discovery of
 radio-activity has brought to light, and which has effected a revolution in
 our views. We have seen that in radio-active substances the elements are
 breaking down. Is there a process of building up at work? If the more
 complicated atoms are breaking down into simpler forms, may there not be a
 converse process—a building up from simpler elements to more
 complicated elements? It is probably the case that both processes are at
 work.</p>
            <p>There are some eighty-odd chemical elements on the earth to-day: are they
 all the outcome of an inorganic evolution, element giving rise to element,
 going back and back to some primeval<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 266]</ph> stuff from which they were all originally
 derived infinitely long ago? Is there an evolution in the inorganic world
 which may be going on, parallel to that of the evolution of living things; or
 is organic evolution a continuation of inorganic evolution? We have seen what
 evidence there is of this inorganic evolution in the case of the stars. We
 cannot go deeply into the matter here, nor has the time come for any direct
 statement that can be based on the findings of modern investigation. Taking
 it altogether the evidence is steadily accumulating, and there are
 authorities who maintain that already the evidence of inorganic evolution is
 convincing enough. The heavier atoms would appear to behave as though they
 were evolved from the lighter. The more complex forms, it is supposed, have
 <i>evolved</i> from the simpler forms. Moseley's discovery, to which
 reference has been made, points to the conclusion that the elements are built
 up one from another.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 8</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8597">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Other New Views</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>We may here refer to another new conception to which the discovery of
 radio-activity has given rise. Lord Kelvin, who estimated the age of the
 earth at twenty million years, reached this estimate by considering the earth
 as a body which is gradually cooling down, "losing its primitive heat,
 like a loaf taken from the oven, at a rate which could be calculated, and
 that the heat radiated by the sun was due to contraction." Uranium and
 radio-activity were not known to Kelvin, and their discovery has upset both
 his arguments. Radio-active substances, which are perpetually giving out
 heat, introduce an entirely new factor. We cannot now assume that the earth
 is necessarily cooling down; it may even, for all we know, be getting hotter.
 At the 1921 meeting of the British Association, Professor Rayleigh stated
 that further knowledge had extended the probable period during which there
 had been life on this globe to about one thousand<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 267]</ph> million years,
 and the total age of the earth to some small multiple of that. The earth, he
 considers, is not cooling, but "contains an internal source of heat from
 the disintegration of uranium in the outer crust." On the whole the
 estimate obtained would seem to be in agreement with the geological
 estimates. The question, of course, cannot, in the present state of our
 knowledge, be settled within fixed limits that meet with general
 agreement.</p>
            <fig id="image420"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>MAKING THE INVISIBLE VISIBLE</p>

               <p>Radium, as explained in the text, emits rays—the
   "Alpha," the "Beta" (electrons), and "Gamma"
   rays. The above illustration indicates the method by which these invisible
   rays are made visible, and enables the nature of the rays to be
   investigated. To the right of the diagram is the instrument used, the
   Spinthariscope, making the impact of radium rays visible on a screen.</p>

               <p>The radium rays shoot out in all directions; those that
   fall on the screen make it glow with points of light. These points of light
   are observed by the magnifying lens.</p>

               <p>A. Magnifying lens. B. A zinc sulphite screen. C. A needle
   on whose point is placed a speck of radium.</p>

               <p>The lower picture shows the screen and needle
   magnified..</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image420_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>MAKING THE INVISIBLE VISIBLE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image421a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE THEORY OF ELECTRONS</p>

               <p>An atom of matter is composed of electrons. We picture an
   atom as a sort of miniature solar system, the electrons (particles of
   negative electricity) rotating round a central nucleus of positive
   electricity, as described in the text. In the above pictorial
   representation of an atom the whirling electrons are indicated in the outer
   ring. Electrons move with incredible speed as they pass from one atom to
   another.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image421a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE THEORY OF ELECTRONS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image421b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>ARRANGEMENTS OF ATOMS IN A DIAMOND</p>

               <p>The above is a model (seen from two points of view) of the
   arrangement of the atoms in a diamond. The arrangement is found by studying
   the X-ray spectra of the diamond.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image421b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>ARRANGEMENTS OF ATOMS IN A DIAMOND</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>As we have said, there are other fundamental existences which give rise to
 more complex problems. The three great fundamental entities in the physical
 universe are matter, ether, and energy; so far as we know, outside these
 there is nothing. We have dealt with matter, there remain ether and energy.
 We shall see that just as no particle of matter, however small, may be
 created or destroyed, and just as there is no such thing as empty
 space—ether pervades everything—so there is no such thing as
 <i>rest</i>. Every particle that goes to make up our solid earth is in a
 state of perpetual unremitting vibration; energy "is the universal
 commodity on which all life depends." Separate and distinct as these
 three fundamental entities—matter, ether, and energy—may appear,
 it may be that, after all, they are only different and mysterious phases of
 an essential "oneness" of the universe.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 9</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8669">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Future</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Let us, in concluding this chapter, give just one illustration of the way
 in which all this new knowledge may prove to be as valuable practically as it
 is wonderful intellectually. We saw that electrons are shot out of atoms at a
 speed that may approach 160,000 miles a second. Sir Oliver Lodge has written
 recently that a seventieth of a grain of radium discharges, at a speed a
 thousand times that of a rifle bullet, thirty million electrons a second.
 Professor Le Bon has calculated that it would take 1,340,000 barrels of
 powder to give a bullet the speed of one of these electrons. He shows that
 the smallest French copper coin—smaller<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 268]</ph> than a farthing—contains
 an energy equal to eighty million horsepower. A few pounds of matter contain
 more energy than we could extract from millions of tons of coal. Even in the
 atoms of hydrogen at a temperature which we could produce in an electric
 furnace the electrons spin round at a rate of nearly a hundred trillion
 revolutions a second!</p>
            <p>Every man asks at once: "Will science ever tap this energy?" If
 it does, no more smoke, no mining, no transit, no bulky fuel. The energy of
 an atom is of course only liberated when an atom passes from one state to
 another. The stored up energy is fortunately fast bound by the electrons
 being held together as has been described. If it were not so "the earth
 would explode and become a gaseous nebula"! It is believed that some day
 we shall be able to release, harness, and utilise atomic energy. "I am
 of opinion," says Sir William Bragg, "that atom energy will supply
 our future need. A thousand years may pass before we can harness the atom, or
 to-morrow might see us with the reins in our hands. That is the peculiarity
 of Physics—research and 'accidental' discovery go hand in
 hand." Half a brick contains as much energy as a small coal-field. The
 difficulties are tremendous, but, as Sir Oliver Lodge reminds us, there was
 just as much scepticism at one time about the utilisation of steam or
 electricity. "Is it to be supposed," he asks, "that there can
 be no fresh invention, that all the discoveries have been made?" More
 than one man of science encourages us to hope. Here are some remarkable words
 written by Professor Soddy, one of the highest authorities on radio-active
 matter, in our chief scientific weekly (<i>Nature</i>, November 6, 1919):</p>
            <lq>
               <p>The prospects of the successful accomplishment of artificial
  transmutation brighten almost daily. The ancients seem to have had something
  more than an inkling that the accomplishment of transmutation would confer
  upon men powers hitherto the prerogative of the gods. But now we know
  definitely that the material aspect of transmutation<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 269]</ph> would be of
  small importance in comparison with the control over the inexhaustible
  stores of internal atomic energy to which its successful accomplishment
  would inevitably lead. It has become a problem, no longer redolent of the
  evil associations of the age of alchemy, but one big with the promise of a
  veritable physical renaissance of the whole world.</p>
            </lq>
            <p>If that "promise" is ever realised, the economic and social face
 of the world will be transformed.</p>
            <p>Before passing on to the consideration of ether, light, and energy, let us
 see what new light the discovery of the electron has thrown on the nature and
 manipulation of electricity.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e8696">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">WHAT IS ELECTRICITY?</ph> 
      </title>
      <body/>
      <topic id="d1e8698">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Nature of Electricity</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>There is at least one manifestation in nature, and so late as twenty years
 ago it seemed to be one of the most mysterious manifestations of all, which
 has been in great measure explained by the new discoveries. Already, at the
 beginning of this century, we spoke of our "age of electricity,"
 yet there were few things in nature about which we knew less. The
 "electric current" rang our bells, drove our trains, lit our rooms,
 but none knew what the current was. There was a vague idea that it was a sort
 of fluid that flowed along copper wires as water flows in a pipe. We now
 suppose that it is <i>a rapid movement of electrons from atom to atom</i> in
 the wire or wherever the current is.</p>
            <p>Let us try to grasp the principle of the new view of electricity and see
 how it applies to all the varied electrical phenomena in the world about us.
 As we saw, the nucleus of an atom of matter consists of positive electricity
 which holds together a number of electrons, or charges of negative
 electricity.<xref href="#unknown/Footnote_4_4" type="fn"><!--[4]--></xref> This<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 270]</ph> certainly tells us to some
 extent what electricity is, and how it is related to matter, but it leaves us
 with the usual difficulty about fundamental realities. But we now know that
 electricity, like matter, is atomic in structure; a charge of electricity is
 made up of a number of small units or charges of a definite, constant amount.
 It has been suggested that the two kinds of electricity, i.e. positive and
 negative, are right-handed and left-handed vortices or whirlpools in ether,
 or rings in ether, but there are very serious difficulties, and we leave this
 to the future.</p>
            <p outputclass="fn-holder">
               <fn id="Footnote_4_4"> The words
  "positive" and "negative" electricity belong to the days
  when it was regarded as a fluid. A body overcharged with the fluid was
  called positive; an undercharged body was called negative. A
  positively-electrified body is now one whose atoms have lost some of their
  outlying electrons, so that the positive charge of electricity predominates.
  The negatively-electrified body is one with more than the normal number of
  electrons.</fn>
            </p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 10</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8726">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">What an Electric Current is</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The discovery of these two kinds of electricity has, however, enabled us
 to understand very fairly what goes on in electrical phenomena. The outlying
 electrons, as we saw, may pass from atom to atom, and this, on a large scale,
 is the meaning of the electric current. In other words, we believe an
 electric current to be a flow of electrons. Let us take, to begin with, a
 simple electrical "cell," in which a feeble current is generated:
 such a cell as there is in every house to serve its electric bells.</p>
            <p>In the original form this simple sort of "battery" consisted of
 a plate of zinc and a plate of copper immersed in a chemical. Long before
 anything was known about electrons it was known that, if you put zinc and
 copper together, you produce a mild current of electricity. We know now what
 this means. Zinc is a metal the atoms of which are particularly disposed to
 part with some of their outlying electrons. Why, we do not know; but the fact
 is the basis of these small batteries. Electrons from the atoms of zinc pass
 to the atoms of copper, and their passage is a "current." Each atom
 gives up an electron to its neighbour. It was further found long ago that if
 the zinc and copper were immersed in certain chemicals, which slowly dissolve
 the zinc, and the two metals were connected by a copper wire, the current was
 stronger. In modern language, there is a brisker flow of<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 271]</ph> electrons. The
 reason is that the atoms of zinc which are stolen by the chemical leave their
 detachable electrons behind them, and the zinc has therefore more electrons
 to pass on to the copper.</p>
            <fig id="image426a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>DISINTEGRATION OF ATOMS</p>

               <p>An atom of Uranium, by ejecting an Alpha particle, becomes
   Uranium X. This substance, by ejecting Beta and Gamma rays, becomes Radium.
   Radium passes through a number of further changes, as shown in the diagram,
   and finally becomes lead. Some radio-active substances disintegrate much
   faster than others. Thus Uranium changes very slowly, taking 5,000,000,000
   years to reach the same stage of disintegration that Radium A reaches in 3
   minutes. As the disintegration proceeds, the substances become of lighter
   and lighter atomic weights. Thus Uranium has an atomic weight of 238,
   whereas lead has an atomic weight of only 206. The breaking down of atoms
   is fully explained in the text.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image426a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>DISINTEGRATION OF ATOMS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image426b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Reproduced by permission from "The Interpretation of
   Radium" (John Murray).</i>
               </p>

               <p>SILK TASSEL ELECTRIFIED</p>

               <p>The separate threads of the tassel, being each electrified
   with the same kind of electricity, repel one another, and thus the tassel
   branches out as in the photograph.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image426b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SILK TASSEL ELECTRIFIED</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image426c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>SILK TASSEL DISCHARGED BY THE RAYS FROM RADIUM</p>

               <p>When the radium rays, carrying an opposite electric charge
   to that on the tassel, strikes the threads, the threads are neutralised,
   and hence fall together again.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image426c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SILK TASSEL DISCHARGED BY THE RAYS FROM RADIUM</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image427a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>A HUGE ELECTRIC SPARK</p>

               <p>This is an actual photograph of an electric spark. It is
   leaping a distance of about 10 feet, and is the discharge of a million
   volts. It is a graphic illustration of the tremendous energy of
   electrons.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image427a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A HUGE ELECTRIC SPARK</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image427b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>From "Scientific Ideas of To-day</i>."</p>

               <p>ELECTRICAL ATTRACTION BETWEEN COMMON OBJECTS</p>

               <p>Take an ordinary flower-vase well dried and energetically
   rub it with a silk handkerchief. The vase which thus becomes electrified
   will attract any light body, such as a feather, as shown in the above
   illustration.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image427b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>ELECTRICAL ATTRACTION BETWEEN COMMON OBJECTS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>Such cells are now made of zinc and carbon, immersed in sal-ammoniac, but
 the principle is the same. The flow of electricity is a flow of electrons;
 though we ought to repeat that they do not flow in a body, as molecules of
 water do. You may have seen boys place a row of bricks, each standing on one
 end, in such order that the first, if it is pushed, will knock over the
 second, the second the third, and so on to the last. There is a flow of
 <i>movement</i> all along the line, but each brick moves only a short
 distance. So an electron merely passes to the next atom, which sends on an
 electron to a third atom, and so on. In this case, however, the movement from
 atom to atom is so rapid that the ripple of movement, if we may call it so,
 may pass along at an enormous speed. We have seen how swiftly electrons
 travel.</p>
            <p>But how is this turned into power enough even to ring a bell? The actual
 mechanical apparatus by which the energy of the electron current is turned
 into sound, or heat, or light will be described in a technical section later
 in this work. We are concerned here only with the principle, which is clear.
 While zinc is very apt to part with electrons, copper is just as obliging in
 facilitating their passage onward. Electrons will travel in this way in most
 metals, but copper is one of the best "conductors." So we lengthen
 the copper wire between the zinc and the carbon until it goes as far as the
 front door and the bell, which are included in the circuit. When you press
 the button at the door, two wires are brought together, and the current of
 electrons rushes round the circuit; and at the bell its energy is diverted
 into the mechanical apparatus which rings the bell.</p>
            <p>Copper is a good conductor—six times as good as iron—and is
 therefore so common in electrical industries. Some other substances are just
 as stubborn as copper is yielding, and we call them "insulators,"
 because they resist the current instead of letting<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 272]</ph> it flow. Their
 atoms do not easily part with electrons. Glass, vulcanite, and porcelain are
 very good insulators for this reason.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8839">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">What the Dynamo does</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>But even several cells together do not produce the currents needed in
 modern industry, and the flow is produced in a different manner. As the
 invisible electrons pass along a wire they produce what we call a magnetic
 field around the wire, they produce a disturbance in the surrounding ether.
 To be exact, it is through the ether surrounding the wire that the energy
 originated by the electrons is transmitted. To set electrons moving on a
 large scale we use a "dynamo." By means of the dynamo it is
 possible to transform mechanical energy into electrical energy. The modern
 dynamo, as Professor Soddy puts it, may be looked upon as an electron pump.
 We cannot go into the subject deeply here, we would only say that a large
 coil of copper wire is caused to turn round rapidly between the poles of a
 powerful magnet. That is the essential construction of the
 "dynamo," which is used for generating strong currents. We shall
 see in a moment how magnetism differs from electricity, and will say here
 only that round the poles of a large magnet there is a field of intense
 disturbance which will start a flow of electrons in any copper that is
 introduced into it. On account of the speed given to the coil of wire its
 atoms enter suddenly this magnetic field, and they give off crowds of
 electrons in a flash.</p>
            <p>It is found that a similar disturbance is caused, though the flow is in
 the <i>opposite</i> direction, when the coil of wire leaves the magnetic
 field. And as the coil is revolving very rapidly we get a powerful current of
 electricity that runs in alternate directions—an
 "alternating" current. Electricians have apparatus for converting
 it into a continuous current where this is necessary.</p>
            <p>A current, therefore, means a steady flow of the electrons from atom to
 atom. Sometimes, however, a number of electrons<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 273]</ph> rush violently and explosively
 from one body to another, as in the electric spark or the occasional flash
 from an electric tram or train. The grandest and most spectacular display of
 this phenomenon is the thunderstorm. As we saw earlier, a portentous furnace
 like the sun is constantly pouring floods of electrons from its atoms into
 space. The earth intercepts great numbers of these electrons. In the upper
 regions of the air the stream of solar electrons has the effect of separating
 positively-electrified atoms from negatively-electrified ones, and the
 water-vapour, which is constantly rising from the surface of the sea, gathers
 more freely round the positively-electrified atoms, and brings them down, as
 rain, to the earth. Thus the upper air loses a proportion of positive
 electricity, or becomes "negatively electrified." In the
 thunderstorm we get both kinds of clouds—some with large excesses of
 electrons, and some deficient in electrons—and the tension grows until
 at last it is relieved by a sudden and violent discharge of electrons from
 one cloud to another or to the earth—an electric spark on a prodigious
 scale.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 11</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8857">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Magnetism</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>We have seen that an electric current is really a flow of electrons. Now
 an electric current exhibits a magnetic effect. The surrounding space is
 endowed with energy which we call electro-magnetic energy. A piece of
 magnetised iron attracting other pieces of iron to it is the popular idea of
 a magnet. If we arrange a wire to pass vertically through a piece of
 cardboard and then sprinkle iron filings on the cardboard we shall find that,
 on passing an electric current through the wire, the iron filings arrange
 themselves in circles round it. The magnetic force, due to the electric
 current, seems to exist in circles round the wire, an ether disturbance being
 set up. Even a single electron, when in movement, creates a magnetic
 "field," as it is called, round its path. There is no movement of
 electrons without this attendant field<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 274]</ph> of energy, and their motion is
 not stopped until that field of energy disappears from the ether. The modern
 theory of magnetism supposes that all magnetism is produced in this way. All
 magnetism is supposed to arise from the small whirling motions of the
 electrons contained in the ultimate atoms of matter. We cannot here go into
 the details of the theory nor explain why, for instance, iron behaves so
 differently from other substances, but it is sufficient to say that here,
 also, the electron theory provides the key. This theory is not yet definitely
 <i>proved</i>, but it furnishes a sufficient theoretical basis for future
 research. The earth itself is a gigantic magnet, a fact which makes the
 compass possible, and it is well known that the earth's magnetism is
 affected by those great outbreaks on the sun called sun-spots. Now it has
 been recently shown that a sun-spot is a vast whirlpool of electrons and that
 it exerts a strong magnetic action. There is doubtless a connection between
 these outbreaks of electronic activity and the consequent changes in the
 earth's magnetism. The precise mechanism of the connection, however, is
 still a matter that is being investigated.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e8868">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">ETHER AND WAVES</ph> 
      </title>
      <body/>
      <topic id="d1e8870">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Ether and Waves</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The whole material universe is supposed to be embedded in a vast medium
 called the ether. It is true that the notion of the ether has been abandoned
 by some modern physicists, but, whether or not it is ultimately dispensed
 with, the conception of the ether has entered so deeply into the scientific
 mind that the science of physics cannot be understood unless we know
 something about the properties attributed to the ether. The ether was
 invented to explain the phenomena of light, and to account for the flow of
 energy across empty space. Light takes time to travel. We see the sun at any
 moment by the light that left it 8 minutes before. It has taken that 8
 minutes for the light from the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 275]</ph> sun to travel that 93,000,000 miles odd which
 separates it from our earth. Besides the fact that light takes time to
 travel, it can be shown that light travels in the form of waves. We know that
 sound travels in waves; sound consists of waves in the air, or water or wood
 or whatever medium we hear it through. If an electric bell be put in a glass
 jar and the air be pumped out of the jar, the sound of the bell becomes
 feebler and feebler until, when enough air has been taken out, we do not hear
 the bell at all. Sound cannot travel in a vacuum. We continue to <i>see</i>
 the bell, however, so that evidently light can travel in a vacuum. The
 invisible medium through which the waves of light travel is the ether, and
 this ether permeates all space <i>and all matter</i>. Between us and the
 stars stretch vast regions empty of all matter. But we see the stars; their
 light reaches us, even though it may take centuries to do so. We conceive,
 then, that it is the universal ether which conveys that light. All the energy
 which has reached the earth from the sun and which, stored for ages in our
 coal-fields, is now used to propel our trains and steamships, to heat and
 light our cities, to perform all the multifarious tasks of modern life, was
 conveyed by the ether. Without that universal carrier of energy we should
 have nothing but a stagnant, lifeless world.</p>
            <fig id="image432"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Leadbeater.</i>
               </p>

               <p>AN ELECTRIC SPARK</p>

               <p>An electric spark consists of a rush of electrons across
   the space between the two terminals. A state of tension is established in
   the ether by the electric charges, and when this tension passes a certain
   limit the discharge takes place.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image432_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>AN ELECTRIC SPARK</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image433"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>From "Scientific Ideas of To-day."</i>
               </p>

               <p>AN ETHER DISTURBANCE AROUND AN ELECTRON CURRENT</p>

               <p>In the left-hand photograph an electric current is passing
   through the coil, thus producing a magnetic field and transforming the
   poker into a magnet. The poker is then able to support a pair of scissors.
   As soon as the electric current is broken off, as in the second photograph,
   the ether disturbance ceases. The poker loses its magnetism, and the
   scissors fall.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image433_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>AN ETHER DISTURBANCE AROUND AN ELECTRON CURRENT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>We have said that light consists of waves. The ether may be considered as
 resembling, in some respects, a jelly. It can transmit vibrations. The waves
 of light are really excessively small ripples, measuring from crest to crest.
 The distance from crest to crest of the ripples in a pond is sometimes no
 more than an inch or two. This distance is enormously great compared to the
 longest of the wave-lengths that constitute light. We say the longest, for
 the waves of light differ in length; the colour depends upon the length of
 the light. Red light has the longest waves and violet the shortest. The
 longest waves, the waves of deep-red light, are seven two hundred and fifty
 thousandths of an inch in length (7/250,000 inch). This is nearly twice the
 length<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 276]</ph> of deep-violet light-waves, which are 1/67,000 inch. But
 light-waves, the waves that affect the eye, are not the only waves carried by
 the ether. Waves too short to affect the eye can affect the photographic
 plate, and we can discover in this way the existence of waves only half the
 length of the deep-violet waves. Still shorter waves can be discovered, until
 we come to those excessively minute rays, the X-rays.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8930">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Below the Limits of Visibility</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>But we can extend our investigations in the other direction; we find that
 the ether carries many waves longer than light-waves. Special photographic
 emulsions can reveal the existence of waves five times longer than
 violet-light waves. Extending below the limits of visibility are waves we
 detect as heat-waves. Radiant heat, like the heat from a fire, is also a form
 of wave-motion in the ether, but the waves our senses recognise as heat are
 longer than light-waves. There are longer waves still, but our senses do not
 recognise them. But we can detect them by our instruments. These are the
 waves used in wireless telegraphy, and their length may be, in some cases,
 measured in miles. These waves are the so-called electro-magnetic waves.
 Light, radiant heat, and electro-magnetic waves are all of the same nature;
 they differ only as regards their wave-lengths.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e8935">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">LIGHT—VISIBLE AND INVISIBLE</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>If Light, then, consists of waves transmitted through the ether, what
 gives rise to the waves? Whatever sets up such wonderfully rapid series of
 waves must be something with an enormous vibration. We come back to the
 electron: all atoms of matter, as we have seen, are made up of electrons
 revolving in a regular orbit round a nucleus. These electrons may be affected
 by out-side influences, they may be agitated and their speed or vibration
 increased.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 277]</ph>
         </p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e8942">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Electrons and Light</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The particles even of a piece of cold iron are in a state of vibration. No
 nerves of ours are able to feel and register the waves they emit, but your
 cold poker is really radiating, or sending out a series of wave-movements, on
 every side. After what we saw about the nature of matter, this will surprise
 none. Put your poker in the fire for a time. The particles of the glowing
 coal, which are violently agitated, communicate some of their energy to the
 particles of iron in the poker. They move to and fro more rapidly, and the
 waves which they create are now able to affect your nerves and cause a
 sensation of heat. Put the poker again in the fire, until its temperature
 rises to 500° C. It begins to glow with a dull red. Its particles are now
 moving very violently, and the waves they send out are so short and rapid
 that they can be picked up by the eye—we have <i>visible</i> light.
 They would still not affect a photographic plate. Heat the iron further, and
 the crowds of electrons now send out waves of various lengths which blend
 into white light. What is happening is the agitated electrons flying round in
 their orbits at a speed of trillions of times a second. Make the iron
 "blue hot," and it pours out, in addition to light, the
 <i>invisible</i> waves which alter the film on the photographic plate. And
 beyond these there is a long range of still shorter waves, culminating in the
 X-rays, which will pass between the atoms of flesh or stone.</p>
            <p>Nearly two hundred and fifty years ago it was proved that light travelled
 at least 600,000 times faster than sound. Jupiter, as we saw, has moons,
 which circle round it. They pass behind the body of the planet, and reappear
 at the other side. But it was noticed that, when Jupiter is at its greatest
 distance from us, the reappearance of the moon from behind it is 16 minutes
 and 36 seconds later than when the planet is nearest to us. Plainly this was
 because light took so long to cover the additional distance. The distance was
 then imperfectly known, and the speed<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 278]</ph> of light was underrated. We now know the
 distance, and we easily get the velocity of light.</p>
            <p>No doubt it seems far more wonderful to discover this within the walls of
 a laboratory, but it was done as long ago as 1850. A cogged wheel is so
 mounted that a ray of light passes between two of the teeth and is reflected
 back from a mirror. Now, slight as is the fraction of a second which light
 takes to travel that distance, it is possible to give such speed to the wheel
 that the next tooth catches the ray of light on its return and cuts it off.
 The speed is increased still further until the ray of light returns to the
 eye of the observer through the notch <i>next</i> to the one by which it had
 passed to the mirror! The speed of the wheel was known, and it was thus
 possible again to gather the velocity of light. If the shortest waves are
 1/67,000 of an inch in length, and light travels at 186,000 miles a second,
 any person can work out that about 800 trillion waves enter the eye in a
 second when we see "violet."</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e8963">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Sorting out Light-waves</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The waves sent out on every side by the energetic electrons become faintly
 visible to us when they reach about 1/35,000 of an inch. As they become
 shorter and more rapid, as the electrons increase their speed, we get, in
 succession, the colours red, orange, yellow, green, blue, indigo, and violet.
 Each distinct sensation of colour means a wave of different length. When they
 are all mingled together, as in the light of the sun, we get white light.
 When this white light passes through glass, the speed of the waves is
 lessened; and, if the ray of light falls obliquely on a triangular piece of
 glass, the waves of different lengths part company as they travel through it,
 and the light is spread out in a band of rainbow-colour. The waves are sorted
 out according to their lengths in the "obstacle race" through the
 glass. Anyone may see this for himself by holding up a wedge-shaped piece of
 crystal between the sunlight and the eye; the prism separates the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 279]</ph> sunlight into
 its constituent colours, and these various colours will be seen quite
 readily. Or the thing may be realised in another way. If the seven colours
 are painted on a wheel as shown opposite page 280 (in the proportion shown),
 and the wheel rapidly revolved on a pivot, the wheel will appear a dull
 white, the several colours will not be seen. But <i>omit</i> one of the
 colours, then the wheel, when revolved, will not appear white, but will give
 the impression of one colour, corresponding to what the union of six colours
 gives. Another experiment will show that some bodies held up between the eye
 and a white light will not permit all the rays to pass through, but will
 intercept some; a body that intercepts all the seven rays except red will
 give the impression of red, or if all the rays except violet, then violet
 will be the colour seen.</p>
            <fig id="image438"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: H. J. Shepstone.</i>
               </p>

   

               <p>In a thunderstorm we have the most spectacular display in
   lightning of a violent and explosive rush of electrons (electricity) from
   one body to another, from cloud to cloud, or to the earth. In this
   wonderful photograph of an electrical storm note the long branched and
   undulating flashes of lightning. Each flash lasts no longer than the one
   hundred-thousandth part of a second of time.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image438_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>LIGHTNING</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image439a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>LIGHT WAVES</p>

               <p>Light consists of waves transmitted through the ether.
   Waves of light differ in length. The colour of the light depends on the
   wave-length. Deep-red waves (the longest) are 7/250000 inch and deep-violet
   waves 1/67000 inch. The diagram shows two wave-motions of different
   wave-lengths. From crest to crest, or from trough to trough, is the length
   of the wave.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image439a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>LIGHT WAVES</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image439b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE MAGNETIC CIRCUIT OF AN ELECTRIC CURRENT</p>

               <p>The electric current passing in the direction of the arrow
   round the electric circuit generates in the surrounding space circular
   magnetic circuits as shown in the diagram. It is this property which lies
   at the base of the electro-magnet and of the electric dynamo.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image439b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE MAGNETIC CIRCUIT OF AN ELECTRIC CURRENT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image439c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE MAGNET</p>

               <p>The illustration shows the lines of force between two
   magnets. The lines of force proceed from the north pole of one magnet to
   the south pole of the other. They also proceed from the north to the south
   poles of the same magnet. These facts are shown clearly in the diagram. The
   north pole of a magnet is that end of it which turns to the north when the
   magnet is freely suspended.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image439c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE MAGNET</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e9043">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Fate of the World</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Professor Soddy has given an interesting picture of what might happen when
 the sun's light and heat is no longer what it is. The human eye "has
 adapted itself through the ages to the peculiarities of the sun's light,
 so as to make the most of that wave-length of which there is most.... Let us
 indulge for a moment in these gloomy prognostications, as to the consequences
 to this earth of the cooling of the sun with the lapse of ages, which used to
 be in vogue, but which radio-activity has so rudely shaken. Picture the fate
 of the world when the sun has become a dull red-hot ball, or even when it has
 cooled so far that it would no longer emit light to us. That does not all
 mean that the world would be in inky darkness, and that the sun would not
 emit light to the people then inhabiting this world, if any had survived and
 could keep themselves from freezing. To such, if the eye continued to adapt
 itself to the changing conditions, our blues and violets would be
 ultra-violet and invisible, but our dark heat would be light and hot bodies
 would be luminous to them which would be dark to us."<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 280]</ph>
            </p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 12</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e9052">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">What the Blue "Sky" means</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>We saw in a previous chapter how the spectroscope splits up light-waves
 into their colours. But nature is constantly splitting the light into its
 different-lengthed waves, its colours. The rainbow, where dense moisture in
 the air acts as a spectroscope, is the most familiar example. A piece of
 mother-of-pearl, or even a film of oil on the street or on water, has the
 same effect, owing to the fine inequalities in its surface. The atmosphere
 all day long is sorting out the waves. The blue "sky" overhead
 means that the fine particles in the upper atmosphere catch the shorter
 waves, the blue waves, and scatter them. We can make a tubeful of blue sky in
 the laboratory at any time. The beautiful pink-flush on the Alps at sunrise,
 the red glory that lingers in the west at sunset, mean that, as the sun's
 rays must struggle through denser masses of air when it is low on the
 horizon, the long red waves are sifted out from the other shafts.</p>
            <p>Then there is the varied face of nature which, by absorbing some waves and
 reflecting others, weaves its own beautiful robe of colour. Here and there is
 a black patch, which <i>absorbs</i> all the light. White surfaces
 <i>reflect</i> the whole of it. What is reflected depends on the period of
 vibration of the electrons in the particular kind of matter. Generally, as
 the electrons receive the flood of trillions of waves, they absorb either the
 long or the medium or the short, and they give us the wonderful colour-scheme
 of nature. In some cases the electrons continue to radiate long after the
 sunlight has ceased to fall upon them. We get from them "black" or
 invisible light, and we can take photographs by it. Other bodies, like glass,
 vibrate in unison with the period of the light-waves and let them stream
 through.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e9064">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Light without Heat</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>There are substances—"phosphorescent" things we call
 them—which give out a mysterious cold light of their own. It is
 one<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 281]</ph>
 of the problems of science, and one of profound practical interest. If we
 could produce light without heat our "gas bill" would shrink
 amazingly. So much energy is wasted in the production of heat-waves and
 ultra-violet waves which we do not want, that 90 per cent. or more of the
 power used in illumination is wasted. Would that the glow-worm, or even the
 dead herring, would yield us its secret! Phosphorus is the one thing we know
 as yet that suits the purpose, and—it smells! Indeed, our artificial
 light is not only extravagant in cost, but often poor in colour. The unwary
 person often buys a garment by artificial light, and is disgusted next
 morning to find in it a colour which is not wanted. The colour disclosed by
 the sun was not in the waves of the artificial light.</p>
            <fig id="image442"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>ROTATING DISC OF SIR ISAAC NEWTON FOR MIXING COLOURS</p>

               <p>The Spectroscope sorts out the above seven colours from
   sunlight (which is compounded of these seven colours). If painted in proper
   proportions on a wheel, as shown in the coloured illustration, and the
   wheel be turned rapidly on a pivot through its centre, only a dull white
   will be perceived. If one colour be omitted, the result will be one
   colour—the result of the union of the remaining six.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image442_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>ROTATING DISC OF SIR ISAAC NEWTON FOR MIXING COLOURS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>Beyond the waves of violet light are the still shorter and more rapid
 waves—the "ultra-violet" waves—which are precious to
 the photographer. As every amateur knows, his plate may safely be exposed to
 light that comes through a red or an orange screen. Such a screen means
 "no thoroughfare" for the blue and "beyond-blue" waves,
 and it is these which arrange the little grains of silver on the plate. It is
 the same waves which supply the energy to the little green grains of matter
 (chlorophyll) in the plant, preparing our food and timber for us, as will be
 seen later. The tree struggles upward and spreads out its leaves fanwise to
 the blue sky to receive them. In our coal-measures, the mighty dead forests
 of long ago, are vast stores of sunlight which we are prodigally using
 up.</p>
            <p>The X-rays are the extreme end, the highest octave, of the series of
 waves. Their power of penetration implies that they are excessively minute,
 but even these have not held their secret from the modern physicist. From a
 series of beautiful experiments, in which they were made to pass amongst the
 atoms of a crystal, we learned their length. It is about the ten-millionth of
 a millimetre, and a millimetre is about the 1/25 of an inch!</p>
            <p>One of the most recent discoveries, made during a recent<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 282]</ph> eclipse of the
 sun, is that light is subject to gravitation. A ray of light from a star is
 bent out of its straight path when it passes near the mass of the sun.
 Professor Eddington tells us that we have as much right to speak of a pound
 of light as of a pound of sugar. Professor Eddington even calculates that the
 earth receives 160 tons of light from the sun every year!</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e9099">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">ENERGY: HOW ALL LIFE DEPENDS ON IT</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>As we have seen in an earlier chapter, one of the fundamental entities of
 the universe is matter. A second, not less important, is called energy.
 Energy is indispensable if the world is to continue to exist, since all
 phenomena, including life, depend on it. Just as it is humanly impossible to
 create or to destroy a particle of matter, so is it impossible to create or
 to destroy energy. This statement will be more readily understood when we
 have considered what energy is.</p>
         <p>Energy, like matter, is indestructible, and just as matter exists in
 various forms so does energy. And we may add, just as we are ignorant of what
 the negative and positive particles of electricity which constitute matter
 really are, so we are ignorant of the true nature of energy. At the same
 time, energy is not so completely mysterious as it once was. It is another of
 nature's mysteries which the advance of modern science has in some
 measure unveiled. It was only during the nineteenth century that energy came
 to be known as something as distinct and permanent as matter itself.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e9105">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Forms of Energy</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The existence of various forms of energy had been known, of course, for
 ages; there was the energy of a falling stone, the energy produced by burning
 wood or coal or any other substance, but the essential <i>identity</i> of all
 these forms of energy had not been suspected. The conception of energy as
 something which, like<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 283]</ph> matter, was constant in amount, which could
 not be created nor destroyed, was one of the great scientific acquisitions of
 the past century.</p>
            <fig id="image446a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>WAVE SHAPES</p>

               <p>Wave-motions are often complex. The above illustration
   shows some fairly complicated wave shapes. All such wave-motions can be
   produced by superposing a number of simple wave forms.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image446a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>WAVE SHAPES</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image446b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE POWER OF A MAGNET</p>

               <p>The illustration is that of a "Phœnix"
   electric magnet lifting scrap from railway trucks. The magnet is 52 inches
   in diameter and lifts a weight of 26 tons. The same type of magnet, 62
   inches in diameter, lifts a weight of 40 tons.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image446b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE POWER OF A MAGNET</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image447a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: The Locomotive Publishing Co., Ltd.</i>
               </p>

               <p>THE SPEED OF LIGHT</p>

               <p>A train travelling at the rate of sixty miles per hour
   would take rather more than seventeen and a quarter days to go round the
   earth at the equator, i.e. a distance of 25,000 miles. Light, which travels
   at the rate of 186,000 miles per second, would take between one-seventh and
   one-eighth of a second to go the same distance.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image447a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SPEED OF LIGHT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image447b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>ROTATING DISC OF SIR ISAAC NEWTON FOR MIXING COLOURS</p>

               <p>The Spectroscope sorts out the above seven colours from
   sunlight (which is compounded of these seven colours). If painted in proper
   proportions on a wheel, as shown in the coloured illustration, and the
   wheel turned rapidly on a pivot through its centre, only a dull white will
   be perceived. If one colour be omitted, the result will be one
   colour—the result of the union of the remaining six.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image447b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>ROTATING DISC OF SIR ISAAC NEWTON FOR MIXING COLOURS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>It is not possible to enter deeply into this subject here. It is
 sufficient if we briefly outline its salient aspects. Energy is recognised in
 two forms, kinetic and potential. The form of energy which is most apparent
 to us is the <i>energy of motion</i>; for example, a rolling stone, running
 water, a falling body, and so on. We call the energy of motion <i>kinetic
 energy</i>. Potential energy is the energy a body has in virtue of its
 position—it is its capacity, in other words, to acquire kinetic energy,
 as in the case of a stone resting on the edge of a cliff.</p>
            <p>Energy may assume different forms; one kind of energy may be converted
 directly or indirectly into some other form. The energy of burning coal, for
 example, is converted into heat, and from heat energy we have mechanical
 energy, such as that manifested by the steam-engine. In this way we can
 transfer energy from one body to another. There is the energy of the great
 waterfalls of Niagara, for instance, which are used to supply the energy of
 huge electric power stations.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e9195">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">What Heat is</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>An important fact about energy is, that all energy <i>tends to take the
 form of heat energy</i>. The impact of a falling stone generates heat; a
 waterfall is hotter at the bottom than at the top—the falling particles
 of water, on striking the ground, generate heat; and most chemical changes
 are attended by heat changes. Energy may remain latent indefinitely in a lump
 of wood, but in combustion it is liberated, and we have heat as a result. The
 atom of radium or of any other radio-active substance, as it disintegrates,
 generates heat. "Every hour radium generates sufficient heat to raise
 the temperature of its own weight of water, from the freezing point to the
 boiling point." And what is heat? <i>Heat is molecular motion.</i> The
 molecules of every substance, as<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 284]</ph> we have seen on a previous page, are in a
 state of continual motion, and the more vigorous the motion the hotter the
 body. As wood or coal burns, the invisible molecules of these substances are
 violently agitated, and give rise to ether waves which our senses interpret
 as light and heat. In this constant movement of the molecules, then, we have
 a manifestation of the energy of motion and of heat.</p>
            <p>That energy which disappears in one form reappears in another has been
 found to be universally true. It was Joule who, by churning water, first
 showed that a measurable quantity of mechanical energy could be transformed
 into a measurable quantity of heat energy. By causing an apparatus to stir
 water vigorously, that apparatus being driven by falling weights or a
 rotating flywheel or by any other mechanical means, the water became heated.
 A certain amount of mechanical energy had been used up and a certain amount
 of heat had appeared. The relation between these two things was found to be
 invariable. Every physical change in nature involves a transformation of
 energy, but the total quantity of energy in the universe remains unaltered.
 This is the great doctrine of the Conservation of Energy.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 13</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e9213">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Substitutes for Coal</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Consider the source of nearly all the energy which is used in modern
 civilisation—coal. The great forests of the Carboniferous epoch now
 exists as beds of coal. By the burning of coal—a chemical
 transformation—the heat energy is produced on which at present our
 whole civilisation depends. Whence is the energy locked up in the coal
 derived? From the sun. For millions of years the energy of the sun's rays
 had gone to form the vast vegetation of the Carboniferous era and had been
 transformed, by various subtle processes, into the potential energy that
 slumbers in those immense fossilized forests.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 285]</ph>
            </p>
            <p>The exhaustion of our coal deposits would mean, so far as our knowledge
 extends at present, the end of the world's civilisation. There are other
 known sources of energy, it is true. There is the energy of falling water;
 the great falls of Niagara are used to supply the energy of huge electric
 power stations. Perhaps, also, something could be done to utilise the energy
 of the tides—another instance of the energy of moving water. And
 attempts have been made to utilise directly the energy of the sun's rays.
 But all these sources of energy are small compared with the energy of coal. A
 suggestion was made at a recent British Association meeting that deep borings
 might be sunk in order to utilise the internal heat of the earth, but this is
 not, perhaps, a very practical proposal. By far the most effective
 substitutes for coal would be found in the interior energy of the atom, a
 source of energy which, as we have seen, is practically illimitable. If the
 immense electrical energy in the interior of the atom can ever be liberated
 and controlled, then our steadily decreasing coal supply will no longer be
 the bugbear it now is to all thoughtful men.</p>
            <p>The stored-up energy of the great coal-fields can be used up, but we
 cannot replace it or create fresh supplies. As we have seen, energy cannot be
 destroyed, but it can become <i>unavailable</i>. Let us consider what this
 important fact means.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 14</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e9230">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Dissipation of Energy</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Energy may become dissipated. Where does it go? since if it is
 indestructible it must still exist. It is easier to ask the question than to
 give a final answer, and it is not possible in this <ph outputclass="smcap">Outline</ph>, where an advanced knowledge of physics is not assumed
 on the part of the reader, to go fully into the somewhat difficult theories
 put forward by physicists and chemists. We may raise the temperature, say, of
 iron, until it is white-hot. If we stop the process the temperature of the
 iron will gradually<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 286]</ph> settle down to the temperature of surrounding bodies. As it
 does so, where does its previous energy go? In some measure it may pass to
 other bodies in contact with the piece of iron, but ultimately the heat
 becomes radiated away in space where we cannot follow it. It has been added
 to the vast reservoir of <i>unavailable</i> heat energy of uniform
 temperature. It is sufficient here to say that if all bodies had a uniform
 temperature we should experience no such thing as heat, because heat only
 travels from one body to another, having the effect of cooling the one and
 warming the other. In time the two bodies acquire the same temperature. The
 sum-total of the heat in any body is measured in terms of the kinetic energy
 of its moving molecules.</p>
            <p>There must come a time, so far as we can see at present, when, even if all
 the heat energy of the universe is not radiated away into empty infinite
 space, yet a uniform temperature will prevail. If one body is hotter than
 another it radiates heat to that body until both are at the same temperature.
 Each body may still possess a considerable quantity of heat energy, which it
 has absorbed, but that energy, so far as reactions between those two bodies
 are concerned, <i>is now unavailable</i>. The same principle applies whatever
 number of bodies we consider. Before heat energy can be utilised we must have
 bodies with different temperature. If the whole universe were at some uniform
 temperature, then, although it might possess an enormous amount of heat
 energy, this energy would be unavailable.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e9249">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">What a Uniform Temperature would mean</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>And what does this imply? It implies a great deal: for if all the energy
 in the world became unavailable, the universe, as it now is, would cease to
 be. It is possible that, by the constant interchange of heat radiations, the
 whole universe is tending to some uniform temperature, in which case,
 although all molecular motion would not have ceased, it would have become
 unavailable. In this sense it may be said that the universe is running
 down.</p>
            <fig id="image452"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>NIAGARA FALLS</p>

               <p>The energy of this falling water is prodigious. It is used
   to generate thousands of horse-power in great electrical installations. The
   power is used to drive electric trams in cities 150 to 250 miles away.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image452_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>NIAGARA FALLS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image453a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Stephen Cribb.</i>
               </p>

               <p>TRANSFORMATION OF ENERGY</p>

               <p>An illustration of Energy. The chemical energy brought into
   existence by firing the explosive manifesting itself as mechanical energy,
   sufficient to impart violent motion to tons of water.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image453a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>TRANSFORMATION OF ENERGY</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image453b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Underwood &amp; Underwood.</i>
               </p>

               <p>"BOILING" A KETTLE ON ICE</p>

               <p>When a kettle containing liquid air is placed on ice it
   "boils" because the ice is intensely hot <i>when compared with
   the very low temperature of the liquid air</i>.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image453b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>'BOILING' A KETTLE ON ICE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 287]</ph>
            </p>
            <p>If all the molecules of a substance were brought to a standstill, that
 substance would be at the absolute zero of temperature. There could be
 nothing colder. The temperature at which all molecular motions would cease is
 known: it is -273° C. No body could possibly attain a lower temperature than
 this: a lower temperature could not exist. Unless there exists in nature some
 process, of which we know nothing at present, whereby energy is renewed, our
 solar system must one day sink to this absolute zero of temperature. The sun,
 the earth, and every other body in the universe is steadily radiating heat,
 and this radiation cannot go on for ever, because heat continually tends to
 diffuse and to equalise temperatures.</p>
            <p>But we can see, theoretically, that there is a way of evading this law. If
 the chaotic molecular motions which constitute heat could be
 <i>regulated</i>, then the heat energy of a body could be utilised directly.
 Some authorities think that some of the processes which go on in the living
 body do not involve any waste energy, that the chemical energy of food is
 transformed directly into work without any of it being dissipated as useless
 heat energy. It may be, therefore, that man will finally discover some way of
 escape from the natural law that, while energy cannot be destroyed, it has a
 tendency to become unavailable.</p>
            <p>The primary reservoir of energy is the atom; it is the energy of the atom,
 the atom of elements in the sun, the stars, the earth, from which nature
 draws for all her supply of energy. Shall we ever discover how we can
 replenish the dwindling resources of energy, or find out how we can call into
 being the at present unavailable energy which is stored up in uniform
 temperature?</p>
            <lq>
               <p>It looks as if our successors would witness an interesting race, between
  the progress of science on the one hand and the depletion of natural
  resources upon the other. The natural rate of flow of energy from its
  primary atomic reservoirs to the sea of waste heat energy of uniform
  temperature, allows life to proceed at a complete pace sternly<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 288]</ph> regulated by
  the inexorable laws of supply and demand, which the biologists have
  recognised in their field as the struggle for existence.<xref href="#unknown/Footnote_5_5" type="fn"><!--[5]--></xref>
               </p>
            </lq>
            <p outputclass="fn-holder">
               <fn id="Footnote_5_5"> 
                  <i>Matter and Energy</i>,
  by Professor Soddy.</fn>
            </p>
            <p>It is certain that energy is an actual entity just as much as matter, and
 that it cannot be created or destroyed. Matter and ether are receptacles or
 vehicles of energy. As we have said, what these entities really are in
 themselves we do not know. It may be that all forms of energy are in some
 fundamental way aspects of the same primary entity which constitutes matter:
 how all matter is constituted of particles of electricity we have already
 seen. The question to which we await an answer is: What is electricity?</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 15</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e9354">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">MATTER, ETHER, AND EINSTEIN</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>The supreme synthesis, the crown of all this progressive conquest of
 nature, would be to discover that the particles of positive and negative
 electricity, which make up the atoms of matter, are points or centres of
 disturbances of some kind in a universal ether, and that all our
 "energies" (light, magnetism, gravitation, etc.) are waves or
 strains of some kind set up in the ether by these clusters of electrons.</p>
         <p>It is a fascinating, tantalising dream. Larmor suggested in 1900 that the
 electron is a tiny whirlpool, or "vortex," in ether; and, as such a
 vortex may turn in either of two opposite ways, we seem to see a possibility
 of explaining positive and negative electricity. But the difficulties have
 proved very serious, and the nature of the electron is unknown. A recent view
 is that it is "a ring of negative electricity rotating about its axis at
 a high speed," though that does not carry us very far. The unit of
 positive electricity is even less known. We must be content to
 know<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 289]</ph> the general lines on which thought is moving toward the final
 unification.</p>
         <p>We say "unification," but it would be a grave error to think
 that ether is the only possible basis for such unity, or to make it an
 essential part of one's philosophy of the universe. Ether was never more
 than an imagined entity to which we ascribed the most extraordinary
 properties, and which seemed then to promise considerable aid. It was
 conceived as an elastic solid of very great density, stretching from end to
 end of the universe, transmitting waves from star to star at the rate of
 186,000 miles a second; yet it was believed that the most solid matter passed
 through it as if it did not exist.</p>
         <p>Some years ago a delicate experiment was tried for the purpose of
 detecting the ether. Since the earth, in travelling round the sun, must move
 through the ether if the ether exists, there ought to be a stream of ether
 flowing through every laboratory; just as the motion of a ship through a
 still atmosphere will make "a wind." In 1887 Michelson and Morley
 tried to detect this. Theoretically, a ray of light in the direction of the
 stream ought to travel at a different rate from a ray of light against the
 stream or across it. They found no difference, and scores of other
 experiments have failed. This does not prove that there is no ether, as there
 is reason to suppose that our instruments would appear to shrink in precisely
 the same proportion as the alteration of the light; but the fact remains that
 we have no proof of the existence of ether. J. H. Jeans says that
 "nature acts as if no such thing existed." Even the phenomena of
 light and magnetism, he says, do not imply ether; and he thinks that the
 hypothesis may be abandoned. The primary reason, of course, for giving up the
 notion of the ether is that, as Einstein has shown, there is no way of
 detecting its existence. If there is an ether, then, since the earth is
 moving through it, there should be some way of detecting this motion. The
 experiment has been tried, as we have said, but, although the method used was
 very sensitive, no motion was<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 290]</ph> discovered. It is Einstein who, by
 revolutionising our conceptions of space and time, showed that no such motion
 ever could be discovered, whatever means were employed, and that the usual
 notion of the ether must be abandoned. We shall explain this theory more
 fully in a later section.</p>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e9373">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">INFLUENCE OF THE TIDES: ORIGIN OF THE MOON: THE EARTH SLOWING DOWN</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 16</p>
         <p>Until comparatively recent times, until, in fact, the full dawn of modern
 science, the tides ranked amongst the greatest of nature's mysteries.
 And, indeed, what agency could be invoked to explain this mysteriously
 regular flux and reflux of the waters of the ocean? It is not surprising that
 that steady, rhythmical rise and fall suggested to some imaginative minds the
 breathing of a mighty animal. And even when man first became aware of the
 fact that this regular movement was somehow associated with the moon, was he
 much nearer an explanation? What bond could exist between the movements of
 that distant world and the diurnal variation of the waters of the earth? It
 is reported that an ancient astronomer, despairing of ever resolving the
 mystery, drowned himself in the sea.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e9379">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Earth Pulled by the Moon</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>But it was part of the merit of Newton's mighty theory of gravitation
 that it furnished an explanation even of this age-old mystery. We can see, in
 broad outlines at any rate, that the theory of universal attraction can be
 applied to this case. For the moon, Newton taught us, pulls every particle of
 matter throughout the earth. If we imagine that part of the earth's
 surface which comprises the Pacific Ocean, for instance, to be turned towards
 the moon, we see that the moon's pull, <i>acting on the loose and mobile
 water</i>, would tend to heap it up into a sort<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 291]</ph> of mound. The whole earth is
 pulled by the moon, but the water is more free to obey this pull than is the
 solid earth, although small tides are also caused in the earth's solid
 crust. It can be shown also that a corresponding hump would tend to be
 produced on the other side of the earth, owing, in this case, to the tendency
 of the water, being more loosely connected, to lag behind the solid earth. If
 the earth's surface were entirely fluid the rotation of the earth would
 give the impression that these two humps were continually travelling round
 the world, once every day. At any given part of the earth's surface,
 therefore, there would be two humps daily, i.e. two periods of high water.
 Such is the simplest possible outline of the gravitational theory of the
 tides.</p>
            <fig id="image458a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE CAUSE OF TIDES</p>

               <p>The tides of the sea are due to the pull of the moon, and,
   in lesser degree, of the sun. The whole earth is pulled by the moon, but
   the loose and mobile water is more free to obey this pull than is the solid
   earth, although small tides are also caused in the earth's solid crust.
   The effect which the tides have on slowing down the rotation of the earth
   is explained in the text.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image458a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE CAUSE OF TIDES</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image458b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: G. Brocklehurst.</i>
               </p>

               <p>THE AEGIR ON THE TRENT</p>

               <p>An exceptionally smooth formation due to perfect weather
   conditions. The wall-like formation of these tidal waves (see next page
   also) will be noticed. The reason for this is that the downward current in
   the river heads the sea-water back, and thus helps to exaggerate the
   advancing slope of the wave. The exceptional spring tides are caused by the
   combined operation of the moon and the sun, as is explained in the
   text.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image458b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE AEGIR ON THE TRENT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image459"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: G. Brocklehurst.</i>
               </p>

               <p>A BIG SPRING TIDE, THE AEGIR ON THE TRENT</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image459_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A BIG SPRING TIDE, THE AEGIR ON THE TRENT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>The actually observed phenomena are vastly more complicated, and the
 complete theory bears very little resemblance to the simple form we have just
 outlined. Everyone who lives in the neighbourhood of a port knows, for
 instance, that high water seldom coincides with the time when the moon
 crosses the meridian. It may be several hours early or late. High water at
 London Bridge, for instance, occurs about one and a half hours after the moon
 has passed the meridian, while at Dublin high water occurs about one and a
 half hours before the moon crosses the meridian. The actually observed
 phenomena, then, are far from simple; they have, nevertheless, been very
 completely worked out, and the times of high water for every port in the
 world can now be prophesied for a considerable time ahead.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e9445">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Action of Sun and Moon</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It would be beyond our scope to attempt to explain the complete theory,
 but we may mention one obvious factor which must be taken into account. Since
 the moon, by its gravitational attraction, produces tides, we should expect
 that the sun, whose gravitational attraction is so much stronger, should also
 produce tides and, we would suppose at first sight, more powerful tides than
 the moon. But while it is true that the sun produces tides, it is<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 292]</ph> not true that
 they are more powerful than those produced by the moon. The sun's
 tide-producing power is, as a matter of fact, less than half that of the
 moon. The reason of this is that <i>distance</i> plays an enormous rôle in
 the production of tides. The mass of the sun is 26,000,000 times that of the
 moon; on the other hand it is 386 times as far off as the moon. This greater
 distance more than counterbalances its greater mass, and the result, as we
 have said, is that the moon is more than twice as powerful. Sometimes the sun
 and moon act together, and we have what are called spring tides; sometimes
 they act against one another, and we have neap tides. These effects are
 further complicated by a number of other factors, and the tides, at various
 places, vary enormously. Thus at St. Helena the sea rises and falls about
 three feet, whereas in the Bay of Fundy it rises and falls more than fifty
 feet. But here, again, the reasons are complicated.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 17</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e9459">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Origin of the Moon</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>But there is another aspect of the tides which is of vastly greater
 interest and importance than the theory we have just been discussing. In the
 hands of Sir George H. Darwin, the son of Charles Darwin, the tides had been
 made to throw light on the evolution of our solar system. In particular, they
 have illustrated the origin and development of the system formed by our earth
 and moon. It is quite certain that, long ages ago, the earth was rotating
 immensely faster than it is now, and that the moon was so near as to be
 actually in contact with the earth. In that remote age the moon was just on
 the point of separating from the earth, of being thrown off by the earth.
 Earth and moon were once one body, but the high rate of rotation caused this
 body to split up into two pieces; one piece became the earth we now know, and
 the other became the moon. Such is the conclusion to which we are led by an
 examination of the tides. In the first place let us consider the energy
 produced by the tides. We see<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 293]</ph> evidences of this energy all round the
 word's coastlines. Estuaries are scooped out, great rocks are gradually
 reduced to rubble, innumerable tons of matter are continually being set in
 movement. Whence is this energy derived? Energy, like matter, cannot be
 created from nothing; what, then, is the source which makes this colossal
 expenditure possible.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e9467">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Earth Slowing down</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The answer is simple, but startling. <i>The source of tidal energy is the
 rotation of the earth.</i> The massive bulk of the earth, turning every
 twenty-four hours on its axis, is like a gigantic flywheel. In virtue of its
 rotation it possesses an enormous store of energy. But even the heaviest and
 swiftest flywheel, if it is doing work, or even if it is only working against
 the friction of its bearings, cannot dispense energy for ever. It must,
 gradually, slow down. There is no escape from this reasoning. It is the
 rotation of the earth which supplies the energy of the tides, and, as a
 consequence, the tides must be slowing down the earth. The tides act as a
 kind of brake on the earth's rotation. These masses of water, <i>held
 back by the moon</i>, exert a kind of dragging effect on the rotating earth.
 Doubtless this effect, measured by our ordinary standards, is very small; it
 is, however, continuous, and in the course of the millions of years dealt
 with in astronomy, this small but constant effect may produce very
 considerable results.</p>
            <p>But there is another effect which can be shown to be a necessary
 mathematical consequence of tidal action. It is the moon's action on the
 earth which produces the tides, but they also react on the moon. The tides
 are slowing down the earth, and they are also driving the moon farther and
 farther away. This result, strange as it may seem, does not permit of doubt,
 for it is the result of an indubitable dynamical principle, which cannot be
 made clear without a mathematical discussion. Some interesting consequences
 follow.</p>
            <p>Since the earth is slowing down, it follows that it was once<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 294]</ph> rotating
 faster. There was a period, a long time ago, when the day comprised only
 twenty hours. Going farther back still we come to a day of ten hours, until,
 inconceivable ages ago, the earth must have been rotating on its axis in a
 period of from three to four hours.</p>
            <p>At this point let us stop and inquire what was happening to the moon. We
 have seen that at present the moon is getting farther and farther away. It
 follows, therefore, that when the day was shorter the moon was nearer. As we
 go farther back in time we find the moon nearer and nearer to an earth
 rotating faster and faster. When we reach the period we have already
 mentioned, the period when the earth completed a revolution in three or four
 hours, we find that the moon was so near as to be almost grazing the earth.
 This fact is very remarkable. Everybody knows that there is a <i>critical
 velocity</i> for a rotating flywheel, a velocity beyond which the flywheel
 would fly into pieces because the centrifugal force developed is so great as
 to overcome the cohesion of the molecules of the flywheel. We have already
 likened our earth to a flywheel, and we have traced its history back to the
 point where it was rotating with immense velocity. We have also seen that, at
 that moment, the moon was barely separated from the earth. The conclusion is
 irresistible. In an age more remote the earth <i>did</i> fly in pieces, and
 one of those pieces is the moon. Such, in brief outline, is the tidal theory
 of the origin of the earth-moon system.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e9493">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Day Becoming Longer</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>At the beginning, when the moon split off from the earth, it obviously
 must have shared the earth's rotation. It flew round the earth in the
 same time that the earth rotated, that is to say, the month and the day were
 of equal length. As the moon began to get farther from the earth, the month,
 because the moon took longer to rotate round the earth, began to get
 correspondingly longer. The day also became longer, because the earth was
 slowing<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 295]</ph> down, taking longer to rotate on its axis, but the month
 increased at a greater rate than the day. Presently the month became equal to
 two days, then to three, and so on. It has been calculated that this process
 went on until there were twenty-nine days in the month. After that the number
 of days in the month began to decrease until it reached its present value or
 magnitude, and will continue to decrease until once more the month and the
 day are equal. In that age the earth will be rotating very slowly. The
 braking action of the tides will cause the earth always to keep the same face
 to the moon; it will rotate on its axis in the same time that the moon turns
 round the earth. If nothing but the earth and moon were involved this state
 of affairs would be final. But there is also the effect of the solar tides to
 be considered. The moon makes the day equal to the month, but the sun has a
 tendency, by still further slowing down the earth's rotation on its axis,
 to make the day equal to the year. It would do this, of course, by making the
 earth take as long to turn on its axis as to go round the sun. It cannot
 succeed in this, owing to the action of the moon, but it can succeed in
 making the day rather longer than the month.</p>
            <p>Surprising as it may seem, we already have an illustration of this
 possibility in the satellites of Mars. The Martian day is about one half-hour
 longer than ours, but when the two minute satellites of Mars were discovered
 it was noticed that the inner one of the two revolved round Mars in about
 seven hours forty minutes. In one Martian day, therefore, one of the moons of
 Mars makes more than three complete revolutions round that planet, so that,
 to an inhabitant of Mars, there would be more than three months in a day.</p>
            <!--hr--></body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e9505">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">BIBLIOGRAPHY</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Arrhenius, Svante</ph>, <i>Worlds in the Making</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Clerk-Maxwell, James</ph>, <i>Matter and Motion</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 296]</ph>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Daniell, Alfred</ph>, <i>A Text-Book of
 the Principles of Physics</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Darwin, Sir G. H.</ph>, <i>The Tides</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Holman</ph>, <i>Matter, Energy, Force and Work</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Kapp, Gisbert</ph>, <i>Electricity</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Kelvin, Lord</ph>, <i>Popular Lectures and
 Addresses</i>. Vol. i. <i>Constitution of Matter.</i>
            <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Lockyer, Sir Norman</ph>, <i>Inorganic Evolution</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Lodge, Sir Oliver</ph>, <i>Electrons</i> and <i>The
 Ether of Space</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Perrin, Jean</ph>, <i>Brownian Movement and Molecular
 Reality</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Soddy, Frederick</ph>, <i>Matter and Energy</i> and
 <i>The Interpretation of Radium</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Thompson, Silvanus P.</ph>, <i>Light, Visible and
 Invisible</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Thomson, Sir J. J.</ph>, <i>The Corpuscular Theory of
 Matter</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
         </p>
         
      </body>
   </topic>
</topic>