<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="chapter_01">
   <title>
      <ph outputclass="title-line">INTRODUCTION</ph> 
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>There is abundant evidence of a widened and deepened interest in modern
 science. How could it be otherwise when we think of the magnitude and the
 eventfulness of recent advances?</p>
      <p>But the interest of the general public would be even greater than it is if
 the makers of new knowledge were more willing to expound their discoveries in
 ways that could be "understanded of the people." No one objects
 very much to technicalities in a game or on board a yacht, and they are
 clearly necessary for terse and precise scientific description. It is
 certain, however, that they can be reduced to a minimum without sacrificing
 accuracy, when the object in view is to explain "the gist of the
 matter." So this <ph outputclass="smcap">Outline of Science</ph> is meant
 for the general reader, who lacks both time and opportunity for special
 study, and yet would take an intelligent interest in the progress of science
 which is making the world always new.</p>
      <p>The story of the triumphs of modern science is one of which Man may well
 be proud. Science reads the secret of the distant star and anatomises the
 atom; foretells the date of the comet's return and predicts the kinds of
 chickens that will hatch from a dozen eggs; discovers the laws of the wind
 that bloweth where it listeth and reduces to order the disorder of disease.
 Science is always setting forth on Columbus voyages, discovering new worlds
 and conquering them by understanding. For Knowledge means Foresight and
 Foresight means Power.</p>
      <p>The idea of Evolution has influenced all the sciences, forcing us to think
 of <i>everything</i> as with a history behind it, for we have travelled far
 since Darwin's day. The solar system, the earth, the mountain ranges, and
 the great deeps, the rocks and<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 4]</ph> crystals, the plants and animals, man himself and
 his social institutions—all must be seen as the outcome of a long
 process of Becoming. There are some eighty-odd chemical elements on the earth
 to-day, and it is now much more than a suggestion that these are the outcome
 of an inorganic evolution, element giving rise to element, going back and
 back to some primeval stuff, from which they were all originally derived,
 infinitely long ago. No idea has been so powerful a tool in the fashioning of
 New Knowledge as this simple but profound idea of Evolution, that the present
 is the child of the past and the parent of the future. And with the picture
 of a continuity of evolution from nebula to social systems comes a promise of
 an increasing control—a promise that Man will become not only a more
 accurate student, but a more complete master of his world.</p>
      <p>It is characteristic of modern science that the whole world is seen to be
 more vital than before. Everywhere there has been a passage from the static
 to the dynamic. Thus the new revelations of the constitution of matter, which
 we owe to the discoveries of men like Professor Sir J. J. Thomson, Professor
 Sir Ernest Rutherford, and Professor Frederick Soddy, have shown the very
 dust to have a complexity and an activity heretofore unimagined. Such phrases
 as "dead" matter and "inert" matter have gone by the
 board.</p>
      <p>The new theory of the atom amounts almost to a new conception of the
 universe. It bids fair to reveal to us many of nature's hidden secrets.
 The atom is no longer the indivisible particle of matter it was once
 understood to be. We know now that there is an atom within the
 atom—that what we thought was elementary can be dissociated and broken
 up. The present-day theories of the atom and the constitution of matter are
 the outcome of the comparatively recent discovery of such things as radium,
 the X-rays, and the wonderful revelations of such instruments as the
 spectroscope and other highly perfected scientific instruments.</p>
      <p>The advent of the electron theory has thrown a flood of light on what
 before was hidden or only dimly guessed at. It has given us a new conception
 of the framework of the universe. We are beginning to know and realise of
 what matter is made<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 5]</ph> and what electric phenomena mean. We can glimpse the vast
 stores of energy locked up in matter. The new knowledge has much to tell us
 about the origin and phenomena, not only of our own planet, but other
 planets, of the stars, and the sun. New light is thrown on the source of the
 sun's heat; we can make more than guesses as to its probable age. The
 great question to-day is: is there <i>one</i> primordial substance from which
 all the varying forms of matter have been evolved?</p>
      <p>But the discovery of electrons is only one of the revolutionary changes
 which give modern science an entrancing interest.</p>
      <p>As in chemistry and physics, so in the science of living creatures there
 have been recent advances that have changed the whole prospect. A good
 instance is afforded by the discovery of the "hormones," or
 chemical messengers, which are produced by ductless glands, such as the
 thyroid, the supra-renal, and the pituitary, and are distributed throughout
 the body by the blood. The work of physiologists like Professor Starling and
 Professor Bayliss has shown that these chemical messengers regulate what may
 be called the "pace" of the body, and bring about that regulated
 harmony and smoothness of working which we know as health. It is not too much
 to say that the discovery of hormones has changed the whole of physiology.
 Our knowledge of the human body far surpasses that of the past
 generation.</p>
      <p>The persistent patience of microscopists and technical improvements like
 the "ultramicroscope" have greatly increased our knowledge of the
 invisible world of life. To the bacteria of a past generation have been added
 a multitude of microscopic <i>animal</i> microbes, such as that which causes
 Sleeping Sickness. The life-histories and the weird ways of many important
 parasites have been unravelled; and here again knowledge means mastery. To a
 degree which has almost surpassed expectations there has been a revelation of
 the intricacy of the stones and mortar of the house of life, and the
 microscopic study of germ-cells has wonderfully supplemented the epoch-making
 experimental study of heredity which began with Mendel. It goes without
 saying that no one can call himself educated who does not understand the
 central and simple ideas of Mendelism and other new departures in
 biology.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 6]</ph>
      </p>
      <p>The procession of life through the ages and the factors in the sublime
 movement; the peopling of the earth by plants and animals and the linking of
 life to life in subtle inter-relations, such as those between flowers and
 their insect-visitors; the life-histories of individual types and the
 extraordinary results of the new inquiry called "experimental
 embryology"—these also are among the subjects with which this
 <ph outputclass="smcap">Outline</ph> will deal.</p>
      <p>The behaviour of animals is another fascinating study, leading to a
 provisional picture of the dawn of mind. Indeed, no branch of science
 surpasses in interest that which deals with the ways and habits—the
 truly wonderful devices, adaptations, and instincts—of insects, birds,
 and mammals. We no longer deny a degree of intelligence to some members of
 the animal world—even the line between intelligence and reason is
 sometimes difficult to find.</p>
      <p>Fresh contacts between physiology and the study of man's mental life;
 precise studies of the ways of children and wild peoples; and new methods
 like those of the psycho-analyst must also receive the attention they
 deserve, for they are giving us a "New Psychology" and the claims
 of psychical research must also be recognised by the open-minded.</p>
      <p>The general aim of the <ph outputclass="smcap">Outline</ph> is to give the
 reader a clear and concise view of the essentials of present-day science, so
 that he may follow with intelligence the modern advance and share
 appreciatively in man's continued conquest of his kingdom.</p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="smcap">J. Arthur Thomson.</ph>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 7]</ph>
      </p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 8]</ph>
      </p>
      <p> </p>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 9]</ph>
      </p>
      <!--hr--></body>
</topic>