<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="chapter_02">
   <title>
      <ph outputclass="title-line">I</ph> 
      <ph outputclass="title-line">THE ROMANCE OF THE HEAVENS</ph> 
   </title>
   <body><!--hr--></body>
   <topic id="d1e89">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE SCALE OF THE UNIVERSE—THE SOLAR SYSTEM</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 1</p>
         <p>The story of the triumphs of modern science naturally opens with
 Astronomy. The picture of the Universe which the astronomer offers to us is
 imperfect; the lines he traces are often faint and uncertain. There are many
 problems which have been solved, there are just as many about which there is
 doubt, and notwithstanding our great increase in knowledge, there remain just
 as many which are entirely unsolved.</p>
         <lq>
            <p>The problem of the structure and duration of the universe [said the great
  astronomer Simon Newcomb] is the most far-reaching with which the mind has
  to deal. Its solution may be regarded as the ultimate object of stellar
  astronomy, the possibility of reaching which has occupied the minds of
  thinkers since the beginning of civilisation. Before our time the problem
  could be considered only from the imaginative or the speculative point of
  view. Although we can to-day attack it to a limited extent by scientific
  methods, it must be admitted that we have scarcely taken more than the first
  step toward the actual solution.... What is the duration of the universe in
  time? Is it fitted to last for ever in its present form, or does it contain
  within itself the seeds of dissolution? Must it, in the course of time, in
  we know not how many millions of ages, be transformed into something very
  different from what it now is? This question is intimately associated with
  the question whether the stars form<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 10]</ph> a system. If they do, we may suppose that
  system to be permanent in its general features; if not, we must look further
  for our conclusions.</p>
         </lq>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e104">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Heavenly Bodies</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The heavenly bodies fall into two very distinct classes so far as their
 relation to our Earth is concerned; the one class, a very small one,
 comprises a sort of colony of which the Earth is a member. These bodies are
 called <i>planets</i>, or wanderers. There are eight of them, including the
 Earth, and they all circle round the sun. Their names, in the order of their
 distance from the sun, are Mercury, Venus, Earth, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn,
 Uranus, Neptune, and of these Mercury, the nearest to the sun, is rarely seen
 by the naked eye. Uranus is practically invisible, and Neptune quite so.
 These eight planets, together with the sun, constitute, as we have said, a
 sort of little colony; this colony is called the Solar System.</p>
            <p>The second class of heavenly bodies are those which lie <i>outside</i> the
 solar system. Every one of those glittering points we see on a starlit night
 is at an immensely greater distance from us than is any member of the Solar
 System. Yet the members of this little colony of ours, judged by terrestrial
 standards, are at enormous distances from one another. If a shell were shot
 in a straight line from one side of Neptune's orbit to the other it would
 take five hundred years to complete its journey. Yet this distance, the
 greatest in the Solar System as now known (excepting the far swing of some of
 the comets), is insignificant compared to the distances of the stars. One of
 the nearest stars to the earth that we know of is Alpha Centauri, estimated
 to be some twenty-five million millions of miles away. Sirius, the brightest
 star in the firmament, is double this distance from the earth.</p>
            <p>We must imagine the colony of planets to which we belong as a compact
 little family swimming in an immense void. At distances which would take our
 shell, not hundreds, but millions<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 11]</ph> of years to traverse, we reach the
 stars—or rather, a star, for the distances between stars are as great
 as the distance between the nearest of them and our Sun. The Earth, the
 planet on which we live, is a mighty globe bounded by a crust of rock many
 miles in thickness; the great volumes of water which we call our oceans lie
 in the deeper hollows of the crust. Above the surface an ocean of invisible
 gas, the atmosphere, rises to a height of about three hundred miles, getting
 thinner and thinner as it ascends.</p>
            <fig id="image032a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>LAPLACE</p>

               <p>One of the greatest mathematical astronomers of all time
   and the originator of the nebular theory.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image032a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>LAPLACE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image032b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Royal Astronomical Society.</i>
               </p>

               <p>PROFESSOR J. C. ADAMS</p>

               <p>who, anticipating the great French mathematician, Le
   Verrier, discovered the planet Neptune by calculations based on the
   irregularities of the orbit of Uranus. One of the most dramatic discoveries
   in the history of Science.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image032b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROFESSOR J. C. ADAMS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image032c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Elliott &amp; Fry, Ltd.</i>
               </p>

               <p>PROFESSOR EDDINGTON</p>

               <p>Professor of Astronomy at Cambridge. The most famous of the English
   disciples of Einstein.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image032c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>PROFESSOR EDDINGTON</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image033a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FIG. 1.—DIAGRAMS OF THE SOLAR SYSTEM</p>

               <p>THE COMPARATIVE DISTANCES OF THE PLANETS</p>

               <p>(Drawn approximately to scale)</p>

               <p>The isolation of the Solar System is very great. On the
   above scale the <i>nearest</i> star (at a distance of 25 trillions of
   miles) would be over <i>one half mile</i> away. The hours, days, and years
   are the measures of time as we use them; that is: Jupiter's
   "Day" (one rotation of the planet) is made in ten of <i>our
   hours</i>; Mercury's "Year" (one revolution of the planet
   around the Sun) is eighty-eight of <i>our days</i>. Mercury's
   "Day" and "Year" are the same. This planet turns always
   the same side to the Sun.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image033a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>DIAGRAMS OF THE SOLAR SYSTEM</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image033b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE COMPARATIVE SIZES OF THE SUN AND THE PLANETS</p>

               <p>(Drawn approximately to scale)</p>

               <p>On this scale the Sun would be 17½ inches in diameter; it
   is far greater than all the planets put together. Jupiter, in turn, is
   greater than all the other planets put together.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image033b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE COMPARATIVE SIZES OF THE SUN AND THE PLANETS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>Except when the winds rise to a high speed, we seem to live in a very
 tranquil world. At night, when the glare of the sun passes out of our
 atmosphere, the stars and planets seem to move across the heavens with a
 stately and solemn slowness. It was one of the first discoveries of modern
 astronomy that this movement is only apparent. The apparent creeping of the
 stars across the heavens at night is accounted for by the fact that the earth
 turns upon its axis once in every twenty-four hours. When we remember the
 size of the earth we see that this implies a prodigious speed.</p>
            <p>In addition to this the earth revolves round the sun at a speed of more
 than a thousand miles a minute. Its path round the sun, year in year out,
 measures about 580,000,000 miles. The earth is held closely to this path by
 the gravitational pull of the sun, which has a mass 333,432 times that of the
 earth. If at any moment the sun ceased to exert this pull the earth would
 instantly fly off into space straight in the direction in which it was moving
 at the time, that is to say, at a tangent. This tendency to fly off at a
 tangent is continuous. It is the balance between it and the sun's pull
 which keeps the earth to her almost circular orbit. In the same way the seven
 other planets are held to their orbits.</p>
            <p>Circling round the earth, in the same way as the earth circles round the
 sun, is our moon. Sometimes the moon passes directly between us and the sun,
 and cuts off the light from us.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 12]</ph> We then have a total or partial eclipse of the
 sun. At other times the earth passes directly between the sun and the moon,
 and causes an eclipse of the moon. The great ball of the earth naturally
 trails a mighty shadow across space, and the moon is "eclipsed"
 when it passes into this.</p>
            <p>The other seven planets, five of which have moons of their own, circle
 round the sun as the earth does. The sun's mass is immensely larger than
 that of all the planets put together, and all of them would be drawn into it
 and perish if they did not travel rapidly round it in gigantic orbits. So the
 eight planets, spinning round on their axes, follow their fixed paths round
 the sun. The planets are secondary bodies, but they are most important,
 because they are the only globes in which there can be life, as we know
 life.</p>
            <p>If we could be transported in some magical way to an immense distance in
 space above the sun, we should see our Solar System as it is drawn in the
 accompanying diagram (Fig. 1), except that the planets would be mere specks,
 faintly visible in the light which they receive from the sun. (This diagram
 is drawn approximately to scale.) If we moved still farther away, trillions
 of miles away, the planets would fade entirely out of view, and the sun would
 shrink into a point of fire, a star. And here you begin to realize the nature
 of the universe. <i>The sun is a star. The stars are suns.</i> Our sun looks
 big simply because of its comparative nearness to us. The universe is a
 stupendous collection of millions of stars or suns, many of which may have
 planetary families like ours.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 2</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e251">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Scale of the Universe</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>How many stars are there? A glance at a photograph of star-clouds will
 tell at once that it is quite impossible to count them. The fine photograph
 reproduced in Figure 2 represents<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 13]</ph> a very small patch of that pale-white belt, the
 Milky Way, which spans the sky at night. It is true that this is a
 particularly rich area of the Milky Way, but the entire belt of light has
 been resolved in this way into masses or clouds of stars. Astronomers have
 counted the stars in typical districts here and there, and from these partial
 counts we get some idea of the total number of stars. There are estimated to
 be between two and three thousand million stars.</p>
            <p>Yet these stars are separated by inconceivable distances from each other,
 and it is one of the greatest triumphs of modern astronomy to have mastered,
 so far, the scale of the universe. For several centuries astronomers have
 known the relative distances from each other of the sun and the planets. If
 they could discover the actual distance of any one planet from any other,
 they could at once tell all the distances within the Solar System.</p>
            <p>The sun is, on the latest measurements, at an average distance of
 92,830,000 miles from the earth, for as the orbit of the earth is not a true
 circle, this distance varies. This means that in six months from now the
 earth will be right at the opposite side of its path round the sun, or
 185,000,000 miles away from where it is now. Viewed or photographed from two
 positions so wide apart, the nearest stars show a tiny "shift"
 against the background of the most distant stars, and that is enough for the
 mathematician. He can calculate the distance of any star near enough to show
 this "shift." We have found that the nearest star to the earth, a
 recently discovered star, is twenty-five trillion miles away. Only thirty
 stars are known to be within a hundred trillion miles of us.</p>
            <p>This way of measuring does not, however, take us very far away in the
 heavens. There are only a few hundred stars within five hundred trillion
 miles of the earth, and at that distance the "shift" of a star
 against the background (parallax, the astronomer calls it) is so minute that
 figures are very uncertain. At this point the astronomer takes up a new
 method. He learns the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 14]</ph> different types of stars, and then he is able to deduce more
 or less accurately the distance of a star of a known type from its faintness.
 He, of course, has instruments for gauging their light. As a result of twenty
 years work in this field, it is now known that the more distant stars of the
 Milky Way are at least a hundred thousand trillion (100,000,000,000,000,000)
 miles away from the sun.</p>
            <p>Our sun is in a more or less central region of the universe, or a few
 hundred trillion miles from the actual centre. The remainder of the stars,
 which are all outside our Solar System, are spread out, apparently, in an
 enormous disc-like collection, so vast that even a ray of light, which
 travels at the rate of 186,000 miles a second, would take 50,000 years to
 travel from one end of it to the other. This, then is what we call our
 universe.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e272">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Are there other Universes?</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Why do we say "our universe"? Why not <i>the</i> universe? It is
 now believed by many of our most distinguished astronomers that our colossal
 family of stars is only one of many universes. By a universe an astronomer
 means any collection of stars which are close enough to control each
 other's movements by gravitation; and it is clear that there might be
 many universes, in this sense, separated from each other by profound abysses
 of space. Probably there are.</p>
            <p>For a long time we have been familiar with certain strange objects in the
 heavens which are called "spiral nebulæ" (Fig 4). We shall see at a
 later stage what a nebula is, and we shall see that some astronomers regard
 these spiral nebulæ as worlds "in the making." But some of the most
 eminent astronomers believe that they are separate
 universes—"island-universes" they call them—or great
 collections of millions of stars like our universe. There are certain
 peculiarities in the structure of the Milky Way which lead these astronomers
 to think that our universe may be<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 15]</ph> a spiral nebula, and that the other spiral
 nebulæ are "other universes."</p>
            <fig id="image038a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Harvard College Observatory.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 2.—THE MILKY WAY</p>

               <p>Note the cloud-like effect.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image038a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE MILKY WAY</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image038b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FIG. 3—THE MOON ENTERING THE SHADOW CAST BY THE EARTH</p>

               <p>The diagram shows the Moon partially eclipsed.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image038b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE MOON ENTERING THE SHADOW CAST BY THE EARTH</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image039"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>From a photograph taken at the Yerkes Observatory</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 4.—THE GREAT NEBULA IN ANDROMEDA, MESSIER 31</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image039_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE GREAT NEBULA IN ANDROMEDA, MESSIER 31</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>Vast as is the Solar System, then, it is excessively minute in comparison
 with the Stellar System, the universe of the Stars, which is on a scale far
 transcending anything the human mind can apprehend.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e341">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE SOLAR SYSTEM</ph> 
      </title>
      <body/>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e343">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE SUN</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 1</p>
         <p>But now let us turn to the Solar System, and consider the members of our
 own little colony.</p>
         <p>Within the Solar System there are a large number of problems that interest
 us. What is the size, mass, and distance of each of the planets? What
 satellites, like our Moon, do they possess? What are their temperatures? And
 those other, sporadic members of our system, comets and meteors, what are
 they? What are their movements? How do they originate? And the Sun itself,
 what is its composition, what is the source of its heat, how did it
 originate? Is it running down?</p>
         <p>These last questions introduce us to a branch of astronomy which is
 concerned with the physical constitution of the stars, a study which, not so
 very many years ago, may well have appeared inconceivable. But the
 spectroscope enables us to answer even these questions, and the answer opens
 up questions of yet greater interest. We find that the stars can be arranged
 in an order of development—that there are stars at all stages of their
 life-history. The main lines of the evolution of the stellar universe can be
 worked out. In the sun and stars we have furnaces with temperatures
 enormously high; it is in such conditions that substances are resolved into
 their simplest forms, and it is thus we are enabled to obtain a knowledge of
 the most primitive forms of matter. It is in this direction that the
 spectroscope<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 16]</ph> (which we shall refer to immediately) has helped us so much.
 It is to this wonderful instrument that we owe our knowledge of the
 composition of the sun and stars, as we shall see.</p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 17]</ph>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 18]</ph>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 19]</ph>
         </p>
         <lq>
            <p>"That the spectroscope will detect the millionth of a milligram of
  matter, and on that account has discovered new elements, commands our
  admiration; but when we find in addition that it will detect the nature of
  forms of matter trillions of miles away, and moreover, that it will measure
  the velocities with which these forms of matter are moving with an absurdly
  small per cent. of possible error, we can easily acquiesce in the statement
  that it is the greatest instrument ever devised by the brain and hand of
  man."</p>
         </lq>
         <p>Such are some of the questions with which modern astronomy deals. To
 answer them requires the employment of instruments of almost incredible
 refinement and exactitude and also the full resources of mathematical genius.
 Whether astronomy be judged from the point of view of the phenomena studied,
 the vast masses, the immense distances, the æons of time, or whether it be
 judged as a monument of human ingenuity, patience, and the rarest type of
 genius, it is certainly one of the grandest, as it is also one of the oldest,
 of the sciences.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e381">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Solar System</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>In the Solar System we include all those bodies dependent on the sun which
 circulate round it at various distances, deriving their light and heat from
 the sun—the planets and their moons, certain comets and a multitude of
 meteors: in other words, all bodies whose movements in space are determined
 by the gravitational pull of the sun.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e385">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Sun</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Thanks to our wonderful modern instruments and the ingenious methods used
 by astronomers, we have to-day a remarkable knowledge of the sun.</p>
            <p>Look at the figure of the sun in the frontispiece. The picture represents
 an eclipse of the sun; the dark body of the moon has screened the sun's
 shining disc and taken the glare out of our eyes; we see a silvery halo
 surrounding the great orb on every side. It is the sun's atmosphere, or
 "crown" (corona), stretching for millions of miles into space in
 the form of a soft silvery-looking light; probably much of its light is
 sunlight reflected from particles of dust, although the spectroscope shows an
 element in the corona that has not so far been detected anywhere else in the
 universe and which in consequence has been named Coronium.</p>
            <p>We next notice in the illustration that at the base of the halo there are
 red flames peeping out from the edges of the hidden disc. When one remembers
 that the sun is 866,000 miles in diameter, one hardly needs to be told that
 these flames are really gigantic. We shall see what they are presently.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e393">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Regions of the Sun</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The astronomer has divided the sun into definite concentric regions or
 layers. These layers envelop the nucleus or central body of the sun somewhat
 as the atmosphere envelops our earth. It is through these vapour layers that
 the bright white body of the sun is seen. Of the innermost region, the heart
 or nucleus of the sun, we know almost nothing. The central body or nucleus is
 surrounded by a brilliantly luminous envelope or layer of vaporous matter
 which is what we see when we look at the sun and which the astronomer calls
 the photosphere.</p>
            <p>Above—that is, overlying—the photosphere there is a second
 layer of glowing gases, which is known as the reversing layer. This layer is
 cooler than the underlying photosphere; it forms a veil of smoke-like haze
 and is of from 500 to 1,000 miles in thickness.</p>
            <p>A third layer or envelope immediately lying over the last one is the
 region known as the chromosphere. The chromosphere extends from 5,000 to
 10,000 miles in thickness—a "sea" of red tumultuous surging
 fire. Chief among the glowing gases is the vapour of hydrogen. The intense
 white heat of the photosphere beneath shines through this layer, overpowering
 its brilliant redness. From the uppermost portion of the chromosphere great
 fiery tongues of glowing hydrogen and calcium vapour shoot out for many
 thousands of miles, driven outward by some prodigious expulsive force. It is
 these red "prominences" which are such a notable feature in the
 picture of the eclipse of the sun already referred to.</p>
            <p>During the solar eclipse of 1919 one of these red flames rose in less than
 seven hours from a height of 130,000 miles to more than 500,000 miles above
 the sun's surface. This immense column of red-hot gas, four or five times
 the thickness of the earth, was soaring upward at the rate of 60,000 miles an
 hour.</p>
            <p>These flaming jets or prominences shooting out from the chromosphere are
 not to be seen every day by the naked eye; the dazzling light of the sun
 obscures them, gigantic as they are. They can be observed, however, by the
 spectroscope any day, and they are visible to us for a very short time during
 an eclipse of the sun. Some extraordinary outbursts have been witnessed. Thus
 the late Professor Young described one on September 7, 1871, when he had been
 examining a prominence by the spectroscope:</p>
            <lq>
               <p>It had remained unchanged since noon of the previous day—a long,
  low, quiet-looking cloud, not very dense, or brilliant, or in any way
  remarkable except for its size. At 12:30 p.m. the Professor left the
  spectroscope for a short time, and on returning half an hour later to his
  observations, he was astonished to find the gigantic Sun flame shattered to
  pieces. The solar atmosphere was filled with flying debris, and some of
  these portions reached a height of 100,000 miles above the solar surface.
  Moving with a velocity which, even at the distance of 93,000,000 miles, was
  almost perceptible to the eye, these fragments doubled their height in ten
  minutes. On January 30, 1885, another distinguished solar observer, the late
  Professor Tacchini of Rome, observed one of the greatest prominences ever
  seen by man. Its height was no less than 142,000 miles—eighteen times
  the diameter of the earth. Another mighty flame was so vast that supposing
  the eight large planets of the solar system ranged one on top of the other,
  the prominence would still tower above them.<xref href="#unknown/Footnote_1_1" type="fn"><!--[1]--></xref>
               </p>
            </lq>
            <p outputclass="fn-holder">
               <fn id="Footnote_1_1"> 
                  <i>The Romance of
  Astronomy</i>, by H. Macpherson.</fn>
            </p>
            <fig id="image044a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FIG. 5.—DIAGRAM SHOWING THE MAIN LAYERS OF THE SUN</p>

               <p>Compare with frontispiece.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image044a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>DIAGRAM SHOWING THE MAIN LAYERS OF THE SUN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image044b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Royal Observatory, Greenwich.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 6.—SOLAR PROMINENCES SEEN AT TOTAL SOLAR ECLIPSE, May 29,
   1919. TAKEN AT SOBRAL, BRAZIL.</p>

               <p>The small Corona is also visible.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image044b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SOLAR PROMINENCES SEEN AT TOTAL SOLAR ECLIPSE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image045a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FIG. 7.—THE VISIBLE SURFACE OF THE SUN</p>

               <p>A photograph taken at the Mount Wilson Observatory of the
   Carnegie Institution at Washington.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image045a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE VISIBLE SURFACE OF THE SUN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image045b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FIG. 8.—THE SUN</p>

               <p>Photographed in the light of glowing hydrogen, at the Mount
   Wilson Observatory of the Carnegie Institution of Washington: vortex
   phenomena near the spots are especially prominent.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image045b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SUN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>The fourth and uppermost layer or region is that of the corona, of immense
 extent and fading away into the surrounding sky—this we have already
 referred to. The diagram (Fig. 5) shows the dispositions of these various
 layers of the sun. It is through these several transparent layers that we see
 the white light body of the sun.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 2</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e499">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Surface of the Sun</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Here let us return to and see what more we know about the
 photosphere—the sun's surface. It is from the photosphere that we
 have gained most of our knowledge of the composition of the sun, which is
 believed not to be a solid body. Examination of the photosphere shows that
 the outer surface is never at rest. Small bright cloudlets come and go in
 rapid succession, giving the surface, through contrasts in luminosity, a
 granular appearance. Of course, to be visible at all at 92,830,000 miles the
 cloudlets cannot be small. They imply enormous activity in the photosphere.
 If we might speak picturesquely the sun's surface resembles a boiling
 ocean of white-hot metal vapours. We have to-day a wonderful instrument,
 which will be described later, which dilutes, as it were, the general glare
 of the sun, and enables us to observe these fiery eruptions at any hour. The
 "oceans" of red-hot gas and white-hot metal vapour at the sun's
 surface are constantly driven by great storms. Some unimaginable energy
 streams out from the body or muscles of the sun and blows its outer layers
 into gigantic shreds, as it were.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 20]</ph>
            </p>
            <p>The actual temperature at the sun's surface, or what appears to us to
 be the surface—the photosphere—is, of course, unknown, but
 careful calculation suggests that it is from 5,000° C. to 7,000° C. The
 interior is vastly hotter. We can form no conception of such temperatures as
 must exist there. Not even the most obdurate solid could resist such
 temperatures, but would be converted almost instantaneously into gas. But it
 would not be gas as we know gases on the earth. The enormous pressures that
 exist on the sun must convert even gases into thick treacly fluids. We can
 only infer this state of matter. It is beyond our power to reproduce it.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e508">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Sun-spots</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It is in the brilliant photosphere that the dark areas known as sun-spots
 appear. Some of these dark spots—they are dark only by contrast with
 the photosphere surrounding them—are of enormous size, covering many
 thousands of square miles of surface. What they are we cannot positively say.
 They look like great cavities in the sun's surface. Some think they are
 giant whirlpools. Certainly they seem to be great whirling streams of glowing
 gases with vapours above them and immense upward and downward currents within
 them. Round the edges of the sun-spots rise great tongues of flame.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the most popularly known fact about sun-spots is that they are
 somehow connected with what we call magnetic storms on earth. These magnetic
 storms manifest themselves in interruptions of our telegraphic and telephonic
 communications, in violent disturbances of the mariner's compass, and in
 exceptional auroral displays. The connection between the two sets of
 phenomena cannot be doubted, even although at times there may be a great spot
 on the sun without any corresponding "magnetic storm" effects on
 the earth.</p>
            <p>A surprising fact about sun-spots is that they show definite periodic
 variations in number. The best-defined period is one of<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 21]</ph> about eleven
 years. During this period the spots increase to a maximum in number and then
 diminish to a minimum, the variation being more or less regular. Now this can
 only mean one thing. To be periodic the spots must have some deep-seated
 connection with the fundamental facts of the sun's structure and
 activities. Looked at from this point of view their importance becomes
 great.</p>
            <fig id="image048"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Reproduction from "The Forces of Nature"</i> (<i>Messrs.
   Macmillan</i>)</p>

               <p>THE AURORA BOREALIS</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image048_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE AURORA BOREALIS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>The aurora borealis is one of the most beautiful spectacles in the sky.
 The colours and shape change every instant; sometimes a fan-like cluster of
 rays, at other times long golden draperies gliding one over the other. Blue,
 green, yellow, red, and white combine to give a glorious display of colour.
 The theory of its origin is still, in part, obscure, but there can be no
 doubt that the aurora is related to the magnetic phenomena of the earth and
 therefore is connected with the electrical influence of the sun.]</p>
            <p>It is from the study of sun-spots that we have learned that the sun's
 surface does not appear to rotate all at the same speed. The
 "equatorial" regions are rotating quicker than regions farther
 north or south. A point forty-five degrees from the equator seems to take
 about two and a half days longer to complete one rotation than a point on the
 equator. This, of course, confirms our belief that the sun cannot be a solid
 body.</p>
            <p>What is its composition? We know that there are present, in a gaseous
 state, such well-known elements as sodium, iron, copper, zinc, and magnesium;
 indeed, we know that there is practically every element in the sun that we
 know to be in the earth. How do we know?</p>
            <p>It is from the photosphere, as has been said, that we have won most of our
 knowledge of the sun. The instrument used for this purpose is the
 spectroscope; and before proceeding to deal further with the sun and the
 source of its energy it will be better to describe this instrument.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e550">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">A WONDERFUL INSTRUMENT AND WHAT IT REVEALS</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The spectroscope is an instrument for analysing light. So important is it
 in the revelations it has given us that it will be best to describe it fully.
 Every substance to be examined must first be made to glow, made luminous; and
 as nearly everything in the heavens <i>is</i> luminous the instrument has a
 great range in Astronomy. And when we speak of analysing light, we mean
 that<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 22]</ph>
 the light may be broken up into waves of different lengths. What we call
 light is a series of minute waves in ether, and these waves
 are—measuring them from crest to crest, so to say—of various
 lengths. Each wave-length corresponds to a colour of the rainbow. The
 shortest waves give us a sensation of violet colour, and the largest waves
 cause a sensation of red. The rainbow, in fact, is a sort of natural
 spectrum. (The meaning of the rainbow is that the moisture-laden air has
 sorted out these waves, in the sun's light, according to their length.)
 Now the simplest form of spectroscope is a glass prism—a
 triangular-shaped piece of glass. If white light (sunlight, for example)
 passes through a glass prism, we see a series of rainbow-tinted colours.
 Anyone can notice this effect when sunlight is shining through any kind of
 cut glass—the stopper of a wine decanter, for instance. If, instead of
 catching with the eye the coloured lights as they emerge from the glass
 prism, we allow them to fall on a screen, we shall find that they pass, by
 continuous gradations, from red at the one end of the screen, through orange,
 yellow, green, blue, and indigo, to violet at the other end. <i>In other
 words, what we call white light is composed of rays of these several colours.
 They go to make up the effect which we call white.</i> And now just as water
 can be split up into its two elements, oxygen and hydrogen, so sunlight can
 be broken up into its primary colours, which are those we have just
 mentioned.</p>
            <p>This range of colours, produced by the spectroscope, we call the solar
 spectrum, and these are, from the spectroscopic point of view, primary
 colours. Each shade of colour has its definite position in the spectrum. That
 is to say, the light of each shade of colour (corresponding to its
 wave-length) is reflected through a certain fixed angle on passing through
 the glass prism. Every possible kind of light has its definite position, and
 is denoted by a number which gives the wave-length of the vibrations
 constituting that particular kind of light.</p>
            <p>Now, other kinds of light besides sunlight can be analysed.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 23]</ph> Light from any
 substance which has been made incandescent may be observed with the
 spectroscope in the same way, and each element can be thus separated. It is
 found that each substance (in the same conditions of pressure, etc.) gives a
 constant spectrum of its own. <i>Each metal displays its own distinctive
 colour. It is obvious, therefore, that the spectrum provides the means for
 identifying a particular substance.</i> It was by this method that we
 discovered in the sun the presence of such well-known elements as sodium,
 iron, copper, zinc, and magnesium.</p>
            <fig id="image052a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Yerkes Observatory.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 9.—THE GREAT SUN-SPOT OF JULY 17, 1905</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image052a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE GREAT SUN-SPOT OF JULY 17, 1905</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image052b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>From photographs taken at the Yerkes Observatory.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 10.—SOLAR PROMINENCES</p>

               <p>These are about 60,000 miles in height. The two photographs show the
   vast changes occurring in ten minutes. October 10, 1910.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image052b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SOLAR PROMINENCES</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image053a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Mount Wilson Observatory.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 11.—MARS, October 5, 1909</p>

               <p>Showing the dark markings and the Polar Cap.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image053a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>MARS, October 5, 1909</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image053b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FIG. 12.—JUPITER</p>

               <p>Showing the belts which are probably cloud formations.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image053b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>JUPITER</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image053c"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Professor E. E. Barnard, Yerkes Observatory.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 13.—SATURN, November 19, 1911</p>

               <p>Showing the rings, mighty swarms of meteorites.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image053c_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>SATURN</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>Every chemical element known, then, has a distinctive spectrum of its own
 when it is raised to incandescence, and this distinctive spectrum is as
 reliable a means of identification for the element as a human face is for its
 owner. Whether it is a substance glowing in the laboratory or in a remote
 star makes no difference to the spectroscope; if the light of any substance
 reaches it, that substance will be recognised and identified by the
 characteristic set of waves.</p>
            <p>The spectrum of a glowing mass of gas will consist in a number of bright
 lines of various colours, and at various intervals; corresponding to each
 kind of gas, there will be a peculiar and distinctive arrangement of bright
 lines. But if the light from such a mass of glowing gas be made to pass
 through a cool mass of the <i>same</i> gas it will be found that dark lines
 replace the bright lines in the spectrum, the reason for this being that the
 cool gas absorbs the rays of light emitted by the hot gas. Experiments of
 this kind enable us to reach the important general statement that every gas,
 when cold, absorbs the same rays of light which it emits when hot.</p>
            <p>Crossing the solar spectrum are hundreds and hundreds of dark lines. These
 could not at first be explained, because this fact of discriminative
 absorption was not known. We understand now. The sun's white light comes
 from the photosphere, but between us and the photosphere there is, as we have
 seen, another solar envelope of relatively cooler vapours—the
 reversing<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 24]</ph> layer. Each constituent element in this outer envelope stops
 its own kind of light, that is, the kind of light made by incandescent atoms
 of the same element in the photosphere. The "stoppages" register
 themselves in the solar spectrum as dark lines placed exactly where the
 corresponding bright lines would have been. The explanation once attained,
 dark lines became as significant as bright lines. The secret of the sun's
 composition was out. We have found practically every element in the sun that
 we know to be in the earth. We have identified an element in the sun before
 we were able to isolate it on the earth. We have been able even to point to
 the coolest places on the sun, the centres of sun-spots, where alone the
 temperature seems to have fallen sufficiently low to allow chemical compounds
 to form.</p>
            <p>It is thus we have been able to determine what the stars, comets, or
 nebulæ are made of.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e684">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">A Unique Discovery</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>In 1868 Sir Norman Lockyer detected a light coming from the prominences of
 the sun which was not given by any substance known on earth, and attributed
 this to an unknown gas which he called helium, from the Greek <i>helios</i>,
 the sun. <i>In 1895 Sir William Ramsay discovered in certain minerals the
 same gas identified by the spectroscope.</i> We can say, therefore, that this
 gas was discovered in the sun nearly thirty years before it was found on
 earth; this discovery of the long-lost heir is as thrilling a chapter in the
 detective story of science as any in the sensational stories of the day, and
 makes us feel quite certain that our methods really tell us of what elements
 sun and stars are built up. The light from the corona of the sun, as we have
 mentioned indicates a gas still unknown on earth, which has been christened
 Coronium.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e694">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Measuring the Speed of Light</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>But this is not all; soon a new use was found for the spectroscope. We
 found that we could measure with it the most difficult<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 25]</ph> of all speeds to
 measure, speed in the line of sight. Movement at right angles to the
 direction in which one is looking is, if there is sufficient of it, easy to
 detect, and, if the distance of the moving body is known, easy to measure.
 But movement in the line of vision is both difficult to detect and difficult
 to measure. Yet, even at the enormous distances with which astronomers have
 to deal, the spectroscope can detect such movement and furnish data for its
 measurement. If a luminous body containing, say, sodium is moving rapidly
 towards the spectroscope, it will be found that the sodium lines in the
 spectrum have moved slightly from their usual definite positions towards the
 violet end of the spectrum, the amount of the change of position increasing
 with the speed of the luminous body. If the body is moving away from the
 spectroscope the shifting of the spectral lines will be in the opposite
 direction, towards the red end of the spectrum. In this way we have
 discovered and measured movements that otherwise would probably not have
 revealed themselves unmistakably to us for thousands of years. In the same
 way we have watched, and measured the speed of, tremendous movements on the
 sun, and so gained proof that the vast disturbances we should expect there
 actually do occur.</p>
            <fig id="image056"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE SPECTROSCOPE IS AN INSTRUMENT FOR ANALYSING LIGHT; IT PROVIDES THE
   MEANS FOR IDENTIFYING DIFFERENT SUBSTANCES</p>

               <p>This pictorial diagram illustrates the principal of
   Spectrum Analysis, showing how sunlight is decomposed into its primary
   colours. What we call white light is composed of seven different colours.
   The diagram is relieved of all detail which would unduly obscure the simple
   process by which a ray of light is broken up by a prism into different
   wave-lengths. The spectrum rays have been greatly magnified.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image056_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SPECTROSCOPE IS AN INSTRUMENT FOR ANALYSING LIGHT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e718">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">IS THE SUN DYING?</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 3</p>
         <p>Now let us return to our consideration of the sun.</p>
         <p>To us on the earth the most patent and most astonishing fact about the sun
 is its tremendous energy. Heat and light in amazing quantities pour from it
 without ceasing.</p>
         <p>Where does this energy come from? Enormous jets of red glowing gases can
 be seen shooting outwards from the sun, like flames from a fire, for
 thousands of miles. Does this argue fire, as we know fire on the earth? On
 this point the scientist is sure. The sun is not burning, and combustion is
 not the source of its<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 26]</ph> heat. Combustion is a chemical reaction between atoms. The
 conditions that make it possible are known and the results are predictable
 and measurable. But no chemical reaction of the nature of combustion as we
 know it will explain the sun's energy, nor indeed will any ordinary
 chemical reaction of any kind. If the sun were composed of combustible
 material throughout and the conditions of combustion as we understand them
 were always present, the sun would burn itself out in some thousands of
 years, with marked changes in its heat and light production as the process
 advanced. There is no evidence of such changes. There is, instead, strong
 evidence that the sun has been emitting light and heat in prodigious
 quantities, not for thousands, but for millions of years. Every addition to
 our knowledge that throws light on the sun's age seems to make for
 increase rather than decrease of its years. This makes the wonder of its
 energy greater.</p>
         <p>And we cannot avoid the issue of the source of the energy by saying merely
 that the sun is gradually radiating away an energy that originated in some
 unknown manner, away back at the beginning of things. Reliable calculations
 show that the years required for the mere cooling of a globe like the sun
 could not possibly run to millions. In other words, the sun's energy must
 be subject to continuous and more or less steady renewal. However it may have
 acquired its enormous energy in the past, it must have some source of energy
 in the present.</p>
         <p>The best explanation that we have to-day of this continuous accretion of
 energy is that it is due to shrinkage of the sun's bulk under the force
 of gravity. Gravity is one of the most mysterious forces of nature, but it is
 an obvious fact that bodies behave as if they attracted one another, and
 Newton worked out the law of this attraction. We may say, without trying to
 go too deeply into things, that every particle of matter attracts every other
 throughout the universe. If the diameter of the sun were to shrink by one
 mile all round, this would mean that all the millions of tons in
 the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 27]</ph>
 outer one-mile thickness would have a straight drop of one mile towards the
 centre. And that is not all, because obviously the layers below this outer
 mile would also drop inwards, each to a less degree than the one above it.
 What a tremendous movement of matter, however slowly it might take place! And
 what a tremendous energy would be involved! Astronomers calculate that the
 above shrinkage of one mile all round would require fifty years for its
 completion, assuming, reasonably, that there is close and continuous
 relationship between loss of heat by radiation and shrinkage. Even if this
 were true we need not feel over-anxious on this theory; before the sun became
 too cold to support life many millions of years would be required.</p>
         <p>It was suggested at one time that falls of meteoric matter into the sun
 would account for the sun's heat. This position is hardly tenable now.
 The mere bulk of the meteoric matter required by the hypothesis, apart from
 other reasons, is against it. There is undoubtedly an enormous amount of
 meteoric matter moving about within the bounds of the solar system, but most
 of it seems to be following definite routes round the sun like the planets.
 The stray erratic quantities destined to meet their doom by collision with
 the sun can hardly be sufficient to account for the sun's heat.</p>
         <p>Recent study of radio-active bodies has suggested another factor that may
 be working powerfully along with the force of gravitation to maintain the
 sun's store of heat. In radio-active bodies certain atoms seem to be
 undergoing disintegration. These atoms appear to be splitting up into very
 minute and primitive constituents. But since matter may be split up into such
 constituents, may it not be built up from them?</p>
         <p>The question is whether these "radio-active" elements are
 undergoing disintegration, or formation, in the sun. If they are undergoing
 disintegration—and the sun itself is undoubtedly
 radio-active—then we have another source of heat for the sun that will
 last indefinitely.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 28]</ph>
         </p>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e750">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE PLANETS</ph> 
      </title>
      <body/>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e752">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">LIFE IN OTHER WORLDS?</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 1</p>
         <p>It is quite clear that there cannot be life on the stars. Nothing solid or
 even liquid can exist in such furnaces as they are. Life exists only on
 planets, and even on these its possibilities are limited. Whether all the
 stars, or how many of them, have planetary families like our sun, we cannot
 positively say. If they have, such planets would be too faint and small to be
 visible tens of trillions of miles away. Some astronomers think that our sun
 may be exceptional in having planets, but their reasons are speculative and
 unconvincing. Probably a large proportion at least of the stars have planets,
 and we may therefore survey the globes of our own solar system and in a
 general way extend the results to the rest of the universe.</p>
         <p>In considering the possibility of life as we know it we may at once rule
 out the most distant planets from the sun, Uranus and Neptune. They are
 probably intrinsically too hot. We may also pass over the nearest planet to
 the sun, Mercury. We have reason to believe that it turns on its axis in the
 same period as it revolves round the sun, and it must therefore always
 present the same side to the sun. This means that the heat on the sunlit side
 of Mercury is above boiling-point, while the cold on the other side must be
 between two and three hundred degrees below freezing-point.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e761">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Planet Venus</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The planet Venus, the bright globe which is known to all as the morning
 and evening "star," seems at first sight more promising as regards
 the possibility of life. It is of nearly the same size as the earth, and it
 has a good atmosphere, but there are many astronomers who believe that, like
 Mercury, it always presents the same face to the sun, and it would therefore
 have the same disadvantage—a broiling heat on the sunny side and the
 cold of<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 29]</ph> space on the opposite side. We are not sure. The surface of
 Venus is so bright—the light of the sun is reflected to us by such
 dense masses of cloud and dust—that it is difficult to trace any
 permanent markings on it, and thus ascertain how long it takes to rotate on
 its axis. Many astronomers believe that they have succeeded, and that the
 planet always turns the same face to the sun. If it does, we can hardly
 conceive of life on its surface, in spite of the cloud-screen.</p>
            <fig id="image062"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FIG. 14.—THE MOON</p>

               <p>Showing a great plain and some typical craters. There are
   thousands of these craters, and some theories of their origin are explained
   on page 34.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image062_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE MOON</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image063a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FIG. 15.—MARS</p>

               <p>1} Drawings by Prof. Lowell to accompany actual photographs
   of Mars showing many of the
   <ph outputclass="br"/>
   2} canals. Taken in 1907 by Mr. E. C. Slipher of the Lowell Observatory.
   <ph outputclass="br"/>
   3 Drawing by Prof. Lowell made January 6, 1914.
   <ph outputclass="br"/>
   4 Drawing by Prof. Lowell made January 21, 1914.
   <ph outputclass="br"/>
   Nos. 1 and 2 show the effect of the planet's rotation. Nos. 3 and 4
   depict quite different sections. Note the change in the polar snow-caps in
   the last two.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image063a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>MARS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image063b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FIG. 16.—THE MOON, AT NINE AND THREE-QUARTER DAYS</p>

               <p>Note the mysterious "rays" diverging from the
   almost perfectly circular craters indicated by the arrows (Tycho, upper;
   Copernicus, lower), and also the mountains to the right with the lunar dawn
   breaking on them.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image063b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE MOON, AT NINE AND THREE-QUARTER DAYS</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>We turn to Mars; and we must first make it clear why there is so much
 speculation about life on Mars, and why it is supposed that, if there
 <i>is</i> life on Mars, it must be more advanced than life on the earth.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e830">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Is there Life on Mars?</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The basis of this belief is that if, as we saw, all the globes in our
 solar system are masses of metal that are cooling down, the smaller will have
 cooled down before the larger, and will be further ahead in their
 development. Now Mars is very much smaller than the earth, and must have
 cooled at its surface millions of years before the earth did. Hence, if a
 story of life began on Mars at all, it began long before the story of life on
 the earth. We cannot guess what sort of life-forms would be evolved in a
 different world, but we can confidently say that they would tend toward
 increasing intelligence; and thus we are disposed to look for highly
 intelligent beings on Mars.</p>
            <p>But this argument supposes that the conditions of life, namely air and
 water, are found on Mars, and it is disputed whether they are found there in
 sufficient quantity. The late Professor Percival Lowell, who made a lifelong
 study of Mars, maintained that there are hundreds of straight lines drawn
 across the surface of the planet, and he claimed that they are beds of
 vegetation marking the sites of great channels or pipes by means of which the
 "Martians" draw water from their polar ocean. Professor<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 30]</ph> W. H. Pickering,
 another high authority, thinks that the lines are long, narrow marshes fed by
 moist winds from the poles. There are certainly white polar caps on Mars.
 They seem to melt in the spring, and the dark fringe round them grows
 broader.</p>
            <p>Other astronomers, however, say that they find no trace of water-vapour in
 the atmosphere of Mars, and they think that the polar caps may be simply thin
 sheets of hoar-frost or frozen gas. They point out that, as the atmosphere of
 Mars is certainly scanty, and the distance from the sun is so great, it may
 be too cold for the fluid water to exist on the planet.</p>
            <p>If one asks why our wonderful instruments cannot settle these points, one
 must be reminded that Mars is never nearer than 34,000,000 miles from the
 earth, and only approaches to this distance once in fifteen or seventeen
 years. The image of Mars on the photographic negative taken in a big
 telescope is very small. Astronomers rely to a great extent on the eye, which
 is more sensitive than the photographic plate. But it is easy to have
 differences of opinion as to what the eye sees, and so there is a good deal
 of controversy.</p>
            <p>In August, 1924, the planet will again be well placed for observation, and
 we may learn more about it. Already a few of the much-disputed lines, which
 people wrongly call "canals," have been traced on photographs.
 Astronomers who are sceptical about life on Mars are often not fully aware of
 the extraordinary adaptability of life. There was a time when the climate of
 the whole earth, from pole to pole, was semi-tropical for millions of years.
 No animal could then endure the least cold, yet now we have plenty of Arctic
 plants and animals. If the cold came slowly on Mars, as we have reason to
 suppose, the population could be gradually adapted to it. On the whole, it is
 possible that there is advanced life on Mars, and it is not impossible, in
 spite of the very great difficulties of a code of communication, that our
 "elder brothers" may yet flash across space the solution of many of
 our problems.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 31]</ph>
            </p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 2</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e852">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Jupiter and Saturn</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Next to Mars, going outward from the sun, is Jupiter. Between Mars and
 Jupiter, however, there are more than three hundred million miles of space,
 and the older astronomers wondered why this was not occupied by a planet. We
 now know that it contains about nine hundred "planetoids," or small
 globes of from five to five hundred miles in diameter. It was at one time
 thought that a planet might have burst into these fragments (a theory which
 is not mathematically satisfactory), or it may be that the material which is
 scattered in them was prevented by the nearness of the great bulk of Jupiter
 from uniting into one globe.</p>
            <p>For Jupiter is a giant planet, and its gravitational influence must extend
 far over space. It is 1,300 times as large as the earth, and has nine moons,
 four of which are large, in attendance on it. It is interesting to note that
 the outermost moons of Jupiter and Saturn revolve round these planets in a
 direction contrary to the usual direction taken by moons round planets, and
 by planets round the sun. But there is no life on Jupiter.</p>
            <p>The surface which we see in photographs (Fig. 12) is a mass of cloud or
 steam which always envelops the body of the planet. It is apparently red-hot.
 A red tinge is seen sometimes at the edges of its cloud-belts, and a large
 red region (the "red spot"), 23,000 miles in length, has been
 visible on it for half a century. There may be a liquid or solid core to the
 planet, but as a whole it is a mass of seething vapours whirling round on its
 axis once in every ten hours. As in the case of the sun, however, different
 latitudes appear to rotate at different rates. The interior of Jupiter is
 very hot, but the planet is not self-luminous. The planets Venus and Jupiter
 shine very brightly, but they have no light of their own; they reflect the
 sunlight.</p>
            <p>Saturn is in the same interesting condition. The surface in the photograph
 (Fig. 13) is steam, and Saturn is so far away<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 32]</ph> from the sun that the vaporisation
 of its oceans must necessarily be due to its own internal heat. It is too hot
 for water to settle on its surface. Like Jupiter, the great globe turns on
 its axis once in ten hours—a prodigious speed—and must be a
 swirling, seething mass of metallic vapours and gases. It is instructive to
 compare Jupiter and Saturn in this respect with the sun. They are smaller
 globes and have cooled down more than the central fire.</p>
            <p>Saturn is a beautiful object in the telescope because it has ten moons (to
 include one which is disputed) and a wonderful system of "rings"
 round it. The so-called rings are a mighty swarm of meteorites—pieces
 of iron and stone of all sorts and sizes, which reflect the light of the sun
 to us. This ocean of matter is some miles deep, and stretches from a few
 thousand miles from the surface of the planet to 172,000 miles out in space.
 Some astronomers think that this is volcanic material which has been shot out
 of the planet. Others regard it as stuff which would have combined to form an
 eleventh moon but was prevented by the nearness of Saturn itself. There is no
 evidence of life on Saturn.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e868">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE MOON</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>Mars and Venus are therefore the only planets, besides the earth, on which
 we may look for life; and in the case of Venus, the possibility is very
 faint. But what about the moons which attend the planets? They range in size
 from the little ten-miles-wide moons of Mars, to Titan, a moon of Saturn, and
 Ganymede, a satellite of Jupiter, which are about 3,000 miles in diameter.
 May there not be life on some of the larger of these moons? We will take our
 own moon as a type of the class.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e873">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">A Dead World</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The moon is so very much nearer to us than any other heavenly body that we
 have a remarkable knowledge of it. In Fig. 14 you have a photograph, taken in
 one of our largest telescopes,<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 33]</ph> of part of its surface. In a sense such a
 telescope brings the moon to within about fifty miles of us. We should see a
 city like London as a dark, sprawling blotch on the globe. We could just
 detect a Zeppelin or a Diplodocus as a moving speck against the surface. But
 we find none of these things. It is true that a few astronomers believe that
 they see signs of some sort of feeble life or movement on the moon. Professor
 Pickering thinks that he can trace some volcanic activity. He believes that
 there are areas of vegetation, probably of a low order, and that the soil of
 the moon may retain a certain amount of water in it. He speaks of a very thin
 atmosphere, and of occasional light falls of snow. He has succeeded in
 persuading some careful observers that there probably are slight changes of
 some kind taking place on the moon.</p>
            <fig id="image068a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FIG. 17.—A MAP OF THE CHIEF PLAINS AND CRATERS OF THE MOON</p>

               <p>The plains were originally supposed to be seas: hence the name
   "Mare."</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image068a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A MAP OF THE CHIEF PLAINS AND CRATERS OF THE MOON</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image068b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>FIG. 18.—A DIAGRAM OF A STREAM OF METEORS SHOWING THE EARTH
   PASSING THROUGH THEM</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image068b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A DIAGRAM OF A STREAM OF METEORS SHOWING THE EARTH PASSING THROUGH THEM</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image069a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Royal Observatory, Greenwich.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 19.—COMET, September 29, 1908</p>

               <p>Notice the tendency to form a number of tails. (See photograph
   below.)</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image069a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SPECTROSCOPE IS AN INSTRUMENT FOR ANALYSING LIGHT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image069b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Royal Observatory, Greenwich.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 20.—COMET, October 3, 1908</p>

               <p>The process has gone further and a number of distinct tails can now be
   counted.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image069b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SPECTROSCOPE IS AN INSTRUMENT FOR ANALYSING LIGHT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>But there are many things that point to absence of air on the moon. Even
 the photographs we reproduce tell the same story. The edges of the shadows
 are all hard and black. If there had been an appreciable atmosphere it would
 have scattered the sun's light on to the edges and produced a gradual
 shading off such as we see on the earth. This relative absence of air must
 give rise to some surprising effects. There will be no sounds on the moon,
 because sounds are merely air waves. Even a meteor shattering itself to a
 violent end against the surface of the moon would make no noise. Nor would it
 herald its coming by glowing into a "shooting star," as it would on
 entering the earth's atmosphere. There will be no floating dust, no
 scent, no twilight, no blue sky, no twinkling of the stars. The sky will be
 always black and the stars will be clearly visible by day as by night. The
 sun's wonderful corona, which no man on earth, even by seizing every
 opportunity during eclipses, can hope to see for more than two hours in all
 in a long lifetime, will be visible all day. So will the great red flames of
 the sun. Of course, there will be no life, and no landscape effects and
 scenery effects due to vegetation.</p>
            <p>The moon takes approximately twenty-seven of our days to<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 34]</ph> turn once on its
 axis. So for fourteen days there is continuous night, when the temperature
 must sink away down towards the absolute cold of space. This will be followed
 without an instant of twilight by full daylight. For another fourteen days
 the sun's rays will bear straight down, with no diffusion or absorption
 of their heat, or light, on the way. It does not follow, however, that the
 temperature of the moon's surface must rise enormously. It may not even
 rise to the temperature of melting ice. Seeing there is no air there can be
 no check on radiation. The heat that the moon gets will radiate away
 immediately. We know that amongst the coldest places on the earth are the
 tops of very high mountains, the points that have reared themselves nearest
 to the sun but farthest out of the sheltering blanket of the earth's
 atmosphere. The actual temperature of the moon's surface by day is a moot
 point. It may be below the freezing-point or above the boiling-point of
 water.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e958">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Mountains of the Moon</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The lack of air is considered by many astronomers to furnish the
 explanation of the enormous number of "craters" which pit the
 moon's surface. There are about a hundred thousand of these strange
 rings, and it is now believed by many that they are spots where very large
 meteorites, or even planetoids, splashed into the moon when its surface was
 still soft. Other astronomers think that they are the remains of gigantic
 bubbles which were raised in the moon's "skin," when the globe
 was still molten, by volcanic gases from below. A few astronomers think that
 they are, as is popularly supposed, the craters of extinct volcanoes. Our
 craters, on the earth, are generally deep cups, whereas these ring-formations
 on the moon are more like very shallow and broad saucers. Clavius, the
 largest of them, is 123 miles across the interior, yet its encircling rampart
 is not a mile high.</p>
            <p>The mountains on the moon (Fig. 16) rise to a great height,<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 35]</ph> and are
 extraordinarily gaunt and rugged. They are like fountains of lava, rising in
 places to 26,000 and 27,000 feet. The lunar Apennines have three thousand
 steep and weird peaks. Our terrestrial mountains are continually worn down by
 frost acting on moisture and by ice and water, but there are none of these
 agencies operating on the moon. Its mountains are comparatively
 "everlasting hills."</p>
            <p>The moon is interesting to us precisely because it is a dead world. It
 seems to show how the earth, or any cooling metal globe, will evolve in the
 remote future. We do not know if there was ever life on the moon, but in any
 case it cannot have proceeded far in development. At the most we can imagine
 some strange lowly forms of vegetation lingering here and there in pools of
 heavy gas, expanding during the blaze of the sun's long day, and frozen
 rigid during the long night.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e971">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">METEORS AND COMETS</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>We may conclude our survey of the solar system with a word about
 "shooting stars," or meteors, and comets. There are few now who do
 not know that the streak of fire which suddenly lights the sky overhead at
 night means that a piece of stone or iron has entered our atmosphere from
 outer space, and has been burned up by friction. It was travelling at,
 perhaps, twenty or thirty miles a second. At seventy or eighty miles above
 our heads it began to glow, as at that height the air is thick enough to
 offer serious friction and raise it to a white heat. By the time the meteor
 reached about twenty miles or so from the earth's surface it was entirely
 dissipated, as a rule in fiery vapour.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e975">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Millions of Meteorites</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It is estimated that between ten and a hundred million meteorites enter
 our atmosphere and are cremated, every day.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 36]</ph> Most of them weigh only an ounce or
 two, and are invisible. Some of them weigh a ton or more, but even against
 these large masses the air acts as a kind of "torpedo-net." They
 generally burst into fragments and fall without doing damage.</p>
            <p>It is clear that "empty space" is, at least within the limits of
 our solar system, full of these things. They swarm like fishes in the seas.
 Like the fishes, moreover, they may be either solitary or gregarious. The
 solitary bit of cosmic rubbish is the meteorite, which we have just examined.
 A "social" group of meteorites is the essential part of a comet.
 The nucleus, or bright central part, of the head of a comet (Fig. 19)
 consists of a swarm, sometimes thousands of miles wide, of these pieces of
 iron or stone. This swarm has come under the sun's gravitational
 influence, and is forced to travel round it. From some dark region of space
 it has moved slowly into our system. It is not then a comet, for it has no
 tail. But as the crowded meteors approach the sun, the speed increases. They
 give off fine vapour-like matter and the fierce flood of light from the sun
 sweeps this vapour out in an ever-lengthening tail. Whatever way the comet is
 travelling, the tail always points away from the sun.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e985">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">A Great Comet</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The vapoury tail often grows to an enormous length as the comet approaches
 the sun. The great comet of 1843 had a tail two hundred million miles long.
 It is, however, composed of the thinnest vapours imaginable. Twice during the
 nineteenth century the earth passed through the tail of a comet, and nothing
 was felt. The vapours of the tail are, in fact, so attenuated that we can
 hardly imagine them to be white-hot. They may be lit by some electrical
 force. However that may be, the comet dashes round the sun, often at three or
 four hundred miles a second, then may pass gradually out of our system once
 more. It may be a thousand years, or it may be fifty years,
 before<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 37]</ph>
 the monarch of the system will summon it again to make its fiery journey
 round his throne.</p>
            <fig id="image074"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Harvard College Observatory.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 21.—TYPICAL SPECTRA</p>

               <p>Six main types of stellar spectra. Notice the lines they
   have in common, showing what elements are met with in different types of
   stars. Each of these spectra corresponds to a different set of physical and
   chemical conditions.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image074_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SPECTROSCOPE IS AN INSTRUMENT FOR ANALYSING LIGHT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image075a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Mount Wilson Observatory.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 22.—A NEBULAR REGION SOUTH OF ZETA ORIONIS</p>

               <p>Showing a great projection of "dark matter" cutting off the
   light from behind.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image075a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SPECTROSCOPE IS AN INSTRUMENT FOR ANALYSING LIGHT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image075b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Astrophysical Observatory, Victoria, British Columbia.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 23.—STAR CLUSTER IN HERCULES</p>

               <p>A wonderful cluster of stars. It has been estimated that
   the distance of this cluster is such that it would take light more than
   100,000 years to reach us.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image075b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SPECTROSCOPE IS AN INSTRUMENT FOR ANALYSING LIGHT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e1054">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE STELLAR UNIVERSE</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 1</p>
         <p>The immensity of the Stellar Universe, as we have seen, is beyond our
 apprehension. The sun is nothing more than a very ordinary star, perhaps an
 insignificant one. There are stars enormously greater than the sun. One such,
 Betelgeux, has recently been measured, and its diameter is more than 300
 times that of the sun.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e1060">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Evolution of Stars</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The proof of the similarity between our sun and the stars has come to us
 through the spectroscope. The elements that we find by its means in the sun
 are also found in the same way in the stars. Matter, says the spectroscope,
 is essentially the same everywhere, in the earth and the sun, in the comet
 that visits us once in a thousand years, in the star whose distance is
 incalculable, and in the great clouds of "fire-mist" that we call
 nebulæ.</p>
            <p>In considering the evolution of the stars let us keep two points clearly
 in mind. The starting-point, the nebula, is no figment of the scientific
 imagination. Hundreds of thousands of nebulæ, besides even vaster irregular
 stretches of nebulous matter, exist in the heavens. But the stages of the
 evolution of this stuff into stars are very largely a matter of speculation.
 Possibly there is more than one line of evolution, and the various theories
 may be reconciled. And this applies also to the theories of the various
 stages through which the stars themselves pass on their way to
 extinction.</p>
            <p>The light of about a quarter of a million stars has been analysed in the
 spectroscope, and it is found that they fall into about<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 38]</ph> a dozen classes
 which generally correspond to stages in their evolution (Fig. 21).</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e1072">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Age of Stars</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>In its main lines the spectrum of a star corresponds to its colour, and we
 may roughly group the stars into red, yellow, and white. This is also the
 order of increasing temperature, the red stars being the coolest and the
 white stars the hottest. We might therefore imagine that the white stars are
 the youngest, and that as they grow older and cooler they become yellowish,
 then red, and finally become invisible—just as a cooling white-hot iron
 would do. But a very interesting recent research shows that there are two
 kinds of red stars; some of them are amongst the oldest stars and some are
 amongst the youngest. The facts appear to be that when a star is first formed
 it is not very hot. It is an immense mass of diffuse gas glowing with a
 dull-red heat. It contracts under the mutual gravitation of its particles,
 and as it does so it grows hotter. It acquires a yellowish tinge. As it
 continues to contract it grows hotter and hotter until its temperature
 reaches a maximum as a white star. At this point the contraction process does
 not stop, but the heating process does. Further contraction is now
 accompanied by cooling, and the star goes through its colour changes again,
 but this time in the inverse order. It contracts and cools to yellow and
 finally to red. But when it again becomes a red star it is enormously denser
 and smaller than when it began as a red star. Consequently the red stars are
 divided into two classes called, appropriately, Giants and Dwarfs. This
 theory, which we owe to an American astronomer, H. N. Russell, has been
 successful in explaining a variety of phenomena, and there is consequently
 good reason to suppose it to be true. But the question as to how the red
 giant stars were formed has received less satisfactory and precise
 answers.</p>
            <p>The most commonly accepted theory is the nebular theory.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 39]</ph>
            </p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e1081">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE NEBULAR THEORY</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 2</p>
         <p>Nebulæ are dim luminous cloud-like patches in the heavens, more like wisps
 of smoke in some cases than anything else. Both photography and the telescope
 show that they are very numerous, hundreds of thousands being already known
 and the number being continually added to. They are not small. Most of them
 are immensely large. Actual dimensions cannot be given, because to estimate
 these we must first know definitely the distance of the nebulæ from the
 earth. The distances of some nebulæ are known approximately, and we can
 therefore form some idea of size in these cases. The results are staggering.
 The mere visible surface of some nebulæ is so large that the whole stretch of
 the solar system would be too small to form a convenient unit for measuring
 it. A ray of light would require to travel for years to cross from side to
 side of such a nebula. Its immensity is inconceivable to the human mind.</p>
         <p>There appear to be two types of nebulæ, and there is evidence suggesting
 that the one type is only an earlier form of the other; but this again we do
 not know.</p>
         <p>The more primitive nebulæ would seem to be composed of gas in an extremely
 rarified form. It is difficult to convey an adequate idea of the rarity of
 nebular gases. The residual gases in a vacuum tube are dense by comparison. A
 cubic inch of air at ordinary pressure would contain more matter than is
 contained in millions of cubic inches of the gases of nebulæ. The light of
 even the faintest stars does not seem to be dimmed by passing through a
 gaseous nebula, although we cannot be sure on this point. The most remarkable
 physical fact about these gases is that they are luminous. Whence they derive
 their luminosity we do not know. It hardly seems possible to believe that
 extremely thin gases exposed to the terrific cold of space can be so hot as
 to be luminous and can retain their heat and their luminosity<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 40]</ph> indefinitely. A
 cold luminosity due to electrification, like that of the aurora borealis,
 would seem to fit the case better.</p>
         <p>Now the nebular theory is that out of great "fire-mists," such
 as we have described, stars are born. We do not know whether gravitation is
 the only or even the main force at work in a nebula, but it is supposed that
 under the action of gravity the far-flung "fire-mists" would begin
 to condense round centres of greatest density, heat being evolved in the
 process. Of course the condensation would be enormously slow, although the
 sudden irruption of a swarm of meteors or some solid body might hasten
 matters greatly by providing large, ready-made centres of condensation.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e1098">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Spiral Nebulæ</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>It is then supposed that the contracting mass of gas would begin to rotate
 and to throw off gigantic streamers, which would in their turn form centres
 of condensation. The whole structure would thus form a spiral, having a dense
 region at its centre and knots or lumps of condensed matter along its spiral
 arms. Besides the formless gaseous nebulæ there are hundreds of thousands of
 "spiral" nebulæ such as we have just mentioned in the heavens. They
 are at all stages of development, and they are visible to us at all
 angles—that is to say, some of them face directly towards us, others
 are edge on, and some are in intermediate positions. It appears, therefore,
 that we have here a striking confirmation of the nebular hypothesis. But we
 must not go so fast. There is much controversy as to the nature of these
 spiral nebulæ. Some eminent astronomers think they are other stellar
 universes, comparable in size with our own. In any case they are vast
 structures, and if they represent stars in process of condensation, they must
 be giving birth to huge agglomerations of stars—to star clusters at
 least. These vast and enigmatic objects do not throw much light on the origin
 of our own solar system. The nebular hypothesis, which was invented
 by<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 41]</ph>
 Laplace to explain the origin of our solar system, has not yet met with
 universal acceptance. The explanation offers grave difficulties, and it is
 best while the subject is still being closely investigated, to hold all
 opinions with reserve. It may be taken as probable, however, that the
 universe has developed from masses of incandescent gas.</p>
            <fig id="image080"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Yerkes Observatory.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 24.—THE GREAT NEBULA IN ORION</p>

               <p>The most impressive nebula in the heavens. It is
   inconceivably greater in dimensions than the whole solar system.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image080_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE GREAT NEBULA IN ORION</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image081"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Lick Observatory.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 25—GIANT SPIRAL NEBULA, March 23, 1914</p>

               <p>This spiral nebula is seen full on. Notice the central
   nucleus and the two spiral arms emerging from its opposite directions. Is
   matter flowing out of the nucleus into the arms or along the arms into the
   nucleus? In either case we should get two streams in opposite directions
   within the nucleus.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image081_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>GIANT SPIRAL NEBULA</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e1146">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE BIRTH AND DEATH OF STARS</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 3</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e1151">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Variable, New, and Dark Stars: Dying Suns</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>Many astronomers believe that in "variable stars" we have
 another star, following that of the dullest red star, in the dying of suns.
 The light of these stars varies periodically in so many days, weeks, or
 years. It is interesting to speculate that they are slowly dying suns, in
 which the molten interior periodically bursts through the shell of thick
 vapours that is gathering round them. What we saw about our sun seems to
 point to some such stage in the future. That is, however, not the received
 opinion about variable stars. It may be that they are stars which
 periodically pass through a great swarm of meteors or a region of space that
 is rich in cosmic dust of some sort, when, of course, a great illumination
 would take place.</p>
            <p>One class of these variable stars, which takes its name from the star
 Algol, is of special interest. Every third night Algol has its light reduced
 for several hours. Modern astronomy has discovered that in this case there
 are really two stars, circulating round a common centre, and that every third
 night the fainter of the two comes directly between us and its companion and
 causes an "eclipse." This was until recently regarded as a most
 interesting case in which a dead star revealed itself to us by passing before
 the light of another star. But astronomers have in recent years invented
 something, the "selenium-cell," which is even more sensitive than
 the photographic plate, and on this the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 42]</ph> supposed dead star registers itself
 as very much alive. Algol is, however, interesting in another way. The pair
 of stars which we have discovered in it are hundreds of trillions of miles
 away from the earth, yet we know their masses and their distances from each
 other.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e1161">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Death and Birth of Stars</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>We have no positive knowledge of dead stars; which is not surprising when
 we reflect that a dead star means an invisible star! But when we see so many
 individual stars tending toward death, when we behold a vast population of
 all conceivable ages, we presume that there are many already dead. On the
 other hand, there is no reason to suppose that the universe as a whole is
 "running down." Some writers have maintained this, but their
 argument implies that we know a great deal more about the universe than we
 actually do. The scientific man does not know whether the universe is finite
 or infinite, temporal or eternal; and he declines to speculate where there
 are no facts to guide him. He knows only that the great gaseous nebulæ
 promise myriads of worlds in the future, and he concedes the possibility that
 new nebulæ may be forming in the ether of space.</p>
            <p>The last, and not the least interesting, subject we have to notice is the
 birth of a "new star." This is an event which astronomers now
 announce every few years; and it is a far more portentous event than the
 reader imagines when it is reported in his daily paper. The story is much the
 same in all cases. We say that the star appeared in 1901, but you begin to
 realise the magnitude of the event when you learn that the distant
 "blaze" had really occurred about the time of the death of Luther!
 The light of the conflagration had been speeding toward us across space at
 186,000 miles a second, yet it has taken nearly three centuries to reach us.
 To be visible at all to us at that distance the fiery outbreak must have been
 stupendous. If a mass of petroleum ten times the size of the earth were
 suddenly fired it would not<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 43]</ph> be seen at such a distance. The new star had
 increased its light many hundredfold in a few days.</p>
            <p>There is a considerable fascination about the speculation that in such
 cases we see the resurrection of a dead world, a means of renewing the
 population of the universe. What happens is that in some region of the sky
 where no star, or only a very faint star, had been registered on our charts,
 we almost suddenly perceive a bright star. In a few days it may rise to the
 highest brilliancy. By the spectroscope we learn that this distant blaze
 means a prodigious outpour of white-hot hydrogen at hundreds of miles a
 second. But the star sinks again after a few months, and we then find a
 nebula round it on every side. It is natural to suppose that a dead or dying
 sun has somehow been reconverted in whole or in part into a nebula. A few
 astronomers think that it may have partially collided with another star, or
 approached too closely to another, with the result we described on an earlier
 page. The general opinion now is that a faint or dead star had rushed into
 one of those regions of space in which there are immense stretches of
 nebulous matter, and been (at least in part) vaporised by the friction.</p>
            <p>But the difficulties are considerable, and some astronomers prefer to
 think that the blazing star may merely have lit up a dark nebula which
 already existed. It is one of those problems on which speculation is most
 tempting but positive knowledge is still very incomplete. We may be content,
 even proud, that already we can take a conflagration that has occurred more
 than a thousand trillion miles away and analyse it positively into an
 outflame of glowing hydrogen gas at so many miles a second.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e1175">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">THE SHAPE OF OUR UNIVERSE</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 4</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e1179">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">Our Universe a Spiral Nebula</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>What is the shape of our universe, and what are its dimensions? This is a
 tremendous question to ask. It is like asking<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 44]</ph> an intelligent insect, living on a
 single leaf in the midst of a great Brazilian forest, to say what is the
 shape and size of the forest. Yet man's ingenuity has proved equal to
 giving an answer even to this question, and by a method exactly similar to
 that which would be adopted by the insect. Suppose, for instance, that the
 forest was shaped as an elongated oval, and the insect lived on a tree near
 the centre of the oval. If the trees were approximately equally spaced from
 one another they would appear much denser along the length of the oval than
 across its width. This is the simple consideration that has guided
 astronomers in determining the shape of our stellar universe. There is one
 direction in the heavens along which the stars appear denser than in the
 directions at right angles to it. That direction is the direction in which we
 look towards the Milky Way. If we count the number of stars visible all over
 the heavens, we find they become more and more numerous as we approach the
 Milky Way. As we go farther and farther from the Milky Way the stars thin out
 until they reach a maximum sparseness in directions at right angles to the
 plane of the Milky Way. We may consider the Milky Way to form, as it were,
 the equator of our system, and the line at right angles to point to the north
 and south poles.</p>
            <p>Our system, in fact, is shaped something like a lens, and our sun is
 situated near the centre of this lens. In the remoter part of this lens, near
 its edge, or possibly outside it altogether, lies the great series of star
 clouds which make up the Milky Way. All the stars are in motion within this
 system, but the very remarkable discovery has been made that these motions
 are not entirely random. The great majority of the stars whose motions can be
 measured fall into two groups drifting past one another in opposite
 directions. The velocity of one stream relative to the other is about
 twenty-five miles per second. The stars forming these two groups are
 thoroughly well mixed; it is not a case of an inner stream going one way and
 an outer stream the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 45]</ph> other. But there are not quite as many stars going one way as
 the other. For every two stars in one stream there are three in the other.
 Now, as we have said, some eminent astronomers hold that the spiral nebulæ
 are universes like our own, and if we look at the two photographs (Figs. 25
 and 26) we see that these spirals present features which, in the light of
 what we have just said about our system, are very remarkable. The nebula in
 Coma Berenices is a spiral edge-on to us, and we see that it has precisely
 the lens-shaped middle and the general flattened shape that we have found in
 our own system. The nebula in Canes Venatici is a spiral facing towards us,
 and its shape irresistibly suggests motions along the spiral arms. This
 motion, whether it is towards or away from the central, lens-shaped portion,
 would cause a double streaming motion in that central portion of the kind we
 have found in our own system. Again, and altogether apart from these
 considerations, there are good reasons for supposing our Milky Way to possess
 a double-armed spiral structure. And the great patches of dark absorbing
 matter which are known to exist in the Milky Way (see Fig. 22) would give
 very much the mottled appearance we notice in the arms (which we see edge-on)
 of the nebula in Coma Berenices. The<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 46]</ph> hypothesis, therefore, that our universe is a
 spiral nebula has much to be said for it. If it be accepted it greatly
 increases our estimate of the size of the material universe. For our central,
 lens-shaped system is calculated to extend towards the Milky Way for more
 than twenty thousand times a million million miles, and about a third of this
 distance towards what we have called the poles. If, as we suppose, each
 spiral nebula is an independent stellar universe comparable in size with our
 own, then, since there are hundreds of thousands of spiral nebulæ, we see
 that the size of the whole material universe is indeed beyond our
 comprehension.</p>
            <fig id="image086"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: Mount Wilson Observatory.</i>
               </p>

               <p>FIG. 26.—A SPIRAL NEBULA SEEN EDGE-ON</p>

               <p>Notice the lens-shaped formation of the nucleus and the arm
   stretching as a band across it. See reference in the text to the
   resemblance between this and our stellar universe.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image086_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>A SPIRAL NEBULA SEEN EDGE-ON</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image087"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: H. J. Shepstone.</i>
               </p>

               <p>100-INCH TELESCOPE, MOUNT WILSON</p>

               <p>A reflecting telescope: the largest in the world. The
   mirror is situated at the base of the telescope.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image087_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>100-INCH TELESCOPE, MOUNT WILSON</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <!-- div  center-->
  <table>
               <tgroup cols="3">
                  <colspec colname="col1"/>
                  <colspec colname="col2"/>
                  <colspec colname="col3"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="center">THE SOLAR SYSTEM</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="center">NAME</entry>
                        <entry align="center">MEAN DISTANCE FROM SUN (IN MILLIONS OF MILES)</entry>
                        <entry align="center">PERIOD OF REVOLUTION AROUND SUN (IN YEARS)</entry>
                        <entry align="center">DIAMETER (IN MILES)</entry>
                        <entry align="center">NUMBER OF SATELLITES</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">MERCURY</entry>
                        <entry align="right">36.0</entry>
                        <entry align="right">0.24</entry>
                        <entry align="right">3030</entry>
                        <entry align="right">0</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">VENUS</entry>
                        <entry align="right">67.2</entry>
                        <entry align="right">0.62</entry>
                        <entry align="right">7700</entry>
                        <entry align="right">0</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">EARTH</entry>
                        <entry align="right">92.9</entry>
                        <entry align="right">1.00</entry>
                        <entry align="right">7918</entry>
                        <entry align="right">1</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">MARS</entry>
                        <entry align="right">141.5</entry>
                        <entry align="right">1.88</entry>
                        <entry align="right">4230</entry>
                        <entry align="right">2</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">JUPITER</entry>
                        <entry align="right">483.3</entry>
                        <entry align="right">11.86</entry>
                        <entry align="right">86500</entry>
                        <entry align="right">9</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">SATURN</entry>
                        <entry align="right">886.0</entry>
                        <entry align="right">29.46</entry>
                        <entry align="right">73000</entry>
                        <entry align="right">10</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">URANUS</entry>
                        <entry align="right">1781.9</entry>
                        <entry align="right">84.02</entry>
                        <entry align="right">31900</entry>
                        <entry align="right">4</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">NEPTUNE</entry>
                        <entry align="right">2971.6</entry>
                        <entry align="right">164.78</entry>
                        <entry align="right">34800</entry>
                        <entry align="right">1</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">SUN</entry>
                        <entry align="right">———</entry>
                        <entry align="right">———</entry>
                        <entry align="right">866400</entry>
                        <entry align="right">—</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">MOON</entry>
                        <entry align="right">———</entry>
                        <entry align="right">———</entry>
                        <entry align="right">2163</entry>
                        <entry align="right">—</entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
            <!-- /div  center--><p>FIG. 27</p>
            <!-- div  center-->
  <table>
               <tgroup cols="3">
                  <colspec colname="col1"/>
                  <colspec colname="col2"/>
                  <colspec colname="col3"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="center">STAR DISTANCES</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <i>STAR</i>
                        </entry>
                        <entry align="right">
                           <i>DISTANCE IN LIGHT-YEARS</i>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>POLARIS</entry>
                        <entry align="right">76</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>CAPELLA</entry>
                        <entry align="right">49.4</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>RIGEL</entry>
                        <entry align="right">466</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>SIRIUS</entry>
                        <entry align="right">8.7</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>PROCYON</entry>
                        <entry align="right">10.5</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>REGULUS</entry>
                        <entry align="right">98.8</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>ARCTURUS</entry>
                        <entry align="right">43.4</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>[ALPHA] CENTAURI</entry>
                        <entry align="right">4.29</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>VEGA</entry>
                        <entry align="right">34.7</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>SMALLER MAGELLANIC CLOUD</entry>
                        <entry align="right">32,600[A]</entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>GREAT CLUSTER IN HERCULES</entry>
                        <entry align="right">108,600[A]</entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
            <!-- /div  center--><!-- div  caption-->
  <p>[A] ESTIMATED</p>

            <p>FIG. 28</p>

            <p>The above distances are merely approximate and are subject to further
  revision. A "light-year" is the distance that light, travelling at
  the rate of 186,000 miles per second, would cover in one year.</p>
            <!-- /div  caption--><p>In this simple outline we have not touched on some of the more debatable
 questions that engage the attention of modern astronomers. Many of these
 questions have not yet passed the controversial stage; out of these will
 emerge the astronomy of the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 47]</ph> future. But we have seen enough to convince us
 that, whatever advances the future holds in store, the science of the heavens
 constitutes one of the most important stones in the wonderful fabric of human
 knowledge.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e1456">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">ASTRONOMICAL INSTRUMENTS</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p outputclass="dim">§ 1</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="d1e1461">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Telescope</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>The instruments used in modern astronomy are amongst the finest triumphs
 of mechanical skill in the world. In a great modern observatory the different
 instruments are to be counted by the score, but there are two which stand out
 pre-eminent as the fundamental instruments of modern astronomy. These
 instruments are the telescope and the spectroscope, and without them
 astronomy, as we know it, could not exist.</p>
            <p>There is still some dispute as to where and when the first telescope was
 constructed; as an astronomical instrument, however, it dates from the time
 of the great Italian scientist Galileo, who, with a very small and imperfect
 telescope of his own invention, first observed the spots on the sun, the
 mountains of the moon, and the chief four satellites of Jupiter. A good pair
 of modern binoculars is superior to this early instrument of Galileo's,
 and the history of telescope construction, from that primitive instrument to
 the modern giant recently erected on Mount Wilson, California, is an exciting
 chapter in human progress. But the early instruments have only an historic
 interest: the era of modern telescopes begins in the nineteenth century.</p>
            <p>During the last century telescope construction underwent an unprecedented
 development. An immense amount of interest was taken in the construction of
 large telescopes, and the different countries of the world entered on an
 exciting race to produce the most powerful possible instruments. Besides
 this<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 48]</ph>
 rivalry of different countries there was a rivalry of methods. The telescope
 developed along two different lines, and each of these two types has its
 partisans at the present day. These types are known as <i>refractors</i> and
 <i>reflectors</i>, and it is necessary to mention, briefly, the principles
 employed in each. The <i>refractor</i> is the ordinary, familiar type of
 telescope. It consists, essentially, of a large lens at one end of a tube,
 and a small lens, called the eye-piece, at the other. The function of the
 large lens is to act as a sort of gigantic eye. It collects a large amount of
 light, an amount proportional to its size, and brings this light to a focus
 within the tube of the telescope. It thus produces a small but bright image,
 and the eye-piece magnifies this image. In the <i>reflector</i>, instead of a
 large lens at the top of the tube, a large mirror is placed at the bottom.
 This mirror is so shaped as to reflect the light that falls on it to a focus,
 whence the light is again led to an eye-piece. Thus the refractor and the
 reflector differ chiefly in their manner of gathering light. The powerfulness
 of the telescope depends on the size of the light-gatherer. A telescope with
 a lens four inches in diameter is four times as powerful as the one with a
 lens two inches in diameter, for the amount of light gathered obviously
 depends on the <i>area</i> of the lens, and the area varies as the
 <i>square</i> of the diameter.</p>
            <p>The largest telescopes at present in existence are <i>reflectors</i>. It
 is much easier to construct a very large mirror than to construct a very
 large lens; it is also cheaper. A mirror is more likely to get out of order
 than is a lens, however, and any irregularity in the shape of a mirror
 produces a greater distorting effect than in a lens. A refractor is also more
 convenient to handle than is a reflector. For these reasons great refractors
 are still made, but the largest of them, the great Yerkes' refractor, is
 much smaller than the greatest reflector, the one on Mount Wilson,
 California. The lens of the Yerkes' refractor measures three feet four
 inches in diameter, whereas the Mount Wilson reflector has a diameter of no
 less than eight feet four inches.</p>
            <fig id="image092"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>THE YERKES 40-INCH REFRACTOR</p>

               <p>(The largest <i>refracting</i> telescope in the world. Its
   big lens weighs 1,000 pounds, and its mammoth tube, which is 62 feet long,
   weighs about 12,000 pounds. The parts to be moved weigh approximately 22
   tons.</p>

               <p>The great <i>100-inch reflector</i> of the Mount Wilson
   reflecting telescope—the largest <i>reflecting</i> instrument in the
   world—weighs nearly 9,000 pounds and the moving parts of the
   telescope weigh about 100 tons.</p>

               <p>The new <i>72-inch reflector</i> at the Dominion
   Astrophysical Observatory, near Victoria, B. C., weighs nearly 4,500
   pounds, and the moving parts about 35 tons.)</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image092_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE YERKES 40-INCH REFRACTOR</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <fig id="image093a"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>
                  <i>Photo: H. J. Shepstone.</i>
               </p>

               <p>THE DOUBLE-SLIDE PLATE HOLDER ON YERKES 40-INCH REFRACTING TELESCOPE</p>

               <p>The smaller telescope at the top of the picture acts as a
   "finder"; the field of view of the large telescope is so
   restricted that it is difficult to recognise, as it were, the part of the
   heavens being surveyed. The smaller telescope takes in a larger area and
   enables the precise object to be examined to be easily selected.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image093a_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE DOUBLE-SLIDE PLATE HOLDER ON YERKES 40-INCH REFRACTING TELESCOPE</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>
               <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 49]</ph>
            </p>
            <fig id="image093b"><!-- div  caption-->
   <p>MODERN DIRECT-READING SPECTROSCOPE</p>

               <p>(<i>By A. Hilger, Ltd.</i>)</p>

               <p>The light is brought through one telescope, is split up by
   the prism, and the resulting spectrum is observed through the other
   telescope.</p>
               <!-- /div  caption--><image href="images/image093b_sm.jpg">
                  <alt>THE SPECTROSCOPE IS AN INSTRUMENT FOR ANALYSING LIGHT</alt>
               </image>
            </fig>
            <p>But there is a device whereby the power of these giant instruments, great
 as it is, can be still further heightened. That device is the simple one of
 allowing the photographic plate to take the place of the human eye. Nowadays
 an astronomer seldom spends the night with his eye glued to the great
 telescope. He puts a photographic plate there. The photographic plate has
 this advantage over the eye, that it builds up impressions. However long we
 stare at an object too faint to be seen, we shall never see it. With the
 photographic plate, however, faint impressions go on accumulating. As hour
 after hour passes, the star which was too faint to make a perceptible
 impression on the plate goes on affecting it until finally it makes an
 impression which can be made visible. In this way the photographic plate
 reveals to us phenomena in the heavens which cannot be seen even through the
 most powerful telescopes.</p>
            <p>Telescopes of the kind we have been discussing, telescopes for exploring
 the heavens, are mounted <i>equatorially</i>; that is to say, they are
 mounted on an inclined pillar parallel to the axis of the earth so that, by
 rotating round this pillar, the telescope is enabled to follow the apparent
 motion of a star due to the rotation of the earth. This motion is effected by
 clock-work, so that, once adjusted on a star, and the clock-work started, the
 telescope remains adjusted on that star for any length of time that is
 desired. But a great official observatory, such as Greenwich Observatory or
 the Observatory at Paris, also has <i>transit</i> instruments, or telescopes
 smaller than the equatorials and without the same facility of movement, but
 which, by a number of exquisite refinements, are more adapted to accurate
 measurements. It is these instruments which are chiefly used in the
 compilation of the <i>Nautical Almanac</i>. They do not follow the apparent
 motions of the stars. Stars are allowed to drift across the field of vision,
 and as each star crosses a small group of parallel wires in the eye-piece its
 precise time of passage is recorded. Owing to their relative fixity of
 position these instruments can be constructed to record the<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 50]</ph> 
               <i>positions</i>
 of stars with much greater accuracy than is possible to the more general and
 flexible mounting of equatorials. The recording of transit is comparatively
 dry work; the spectacular element is entirely absent; stars are treated
 merely as mathematical points. But these observations furnish the very basis
 of modern mathematical astronomy, and without them such publications as the
 <i>Nautical Almanac</i> and the <i>Connaissance du Temps</i> would be robbed
 of the greater part of their importance.</p>
            <p outputclass="dim">§ 2</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="d1e1608">
         <title>
            <ph outputclass="title-line">The Spectroscope</ph> 
         </title>
         <body>
            <p>We have already learnt something of the principles of the spectroscope,
 the instrument which, by making it possible to learn the actual constitution
 of the stars, has added a vast new domain to astronomy. In the simplest form
 of this instrument the analysing portion consists of a single prism. Unless
 the prism is very large, however, only a small degree of dispersion is
 obtained. It is obviously desirable, for accurate analytical work, that the
 dispersion—that is, the separation of the different parts of the
 spectrum—should be as great as possible. The dispersion can be
 increased by using a large number of prisms, the light emerging from the
 first prism, entering the second, and so on. In this way each prism produces
 its own dispersive effect and, when a number of prisms are employed, the
 final dispersion is considerable. A considerable amount of light is absorbed
 in this way, however, so that unless our primary source of light is very
 strong, the final spectrum will be very feeble and hard to decipher.</p>
            <p>Another way of obtaining considerable dispersion is by using a
 <i>diffraction grating</i> instead of a prism. This consists essentially of a
 piece of glass on which lines are ruled by a diamond point. When the lines
 are sufficiently close together they split up light falling on them into its
 constituents and produce a spectrum.<ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg 51]</ph> The modern diffraction grating is a truly
 wonderful piece of work. It contains several thousands of lines to the inch,
 and these lines have to be spaced with the greatest accuracy. But in this
 instrument, again, there is a considerable loss of light.</p>
            <p>We have said that every substance has its own distinctive spectrum, and it
 might be thought that, when a list of the spectra of different substances has
 been prepared, spectrum analysis would become perfectly straightforward. In
 practice, however, things are not quite so simple. The spectrum emitted by a
 substance is influenced by a variety of conditions. The pressure, the
 temperature, the state of motion of the object we are observing, all make a
 difference, and one of the most laborious tasks of the modern spectroscopist
 is to disentangle these effects from one another. Simple as it is in its
 broad outlines, spectroscopy is, in reality, one of the most intricate
 branches of modern science.</p>
            <!--hr--></body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="d1e1624">
      <title>
         <ph outputclass="title-line">BIBLIOGRAPHY</ph> 
      </title>
      <body>
         <p>(The following list of books may be useful to readers wishing to pursue
 further the study of Astronomy.)</p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Ball</ph>, <i>The Story of the Heavens</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Ball</ph>, <i>The Story of the Sun</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Forbes</ph>, <i>History of Astronomy</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Hincks</ph>, <i>Astronomy</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Kippax</ph>, <i>Call of the Stars</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Lowell</ph>, <i>Mars and Its Canals</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Lowell</ph>, <i>Evolution of Worlds</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">McKready</ph>, <i>A Beginner's Star-Book</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Newcomb</ph>, <i>Popular Astronomy</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Newcomb</ph>, <i>The Stars: A Study of the
 Universe</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Olcott</ph>, <i>Field Book of the Stars</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Price</ph>, <i>Essence of Astronomy</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Serviss</ph>, <i>Curiosities of the Skies</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Webb</ph>, <i>Celestial Objects for Common
 Telescopes</i>.
 <ph outputclass="br"/>
            <ph outputclass="smcap">Young</ph>, <i>Text-Book of General Astronomy</i>.</p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 52]</ph>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 53]</ph>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 54]</ph>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <ph outputclass="pagenum">[Pg
 55]</ph>
         </p>
         <!--hr--></body>
   </topic>
</topic>