<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd">
<topic id="license">
  <title>Project Gutenberg License</title>
  <body>
    <pre>
      The Project Gutenberg EBook The Mysterious Island, by Jules Verne
      #6 in our series by Jules Verne
      
      Copyright laws are changing all over the world. Be sure to check the
      copyright laws for your country before downloading or redistributing
      this or any other Project Gutenberg eBook.
      
      This header should be the first thing seen when viewing this Project
      Gutenberg file.  Please do not remove it.  Do not change or edit the
      header without written permission.
      
      Please read the "legal small print," and other information about the
      eBook and Project Gutenberg at the bottom of this file.  Included is
      important information about your specific rights and restrictions in
      how the file may be used.  You can also find out about how to make a
      donation to Project Gutenberg, and how to get involved.
      
      
      **Welcome To The World of Free Plain Vanilla Electronic Texts**
      
      **EBooks Readable By Both Humans and By Computers, Since 1971**
      
      *****These EBooks Were Prepared By Thousands of Volunteers*****
      
      
      Title: The Mysterious Island
      
      Author: Jules Verne
      
      Release Date: April, 1998  [EBook #1268]
      
      Date last updated: February 10, 2008]
      
      Edition: 11
      
      Language: English
      
      Character set encoding: ASCII
      
      
      
      
      
      *** START OF THE PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK THE MYSTERIOUS ISLAND, BY VERNE***
      
      
      This etext was first prepared by Anthony Matonak
      This updated edition was produced by David Widger <xref href="mailto:widger@cecomet.net" scope="external" format="email">&lt;widger@cecomet.net&gt;</xref>
        Extensive proofing was done by Trevor Carlson
        
        DITA version prepared by W. Eliot Kimber
      
    </pre>
  </body>
</topic>
